<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="manuscript_3052">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>MS. Canon. Liturg. 37</title>
            <title type="collection">MSS. Canon. Liturg. (Canonici Liturgical)</title>
            <respStmt xml:id="PK">
               <resp when="2021-04">Cataloguer</resp>
               <persName>Peter Kidd</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="MLH">
               <resp when="2021-04">Encoding and markup</resp>
               <persName>Matthew Holford</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </publisher>
            <idno type="msID">MS_Canon_Liturg_37</idno>
            <idno type="collection">Canon_Liturg</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="MS_Canon_Liturg_37" xml:lang="en">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <region type="county">Oxfordshire</region>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <institution>University of Oxford</institution>
                  <repository>Bodleian Library</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">MS. Canon. Liturg. 37</idno>
                  <idno type="ieArk">ark:29072/x06395w772gx</idno><idno type="crArk">ark:29072/x04q77fs28zc</idno><altIdentifier type="internal">
                     <idno type="SCN">19247</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
               <head>Premonstratensian prayerbook, in Latin (one prayer in German); Germany (Regensburg diocese?), 1507</head>
               <msContents>
                  <msItem class="#liturgica #oratio" n="1" xml:id="MS_Canon_Liturg_37-item1">
                     <title key="work_13588" type="desc">Offices and prayers (Premonstratensian)</title>
                     <note>The rubrics are often on the page before the start of the text.</note>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="1r" to="9v">(fols. 1r–9v)</locus>
                        <rubric>Accessus altaris premonstratensium</rubric>
                        <incipit>Adiutorium nostrum in nomine domini Qui fecit. Domine labia mea aperies</incipit>
                        <note>With antiphons, versicles, hymn, psalms, collects, etc.</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="10r" to="10v">(fol. 10r–v)</locus>
                        <rubric>Oracio de passone domini</rubric>
                        <incipit>Precor te pijissime domine Ihesu Christe propter illam eximiam caritatem </incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="10v" to="11v">(fols. 10v–11v)</locus>
                        <rubric>Devota oratio sancti Augustini</rubric>
                        <incipit>Omnipotens pater cordis mei inspector gratias tibi ago hodie de sancta incarnatione tua</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="11v" to="15r">(fols. 11v–15r)</locus>
                        <rubric> Recessus Altaris. Antiphona</rubric>
                        <incipit>Trium puerorum cantemus. Benedicite omnia opera domini domino laudate</incipit>
                        <note>The canticle ‘Benedicite’ followed by psalms, collects, etc.</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="16r" to="24r">(fols. 16r–24r)</locus>
                        <title level="a" type="desc">The Seven Penitential Psalms</title>
                        <rubric>Secuntur septem psalmus</rubric>
                        <note>Pss. 6, 31, 37, 50, 101, 129, and 142, as usual. The rubric is on fol. 15r; fol. 15v is unwritten.</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fols. 24v–31v) Litany, petitions, and collects</locus>
                        <rubric>Letania</rubric>
                        <note>With Savine second (after Stephen) among the martyrs; Augustine twice among the confessors, and ending with the series: Conrade, Wolgange, Geharde, Galle, Othmare, Udalrice, and Ruperte; the virgins end with Serena, Elizabeth, and Affra.</note>
                        <note>The collects are the same series as MS. Liturg. 402 (Premonstratensian, of the diocese of Regensburg), except that after ‘Ineffabilem misericordiam tuam domine’ the present MS. includes ‘Exaudi quesumus domine supplicum preces …’.</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="31v" to="36r">(fols. 31v–36r)</locus>
                        <note>Seven Last Words</note>
                        <rubric>Sequitur oratio venerabilis Bede presbiteri de septem verbis ultimis</rubric>
                        <incipit> Domine Ihesu Christe qui septem verba die ultimo vite tue in cruce pendens dixisti </incipit>
                        <note>A few words and a longer passage are erased at fols. 33v–34r.</note>
                        <note>The common devotion; cf. MS. Buchanan g. 1, fols. 255r–257v </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="36r" to="39r">(fols. 36r–39r)</locus>
                        <note>Seven Joys of the Virgin</note>
                        <rubric>Legitur quod beatus Thomas martir Cantuariensis archiepiscopus septem gaudia temporalia beate Marie cottidie cum magna devotione dicebat</rubric>
                        <incipit>Gaude virgo stella maris mater Christi singularis</incipit>
                        <rubric>Quicumque cum istis septem gaudijs <sic>letabundo</sic> in hoc seculo</rubric>
                        <note>A rhyming verse hymn followed by a collect.</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="39r" to="40r">(fols. 39r–40r)</locus>
                        <note>Prayer</note>
                        <incipit> Vos sancti sancteque dei omnipotentis Georgi Cristoffore Vite Panthaleon Achaci Eustachi Erasme Nicolae Leonharde Blasi Egidi Katherina Barbara Margareta</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="40r" to="41r">(fols. 40r–41r)</locus>
                        <note> Devotion to St Onuphrius</note>
                        <rubric> Oratio bona de sancto Onoffero</rubric>
                        <incipit>Egregie confessor Christi sancto Onoffore qui terrena contempti et celi gaudia exultans</incipit>
                        <note>Antiphon, verse, and collect.</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="41r" to="43r">(fols. 41r–43r)</locus>
                        <note> Devotion to St Erasmus</note>
                        <rubric> Oratio de sancto Erasmo martire</rubric>
                        <incipit>Sancte Erasme martir preciose et pontifex Christi </incipit>
                        <note>Prayer, antiphon, verse, and collect.</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="43r" to="48r">(fols. 43r–48r)</locus>
                        <locus> Devotion to the Virgin</locus>
                        <rubric> De beata virgine oratio bona</rubric>
                        <incipit>Domina mea sancta maria perpetua virgo virginum mater summe benignitas </incipit>
                        <note>Prayer and petition.</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="48r" to="64v">(fols. 48r–64v)</locus>
                        <note>Five Psalms</note>
                        <rubric>Hic secuntur quinque psalmi de passione domini</rubric>
                        <note>Not the usual Psalms of the Passion (i.e. Pss. 21–30): Pss. 21, 34, 54, 68, and 108, each followed by one or two responses, verses, and a collect, the last also with a hymn.</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="64v" to="67v">(fols. 64v–67v)</locus>
                        <rubric>Oratio Augustini ad sanctam trinitatem</rubric>
                        <incipit>Confiteor te patrem et filium et spiritum sanctum in personis trinum in substantia unum verum deum omnipotentem</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="67v" to="69v">(fols. 67v–69v)</locus>
                        <rubric> De singulis articulis passionis Ihesu Cristi oratio multum devota</rubric>
                        <incipit>Ave Ihesu splendor paterne glorie flostulus fecunditatis virginee</incipit>
                        <explicit>inter ubera anime mee Amen.</explicit>
                        <note>Fol. 70r–v is unwritten; the following texts occupy the final quire.</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="71r" to="72r">(fols. 71r–72r)</locus>
                        <note>Prayer, in German</note>
                        <incipit>Got der dw fur die erlosung der werlt hast wellen werden geporen</incipit>
                        <explicit>mit dem vater un<ex>d</ex> dem heiligen geist lebst un<ex>d</ex> herschest in ewigkait der ewigkait amen.</explicit>
                        <finalRubric>Wer diß gebet ein mal im tag spricht hat lxxx tausent iar ablas todlicher sündt auch versaümbnuß der tagzeit un<ex>d</ex> ist zw Rom in der kirchen Latran in ainen stain gegraven.</finalRubric>
                        <bibl>Translation of the Latin prayer 'Deus qui pro redemptione' (<persName key="person_7386286" role="aut">Ps.-Augustine</persName>). For literature and transmission see A. Vizkelety, <title>Beschreibendes Verzeichnis der altdeutschen Handschriften in ungarischen Bibliotheken: Bd. 1. Széchényi-Nationalbibliothek</title> (Wiesbaden: Harrassowitz, 1969), 144 (on Cod. Germ. 60, art. 8)</bibl>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="72v" to="73r">(fols. 72v–73r)</locus>
                        <rubric>Sequitur oratio pulchra et brevis s<ex>ancti</ex> Bernhardi contra subitaneam mortem de qua sunt ccc dies indulgenciarum eam devote dicentibus</rubric>
                        <incipit>O bone Ihesu duo in me agnosce <note>[sic, usually agnosco or cognosco]</note> naturam quam fecisti et peccatum quod ego adieci </incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="73v">(fol. 73v)</locus>
                        <note> Devotion to St Anne</note>
                        <rubric>Oratio ad sanctissimam matrem Annam</rubric>
                        <note>With antiphon, verse, and collect.</note>
                        <note>This and the following texts are by a different scribe.</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="74r" to="77v">(fols. 74r–77v)</locus>
                        <note> Mass prayers</note>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="74r" to="74v">(fol. 74r–v)</locus>
                           <rubric> Clemens tertius papa: sacerdotibus post missam devote dicentibus infra scriptam orationem relaxat omnia verba in canone sincopata uel iterata: deditque ccc dies indulgenciarum …</rubric>
                           <incipit>Obsecro te dulcissime domine Ihesu Chrsite ut passio tua sit michi virtus</incipit>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="74v" to="75r">(fols. 74v–75r)</locus>
                           <rubric> Oratio post communionem ad beatam virginem</rubric>
                           <incipit>O serenissima et inclita virgo Maria mater domini nostri Ihesu Christi regina celi </incipit>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="75r" to="75v">(fol. 75r–v)</locus>
                           <rubric>Secuntur alia post communionem</rubric>
                           <incipit>O benignissime domine Ihesu Christe inspice super me indignum famulum tuum </incipit>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="75v">(fol. 75v)</locus>
                           <rubric>Sequuntur orationes infra et post elevationem corpus Christi dicende</rubric>
                           <incipit>Ave verum corpus Christi natum ex Maria virgine</incipit>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="76r">(fol. 76r)</locus>
                           <rubric>Alia oratio</rubric>
                           <incipit>Ave caro Christi chara <note>[sic]</note> ymolata crucis ara</incipit>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="76r" to="76v">(fol. 76r–v)</locus>
                           <rubric>Adhuc alia oratio</rubric>
                           <incipit>Salve lux mundi verbum patris hostia vera viva caro</incipit>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="76v" to="77r">(fols. 76v–77r)</locus>
                           <rubric> Alia oratio</rubric>
                           <incipit>Sanguis tuus domine Ihesu Christe pro nobis effusus </incipit>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="77r" to="77v">(fol. 77r–v)</locus>
                           <rubric>Oratio in mediate post elevationem dicenda ad quam Innocentius papa sextus contulit plures indulgencias ad supplicationem Phylippi regis Francie. Oracio sequitur</rubric>
                           <incipit> Domine Ihesu Christe fili dei vivi qui hanc sacratissimam carnem et hunc preciosissium sanguinem </incipit>
                           <explicit>et periculis presentibus preteritis et futuris Amen. 1507</explicit>
                           <note>Fol. 78r–v is unwritten and was perhaps formerly a pastedown.</note>
                        </msItem>
                     </msItem>
                     <textLang mainLang="la" otherLangs="de">Latin with a little German (dialect of eastern upper Germany / Ostoberdeutsch)</textLang>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="perg">
                        <support>parchment</support>
                        <extent> 78 leaves <dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                              <height>105</height>
                              <width>85</width>
                           </dimensions>
                        </extent>
                        <foliation> 1–78 mostly in 19th-century pencil; an older ink leaf-count ‘76’ is on fol. 77r.</foliation>
                        <collation>1<hi rend="superscript">8</hi>, 2<hi rend="superscript">6</hi>, 3–9<hi rend="superscript">8</hi> (fols. 1–70); 10<hi rend="superscript">8</hi> (fols. 71–78) </collation>
                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout columns="1" writtenLines="14 16">Frame-ruled in ink, written with 14–16 lines per page; ruled space <dimensions type="ruled" unit="mm">
                              <height max="70" min="65">65–70</height>
                              <width>60</width>
                           </dimensions></layout>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc>
                     <handNote script="hybrida">Angular gothic hybrida; more cursive from fol. 71r</handNote>
                  </handDesc>
                  <decoDesc>
                     <decoNote type="colInit">1- and 2-line initials alternately plain red or blue, sometimes with simple ornament.</decoNote>
                  </decoDesc>
                  <bindingDesc resp="#BCBB">
                     <binding notAfter="1600" notBefore="1500">
                        <p>16th century, early, <placeName key="place_7000084">German</placeName> (as MS.), sewn on two double bands and strongly bound for partly processional use: wood boards; polished pigskin, blind-tooled with double or triple lines and stamps in an all-over pattern, differing on each cover; remains of central clasp with lost strap of light brown leather running from back fore-edge to a front catch-plate embossed with a pattern which roughly matches the adjacent stamp; four metal corner-pieces and a centrepiece on each cover, each with several boss-like protrusions; glue-marks on front paste-down from a lost item (? an image) formerly pasted there; cf. the traces of glue on fol. 70v. (<dimensions type="binding" unit="mm">
                              <height quantity="115">115</height>
                              <width precision="medium" quantity="93">c. 93</width>
                              <depth max="36" min="35" precision="medium">c. 35–36</depth>
                           </dimensions> (book closed). A piece of waste MS. is used for the front pastedown, with a stub after fol. 8. The spine has a paper label printed ‘Canonici Liturg.’ and the head of the spine is numbered ‘37’ in white paint. (Description based on Barker-Benfield: see bibliography.)</p>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origDate calendar="Gregorian" cert="high" when="1507">1507</origDate>
                     <origPlace>
                        <country key="place_7000084">German</country>, <region>Bavaria</region>
                     </origPlace>
                  </origin>
                  <provenance>The final prayer ends with the date ‘1507’ (fol. 77v). Watson notes that the script is more cursive in fols. 71–77v (the final quire) than in the preceding section, ‘but the hand may be the same throughout and the decoration in the two parts is identical’ (<title>Dated and datable</title>, no. 256).</provenance>
                  <provenance>The first rubric and the double invocation of Augustine in the litany show that the manuscript was written for Premonstratensian use; the very high grading of Savinus/Sabinus in the litany suggests an affiliation with Windberg Abbey, a Premonstratensian house in the diocese of Regensburg, which had his relics. St Onuphrius, to whom the first in a series of devotions is directed (fols. 40r–41r), was specially venerated at Augsburg cathedral, also in Bavaria.</provenance>
                  <provenance><persName key="person_2384880" role="fmo">Matteo Luigi Canonici (1727–1806)</persName>, Jesuit and bibliophile of (from 1773) Venice; from whom they passed to his brother, <persName key="person_446" role="fmo">Giuseppe (d. 1807)</persName>.</provenance>
                  <acquisition when="1817">On the latter’s death to Giovanni Perisinotti, from whom over 2,000 were bought by the Bodleian Library in 1817. Former Bodleian shelfmarks: ‘Lit. Misc. xxxvij’ (fol. 1r) </acquisition>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>Description (April 2021) by Peter Kidd, edited by Matthew Holford; with thanks to Nigel Palmer for advice on the German text. Previously described in the Summary Catalogue. <listBibl>
                              <bibl facs="aaz0357.gif" type="SC">Summary Catalogue, vol. 4, p. 338</bibl>
                           </listBibl>
                        </source>
                     </recordHist>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <surrogates>
                     <bibl subtype="full" type="digital-facsimile">
                        <ref target="https://digital.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/objects/03cc1e37-9cef-4f51-8248-2bbab76cff6b/">
                           <title>Digital Bodleian</title></ref>
                        <note>(full digital facsimile)</note>
                     </bibl>
                  </surrogates>
                  <listBibl type="WRAPPER">
                     <listBibl type="INTERNET">
                        <head>Online resources:</head>
                        <bibl><ref target="https://hab.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/en/"><title>Manuscripts from German-Speaking Lands – A Polonsky Foundation Digitization Project</title></ref></bibl>
                        <bibl><ref target="http://www.handschriftencensus.de/24493"><title>Handschriftencensus: Eine Bestandsaufnahme der handschriftlichen Überlieferung deutschsprachiger Texte des Mittelalters</title></ref></bibl>
                     </listBibl>
                     <listBibl type="PRINT">
                        <head>Printed descriptions:</head>
                        <bibl>B. C. Barker-Benfield, <title>Bookbindings of Canonici manuscripts : a survey of early and non-standard bindings, mostly Italian, in the Canonici collection of the Bodleian Library, University of Oxford</title> (Oxford, privately printed, 2020)</bibl>
                        <bibl>A. G. Watson, <title>Dated and Datable Manuscripts in Oxford Libraries</title> (1984), no. 256</bibl>
                        <bibl>S. J. P. Van Dijk, <title>Handlist of the Latin Liturgical Manuscripts in the Bodleian Library Oxford</title> (typescript, 1957) Vol. 1: Mass Books, p. 211</bibl>
                     </listBibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2021-04-16">Description fully revised for Polonsky German digitization project.</change>
         <change when="2020-07-24">Binding description added.</change>
         <change when="2018-07-27" who="#MLH">Revised to incorporate information from van Dijk.</change>
         <change when="2017-07-01">First online publication.</change>
         <change when="2017-05-25"><persName>James Cummings</persName> Up-converted the markup using <ref target="https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl">https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl</ref></change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>