<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="manuscript_2830">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>MS. Canon. Liturg. 126</title>
            <title type="collection">MSS. Canon. Liturg. (Canonici Liturgical)</title>
            <respStmt xml:id="ES">
               <resp when="2013">Cataloguer</resp>
               <persName>Elizabeth Solopova</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="MH">
               <resp when="2024">Encoding</resp>
               <persName>Matthew Holford</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </publisher>
            <idno type="msID">MS_Canon_Liturg_126</idno>
            <idno type="collection">Canon_Liturg</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="MS_Canon_Liturg_126" xml:lang="en">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <region type="county">Oxfordshire</region>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <institution>University of Oxford</institution>
                  <repository>Bodleian Library</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">MS. Canon. Liturg. 126</idno>
                  <idno type="ieArk">ark:29072/x0hm50tr708w</idno>
                  <idno type="crArk">ark:29072/x0f4752h109d</idno>
                  <altIdentifier type="internal">
                     <idno type="SCN">19267</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
               <head>Portable Secular Psalter with Antiphons; Flanders, Liège, late 13th or early
                  14th century</head>
               <msContents>
                  <msItem class="#liturgica #biblia" n="1" xml:id="MS_Canon_Liturg_126-item1">
                     <title key="work_14114" type="desc">Portable secular psalter with
                        antiphons</title>
                     <note>Fol. i is a fly-leaf; fol. 1r is blank apart from modern notes.</note>
                     <msItem n="1">
                        <locus from="1v" to="13r">(fols. 1v–13r)</locus>
                        <note> Calendar, laid out one month per two facing pages, written in black
                           and red, less than half full, not graded. Includes saints and feasts
                           characteristic of the Mosan region and Liège (the calendar of the Mosan
                           region and a list of local feasts of the Mosan region and Liège are
                           published by Oliver, 1988, Appendix 1): Servatius, bishop of Tongres (13
                           May) with octave and translation (7 June), and Lambert, bishop of Liège
                           (17 September) with octave and translation (28 April), both in red;
                           Vedast and Amand (6 February), Gertrude of Nivelles (17 March), Ursmar of
                           Lobbes (18 April), Domitian, bishop of Tongres and Maastricht (7 May),
                           Gengulfus of Florennes (11 May), Remacle, bishop of Tongres and Liège (3
                           September), Severinus of Tongeren/Cologne (23 October), Foillanus of
                           Fosses (31 October) and Eugenius de Deuil (15 November). The months are
                           headed by verses on the ‘Egyptian’ days, which largely correspond to
                           Hennig’s (1955) set I, and notes on the length of the solar and lunar
                           month.</note>
                        <note> 15th-century additions in an Italian hand comprise Roman saints and
                           feasts, including Valentine (14 February), the dedication of the Lateran
                           Basilica (9 November), the dedication of the Basilica Santa Maria
                           Maggiore (‘Sancte Marie ad Niues’, 5 August), the dedication of the
                           Basilicas of Sts Peter and Paul (November 18) and the feasts of Peter and
                           Paul. Other added feasts are Matthias (February 24), the Visitation (3
                           July), Anne (26 July), Assumption of the Virgin Mary (15 August),
                           Bartholomew (24 August), All Saints and All Souls (1–2 November), Ambrose
                           (7 December) and the Immaculate Conception of the Virgin Mary (8
                           December). The feasts of Agnes (21 January), Mark (25 April), the
                           martyrdom of John the Baptist (29 August) and the Exaltation of the Cross
                           (September 14) are underlined in dark red ink, apparently by the hand
                           which added the Roman feasts. </note>
                        <note>Fol. 13v is ruled for the calendar, but blank, apart from modern
                           notes. </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="2">
                        <locus from="14r" to="213v">(fols. 14r–213v)</locus>
                        <note> Psalms 1–150, in the biblical order, laid out as prose, without
                           numbers. Psalm 108 is followed by Gloria. Rubric ‘PS’ (‘psalmus’) at the
                           beginning of most psalms. Punctuated throughout with punctus elevatus
                           used to mark metrum and minor pauses, and punctus used to mark the ends
                           of verses. Some psalms are accompanied by cues of antiphons and hymns,
                           without rubrics. The following text is missing: <list>
                              <item>– two bifolia (?) missing after fol. 53 (missing text 32: 16–34:
                                 1) </item>
                              <item>– one bifolium missing after fol. 61 (missing text 37: 12–38: 6) </item>
                              <item>– one bifolium missing after fol. 79 (missing text 51: 4–52: 6) </item>
                              <item>– one leaf missing after fol. 118 (missing text 77: 70–78:
                                 9)</item>
                              <item> – one leaf missing after fol. 120 (missing text 80: 1–9) </item>
                              <item>– one leaf missing after fol. 144 (missing text 101: 1–8) </item>
                              <item>– one bifolium missing after fol. 213 (missing text 149:
                                 2–150).</item>
                           </list> There are textual divisions at psalms 26, 51, 68, 97 and 109 (see
                           ‘Decoration’). Originally there were probably illuminated initials at the
                           beginnings of psalms 38, 52, 80 and 101, now missing. Subdivisions within
                           psalms are not indicated, apart from psalm 118, subdivided into
                           twenty-two 8-verse units. Psalm 66 is repeated on fol. 90v, after psalm
                           62. Psalms 62 and 66 were appointed to be recited as the third and fourth
                           psalms at all Lauds during the week in the secular use. </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="3">
                        <locus from="214r" to="227r">(fols. 214r–227r)</locus>
                        <note> Weekly canticles, without titles: <list>
                              <item> (1) Confitebor tibi domine (Isaiah 12), beginning imperfectly
                                 at ‘sus est furor tuus et consolatus es me ...’;</item>
                              <item>(2) Ego dixi (Isaiah 38: 10–21);</item>
                              <item>(3) Exultauit cor meum (1 Samuel 2: 1–11);</item>
                              <item>(4) Cantemus domino (Exodus 15: 1–20);</item>
                              <item>(5) Domine audiui (Habakkuk 3);</item>
                              <item>(6) Audite celi (Deuteronomy 32: 1–44).</item>
                           </list>
                        </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="4">
                        <locus from="227r" to="236v">(fols. 227r–236v)</locus>
                        <note> Litany, including Egidius, Remacle, Heribert, Severinus, Francis and
                           Trudo among the confessors; Agnes, Gertrude, Catherine, Aldegundis,
                           Odilia, Corona and Oda among the virgins. The litany is similar to those
                           in psalters from the Mosan region and Liège (see Oliver, 1988, Appendix
                           1) and is accompanied by a petition ‘Ut clerum et plebem sancte marie
                           sanctique lamberti conseruare digneris’ (fol. 232r), followed by two
                           versions of ‘Ut dompnum apostolicum ...’ (fol. 231r), more petitions (Ego
                           dixi domine miserere mei. Sana animam meam quia peccaui tibi. Oremus pro
                           omni gradii ecclesie ..., fol. 233r), and collects (fols. 235v–236v): <list>
                              <item>(1) Concede quesumus omnipotens deus ut sancta dei genitrix
                                 uirgo maria sanctique tui apostoli martyres confessores uirgines
                                 ... atque omnes sancti quorum reliquie in ista continentur ecclesia
                                 ...</item>
                              <item>(2) Deus a quo sancta desideria recta ...</item>
                              <item>(3) Ineffabilem misericordiam tuam nobis ...</item>
                              <item>(4) Omnipotens sempiterne deus qui uiuorum dominaris simul et
                                 mortuorum ...</item>
                           </list>
                        </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="5">
                        <locus from="237r" to="244r">(fols. 237r–244r)</locus>
                        <note> Daily canticles, prayers and creeds, without titles: <list>
                              <item>(1) Benedicite omnia opera (fol. 237r), ending imperfectly at
                                 ‘Benedicite omnes bestie et pe ...’ because of the loss of a leaf
                                 after fol. 237;</item>
                              <item> (2) Benedictus dominus deus (fol. 238r) beginning imperfectly
                                 at ‘dum quod iurauit ad abraham patrem nostrum ...’</item>
                              <item>(3) Te deum laudamus (fol. 238v);</item>
                              <item>(4) Magnificat (fol. 240r);</item>
                              <item>(5) Athanasian Creed (Quicumque uult ...) (fol. 240v).</item>
                           </list> Erased text at the end of the creed (five lines). </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="6">
                        <locus from="244v">(fol. 244v)</locus>
                        <note> Added prayer in a 15th-century Italian hand, imperfect at the end:
                           ‘Benedictus sis tu deus creator omnium qui cum Maria virgine esse sine
                           grauamine voluisti et de ea immaculatam carnem sine peccato assumere
                           dignatus es. Benedictus sis tu deus qui ad uirginem cum gaudio anime eius
                           et omnium membrorum uenisti. Et cum gaudio omnium membro ...’. The prayer
                           is preceded by a partially erased rubric beginning ‘Hanc orationem ...
                           beatissima ... <supplied>m</supplied>aria ...’. </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <p><secFol> Quare fremuerunt <locus>(psalter, fol. 15r)</locus></secFol></p>
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="perg">
                        <support> parchment; paper fly-leaves</support>
                        <extent> <measure type="leaf" quantity="246">246</measure> leaves <dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                              <height quantity="107">c. 107</height>
                              <width>75</width>
                           </dimensions><note>Leaves were trimmed in rebinding, frequently causing
                              the loss of decoration.</note>
                        </extent>



                        <foliation> modern, in pencil; i + 1–245.</foliation>
                        <collation> (fols. i) paper fly-leaf conjoint with the upper pastedown |
                           (fols. 1–14) I (14) | (fols. 15–26) II (12) | (fols. 27–30) III (4) |
                           (fols. 31–50) IV–V (10) | (fols. 51–56) VI (10−2) missing 4, 5, 6, 7 (?)
                           | (fols. 57–65) VII (10−2+1) missing 5 and 6 (a bifolium is lost after
                           fol. 61); fol. 58 is a single leaf | (fols. 66–75) VIII (10) | (fols.
                           76–83) IX (10−2) missing 5 and 6 (a bifolium is lost after fol. 79) |
                           (fols. 84–93) X (10) | (fols. 94–105) XI (12) | (fols. 106–115) XII (10)
                           | (fols. 116–123) XIII (10−2) missing 4 and 7 | (fols. 124–143) XIV–XV
                           (10) | (fols. 144–152) XVI (10−1) missing 2 | (fols. 153–172) XVII–XVIII
                           (10) | (fols. 173–208) XIX–XXI (12) | (fols. 209–218) XXII (12−2) missing
                           6 and 7 (a bifolium is lost after fol. 213) | (fols. 219–230) XXIII (12)
                           | (fols. 231–238) XXIV (8−1) missing 8 | (fols. 239–244) XXV (8−1)
                           missing 8 | (fol. 245) paper fly-leaf conjoint with the lower pastedown.
                           Catchwords and leaf signatures survive, partly cropped off</collation>





                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout rulingMedium="ink" writtenLines="16" columns="1"> Ruled in ink with
                           single vertical and double horizontal bounding lines extending the full
                           height and width of page; 16 lines per page; prickings survive; written
                           below the top line; written space: <dimensions type="written" unit="mm">
                              <height quantity="63">c. 63</height>
                              <width>45</width>
                           </dimensions></layout>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc>
                     <handNote script="textualisNorthern" execution="formata">Small formal Gothic
                        book hand, black ink.</handNote>
                  </handDesc>
                  <decoDesc>
                     <!--<decoNote type="border">Fine historiated borders, marginal
                        grotesques.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="decInit"> Fine initials. (<ref
                           target="https://catalog.hathitrust.org/Record/000468709">Pächt and
                           Alexander</ref> i. 292, pl. XXI)</decoNote>-->


                     <summary>Illumination is related in style to London, British Library, Stowe MS.
                        17; Copenhagen, Kongelige Bibliotek MS. GKS 3384 8o; Brussels, Bibliothèque
                        Royale MS. IV. 1045 (Saint Jacques Missal) and Darmstadt, Hessische Landes-
                        und Hochschulbibliothek MS. 394 (Pächt and Alexander, 1966–73; Oliver, 1988,
                        vol. 1, pp. 199–201).</summary>
                     <decoNote type="monogram">Pink and blue KL monograms on gold backgrounds and
                        borders, made of pink, blue and gold bars ending with spirals, decorated
                        with foliage and gold discs, in the calendar. Four KL monograms are cut out. </decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="miniature">Panels (gold lozenges set on pink and blue
                        quadrilobes) with the Labours of the Months (rubbed, gold flanking):
                        January: hooded man, drinking from a cup and stirring fire with a fork;
                        table to the left February: man pruning a tree March: man digging with a
                        pickaxe April: man holding two flowering branches May: man playing vielle
                        (found in other Liège psalters, see Oliver, 1978, p. 108) June: woman
                        gathering flowers in a basket July: man mowing hay with a scythe August: man
                        reaping grain September: man treading and eating grapes October: man sowing
                        November: man knocking down acorns for pigs December: man slaughtering a
                        pig.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="histInit">Six (of an original ten (?)) historiated initials
                        with miniatures in architectural frames, on gold background (flaking),
                        occupying most of the page, decorated with coiled tendrils, foliage and
                        latticework, at liturgical divisions, all badly rubbed, those at psalms 38,
                        52, 80, and 101 apparently missing. The initials are accompanied by full
                        borders, decorated with coiled tendrils, foliage, hunting scenes, musicians,
                        grotesques and animals. <list>
                           <item>fol. 14r Psalm 1 (initial B(eatus)) The martyrdom of St Lambert and
                              a deacon.</item>
                           <item>(full border) Lady kneeling in prayer, possibly the patron.</item>
                           <item>fol. 45r Psalm 26 (initial D(ominus)) King David venerating
                              Christ.</item>
                           <item>fol. 79v Psalm 51 (initial Q(uid)) The Massacre of the Innocents.
                              There is an added, partially obliterated inscription in ink on gold
                              background, above the sword held by a soldier: ‘P .....’, probably in
                              an early modern Italian hand responsible for pen trials and drawings
                              in the margins elsewhere in the psalter (see ‘Provenance’).</item>
                           <item>fol. 98v Psalm 68 (initial S(aluum)) Jonah, praying in the mouth of
                              the whale, between two towers with people, floating on boats
                              (representing the towns of Joppa and Tarshish between which Jonah was
                              sailing (Oliver, 1979, p. 111 and figs. 3 and 4, and Oliver, 1988,
                              vol. 1, p. 70)); Christ and the Virgin enthroned above.</item>
                           <item>fol. 141v Psalm 97 (initial C(antate)) Three clerics, singing from
                              a book open on a lectern.</item>
                           <item>fol. 165r Psalm 109 (initial D(ixit)) The Throne of Grace:
                              God-the-Father, holding the arms of the Crucifix, dove flying from
                              Father to Son.</item>
                        </list></decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="border">Borders: see above.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="decInit">3-line historiated initials on gold backgrounds
                        (flaking), infilled with busts and halffigures of men and women, some
                        nimbed, holding books or pointing to the text, and borders made of bars and
                        spirals, decorated with grotesques, birds, apes, human and animal heads,
                        foliage and gold discs, at the beginnings of psalms, canticles and
                        prayers.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="flourInit">Alternating 1-line red, blue and gold initials, with
                        contrasting blue and red penwork, at the beginnings of verses and
                        periods.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="miniature">Pages without 3-line initials have gold bars with
                        red and blue penwork in the left margin, and a miniature in the lower
                        margin. The miniatures depict hunts, fights, grotesques, apes, birds,
                        beasts, insects, fish and scenes involving animals and humans, e.g. a
                        shepherd chasing a wolf from the sheep (fols. 45v–46r); a woman with
                        distaff, spinning, and a cat playing with yarn (fol. 94r); a fox with a
                        cloak and staff speaking to a cock (fols. 96v–97r); a cat with a rat in its
                        mouth (fol. 103r); an angel playing the vielle (fol. 142r); a man with a dog
                        jumping over a stick (fol. 145r); a fox pretending to be dead to attract
                        birds of prey (fols. 223v–224r).</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="rubrication">Added rubric on fol. 244v in red ink.</decoNote>
                  </decoDesc>
                  <bindingDesc resp="#BCBB">
                     <binding notAfter="1800" notBefore="1600">
                        <p>17th century or 18th century, <placeName key="place_1000080"
                              >Italian</placeName>?: pasteboards; parchment covering, sides plain;
                           the flat spine has three horizontal gilt lines at top and bottom, and a
                           gilt title with ornamental border tooled directly onto it, with no label;
                           no clear signs of clasps or ties; edges plain, partly discoloured.
                              <dimensions type="binding" unit="mm">
                              <height max="115" min="113">113–115</height>
                              <width max="80" min="77">77–80</width>
                              <depth max="46" min="43" precision="medium">c. 43–46</depth>
                           </dimensions> (book closed). The manuscript was in Italy by the 15th
                           century, but has a later ex libris in Portuguese on the front
                           paste-down.</p>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="1310" notBefore="1290">13th century,
                        late, or 14th century, early</origDate>
                     <origPlace>
                        <country key="place_7024097">Flemish</country>, <settlement
                           key="place_7007945">Liège</settlement>
                        <!--ORIGINAL: Flemish, Liège-->
                     </origPlace>
                  </origin>
                  <provenance>Made in Liège: evidence of the calendar, litany, decoration, and a
                     prayer for the clergy and people of St Mary and St Lambert (fol. 232r). Perhaps
                     written for a lay noblewoman, depicted on fol. 14r. </provenance>
                  <provenance>In Italy in the 15th century (?): 15th-century additions to the
                     calendar, and a prayer (fol. 244v). </provenance>
                  <provenance>Unidentified Italian (Solopova) or Portuguese (Barker-Benfield) owner:
                     ‘Pertence (or Pertenie (?)) ao <persName role="fmo" key="person_4906">P.
                        Azevedo</persName>’ (upper pastedown, 17th century (?)). </provenance>
                  <provenance>Pen trials and crude drawings in the margins in early modern Italian
                     hands, e.g. fols. 1r, 24r, 66v, 109r, 110r, 123r 177r, 244v, etc. </provenance>
                  <provenance><persName role="fmo" key="person_2384880">Matteo Luigi Canonici of
                        Venice (1727–c. 1806)</persName>: bought soon after 1780 (Mitchell, 1969);
                     not from the libraries of Soranzo or Trevisan. </provenance>
                  <acquisition when="1817">Bodleian Library: bought in 1817 from Canonici’s nephew
                     Giovanni Perissinotti. Earlier shelfmark: ‘Misc. Liturg. 126’ (upper pastedown,
                     cf. fol. 13v). </acquisition>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>Elizabeth Solopova, <title>Latin Liturgical Psalters in the Bodleian
                              Library: A Select Catalogue</title> (Oxford, 2013), pp. 354–60.
                           Binding: <bibl>B. C. Barker-Benfield, <title>Bookbindings of Canonici
                                 manuscripts : a survey of early and non-standard bindings, mostly
                                 Italian, in the Canonici collection of the Bodleian Library,
                                 University of Oxford</title> (Oxford, privately printed,
                              2020).</bibl> Previously described in the Summary Catalogue. <listBibl>
                              <bibl facs="aaz0362.gif" type="SC">Summary Catalogue, vol. 4, p.
                                 343</bibl>
                              <bibl facs="aaz0363.gif" type="SC">Summary Catalogue, vol. 4, p.
                                 344</bibl>
                           </listBibl>
                        </source>
                     </recordHist>
                     <!-- <availability status="none">
                        <p>This manuscript is on display in the Bodleian Libraries exhibition <ref target="https://visit.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/event/sensational-books">Sensational Books</ref> (27 May – 4 December 2022). It cannot be ordered between those dates or for a short period before and after.</p>
                     </availability>-->
                  </adminInfo>
                  <surrogates>
                     <bibl subtype="partial" type="digital-facsimile">
                        <ref
                           target="https://digital.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/objects/ccf5cbd3-617f-4f8c-9304-baada558da00/">
                           <title>Digital Bodleian</title>
                        </ref>
                        <note>(3 images from 35mm slides)</note>
                     </bibl>
                  </surrogates>
                  <listBibl type="WRAPPER">
                     <listBibl type="PRINT">
                        <head>Select bibliography to 2004:</head>

                        <bibl>Weale, W., ‘Liturgical manuscripts in the Bodleian Library, Oxford’,
                              <title>The Ecclesiologist</title> 2 (London, 16 July 1888), p.
                           21.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Frere, no. 463.</bibl>
                        <bibl><title>Burlington Fine Arts Club, Exhibition of illuminated
                              manuscripts</title> (London: Printed for the Burlington Fine Arts Club
                           by Chiswick Press, 1908), p. 57.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Willard, J. F., ‘Occupations of the months in medieval calendars’,
                              <title>BQR</title> 7 (1932), pp. 33–9, at p. 34.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Lyna, F., <title>De vlaamsche miniatuur van 1200 tot 1530</title>
                           (Brussels; Amsterdam: Standaard-Boekhandel, Van Kampen and Zoon, s. d.,
                           1933), p. 47.</bibl>
                        <bibl>S. J. P. van Dijk, <title>Latin Liturgical Manuscripts in the Bodleian
                              Library, Oxford, vol. 2: Office Books</title> (typescript, 1957),
                              <citedRange unit="page" from="96" to="96">p. 96</citedRange>
                        </bibl>
                        <bibl>Sinclair, K., ‘Les manuscrits du psautier de Lambert le Bègue’,
                              R<title>omania</title> 86 (1965), pp. 22–47, at p. 30.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Pächt and Alexander (1966–73), vol. 1, no. 292, pl. XXI.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Oliver, J. H., ‘The Crise Bénédictine and revival at the Abbey of St.
                           Jacques in Liège c. 1300’, <title>Quaerendo</title> 8 (1978), pp. 320–36,
                           at p. 335.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Oliver (1988), vol. 1, pp. 27, 29 n. 1, 32, 60–2, 65 n. 22, 70, 76,
                           104 n. 4, 114, 115, 118, 173, 199–201; vol. 2, no. 33, pp. 213–31, pls.
                           49, 66, 93.</bibl>
                        <bibl><title>In beeld geprezen: miniaturen uit Maaslandse devotieboeken
                              1250–1350. Provinciaal Museum voor Religieuze Kunst, Begijnhofkerk –
                              Sint Truiden, 10 augustus–12 november 1989</title> [exhibition
                           catalogue] (Leuven: Peeters, 1989), p. 134.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Randall, L. M. C., assisted by J. Oliver et al., <title>Medieval and
                              Renaissance manuscripts in the Walters Art Gallery</title>, 5 vols.
                           (Baltimore; London: Johns Hopkins University Press in association with
                           the Walters Art Gallery, 1989–97), vol. 3, Belgium, 1250–1530, part I, p.
                           62.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Büttner, F. O., ‘Der illuminierte Psalter im Westen’ in Büttner
                           (2004), pp. 1–106, at p. 19 n.</bibl>
                        <bibl>53.</bibl>



                     </listBibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
          <change when="2020-07-24">Binding description added.</change>
         <change when="2017-07-01">First online publication.</change>
         <change when="2017-05-25">
            <persName>James Cummings</persName> Up-converted the markup using <ref
               target="https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl"
               >https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl</ref>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
