<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="manuscript_2819">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>MS. Canon. Liturg. 105</title>
            <title type="collection">MSS. Canon. Liturg. (Canonici Liturgical)</title>
            <respStmt xml:id="ES">
               <resp when="2013">Cataloguer</resp>
               <persName>Elizabeth Solopova</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="MH">
               <resp when="2024">Encoding</resp>
               <persName>Matthew Holford</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </publisher>
            <idno type="msID">MS_Canon_Liturg_105</idno>
            <idno type="collection">Canon Liturg</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="MS_Canon_Liturg_105" xml:lang="en">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <region type="county">Oxfordshire</region>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <institution>University of Oxford</institution>
                  <repository>Bodleian Library</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">MS. Canon. Liturg. 105</idno>
                  <idno type="ieArk">ark:29072/x0kd17cs69vd</idno>
                  <idno type="crArk">ark:29072/x0d504rk776j</idno>
                  <altIdentifier type="internal">
                     <idno type="SCN">19259</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
               <head>Psalter, with calendar in French; France, North-Central (?), 13th century, third quarter</head>
               <msContents>
                  <msItem class="#liturgica #biblia" n="2" xml:id="MS_Canon_Liturg_105-item2">
                     <title key="work_14113" type="desc">Psalter</title>

                     <note> Fols. i–iii are fly-leaves containing added notes (see
                        ‘Provenance’).</note>
                     <note> [item 1 occupies quire I]</note>
                     <msItem n="1">
                        <locus>(fols. 1r–6v)</locus>
                        <note> Calendar in French, laid out one month per leaf, written in red, blue
                           and black (both red and blue are used for important feasts),
                           approximately one-third full, not graded. Contains Sulpice of Bourges (17
                           January), Peter of Verona (2 June), Gervasius and Prothasius (19 June),
                           Germanus of Auxerre (31 July), Francis (4 October), Denis (9 October),
                           Leonard of Limousin (6 November), Catherine (25 November), Nicholas (6
                           December) and his translation (9 May), Stephen (26 December) and the
                           invention of his relics (3 August), all in red. Martin (11 November) is
                           in blue with octave in red; his translation (4 July) is in red. Vincent
                           of Saragossa (22 January) is in blue; Benedict (21 March) is in black and
                           his translation (11 July) in red. The calendar also includes Honorina (27
                           February; relics in Conflans, near the mouth of the Oise, France, after
                           1082), Albinus of Angers (1 March), Beneuree (Felix of Dunwich (?), 7
                           March), Arnulf of Metz (18 July), Samson of Dol (28 July), Theodore of
                           Tyre (9 November), Edmund (20 November), Eligius (1 December) and his
                           translation (25 June). Each month is headed with a note on the length of
                           the solar and lunar month (e.g. ‘Januier a .xxxi. Iour. La lune .xxx.’,
                           etc.); the ‘Egyptian’ days are marked with a ‘D’. </note>
                        <textLang mainLang="fro">Old French</textLang>
                     </msItem><note>[items 2–6 occupy
                           quires II–XXI]</note>
                     <msItem n="2">
                        <locus>(fols. 7r–210r)</locus>
                        <note> Psalms 1–150, written with each verse starting on a new line, without
                           titles, with numbers added in the margins in Roman and Arabic numerals
                           (see ‘Provenance’). Punctuated throughout, with punctus used to mark the
                           ends of verses and punctus elevatus used to mark metrum and minor pauses.
                           Psalms 37: 20–38: 12 and 51: 8–52: 4 are missing owing to the removal of
                           leaves at liturgical divisions at psalms 38 and 52 after fols. 57 and 75
                           respectively. The psalms are in the biblical order; subdivisions within
                           psalms are not indicated, apart from psalm 118, subdivided into 8-verse
                           units (verse 137 is not marked, see below). There are textual divisions
                           at psalms 26, 68, 80, 97 and 109. Originally there were also doubtless
                           historiated initials at psalms 38 and 52.</note>
                        <note> There are notes in purplish-red ink in the margins throughout the
                           manuscript, noting errors in the text. Some errors have been corrected,
                           presumably in the original scriptorium, e.g. fols. 188r, 215r, 232r,
                           232v, 233r, etc. Psalm 113 (‘In exitu Israel ...’), fol. 167v, starts
                           with a 1-line initial, even though the second letter is an enlarged
                           capital. Verse 137 (‘Iustus ...’), fol. 182v, in psalm 118 is not marked
                           with a larger initial, even though the psalm is generally subdivided into
                           8-verse units. In both cases the reason is presumably an oversight (‘I’
                           was easy for the illuminator to overlook, because the scribe did not
                           leave a space for it indented into the text area as was his practice with
                           other letters). </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="3">
                        <locus>(fols. 210r–211v)</locus>
                        <note> Canticle Benedicite omnia opera .... </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="4">
                        <locus>(fol. 211v–223v)</locus>
                        <note> Weekly canticles, without titles: <list>
                              <item>(1) Confitebor tibi domine (Isaiah 12);</item>
                              <item>(2) Ego dixi (Isaiah 38: 10–21);</item>
                              <item>(3) Exultauit cor meum (1 Samuel 2: 1–11);</item>
                              <item>(4) Cantemus domino (Exodus 15: 1–20);</item>
                              <item>(5) Domine audiui (Habakkuk 3);</item>
                              <item>(6) Audite celi (Deuteronomy 32: 1–44).</item>
                           </list>
                        </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="5">
                        <locus>(fols. 223v–229v)</locus>
                        <note> Daily canticles, prayers and creeds, without titles: <list>
                              <item>(1) Magnificat (fol. 223v);</item>
                              <item>(2) Benedictus dominus deus (fol. 224r);</item>
                              <item>(3) Nunc dimittis (fol. 225r);</item>
                              <item>(4) Te deum laudamus (fol. 225r);</item>
                              <item>(5) Athanasian Creed (Quicumque uult ...) (fol. 226r).</item>
                           </list>
                        </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="6">
                        <locus>(fols. 229v–235r)</locus>
                        <note> Litany, including Martin (third), Augustine, Germanus, Benedict and
                           Egidius among the confessors, and Thomas, Edmund and Lambert among the
                           martyrs. The litany is followed by collects (fols. 234r–235r): <list>
                              <item>(1) Deus cui proprium est misereri semper et parcere suscipe
                                 ...</item>
                              <item>(2) Omnipotens sempiterne deus qui facis mirabilia magna solus
                                 ...</item>
                              <item>(3) Pretende domine famulis et famulabus tuis dexteram celestis
                                 auxilii ut de toto corde ...</item>
                              <item>(4) Deus a quo sancta desideria recta consilia et iusta sunt
                                 ...</item>
                           </list> Fol. 235r is ruled, but otherwise blank, apart from the last line
                           of the last collect. Fols. 235v–238v are blank except for an inscription
                           on fol. 236v (see ‘Provenance’). </note>
                     </msItem>

                     <textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <p><secFol> Consurge in nocte <locus>(readings, fol. 8r)</locus></secFol></p>
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="perg">
                        <support> parchment; paper fly-leaves</support>
                        <extent> 241 leaves <dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                              <height quantity="213">c. 213</height>
                              <width>152</width>
                           </dimensions><note>Leaves were trimmed in rebinding, frequently causing
                              the loss of decoration.</note>
                        </extent>
                        <foliation> modern, in pencil; i–iii + 1–238; usually differing from an
                           early modern foliation in ink in the centre of the upper margin, which
                           was added before the two leaves containing initials at liturgical
                           divisions were excised (see ‘Provenance’).</foliation>
                        <collation> (fols. i–iii) fol. i is a paper fly-leaf conjoint with the upper
                           pastedown; fol. ii is an 18th-century laid paper fly-leaf; fol. iii is a
                           strip of paper pasted to fol. ii | (fols. 1–6) I (6) | (fols. 7–54) II–V
                           (12) | (fols. 55–65) VI (12−1) missing 4 | (fols. 66–76) VII (12−1)
                           missing 11 | (fols. 77–196) VIII–XVII (12) | (fols. 197–206) XVIII (10) |
                           (fols. 207–218) XIX (12) | (fols. 219–229) XX (10+1) fol. 229 probably
                           originally belonged to the next quire | (fols. 230–236) XXI (6) probably
                           originally a quire of 8, of which the last leaf is missing and the first
                           leaf is bound with the previous quire | (fols. 237–238) fol. 237 is an
                           18th-century laid paper fly-leaf; fol. 238 is a paper fly-leaf conjoint
                           with the lower pastedown. Original (?) leaf signatures survive in some
                           quires (clearest in quires 4, 5, 17 and 19); very faint traces of quire
                           signatures in plummet Roman numerals are occasionally discernible at the
                           ends of quires (e.g. quires 9 and 14); 17th-century (?) quire signatures
                           in ink are on the first recto of each quire, including fols. 207r, 219r
                           and 230r (see ‘Collation’ above)</collation>




                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout rulingMedium="leadpoint" columns="1" writtenLines="17">Ruled in
                           plummet for the tops and bottoms of minims, with double vertical and
                           horizontal bounding lines, extending the full height of page; 17 lines
                           per page; written below the top line; written space: <dimensions
                              type="written" unit="mm">
                              <height quantity="136">c. 136</height>
                              <width>80</width>
                           </dimensions></layout>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc>
                     <handNote execution="formata" script="textualisNorthern">Large formal Gothic
                        book hand, black ink</handNote>
                  </handDesc>
                  <decoDesc>
                     <!-- <summary>Related to the style of <persName key="person_95824803" role="art"
                           >Honoré</persName>'s atelier, according to <ref
                           target="https://catalog.hathitrust.org/Record/000468709">Pächt and
                           Alexander</ref> (<ref
                           target="https://catalog.hathitrust.org/Record/000468709">Pächt and
                           Alexander</ref> i. 539, pl. XLI), but rejected by N. Morgan in
                           <title>Bodleian Library Record</title> 21 (2009), 62–74.</summary>-->

                     <decoNote type="monogram">KL monograms in the calendar in pink and blue with
                        white tracery ornament, on gold backgrounds, with coiled tendrils and
                        foliage extending into the margins.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="histInit">8-line historiated initials in gold frames, with
                        scenes on gold backgrounds, decorated with coiled tendrils and foliage
                        extending into the margins. The Beatus-initial occupies over half a page and
                        has a full border. The Beatus-initial and the initial for psalm 97 have been
                        retouched. <list>
                           <item>fol. 7r Psalm 1 (initial B(eatus)) King David playing harp between
                              two buildings in the upper part; David and Goliath in the lower
                              part.</item>
                           <item>(full border) Gold, blue and pink bars, decorated with coiled
                              tendrils and foliage; hounds chasing a deer in the bas-de-page.</item>
                           <item>fol. 37r Psalm 26 (initial D(ominus)) The Anointing of David:
                              seated, crowned David; standing Samuel, holding oil.</item>
                           <item>fol. 95r Psalm 68 (initial S(aluum)) Nude King David praying in
                              waters in the lower part; half-figure of Christ with cruciform halo,
                              holding an orb and blessing in the upper part.</item>
                           <item>fol. 118v Psalm 80 (initial E(xultate)) King David playing four
                              bells, his harp hanging next to him on the horizontal bar of the
                              initial.</item>
                           <item>fol. 141r Psalm 97 (initial C(antate)) Three tonsured clerics
                              singing from a book open on a lectern.</item>
                           <item> fol. 164v Psalm 109 (initial D(ixit)) Trinity: two seated figures
                              with cruciform halos, holding books and blessing; nimbed white dove
                              descending from above.</item>
                        </list></decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="border">Border: see above.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="decInit">3-line initial at the beginning of the
                        litany.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="decInit">2-line blue and pink initials on blue, pink and
                        sometimes gold backgrounds, with white tracery ornament, decorated with
                        coiled tendrils extending into the margins, as well as foliage, animal
                        heads, grotesques, rabbits, birds and gold discs at the beginnings of
                        psalms, canticles and prayers.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="flourInit">1-line alternating gold and blue initials with
                        contrasting blue and red penwork at the beginnings of periods and
                        verses.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="flourInit">Gold, red and blue penwork borders in the lower
                        margin on every page.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="lineFill">Line-endings with floral and geometric designs,
                        usually in gold and blue. Line-ending with a grotesque on gold background on
                        fol. 7r.</decoNote>

                  </decoDesc>
                  <bindingDesc>

                     <binding notAfter="1761" notBefore="1681">
                        <p> Soranzo’s binding: parchment over pasteboard; small stiff flaps on the
                           fore-edges of covers. ‘105’ written in black ink on the spine. Brown
                           leather label on the spine with gilt lettering ‘PSALTER. || DAVIDICUM ||
                           ETC. || COD . MEMB.’. Discoloration left by another (Bodleian (?)) label
                           on the lower part of the spine. Sewn on four cords. Pastedowns and
                           fly-leaves of paper with burgundy, purple and yellow floral designs
                           (carta bassanese). Further fly-leaves made of 18th-century laid paper; no
                           watermarks. </p>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="1275" notBefore="1250">13th century,
                        third quater</origDate>
                     <origPlace>
                        <country key="place_1000070">French</country>,
                           <region>North-Central</region> (?) </origPlace>
                  </origin>
                  <provenance>Made in north-central France (?). The calendar has many saints
                     venerated in France, but is not particularly specific. Morgan (2009) suggests
                     the Oise region as a possible place of origin. Pächt and Alexander (1966–73)
                     point out that the style of illumination is related to Honoré’s atelier, but
                     this is rejected by Morgan (2009). Vitzthum (1907) argues that the illumination
                     is related to a group of manuscripts which he located in Reims. </provenance>
                  <provenance>A 16th-century Italian owner foliated the volume, numbered psalms in
                     Arabic numerals and wrote a note on fol. 236r, recording folio numbers for the
                     seven Penitential Psalms: ‘Modo &amp; numero datrouare esette salmi
                     penitentiali ...’. The psalter also contains added psalm numbers in Roman
                     numerals, which may be in the same or possibly an earlier hand. </provenance>
                  <provenance><persName role="fmo" key="person_308770014">Jacopo Soranzo (1686–1761)</persName>: binding. After Soranzo’s death by about
                     1780 at Cá Cornèr at San Maurizio (Mitchell, 1969). </provenance>
                  <provenance>A description of the manuscript in Latin on a strip of paper pasted to
                     fol. ii verso (fol. iii). The description is in an Italian, 18th-century (?)
                     hand, but not the hand of Canonici or any of the earlier owners and librarians
                     whose handwriting is illustrated in Mitchell (1969). Similar descriptions in
                     the same hand are also found in MS. Canon. Bibl. Lat. 42, MS. Canon. Bibl. Lat.
                     85, MS. Canon. Pat. Lat. 88, MS. Add. D. 47, MS. Canon. Liturg. 155, MS. Canon.
                     Liturg. 377 and MS. Canon. Liturg. 393.</provenance>
                  <provenance/>
                  <provenance><persName role="fmo" key="person_2384880">Matteo Luigi Canonici of Venice (1727–c. 1806)</persName>: bought soon after
                     1780. </provenance>
                  <acquisition when="1817">Bodleian Library: bought in 1817 from Canonici’s nephew Giovanni
                     Perissinotti. </acquisition>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>Elizabeth Solopova, <title>Latin Liturgical Psalters in the Bodleian
                              Library: A Select Catalogue</title> (Oxford, 2013), pp. 292–7.
                           Previously described in the Summary Catalogue. <listBibl>
                              <bibl facs="aaz0361.gif" type="SC">Summary Catalogue, vol. 4, p.
                                 342</bibl>
                           </listBibl>
                        </source>
                     </recordHist>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <surrogates>
                     <bibl subtype="partial" type="digital-facsimile">
                        <ref
                           target="https://digital.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/objects/287cec00-8f54-4902-af9f-3c02e51076e9/">
                           <title>Digital Bodleian</title>
                        </ref>
                        <note>(1 image from 35mm slides)</note>
                     </bibl>
                  </surrogates>
                  <listBibl type="WRAPPER">
                     <listBibl type="PRINT">
                        <head>Select bibliography to 2009:</head>

                        <bibl>Summary catalogue, vol. 4, no. 19259.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Frere, no. 462.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Vitzthum von Eckstaedt, B. G., <title>Die Pariser Miniaturmalerei von
                              der Zeit des hl. Ludwig bis zu Philipp von Valois und ihr Verhältnis
                              zur Malerei in Nordwesteuropa</title> (Leipzig: Verlag von Quelle
                           &amp; Meyer, 1907), pp. 66–7.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Nordenfalk, C., ‘Insulare und kontinentale
                              Psalterillustrationen aus dem XIII. Jahrhundert’, <title>Acta
                              archaeologica</title> 10 (1939), pp. 107–20, at p. 120.</bibl>
                        <bibl>S. J. P. van Dijk, <title>Latin Liturgical Manuscripts in the Bodleian
                           Library, Oxford, vol. 2: Office Books</title> (typescript, 1957),
                           <citedRange unit="page" from="73" to="73">p. 73</citedRange>
                        </bibl>
                        <bibl>Millar, E. G., <title>The Parisian miniaturist Honoré</title> (London:
                           Faber and Faber, 1959).</bibl>
                        <bibl>Pächt and Alexander (1966–73), vol. 1, no. 539, pl. XLI.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Folda, J., <title>Crusader manuscript illumination at Saint-Jean
                              d’Acre, 1275–1291</title> (Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press,
                           1976), p. 148 n. 139.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Morgan (2009), pp. 64, 65, 67, 72 n. 12.</bibl>


                       
                     </listBibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2024-06">Encode full description from Solopova catalogue.</change>
         <change when="2017-07-01">First online publication.</change>
         <change when="2017-05-25">
            <persName>James Cummings</persName> Up-converted the markup using <ref
               target="https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl"
               >https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl</ref>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
