<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="manuscript_8757">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>MS. Rawl. poet. 163</title>
            <title type="collection">MSS. Rawl. poet. (Rawlinson poetry)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Description</resp>
               <resp when="2024-03">Cataloguer</resp>
               <persName>Charlotte Ross</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </publisher>
            <idno type="msID">MS_Rawl_poet_163</idno>
            <idno type="collection">Rawl_poet</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="MS_Rawl_poet_163" xml:lang="en">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <region type="county">Oxfordshire</region>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <institution>University of Oxford</institution>
                  <repository>Bodleian Library</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">MS. Rawl. poet. 163</idno>
                  <idno type="ieArk">ark:29072/x0rx913p593q</idno><idno type="crArk">ark:29072/x0rv042s75sx</idno><altIdentifier type="internal">
                     <idno type="SCN">14655</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
               <head>Geoffrey Chaucer, <title>Troilus and Criseyde</title> and the unique copy of <title>Balade to Rosamond</title> - fifteenth century, second half</head>
               <msContents>
                  <textLang mainLang="enm">Middle English</textLang>
                  <msItem n="1" xml:id="MS_Rawl_poet_163-item1">
                     <locus from="1r" to="113v">(fols. 1r–113v)</locus>
                     <author key="person_100185203">Geoffrey Chaucer</author>
                     <title key="work_1666">Troilus and Criseyde</title>
                     <incipit><supplied>T</supplied>he doleful sorow of Troilus to tellen <lb/> That was the kyng p<ex>ri</ex>amus sone of Troye</incipit>
                     <explicit>So take vs Ihesus for thy m<ex>er</ex>cy digne <lb/> ffor loue of mayd &amp; modyr thyn benygne</explicit>
                     <finalRubric>Tregentyll { Heer endith the book of Troylus and of Cresseyde } Chaucer</finalRubric>
                     <note>M. C. Seymour places MS Rawl. poet. 163 in <q>Subgroup 2(a): altered states of text</q> category, with St John's College Cambridge, MS L.1 (<title>Catalogue of Chaucer Manuscripts</title>, 1995). Scribes contribute atypical marginal summaries in Middle English throughout the text, presented as glosses, and Latin glosses to Ovid, Statius, and notes to the <q>Auctor</q>. Also contains a unique stanza after Book II, line 1750. Blank space for one stanza is left on folio 26v without any textual omission.
                        <p>Imperfect: <list>
                        <item>Omits (without gap) the proems to Books II, III, and IV, and the Statius argument (V.1498) - this is not due to a physical defect in the manuscript;</item>
                        <item>Book I ll.281-343 missing due to loss of fifth leaf in the first quire (unfoliated, between folios 4 and 5);</item>
                        <item>Book II ll.170-201 and 207-248 damaged and missing due to torn condition of folio 17;</item>
                        <item>Book IV ll.981-982 damaged due to torn condition of folio 80;</item>
                        <item>Book V ll.421-560 missing due to loss of two adjacent leaves in the eleventh quire (unfoliated, between folios 95 and 96);</item>
                     </list></p>
                        <p><bibl type="repertory"><ref target="https://www.dimev.net/record.php?recID=5248#wit-5248-5"><title>DIMEV</title> 5248</ref></bibl></p></note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="2" xml:id="MS_Rawl_poet_163-item2">
                     <locus from="114r">(fol. 114r)</locus>
                     <author key="person_100185203">Geoffrey Chaucer</author>
                     <title key="work_1662">Balade to Rosamond</title>
                     <incipit>Madame ye ben of al beaute shryne <lb/> As fer as cercled is the mapamonde</incipit>
                     <explicit>Do what you lyst I wyl yo<ex>ur</ex> thral be founde <lb/> Though ye to me ne do no daliance</explicit>
                     <finalRubric>tregentil --//-- chaucer</finalRubric>
                     <note>Twenty-four lines, on an additional but contemporary singleton and in the hand of Scribe 1 (see <q>Hands</q> below). This is the only witness of the text. Published in Walter Skeat, <title>Twelve Facsimiles of Old English Manuscripts</title> (Oxford, 1892); and first edited in Skeat, <q>An Unknown Poem by Chaucer</q>, <title>The Athenaeum</title> (London, 1891), 1.440 - a copy of this article is pasted onto the first end leaf at the rear of the manuscript (fols. 115-116).
                        <p><bibl type="repertory"><ref target="https://www.dimev.net/record.php?recID=3317#wit-3317-1"><title>DIMEV</title> 3317</ref></bibl></p></note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="3" xml:id="MS_Rawl_poet_163-item3">
                     <locus from="114v">(fol. 114v)</locus>
                     <note>blank.</note>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="chart">
                        <support>paper</support>
                        <extent><seg type="leaf"><measure type="laterEndleaf" quantity="3">iii (modern paper end leaf from 1985 rebinding)</measure> + <measure type="laterEndleaf" quantity="3">iii (modern paper end leaf from 19<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> century rebinding)</measure> + <measure type="leaf" quantity="115">115 (paper)</measure> + <measure type="laterEndleaf" quantity="3">iii (modern paper end leaf from 19<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> century rebinding)</measure> + <measure type="laterEndleaf" quantity="3">iii (modern paper end leaf from 1985 rebinding)</measure></seg>.  <dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                           <height max="291" min="288">288–291</height>
                           <width>206</width>
                        </dimensions></extent>
                        <foliation>(three leaves unfoliated), i-iii in modern pencil, 1-114 in 18th-century ink (99 is double), 115-119 in modern pencil, (three leaves unfoliated). </foliation>                        
                        <collation>1<hi rend="superscript">10-1</hi> (fifth leaf missing with loss of text, ff.1-9), 2<hi rend="superscript">10</hi>(eighth leaf damaged with loss of text; and first, second, ninth, and tenth leaves are singletons, ff.10-19), 3<hi rend="superscript">12</hi> (third and tenth leaves are singletons, ff.20-31), 4<hi rend="superscript">12-1</hi> (twelfth leaf missing without loss of text, ff.32-42), 5<hi rend="superscript">10</hi> (ff.43-52), 6-10<hi rend="superscript">8</hi> (ff.53-92), 11<hi rend="superscript">8-2</hi> (fourth and fifth leaves missing with loss of text, ff.93-98), 12<hi rend="superscript">8-1</hi> (second leaf foliated 99b torn with stub remaining and with loss of text, ff.99a-105), 13<hi rend="superscript">8+1</hi> (ninth leaf contemporary singleton addition, ff.106-114). See Barker-Benfield, 1986.
                           <p><catchwords>Catchwords present, predominantly in the hand of the scribe of the page (with the exception of quire 3 where scribe 3 copies the catchword on folio 31v).</catchwords></p>
                           <p><signatures>Quire signatures visible on quires 1-5 and 11-13, partially trimmed. Predominantly copied in the hand of the scribe of the page (with the exception of quire 13, folio 107r, which is copied by scribe 3). The first two quires only have alphabetical signatures, hereafter signatures number leaves only.</signatures></p>
                           <p><watermark>Six watermarks present, similar to: (1) Piccard 81161 - Bull’s head with eyes, nose and further face features, above star, rod consisting of one line, outline of the nose below open (Utrecht, 1472), folios 6-9; (2) Piccard 74484 - Bull’s head with eyes and nostrils, above star consisting of one line, without further additional motifs (Veldenz, 1457), folios 11, 12, 15, 16; (3) Piccard 30013 -  Letter Y, cross above, tail consisting of two lines, with cloverleaf, without watermark tangent to chainline, left and right vertical stroke separated, descender on the left vertical stroke (Breda, 1458), folios 19, 29, 55, 57, 59, 60, 62-64, 68, 70, 76-80, 85-87, 89, 95, 97, 98, 100, 101, 105-107, 110, 111; (4) similar to Briquet 4401 - column (Naples, 1456), folios 20, 22, 26-28, 30, 32, 34, 36, 37, 40, 42, 43, 45, 51; (5) Bear with claws, unidentified, folios 47, 49; (6) Piccard 124169 - Fabulous creature, unicorn, horizontal, with dash on the horn (Metz, 1463), folios 71-72.</watermark></p></collation>
                        <condition>Page edges fragile throughout. The manuscript has suffered water damage to the top and bottom of most folios with occasional damage to text, especially affecting the second quires. Insect damage to folios 89-94 and 99a-114. Folios 5, 10, 11, 18, 19, 22, 24, and 114 damaged at the gutter reattached using modern paper (likely in the 1985 conservation at the Bodleian Library - see <title>Binding</title>). Gutters reinforced at folios 9-10 and 21-22 using modern paper. Folios 17, 80, and 99b torn with loss of text - lines lost recorded in <title>Item 1</title>. Folios 21, 22, 82, and 114 torn with modern repairs.</condition>
                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc><layout columns="1" writtenLines="35"> Layout somewhat variable according to scribe, typically 35 written lines but on occasion as many as 52. Written space: </layout>
                        <layout>Scribe 1 <dimensions type="written" unit="mm"><height>220–230</height> <width>130</width> </dimensions></layout><layout> Scribe 2 <dimensions type="written" unit="mm"><height>230</height> <width>100–120</width> </dimensions></layout><layout> Scribe 3 <dimensions type="written" unit="mm"><height>205–210</height> <width>90–110</width> </dimensions></layout><layout>Scribe 4 <dimensions type="written" unit="mm"><height>190–210</height> <width>90–110</width> </dimensions></layout><layout> Scribe 5 <dimensions type="written" unit="mm"><height>205–250</height> <width>110–120</width> </dimensions> (excluding glosses, which are unruled) </layout></layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc hands="5"><handNote script="cursivaAntiquior">Five hands collaborating closely, all writing in distinct scripts with mixtures of Anglicana and Secretary influences. Scribes 2 and 3 have historically been identified as the same individual, see Root 1914, Seymour 1995, and Windeatt 2023, but are here distinguished as two different hands:<list>
                     <item><hi rend="bold">Scribe 1:</hi> folios 1r-9v (Book I ll.1-700), 16r last four lines and 16v-19v (Book II ll.118-433), 29r-v (Book II ll.1044-1113), 59r last two lines and 59v-114r (Book III ll.1373-V.1869, and <title>Balade to Rosamond</title> on folio 114r), leaf signatures to quires 1, 11, 12, 13, and catchwords to quires 1(10v), 2(20v), 6-12. Notable graphs are the single compartment lower-case <q>a</q>, secretary <q>g</q> with separate cross bar, short kidney shaped <q>s</q> in final position, and short zetoid <q>&amp;</q> with circular flourish. The first letter of the line is often flourished, and occasionally the first initial of the page.</item>
                     <item><hi rend="bold">Scribe 2:</hi> folios 10r-15v and 16r except last four lines (Book I ll.701-Book II ll.117), leaf signatures to quire 2. Notable graphs are tall slanted upper-case <q>A</q>, short sigma <q>s</q> with pronounced horizontal stroke in final position, and distinctive <q>&amp;</q> with curled descender below and detached flourish and dot above (similar to type 93 according to Tschichold, 1953).</item> 
                       <item><hi rend="bold">Scribe 3:</hi> folios 43r-51r and 51v first nine lines (Book III ll.306-912), leaf signatures to quire 5 and one signature of 13 (f.107r), and catchword to quire 3. Notable graphs are tall upright upper-case <q>A</q>, elongated sigma <q>s</q> with large body in final position, and short cross-shape <q>&amp;</q> with curved descender (type 94 according to Tschichold, 1953). Descenders on the final line of each page are often elaborately flourished.</item>
                     <item><hi rend="bold">Scribe 4:</hi> folios 20r-28v (Book II ll.434-1043), 30r-42v (Book II ll.1114-Book III ll.305), catchword on folio 31v, and leaf signatures to quires 3 and 4. Notable graphs are secretary <q>g</q> with separate cross bar and right curving descender, short unlooped <q>h</q> with short curved descender and ascender, and a mixture of simple short zetoid <q>&amp;</q> (type 83 according to Tschichold, 1953) and short cross-shape <q>&amp;</q> with curved descender (type 94 according to Tschichold, 1953), as scribe 3. The first letter of each line is flourished, and the first letter of each page is occasionally decorated with elaborate scrolls in black and red.</item>
                     <item><hi rend="bold">Scribe 5:</hi> folios 51v except first nine lines and 52r-58v and 59r except last two lines (Book III ll.913-1372), and catchword to quire 5. Notable graphs are slanted short sigma <q>s</q> with broken stroke in final position, horned <q>p</q> with open body and angled descender, short form of <q>r</q>, and short cross-shape <q>&amp;</q> with minimal descender (type 80 according to Tschichold, 1953). This hand writes with a thicker nib than the other hands in the manuscript. </item>
                  </list> Scribal stints do not align with points of textual division or physical divisions in the manuscript, with the exception of folio 29, a singleton copied by scribe 1 which is on a different paper stock to the rest of the quire.</handNote></handDesc>
                  <decoDesc>
                     <decoNote type="unfilled">Space for large capitals, unexecuted: two lines at I.1 (fol. 1r), four lines at II.50 (fol. 15v), two lines at IV.29 (fol. 66r), and two lines at V.1 (fol. 90r)</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="flourInit"> Flourished ascenders and descenders on folios 1r-9v (scribe 1 stint). Red braces to indicate the rhyme scheme and red inter-stanza divisions on folios 20r-28v and 30r-42v (scribe 4 stint) and 43r-47v (part of scribe 3 stint); glosses within these passages are occasionally but inconsistently framed and braced in red. Ornate flourished initials at with elaborate scroll work in black and red at page-beginnings on folios 23r-28v and 30r, 33v-41r, and 43v. </decoNote>
                  <decoNote type="rubrication">Rubricated rhyme braces, gloss braces and frames, flourishes to large initials, and inter-stanza divisions on folios 20r-28v and 30r-47r (Scribe 4 stints). </decoNote></decoDesc>
                  <additions>A fifteenth century hand annotates the outer margin of 71r with <q>hec indentura fact<ex>a</ex> int<ex>er</ex> Hen</q> in a display script.
                     <p>A mid-sixteenth century hand leaves annotations, pen trials, and marginal doodles throughout the manuscript. A phrase from the Book of Common Prayer is repeated throughout, in its most complete extent on folio 53r: <q>o lord god the father of heauen haue mercy upo<ex>n</ex></q>, also on folios 2v and 114r.</p>
                     <p>A sixteenth (?) century hand records a poem in the margin of folio 99(a)r beginning <q>If I could red this pom<damage></damage> and it well understand <lb/> I thinke I were as happy as anye in this lande</q>. </p></additions>
                  <bindingDesc><binding notAfter="1986" notBefore="1984"><p>The manuscript was rebound by the Bodleian in 1985. The boards from the former binding are housed with the volume in a separate folder. These boards are the typical 18<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> century Rawlinson binding of marbled paper boards with parchment spine lining and paper pastedown. The spine lining shows evidence of six raised sewing supports in the former binding. Six paper end leaves from this binding are still present in the manuscript. A note from Bruce Barker-Benfield on the final of these end leaves (foliated 119) records that <q>One further flyleaf of this late 19<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> cent. paper after 119 was removed and destroyed in the rebinding of 1985</q>. Barker-Benfield also conducted a collation survey of the manuscript after rebinding, now housed in the Bodley Refs, LVI.16. No other conservation records are preserved.</p> 
                     <p>The current binding (1985) comprises paper boards with external bevels covered in grey paper, with white leather spine lining. The spine shows four single raised sewing supports with projected spine tabs and sewn endbands in white thread. During the 1985 rebinding, paper sewing guards were added to the gutters of folios 9-10 and 21-22, and the gutters of folios 1-2, 5, were reinforced.</p>
                  <p>Parchment sewing supports are preserved on folios 14-15, 25-26, 37-38, 56-57, 64-65, 72-73, 80-81, 88-89, 101-102, and 109-110. These are made of recycled documentary material of the fifteenth century, which were formerly adhered to the paper folios. They likely pre-date the Bodleian and Rawlinson bindings, and are possibly contemporary to the production of the manuscript. </p></binding></bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="1500" notBefore="1450">second half of the 15th century</origDate>
                     <origPlace>
                        <country key="place_7002445">English</country>
                     </origPlace>
                  </origin>
                  <provenance>Several clues to the manuscript's origin can be found on the recycled parchment sewing guards, though fragmentary. The majority of fragments were cut from vertical strips with small portions of text running horizontally. The names <q>Rogerius</q>, <q>Ricardus</q>, <q>Johanus</q>, <q>Thomas</q>, <q>Simon</q> and <q>William</q> can be discerned, without legible surnames. Several of the parchment strips are cut from larger records, either manorial payment records or court rolls of fines, with columns of prices still visible. Comparable records can be found in Trinity College Cambridge, MS O.9.38 (item 5), the accounts of Glastonbury Abbey dated 1440-60; Christ Church Oxford, MS Archives xxix.b.13 (folios 4r-17r), the  accounts of the Priory of Daventry dated 1483-1492; and Dulwich Manor Court Rolls, Roll 10, record of tenants' paymento to the lord of the manor dated 1444. 
                     <p>Other fragments resemble legal documents or charters, which likely pertained to an estate that contained a mill or mill house as the word <q>molendin<ex>us</ex></q> can be seen in a strip of Latin text at folios 14-15. The sewing guard at folios 101-2 was cut from a horizontal strip with text running vertically, and contains several lines of Latin text that resembles a jury presentment about a road (<q>via</q>). The phrases <q>portam de Westgate</q> and <q>venellam <gap></gap> Medlane</q> suggest a connection to Westgate and Medlane in Canterbury. Grants from the 13th and 14th centuries in Canterbury Cathedral mention both places by name in a comparable format, e.g. CCA-DCc/ChAnt/M/1; CCA-DCc/ChAnt/C/1042B.</p></provenance>
                  <provenance>Due to the collaborative nature of the scribes' copying, the volume of other contemporary or near-contemporary hands in the margins, the quantity of paper stocks, and the nature of the recycled sewing guards, the manuscript was likely produced in a community of educated literary individuals working closely together, plausibly a religious institution or household that would have access to exemplars to copy and disposable documentary materials for binding.</provenance>
                  <provenance>The meaning of the collophon <q>Tregentil</q> on folios 113v and 114r is unclear. Skeat (1891) suggests it is the name of the scribe but this is speculative. On this debate, see Frese 1982, Brusendorff 1925, MacCracken 1908, and Skeat 1891.</provenance>
                  <provenance>A marginal note on folio 80v records <q><persName role="sgn" key="person_4857">Thomas Howlet</persName> Writ This in the yere of oure Lord god 1568</q>. The same hand records <q>Thomas Howlet</q> on folio 99r after the explicit to <title>Troilus</title>. Howlet may be identified as a descendent of the de Howlett family of Suffolk, possibly Thomas Howlett (d. 1619) whose will is recorded in TNA PROB 11/134/410.</provenance>
                  <provenance notAfter="1755" notBefore="1690" resp="#MMM">The manuscript was later owned by <persName key="person_1203" role="fmo">Thomas Rawlinson (1681–1725)</persName>. It is recorded in the inventory of Thomas Rawlinson's collection in BodL, MS Rawl. C. 937 as item 192.</provenance>
                  <provenance>The manuscript is not listed in the sale catalogue of Thomas Rawlinson's collections by Thomas Ballard in 1733–4, <title>Codicum Manuscriptoru, Bibliothecae Rawlinsonianae Catalogus; cum Appendice Impressorum; in omni fere Facultate et Lingua</title>. However, it must have been acquired by <persName key="person_47563478">Richard Rawlinson (1690–1755) after his brother's death in 1725.</persName></provenance>
                  <acquisition resp="#MMM" when="1755">The manuscript was bequeathed to the Bodleian in 1755 by Richard Rawlinson on his death.</acquisition>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>Description by Charlotte Ross (Mar. 2024). Previously described in the Summary Catalogue (1895). <ref target="https://medieval.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/about"><listBibl>
                              <bibl facs="aas0333.gif" type="SC">Summary Catalogue, Vol. 3, p. 318</bibl>
                           </listBibl></ref>
                           <listBibl type="WRAPPER">
                              <listBibl type="PRINT">
                                 <head>Printed descriptions:</head>
                                 <bibl>Barker-Benfield, Bruce, <title>Unpublished collation diagram of MS Rawl. Poet. 163</title>, Bodley Refs LVI.16 (1986)</bibl>
                                 <bibl>Brusendorff, Aaga, <title>The Chaucer Tradition</title> (London, 1925), 439</bibl>
                                 <bibl>Frese, Dolores Warwick, <q>The ‘Nun’s Priest’s Tale:’ Chaucer’s Identified Master Piece?</q>, <title>The Chaucer Review</title> 16:4 (1982): 330–43</bibl>
                                 <bibl>MacCracken, Henry Noble, <q>'Tregentil Chaucer' and 'A. Godwhen'</q>, <title>The Athenaeum</title> 4192 (1980), 258</bibl>
                                 <bibl>Robert Kilburn Root, <title>The Manuscripts of Chaucer's Troilus: with Collotype Facsimiles of the Various Handwritings</title>, Chaucer Society vol. 98 (London, 1914)</bibl>
                                 <bibl>Skeat, W. W., <q>To Rosemounde</q>, <title>The Athenaeum</title> 742 (1891), 440</bibl>
                                 <bibl>Seymour, M. C.,  <title>A Catalogue of Chaucer Manuscripts, 1: Works before the Canterbury Tales</title> (Aldershot, 1995), 65-6</bibl>
                                 <bibl>Tschichold, Jan, <title>Formenwandlungen der &amp; -Zeichen</title> (Frankfurt, 1953) </bibl>
                                 <bibl>Windeatt, Barry,  <q>Text</q>, <title>Oxford Guides to Chaucer: Troilus and Criseyde</title>, 2nd edn (Oxford, 2023) </bibl></listBibl></listBibl>
                        </source>
                     </recordHist>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl type="WRAPPER">
                     <listBibl type="INTERNET">
                        <head>Online resources:</head>
                        <bibl><ref target="https://www.medievalscribes.com/index.php?browse=manuscripts&amp;&amp;id=53&amp;nav=off"><title>Late Medieval English Scribes</title></ref></bibl>
                     </listBibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2024-03-08">Description by <persName>Charlotte Ross</persName>. Revised with consultation of original.</change>
         <change when="2019-10-31" xml:id="MMM"><persName>Toby Burrows/Mapping Manuscript Migrations</persName>Provenance and acquisition information added using <ref target="https://github.com/mapping-manuscript-migrations/oxford-tei-updates/blob/master/update_oxford_prov.rb">https://github.com/mapping-manuscript-migrations/oxford-tei-updates/blob/master/update_oxford_prov.rb</ref> in collaboration with the <ref target="http://mappingmanuscriptmigrations.org/">Mapping Manuscript Migrations</ref> project.</change>
         <change when="2017-07-01">First online publication.</change>
         <change when="2017-05-25"><persName>James Cummings</persName> Up-converted the markup using <ref target="https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl">https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl</ref></change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>