<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="manuscript_4854">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>MS. Fairfax 2</title>
            <title type="collection">MSS. Fairfax</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Description</resp>
               <persName>Elizabeth Solopova</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Revision</resp>
               <persName>Andrew Dunning</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </publisher>
            <idno type="msID">MS_Fairfax_2</idno>
            <idno type="collection">Fairfax</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="MS_Fairfax_2" xml:lang="en">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <region type="county">Oxfordshire</region>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <institution>University of Oxford</institution>
                  <repository>Bodleian Library</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">MS. Fairfax 2</idno>
                  <idno type="ieArk">ark:29072/x0dr26xx5535</idno><idno type="crArk">ark:29072/x06969z16255</idno><altIdentifier type="internal">
                     <idno type="SCN">3882</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents>
                  <textLang mainLang="enm" otherLangs="la">Middle English with Latin</textLang>
                  <msItem>
                     <note>Fols. i–ii are paper flyleaves, blank apart from modern notes.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="1">
                     <locus from="1r" to="385r">(fols. 1r–385r)</locus>
                     <title key="work_10451" type="desc">Old and New Testaments in the Later Version of the Wycliffite Bible with prefatory epistles</title>
                     <note>New Testament has usual the Later Version of the Wycliffite Bible prologues, Old Testament has prologues in the Earlier Version of the Wycliffite Bible, apart from the prologues to Baruch and Isaiah which are in the Later Version of the Wycliffite Bible; lacks prologues to Jeremiah and Wisdom. Running titles in red on both rectos and versos, consisting of the titles of books preceded by blue paraphs. Brief notes summarising the contents of the text in the hand of the original scribe in the upper margin (such notes are largely absent in the part following the calendar-lectionary, see below). Chapter numbers, most consisting of <q>cᵐ</q> followed by a Roman numeral. Rubrics in black, underlined in red. Alternative translations and crossreferences to other biblical books in the margins; glosses in the margins, indicating the subject matter, comparing the text to the Hebrew version and explaining individual words. Most text in the margins is in the hand of the main scribe, but some is in other contemporary hands. Added material within the text is occasionally underlined in red. Corrections by the main scribe and in a contemporary hand. Added drawings of pointing hands and <q>nota</q> in the margins, as well as notes such as <q>mark wel þis booc</q>
                        <locus>(fols. 201r, 210r)</locus>, late 15th century. Erasures of medieval or early modern inscriptions (e.g., fols. 279v, 303r, 388v); margins occasionally cut out presumably to remove the text they contained.</note>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="1r">(fol. 1r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Prefatory epistles</title>
                        <rubric>Here bigynneþ þe pistel of seynt Ierom prest of alle þe bokis of goddis storie þat is clepid a prolog</rubric>
                        <incipit>Broþer ambrose to me</incipit>
                        <incipit>I haue taken desired epistles</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="3r">(fol. 3r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Genesis</title>
                        <rubric>Here endeþ þe prolog now bigynneþ genesis</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="18r">(fol. 18r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Exodus</title>
                        <rubric>Here endeþ genesis se now exodus</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="30r">(fol. 30r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Leviticus</title>
                        <rubric>Heere endeþ exodus se now leuyticus</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="39r">(fol. 39r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Numbers</title>
                        <rubric>Here endeþ Leuiticus see now þe book of Noumbre</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="51v">(fol. 51v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Deuteronomy</title>
                        <rubric>Heere endeþ þe book of Noumbre &amp; þe lawe Se now Deutronomy</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="62r">(fol. 62r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Prologue to Joshua</title>
                        <rubric>Heere endeþ Pentaceucon se now þe prolog of Iosue</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="62v">(fol. 62v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Joshua</title>
                        <rubric>Here endeþ þe prolog se now þe book of Iosue</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="69v">(fol. 69v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Judges</title>
                        <rubric>Here endeþ Iosue se now þe book of doomes</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="77r">(fol. 77r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Ruth</title>
                        <rubric>Here endeþ þe book of doomes Se now þe booc of Ruth</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="78r">(fol. 78r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Prologue to 1 Kings</title>
                        <rubric>Her endeþ þe booc of Ruth Se now þe prolog of þe bokis foure of kyngis</rubric>
                        <incipit>Forsoþe þe tonge</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="78v">(fol. 78v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">1 Kings</title>
                        <rubric>Her endeþ þe prolog Se now þe firste book of kinges</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="88v">(fol. 88v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">2 Kings</title>
                        <rubric>Here endeþ þe firste book of kinges Se now þe seconde</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="97r">(fol. 97r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">3 Kings</title>
                        <rubric>Here endeþ þe seconde book of kinges Se now þe þridde</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="107v">(fol. 107v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">4 Kings</title>
                        <rubric>Heere endeþ þe þridde book of kinges Se now þe fourþe</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="116v">(fol. 116v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Prologue to 1 Chronicles</title>
                        <rubric>Heere eendiþ þe fourþe book of kinges Se now þe prolog bifore Paralipomenon</rubric>
                        <incipit>If þe making of þe seuenti</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="117r">(fol. 117r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">1 Chronicles</title>
                        <rubric>Heere eendeþ þe prolog Se now þe firste book of Paralipomenon</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="125v">(fol. 125v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">2 Chronicles</title>
                        <rubric>Here endeþ þe firste book of Paralipomenon Se now þe seconde</rubric>
                        <note>Prayer of Manasseh <locus from="136v" to="136v">(fol. 136v)</locus> without a rubric.</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="137r">(fol. 137r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Prologue to 1 Ezra</title>
                        <rubric>Here endeþ þe seconde book of Paralipomenon Se now þe prolog of Esdre</rubric>
                        <incipit>Wheþer it be hardere</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="137v">(fol. 137v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Commendation of Ezra</title>
                        <rubric>Here folowiþ þe comendacioun of Esdre</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="137v">(fol. 137v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">1 Ezra</title>
                        <rubric>Here eendeþ þe prolog of Esdre Se now þe book</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="140v">(fol. 140v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">2 Ezra</title>
                        <rubric>Heere eendeþ þe firste book of Esdre See now þe seconde book of Esdre or Neemye</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="145r">(fol. 145r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Prologue to Tobit</title>
                        <rubric>Here endeþ þe seconde book of Esdre or Neemye See now þe prolog of Tobie</rubric>
                        <incipit>To cromacie</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="145r">(fol. 145r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Tobit</title>
                        <rubric>Here endeþ þe prolog of tobie Se now þe booc</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="148r">(fol. 148r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Prologue to Judith</title>
                        <rubric>Here endeþ þe book of Thobie Se now þe prolog of Iudith</rubric>
                        <incipit>Anentis þe ebrues</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="148v">(fol. 148v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Judith</title>
                        <rubric>Here endeþ þe prolog of Iudith Se now þe booc</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="152v">(fol. 152v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Prologue to Esther</title>
                        <rubric>Here endeþ þe book of Iudith Se now þe prolog of hester</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="152v">(fol. 152v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Esther</title>
                        <rubric>Here endeþ þe prolog of hester Se now þe book</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="156v">(fol. 156v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Prologue to Job</title>
                        <rubric>Heere eendeþ þe book of hester Se now þe prolog of Ioob</rubric>
                        <incipit>I am constreyned bi alle</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="157r">(fol. 157r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Job</title>
                        <rubric>Here endeþ þe prolog of Ioob Se now þe booc</rubric>
                        <note>Gloss: <q>Iob was a verri man in kinde…</q>.</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="165v">(fol. 165v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Prologue to psalms</title>
                        <rubric>Heere eendeþ þe booc of Ioob Se now þe prolog of þe sawter</rubric>
                        <incipit>Whane it is knowen</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="166r">(fol. 166r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Psalms</title>
                        <rubric>Here endeþ þe prolog of þe Sawter Se now þe booc</rubric>
                        <note>The psalms are laid out as prose, preceded by English titles and Latin incipits in black underlined in red. Psalm numbers in the margins in the original hand. Verses start with alternating 1-line red or blue initials. Title and other glosses in the margins of some psalms in a contemporary hand different from that of the main scribe. Liturgical divisions marked with larger initials at psalms 26, 38, 52, 68, 80, 97 and 109; <q>feria</q> followed by a number added in the margins at liturgical divisions in a 16th-century hand.</note>
                     </msItem>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="2">
                     <locus from="178r">(fol. 178r)</locus>
                     <title type="desc">A list in English of weekly canticles: <foreign rend="italic">Confitebor tibi domine</foreign>, <foreign rend="italic">Ego dixi</foreign>, <foreign rend="italic">Exultauit cor meum</foreign>, <foreign rend="italic">Cantemus domino</foreign>, <foreign rend="italic">Domine audiui</foreign>, <foreign rend="italic">Audite celi</foreign>; and daily canticles: <foreign rend="italic">Benedicite omnia opera, Benedictus dominus deus, Magnificat</foreign> and <foreign rend="italic">Nunc dimittis.</foreign></title>
                     <note>The entries for weekly canticles consist of a note (2- to 4-lines long) describing the contents and the circumstances of composition of each canticle, a Latin incipit and a reference to a biblical book and chapter. The entries for daily canticles consist of a Latin incipit and a reference to a biblical source. At the end <q>Here endeþ þe book of salmes</q> and, added in the hand responsible for the Athanasian Creed (see below), <q>blessed be þe holi trynite Amen amen</q>.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="3">
                     <locus from="187v">(fol. 187v)</locus>
                     <title type="desc">Athanasian Creed</title>
                     <note>In a different hand and ink, preceded by a Latin incipit</note>
                     <rubric>Se now Quicumque vult in engliȝssh þe wiche Attanasy a doctor of greke made</rubric>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="4">
                     <locus from="188r" to="193v">(fols. 188r–193v)</locus>
                     <title type="desc">Sarum calendar-lectionary in English</title>
                     <rubric>Se now þe kalender of alle Lessons Pistels &amp; Gospels of al þe ȝeer aftir þe vse of Salisbury</rubric>
                     <rubric>Ƿe effect of þis kalender is to knowe þe Lessons þe pistels &amp; gospellis as þei ben red in þe chirche aftir þe vse of salisbiri ffirst here aboue bigynneþ þe sundai wiþ inne þe vtas of twelf day &amp; þenne dominicals &amp; ferials suyng after eeff &amp; þenne þe feest of ascencion &amp; þe sundai wiþ inne þe vtas. &amp; þe vtas of ascencion &amp; þenne dominicals &amp; ferials suyng aftir þe trinite &amp; þenne aduent wiþ hise dominicals and ferials suyng</rubric>
                     <note>Golden numbers and the dominical letters followed by the names of feasts and saints’ days, followed by the entries for readings consisting of an indexing letter and an abbreviated title and chapter number of a biblical book, without the opening or closing words of a reading. The major feasts are in red, including Augustine of Canterbury (26 May). Does not include David, Chad, John of Beverley, Winifred or Frideswide (promulgated in 1415 under archbishop Chichele; see Pfaff, R. W., <title>The liturgy in medieval England: a history</title> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2009), pp. 440–1), which suggests that the manuscript pre-dates 1415 (see Provenance). The readings for the dominicals and ferials are listed at the end of each month. Contains all feasts characteristic of the Later Version of the Wycliffite Bible (Forshall, J. and Madden, F. (eds), <title>The Holy Bible … in the earliest English versions made from the Latin Vulgate by John Wycliffe and his followers</title>, 4 vols (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1850), vol. 4, pp. 683, 690–6). The translation of Edward the Confessor is entered as <q>of edmund</q> (13 October). Bertinus is added over an erasure in a contemporary hand (5 September, not in Forshall and Madden’s edition of the table of lections (1850), vol. 4, p. 694). Francis is added without readings (4 October), late 15th century. The feast of Thomas Becket and titles ‘pope’ are erased. Commemorations appear in the lower part of leaves containing October, November and December <locus from="192v" to="193r">(fols. 192v–193r)</locus>, in the following order: the Virgin Mary, Trinity, Holy Ghost, angles, peace, rain, <q>A man for him silf</q>, cross, <q>For briþern &amp; sistres</q>, clear weather, <q>In time of batel</q>, <q>For pestilence of beestis</q>, pilgrims, weddings, sinners, sick, dead.</note>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="194r">(fols. 194r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Prologue to Proverbs</title>
                        <rubric>Here bigynneþ þe preface of seint Ierome in þe book of prouerbis</rubric>
                        <incipit>To cromacie</incipit>
                        <note>More than one-third of the first column is left blank on fol. 194r.</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="194r">(fol. 194r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Proverbs</title>
                        <rubric>Here endeþ þe prolog of prouerbis Se now þe book</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="201r">(fol. 201r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Prologue to Ecclesiastes</title>
                        <rubric>Here eendeþ þe booc of prouerbis Se now þe prolog in þe booc of ecclesiates þat is to seie booc of talkere to þe puple or to gidere calle</rubric>
                        <incipit>Þis almost þe fifte</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="201r">(fol. 201r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Ecclesiastes</title>
                        <rubric>Here endeþ þe prolog of ecclesiastes se now þe booc</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="203v">(fol. 203v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Song of Songs</title>
                        <rubric>Here endeþ þe booc of ecclesiastes Se now þe book of song of songis</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="205r">(fol. 205r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Wisdom</title>
                        <rubric>Here endeþ þe book of songis Se now þe booc of Sapiens or wisdom</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="209v">(fol. 209v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Prologue to Ecclesiasticus</title>
                        <rubric>Here endiþ þe booc of Sapiens or wisdom Se now þe prolog of þe booc of Ecclesiastici</rubric>
                        <incipit>Of manye and grete</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="210r">(fol. 210r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Ecclesiasticus</title>
                        <rubric>Here endeþ þe prolog Se now þe booc</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="223r">(fol. 223r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Prologue to Isaiah</title>
                        <rubric>Heere endeþ þe book of ecclesiastici Se now a prolog of Isaye þe profete</rubric>
                        <rubric>Anoper prolog of Isayee and opere profetis</rubric>
                        <incipit>As seynt Ierom seiþ</incipit>
                        <note>In spite of the rubric only the Later Version of the Wycliffite Bible prologue is included.</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="223r">(fol. 223r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Isaiah</title>
                        <rubric>Here eendeþ þe prolog See now Isaie</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="239r">(fol. 239r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Jeremiah</title>
                        <rubric>Heere eendeþ Isaye Se now Ieremye <locus from="238v" to="238v">(fol. 238v)</locus></rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="256r">(fol. 256r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Lamentations of Jeremiah</title>
                        <rubric>Heere bigynneþ þe lamentacion of Ieremye</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="257r">(fol. 257r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Prayer of Jeremiah</title>
                        <rubric>Heere enden þe lamentacions Se now þe preier of Ieremye þe profete</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="257v">(fol. 257v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Prologue to Baruch</title>
                        <rubric>Here endeþ þe book of Ieremie Se now þe prolog of Baruch</rubric>
                        <incipit>Þis book wich is titled</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="257v">(fol. 257v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Baruch</title>
                        <rubric>Here endeþ þe prolog of baruk se now þe booc</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="259v">(fol. 259v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Ezekiel</title>
                        <rubric>Her endeþ Baruc Se now Ezechiel</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="276r">(fol. 276r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Daniel</title>
                        <rubric>Here endeþ ezechiel þe prophete Se now danyel þe prophete</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="283r">(fol. 283r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Hosea</title>
                        <rubric>Here endeþ daniel þe prophete Se now Osee þe profete</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="285r">(fol. 285r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Joel</title>
                        <rubric>Here endeþ þe booc of þe profete Osee Se now Ioel þe prophete</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="286r">(fol. 286r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Amos</title>
                        <rubric>Here endeþ Ioel þe profete see now þe book of þe profete Amos</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="288r">(fol. 288r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Obadiah</title>
                        <rubric>Here endeþ Amos þe profete Se now Abdias þe profete <locus from="287v" to="287v">(fol. 287v)</locus></rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="288r">(fol. 288r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Jonah</title>
                        <rubric>Her endeþ Abdias þe profete Se now Ionas þe profete</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="288v">(fol. 288v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Micah</title>
                        <rubric>Here endeþ Ionas þe profete Se now Micheas þe profete</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="290r">(fol. 290r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Nahum</title>
                        <rubric>Here endeþ Micheas þe profete Se now Naum þe profete</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="290v">(fol. 290v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Habakkuk</title>
                        <rubric>Here endeþ Naum þe profete Se now Abacuk þe profete</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="291r">(fol. 291r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Zephaniah</title>
                        <rubric>Here endeþ Abacuk þe profete Se now þe booc of sophonye þe profete</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="292r">(fol. 292r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Haggai</title>
                        <rubric>Here eendeþ þe booc of Sophonye Se now þe booc of Aggei þe profete</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="292v">(fol. 292v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Zechariah</title>
                        <rubric>Here eendeþ þe booc of Aggei Se now þe booc of Zacharie þe profete</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="295r">(fol. 295r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Malachi</title>
                        <rubric>Here endeþ of Zacarie þe booc Se now Malachie þe profete</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="295v">(fol. 295v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">1 Maccabees</title>
                        <rubric>Heere endeþ Malachie þe profete Se now þe firste book of Macabeus</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="305r">(fol. 305r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">2 Maccabees</title>
                        <rubric>Heere endeþ þe firste book of Macabeus Se now þe second book of macabeus</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="312r">(fol. 312r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Prologue to Matthew</title>
                        <rubric>Heere endeþ þe secounde book of Macabeus and al þe oolde testament Se now þe newe testament <lb/> Heere bygynneþ þe Prolog of Ierom on Matheu</rubric>
                        <incipit>Mathew þat was of Iudee</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="312r">(fol. 312r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Matthew</title>
                        <rubric>Ierom in his prolog on Matheu seiþ þis pleinly</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="321v">(fol. 321v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Prologue to Mark</title>
                        <rubric>Here eendeþ Mathew Se now þe prolog on Mark</rubric>
                        <incipit>Mark þe gospeler was þe chosen seruaunt</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="321v">(fol. 321v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Mark</title>
                        <rubric>Ierom in his prolog on Mark seiþ þis pleynli</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="327r">(fol. 327r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Prologue to Luke</title>
                        <rubric>Here endeþ Mark Se now þe prolog on Luke</rubric>
                        <incipit>Lvke was a man of sirie</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="327r">(fol. 327r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Luke</title>
                        <rubric>Here endeþ þe prolog on Luke Se now þe book of Luk</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="337v">(fol. 337v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Prologue to John</title>
                        <rubric>Here eendeþ Luke Se now þe prolog on Ioon</rubric>
                        <incipit>This is Ioon euangelist</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="337v">(fol. 337v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">John</title>
                        <rubric>Ierom in his prolog on Ioon seiþ al þis Se now þe book</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="345r">(fol. 345r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Prologue to Romans</title>
                        <rubric>Here endeþ Ioon Se now þe prolog to þe Romains</rubric>
                        <incipit>Romains ben in þe cuntre</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="345r">(fol. 345r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Romans</title>
                        <rubric>Ierom seiþ þis in his prolog to þe Romayns Se now þe book</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="348v">(fol. 348v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Prologue to 1 Corinthians</title>
                        <rubric>Here bigynneþ a prolog of Ierom on þe firste pistle to Corinthies</rubric>
                        <incipit>Corinthies ben</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="348v">(fol. 348v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">1 Corinthians</title>
                        <rubric>Ierom in his prolog seiþ al þis</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="352v">(fol. 352v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Prologue to 2 Corinthians</title>
                        <rubric>Here eendiþ þe firste pistle to corinthies Se now a prolog on þe secunde pistle to corinthies</rubric>
                        <incipit>Aftir penaunce</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="352v">(fol. 352v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">2 Corinthians</title>
                        <rubric>Ierom in his prolog seiþ al þis</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="355r">(fol. 355r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Prologue to Galatians</title>
                        <rubric>Here endiþ þe seconde pistle to corinthies Se now þe prolog on þe pistle to Galathies</rubric>
                        <incipit>Galathies ben grekis</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="355r">(fol. 355r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Galatians</title>
                        <rubric>Ierom in his prolog to galathies seiþ al þis</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="356r">(fol. 356r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Prologue to Ephesians</title>
                        <rubric>Here endeþ þe pistel to Galathies Se now þe prolog on þe pistle to Effesies</rubric>
                        <incipit>Effecians ben men of Asie</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="356r">(fol. 356r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Ephesians</title>
                        <rubric>Ierom in his prolog seiþ al þis</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="357v">(fol. 357v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Prologue to Philippians</title>
                        <rubric>Here endeþ þe pistle to Effesies se now þe prolog on þe pistle to ffilipensis</rubric>
                        <incipit>Filipensis ben of macedonye</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="357v">(fol. 357v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Philippians</title>
                        <rubric>Ierom in his prolog seiþ al þis</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="358v">(fol. 358v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Prologue to Colossians</title>
                        <rubric>Here endeþ þe pistle to filipensis se now þe prolog on þe pistle to colocensis</rubric>
                        <incipit>Colocensis ben also laodicensis</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="358v">(fol. 358v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Colossians</title>
                        <rubric>Ierom in his prolog seiþ al þis</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="359r">(fol. 359r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Prologue to 1 Thessalonians</title>
                        <rubric>Here endeþ þe pistle to Colocensis se now þe prolog of þe firste pistel to Tessalonicensis</rubric>
                        <incipit>Tessalonycensis ben macedonies</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="359r">(fol. 359r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">1 Thessalonians</title>
                        <rubric>Ierom in his prolog on þis pistle seiþ þis</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="360r">(fol. 360r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Prologue to 2 Thessalonians</title>
                        <rubric>Here endeþ þe firste pistle to Tessalonicensis se now þe prolog on þe secunde pistle to Tessalonicencis</rubric>
                        <incipit>Þe postle writeþ</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="360r">(fol. 360r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">2 Thessalonians</title>
                        <rubric>Ierom in his prolog on þis pistle seiþ þis</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="360v">(fol. 360v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Prologue to 1 Timothy</title>
                        <rubric>Here endeþ þe secunde pistle to Tessalonicensis se now þe prolog on þe firste pistle to Tymothee</rubric>
                        <incipit>He enfoormeþ and techiþ</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="360v">(fol. 360v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">1 Timothy</title>
                        <rubric>Ierom in his prolog on þis pistle seiþ þis</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="361v">(fol. 361v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Prologue to 2 Timothy</title>
                        <rubric>Here endeþ þe firste pistle to Tymothe se now þe prolog on þe secunde pistle to Timothe</rubric>
                        <incipit>He writeþ also</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="361v">(fol. 361v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">2 Timothy</title>
                        <rubric>Ierom in his prolog on þis pistle seiþ þis</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="362r">(fol. 362r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Prologue to Titus</title>
                        <rubric>Here endeþ þe seconde pistle to Tymothe Se now þe prolog on þe pistle to Tite</rubric>
                        <incipit>He warneþ Tyte</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="362r">(fol. 362r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Titus</title>
                        <rubric>Ierom in his prolog seiþ þis</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="362v">(fol. 362v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Prologue to Philemon</title>
                        <rubric>Here endeþ þe pistle to Tite se now þe prolog to ffilomen</rubric>
                        <incipit>He makeþ familiar</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="362v">(fol. 362v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Philemon</title>
                        <rubric>Ierom in his prolog on þis pistle seiþ þis</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="363r">(fol. 363r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Prologue to Hebrews</title>
                        <rubric>Here endeþ the pistle to ffilomen se now þe prolog on þe pistle to Ebrewes <locus from="362v" to="362v">(fol. 362v)</locus></rubric>
                        <incipit>First it is to seie</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="363r">(fol. 363r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Hebrews</title>
                        <rubric>Ierom in his prolog on þis pistle seiþ þis</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="365v">(fol. 365v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Prologue to Acts</title>
                        <rubric>Here endeþ þe pistel to ebrewes se now þe prolog on þe dedis of apostlis</rubric>
                        <incipit>Lvke of antiochie</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="366r">(fol. 366r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Acts</title>
                        <rubric>Ierom heere in his prolog seiþ þis</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="375v">(fol. 375v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Prologue to Catholic epistles</title>
                        <rubric>Here enden þe dedis of apostlis Se now a prolog on þe pistlis of cristen feiþ þat ben seuene in ordre</rubric>
                        <incipit>Þe ordre of þe seuene epistlis</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="375v">(fol. 375v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">James</title>
                        <rubric>Ierom in his prolog seiþ al þis Se now þe pistel of Iames</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="376v">(fol. 376v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">1 Peter</title>
                        <rubric>Here endeþ þe pistle of Iames Se now þe firste pistle of petre</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="377v">(fol. 377v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">2 Peter</title>
                        <rubric>Here endeþ þe firste pistle of petre Se now þe secounde</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="378r">(fol. 378r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">1 John</title>
                        <rubric>Here endeþ þe secunde pistle of petre se now þe firste pistle of Ioon</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="379r">(fol. 379r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">2 John</title>
                        <rubric>Here endeþ þe firste pistle of Ioon se now þe secunde</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="379v">(fol. 379v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">3 John</title>
                        <rubric>Heere endeþ þe seconde pistle of Ioon se now þe þridde</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="379v">(fol. 379v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Jude</title>
                        <rubric>Here endeþ þe þridde pistle of Ioon Se now þe pistle of Iudas</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="380r">(fol. 380r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Prologue to the Apocalypse</title>
                        <rubric>Here endeþ þe pistle of Iudas se now a prolog on þe apocalips</rubric>
                        <incipit>Alle men þat wolen</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="380r">(fol. 380r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Apocalypse</title>
                        <rubric>Ierom in þis prolog on þis apocalips seiþ þis</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <note>At the end, all in the hand of the main scribe: <q>Here endeþ þe apocalips</q> and <q>Þe eer of þe lord M. CCC<note>[followed by an erasure]</note> &amp; viii þis book was endid</q>. Also: <q>Turne ouer þis leef &amp; se þere þe Table</q>.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="5">
                     <locus from="385v" to="388r">(fols. 385v–388r)</locus>
                     <title type="desc"><foreign rend="italic">Capitula</foreign>-list for gospels, epistles and the Apocalypse</title>
                     <rubric>Here bigynneþ a table of alle þe gospels and pistils and þe Apocalips</rubric>
                     <note>Fol. 388v is blank apart from an erased early modern inscription.</note>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="perg">
                        <support>parchment, paper flyleaves; lower part of some leaves cut off in quires II, VII, XVIII, XXXIV, XL, XLIII</support>
                        <extent><measure type="leaf" quantity="392">392</measure> leaves, <foreign rend="italic">c.</foreign><dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                              <height>426</height>
                              <width>285</width>
                           </dimensions>; leaves were trimmed in rebinding, occasionally causing the loss of decoration and text in the margins</extent>
                        <foliation>modern in pencil: i–ii + 1–389 + unnumbered leaf</foliation>
                        <collation><locus from="i" to="ii">(fol. i–ii)</locus> paper flyleaves, the first conjoint with the upper pastedown | <locus from="1" to="72">(fols. 1–72)</locus> I–IX (8) | <locus from="73" to="128">(fols. 73–128)</locus> X–XV (8) | <locus from="129" to="168">(fols. 129–168)</locus> XVI–XXI (8) | <locus from="169" to="184">(fols. 169–184)</locus> XXII–XXIII (8) | <locus from="185" to="194">(fols. 185–194)</locus> XXIV (10) quire containing the calendar-lectionary | <locus from="195" to="218">(fols. 195–218)</locus> XXV–XXVIII (8) | <locus from="219" to="222">(fols. 219–222)</locus> XXIX (4) | <locus from="223" to="286">(fols. 223–286)</locus> XXX–XXXVII (8) | <locus from="287" to="290">(fols. 287–290)</locus> XXXVIII (4) | <locus from="291" to="370">(fols. 291–370)</locus> XXXIX–XLVIII (8) | <locus from="371" to="386">(fols. 371–386)</locus> XLIX–L (8) | <locus from="387" to="388">(fols. 387–388)</locus> LI (2) | <locus>(fol. 389 and an unnumbered leaf)</locus> paper flyleaves. <catchwords>Catchwords</catchwords> and <signatures>leaf signatures survive.</signatures> Collation does not support Dove’s suggestion (2001, p. 257) that the calendar-lectionary was the last item in vol. 1 of a two-volume bible, because it occupies a quire which also contains the beginning of the following text, the Proverbs. <secFol><q>It is leueful</q>
                              <locus from="2r" to="2r">(fol. 2r)</locus></secFol>
                        </collation>
                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout columns="2" writtenLines="60 61">ruled in plummet for two columns with single vertical and horizontal bounding lines extending the full height and width of page, 60–1 lines per page; prickings survive; written space: <foreign rend="italic">c.</foreign><dimensions type="ruled" unit="mm">
                              <height>310</height>
                              <width min="90" max="98">90–98</width>
                           </dimensions></layout>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc>
                     <handNote script="textualisNorthern">textura, black and brown ink, probably the work of several contemporary scribes</handNote>
                  </handDesc>
                  <decoDesc>
                     <decoNote type="decInit">6-line gold initials on blue and pink background and three-quarters borders made of gold, pink and blue bars, decorated with foliage, at the beginning of prefatory epistles <locus from="1r" to="1r">(fol. 1r)</locus> and Genesis <locus from="3r" to="3r">(fol. 3r)</locus>.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="flourInit">4- to 6-line blue initials decorated with red penwork at the beginnings of Exodus and other books.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="flourInit">3- to 4-line similar initials at the beginnings of prologues.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="flourInit">2-line blue initials decorated with red penwork at the beginnings of chapters.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="colInit">2-line plain red or blue initials in the <foreign rend="italic">capitula</foreign>-list.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="flourInit">Blue KL monograms, decorated with red penwork, and decorative penwork strips separating months in the calendar-lectionary.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="flourInit">Penwork initials are by two artists, the second more professional than the first. The first is responsible for fols. 1–72v (quires I–IX), 129r–168v (quires XVI–XXI), 187v–193v (calendar-lectionary, part of quire XXIV) and 371r–385r (quires XLIX–L); the second is responsible for fols. 73r–128v (quires X–XV), 169r–187r (quires XXII–XXIII and part of quire XXIV) and 194r–370v (part of quire XXIV and quires XXV–XLVIII) (see Collation and Provenance). The quire containing the calendar-lectionary and Athanasian Creed is the only quire that contains the work of both artists. One artist was responsible for the calendar-lectionary and <foreign rend="italic">Quicumque vult</foreign>, and the other for the preceding and following texts.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="marginal">Post-medieval drawings of a human figure pointing to the text <locus from="53v" to="53v">(fol. 53v)</locus> and hands <locus>(fols. 75v, 77v)</locus>.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="rubrication">Rubrics underlined in red; blue paraphs.</decoNote>
                  </decoDesc>
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <binding notAfter="1700" notBefore="1680">
                        <p>Brown leather over thick pasteboard, 17th century. Gilt fillet-line border with floral corner-pieces round the outer edge of both covers. Gild decoration at the centre of both covers. Re-backed in the Bodleian (note on the lower pastedown) with the original spine re-laid. Six raised bands on spine, framed by gilt fillet lines. Gilt floral strips at the top and bottom of the spine, and on the raised bands (mostly lost). ‘Fairfax <lb/> 2’ written in white paint on spine. Two decorated metal clasps. Laid paper pastedowns and flyleaves, and additional 19th-century paper flyleaves. Fol. 388 was probably a pastedown of a medieval binding; there is an erased note in an early modern hand on fol. 338v.</p>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origPlace>
                        <country key="place_7002445">England</country>
                     </origPlace>
                     <origDate calendar="Gregorian" when="1408">1408</origDate>
                     <p>Produced by a team that had access to the texts of the Earlier Version of the Wycliffite Bible and the Later Version of the Wycliffite Bible, or copied from an exemplar that already combined the Later Version of the Wycliffite Bible text with the Earlier Version of the Wycliffite Bible prologues. The <foreign rend="italic">capitula</foreign>-list was added after the rest of the book was completed: it follows the colophon with the date and the initials lack flourishing unlike elsewhere in the manuscript. Marginal glosses and summaries of content which accompany the running titles are partly in the hand of the main scribe, and were probably all added in the original workshop as an afterthought. The margins are not ruled for glosses, the position of the summaries varies and they are largely absent in the part of the book following the calendar-lectionary. Some marginal notes may suggest an interest in Lollardy, for example <q>Of imagis in þe eende of þis chapitre &amp; þe nexte swynge</q> in the hand of the main scribe, fol. 208r, and another similar note on fol. 241v; <q>Loke at þe hond for prestes</q> on fol. 274v which also has a drawing of a hand pointing to a passage on priesthood in Ezekiel, 44.</p>
                     <p>Dialect survey: <list>
                           <item>anye(2)any(6)/ony(2), ech(7)/eche(3), fijr(10), ȝofen(10), lijf(10), lijk(10), miche(10), siȝ(3)/saw(6)/sawȝ(1) (sg.), siȝen(3)/sawen(4) (pl.), silf(3)/self(7), sich(3)/siche(7), þouȝ(8), þorouȝ(7)/þruȝ(2)/þru(1)</item>
                           <item>-eþ(3)/-iþ(7) (pres.ind.3sg.), -en(10) (pres.ind.pl.), -ynge(3)/-inge(4)/-ing(3) (pres.part.), she(9)/sheo(1) (3sg.fem. pronoun, nom.), þei(10) (3pl.pronoun, nom.), hem(10) (3pl.pronoun, oblique), her(10) (3pl.pronoun, possessive)</item>
                        </list> Spellings such as <foreign rend="italic">biȝgge</foreign>, <foreign rend="italic">liȝgge</foreign>, <foreign rend="italic">iȝcching</foreign>, <foreign rend="italic">periȝshe</foreign>, <foreign rend="italic">fleiȝsshis</foreign>, <foreign rend="italic">quyȝsshuns</foreign>, <foreign rend="italic">angwiȝss</foreign>, <foreign rend="italic">biheulde</foreign>, <foreign rend="italic">leose</foreign>, <foreign rend="italic">ȝife</foreign>, <foreign rend="italic">ȝofe</foreign> (‘given’) (Forshall, J. and Madden, F. (eds), <title>The Holy Bible … in the earliest English versions made from the Latin Vulgate by John Wycliffe and his followers</title>, 4 vols (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1850), vol. 1, p. xlviii).</p>
                  </origin>
                  <provenance>The date on fol. 385r may have been altered to avoid censorship, but, according to Watson (1984), examination under UV light suggests that the scribe first wrote ‘M.ccc’ and the ‘and’ symbol, erased the later, wrote it in the right place, and then forgot to insert the fourth ‘c’.</provenance>
                  <provenance>Contains late 15th-century marginal additions, such as <q>nota</q> and other comments, including <q>Of ymages in þis c</q> [chapter] at Isaiah, 44, fol. 233v. The note may be in the hand that added <q>gerard</q> in the lower margin of the psalter, fol. 169r.</provenance>
                  <provenance>Possibly in use in a secular church in the 15th and 16th centuries. St Francis is added to the calendar-lectionary, late 15th century. According to Pfaff (2009, p. 327), Frances is a unique example of a major friar-saint who became ‘widely present in English secular liturgy’. Notes <q>feria</q>, added in a 16th-century hand in the psalter, appear next to liturgical divisions according to secular use. Possibly still in use at Reformation when titles ‘pope’ were erased in the calendar-lectionary.</provenance>
                  <provenance>‘the 29th of Aprill 15(?)58’, 16th century <locus from="377v" to="377v">(fol. 377v)</locus>.</provenance>
                  <provenance><persName key="person_74654593" role="fmo">Thomas Fairfax</persName> (1612–1671); see <title>Oxford Dictionary of National Biography</title>.</provenance>
                  <acquisition when="1671">Bodleian Library: bequeathed by Thomas Fairfax in 1671.</acquisition>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>Elizabeth Solopova, <title><ref target="https://jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1gn6cmr">Manuscripts of the Wycliffite Bible in the Bodleian and Oxford College Libraries</ref></title>, Exeter Medieval Texts and Studies (Liverpool: Liverpool University Press, 2016), no. 21. Previously described: <listBibl>
                              <bibl facs="aaq0131.gif" type="SC">Summary Catalogue, Vol. 2 Part 2, p. 772</bibl>
                           </listBibl>
                        </source>
                     </recordHist>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl type="WRAPPER">
                     <listBibl type="PRINT">
                        <bibl>Forshall, J. and Madden, F. (eds), <title>The Holy Bible … in the earliest English versions made from the Latin Vulgate by John Wycliffe and his followers</title>, 4 vols (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1850), vol. 1, p. xlviii; sigla K; <title>I</title> – prologues to books from Genesis to Ecclesiasticus; <title>K</title> – prologue to 1 Chronicles.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Deanesly, M., <title>The Lollard Bible and other medieval biblical versions</title> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1920), p. 381.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Madan, F. and Craster, H. H. E., <title>Summary catalogue of western manuscripts in the Bodleian Library at Oxford</title>, vol. 2, part I <title>(collections received before 1660 and miscellaneous MSS acquired during the first half of the 17th century), nos. 1–3490</title> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1922), no. 3882.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Fristedt, S. L., <title>The Wycliffe Bible</title>, 3 vols (Stockholm: Almquvist &amp; Wiksells, 1953–73), vol. 1, pp. 12, 17.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Hargreaves, H., ‘The Latin text of Purvey’s Psalter’, <title>Medium Aevum</title> 24 (1955), pp. 73–90 at p. 89 n. 27.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Pächt, O. and Alexander, J. J. G., <title>Illuminated manuscripts in the Bodleian Library, Oxford</title>, 3 vols (Oxford, 1966–73), vol. 3 (1973), no. 798.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Rogers, T. D. (ed.), <title>Sir Frederic Madden at Cambridge: extracts from Madden’s diaries 1831, 1838, 1841–2, 1846, 1859 and 1863</title> (Cambridge: Cambridge Bibliographical Society, 1980), p. 8 and n. 47.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Watson, A. G., <title>Catalogue of dated and datable manuscripts c.435–1600 in Oxford libraries</title>, 2 vols (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1984), vol. 1, <citedRange from="485" to="485" unit="entry"><ref target="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/mdp.39015008982863?urlappend=%3Bseq=106">no. 485</ref></citedRange>, p. 76.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Hudson, A., <title>Lollards and their books</title> (London: Hambledon Press, 1985), p. 148 n. 26.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Lindberg, C. (ed.), <title>The Middle English Bible, The Book of Judges</title> (Oslo: Norwegian University Press, 1989), pp. 42, 70.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Ogilvie-Thomson, S. J., <title>Index of Middle English prose</title>, 18 vols (Cambridge, 1984– ), Handlist VIII (1991), p. 75.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Kuczynski, M. P., <title>Prophetic song: the psalms as moral discourse in late Medieval England</title> (Philadelphia: University of Pennsylvania Press, 1995), p. 264 n. 17.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Boitani, P. et al (eds), <title>Lo spazio letterario del Medioevo. 2, Il Medioevo volgare</title>, 5 vols. in 6 (Rome: Salerno, 1999–2005), vol. 2, p. 726.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Lindberg, C. (ed.), <title>King Henry’s Bible, MS. Bodley 277: the revised version of the Wyclif Bible</title>, 4 vols (Stockholm: Almqvist &amp; Wiksell, 1999–2004), vol. 3, p. 5.</bibl>
                        <bibl>de Hamel, C., <title>The book: a history of the Bible</title> (London: Phaidon, 2001), pp. 176, 177, 182, fig. 128.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Scott, K. L., <title>Dated and datable English manuscript borders, c.1395–1499</title> (London: British Library, 2002), pp. 40–1, pl. VII.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Dove, M., <title>The first English Bible: the text and context of the Wycliffite versions</title> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2007), pp. 257–9.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Solopova, E., ‘Manuscript Evidence for the Patronage, Ownership and Use of the Wycliffite Bible’, in Poleg, E. and Light, L. (eds), <title>Form and Function in the Late Medieval Bible</title> (Leiden: Brill, 2013), pp. 333–49, pp. 336–7.</bibl>
                     </listBibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2023-03-24">Add Solopova description.</change>
         <change when="2022-04-04">Add binding information from Summary Catalogue.</change>
         <change when="2017-07-01">First online publication.</change>
         <change when="2017-05-25">
            <persName>James Cummings</persName> Up-converted the markup using <ref target="https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl">https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl</ref>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>