<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="manuscript_4864">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>MS. Fairfax 3</title>
            <title type="collection">MSS. Fairfax</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp when="2021">Cataloguer</resp>
               <persName>Linne Mooney</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp when="2021">Cataloguer</resp>
               <persName>Derek Pearsall</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp when="2022">Cataloguer</resp>
               <persName>Matthew Holford</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp when="2022">Encoding</resp>
               <persName>Matthew Holford</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </publisher>
            <idno type="msID">MS_Fairfax_3</idno>
            <idno type="collection">Fairfax</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="MS_Fairfax_3" xml:lang="en">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <region type="county">Oxfordshire</region>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <institution>University of Oxford</institution>
                  <repository>Bodleian Library</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">MS. Fairfax 3</idno>
                  <idno type="ieArk">ark:29072/x0c534fp224k</idno><idno type="crArk">ark:29072/x07d278t78k1</idno><altIdentifier type="internal">
                     <idno type="SCN">3883</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
               <head>John Gower, Confessio Amantis and other poems in Latin and French; England, late 14th or early 15th century</head>
               <msContents>
                  <msItem n="1" xml:id="MS_Fairfax_3-item1">
                     <locus from="2ra" to="186v">(fol. 2ra–186v)</locus>
                     <author key="person_120695167">John Gower</author>
                     <title key="work_2706">Confessio amantis</title>
                     <note>(Prol. 1-VIII.3172 end)</note>
                     <incipit>Torpor hebes sensus scola parua labor <lb/> minimusque, etc. (6 lines of
                        Latin verse).</incipit>
                     <incipit>Off hem þat written vs <lb/> tofore</incipit>
                     <explicit>Wher resteþ loue and alle pes <lb/> Oure ioye may ben endeles </explicit>
                     <note>(fol. 1) flyleaf, blank</note>
                     <note> Prologue (fol. 2ra); Book I (fol. 5rb); Book II (fol. 27va); Book III
                        (fol. 47va); Book IV (fol. 62rb); Book V (fol. 82va); Book VI (fol. 125va);
                        Book VII (fol. 138vb, Latin; fol. 139ra, English); Book VIII (fol.
                        168vb).</note>
                     <note> The text has been extensively revised (see Macaulay [ed.], <title>Works of John Gower</title>,
                        II.clvi-clix; Nicholson, 'Gower's Revisions', 'Poet and Scribe', and
                        'Gower's Manuscript', and also with further invaluable help in private
                        communications: M. B. Parkes, 'Patterns of Scribal Activity and Revisions of
                        the Text in Early Copies of Works by John Gower', in Richard Beadle and A.
                        J. Piper (eds), <title>New Science out of Old Books: Studies in Manuscripts
                           and Early Printed Books in Honour of A. I. Doyle</title> [Aldershot,
                        1995], 81-121, see esp. 89-90). Scribe I wrote the whole poem, fols 2r-185v,
                        but fols 2 and 185 have been replaced. Scribe 2 wrote fol. 185, a leaf
                        inserted in place of the one cut away, containing VIII.2967–3146, with the
                        preceding twenty-nine lines (VIII.2938-66) copied in on fol. 184vb over the
                        same number of lines erased. Scribe 3 wrote the first leaf of the text, to
                        replace the one cut away, with Prologue 1-146, and also fols 186-94 (quires
                        xxiv and xxv), including the last lines of the English poem (VIII.3147-72),
                        the Latin poems and rubrics, and the French Traitié. The purpose of scribe
                        2's changes was to remove lines with Venus's praise of Chaucer
                        (VIII.2941-70*), replacing them with lines that do not mention Chaucer. The
                        purpose of scribe 3's changes was to replace the reference to Richard II's
                        'commissioning' of the book in the Prologue with a reference to 'a bok for
                        Engelondes sake' and mention of Henry of Lancaster; and at the end of the
                        poem to replace the praise of Richard II with a lament for the state of
                        England, and to introduce the revised form of 'Quia unusquisque' with
                        vilification of Richard II (now dead) and dedication to Henry of Lancaster.
                        (The changes at the end of the poem may have been anticipated by scribe 2 in
                        leaves now removed.) With the same purpose, scribe 3 also added a marginal
                        gloss at Prol. 193 and erased one at Prol. 331. The original scribe added
                        passages not present in earlier versions of the poem in order to deal with
                        problems of layout caused by the effort to place the beginnings of tales or
                        sections in the first line of the column (with the appropriate decorated
                        initial) and to add text so that column-for-column copying of the exemplar
                        could begin at fol. 22. These changes involved the composition of twenty-six
                        new English lines that can be associated only with the poet's direct
                        intervention.</note>
                     <textLang mainLang="enm" otherLangs="la">Middle English with Latin apparatus</textLang>
                     <note> For further information about the following Latin and French addenda
                        that Gower caused to be added to MSS of the Confessio, see Derek Pearsall and Linne Mooney, <title>A Descriptive Catalogue of the Manuscripts of John Gower's Confessio Amantis</title> (Cambridge: D. S. Brewer, 2021), Appendix III.
                     </note>
                     
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="2" xml:id="MS_Fairfax_3-item2">
                     <locus from="186r">(fol. 186r)</locus><author key="person_120695167">John Gower</author>                     <title type="desc"> 'Explicit iste liber' </title>
                     <incipit> Explicit iste liber</incipit>
                     <explicit> sub eo requiesce futurus </explicit>
                     <note>Later six-line version with dedication to the earl of Derby. Macaulay
                        (ed.), <title>Works</title>, III.478. </note>
                     <textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="3" xml:id="MS_Fairfax_3-item3">
                     <locus from="186r">(fol. 186r)</locus>
                     <author key="person_18781487">Ralph Strode (?)</author>
                     <title type="desc">'Quam cinxere freta'</title>
                     <rubric>Epistola super huius</rubric>
                     <incipit>Quam cinxere freta</incipit>
                     <explicit>stat sine meta </explicit>
                     <note>Macaulay (ed.), <title>Works</title>, III.479. </note>
                     <textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="4" xml:id="MS_Fairfax_3-item4">
                     <locus from="186v" to="190r">(fols 186v–190r)</locus>
                     <author key="person_120695167">John Gower</author>
                     <title key="work_2708">Traitié pour essampler les amantz marietz </title>
                     <incipit>Puisquil ad dit cy deuant</incipit>
                     <explicit>saluement tenir</explicit>
                     <note>(prose rubric) </note>
                     <incipit>Le creatour de toute creature</incipit>
                     <explicit>lamour parfit en dieu se iustifie </explicit>
                     <incipit>Quis sit vel qualis </incipit>
                     <explicit>omne latus </explicit>
                     <note>(concluding rubric) Macaulay (ed.), <title>Works</title>, 1.379-92.</note>
                     <textLang mainLang="xno">Anglo-Norman</textLang>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="5" xml:id="MS_Fairfax_3-item5">
                     <locus from="190v">(fol. 190v)</locus>
                     <author key="person_120695167">John Gower</author>
                     <title>Carmen de variis in amore passionibus </title>
                     <incipit>Est amor in glosa </incipit>
                     <explicit> adhibo thorum</explicit>
                     <note>Macaulay (ed.), <title>Works</title>, IV.359. </note>
                     <textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="6" xml:id="MS_Fairfax_3-item6">
                     <locus from="190v" to="194r">(fols 190v–194r)</locus>
                     <author key="person_120695167">John Gower</author>
                     <title key="work_2704">Carmen super multiplici viciorum pestilencia</title>
                     <incipit>Non excusatur</incipit>
                     <explicit>iura tenenda deo </explicit>
                     <note>Macaulay (ed.), <title>Works</title>, IV.346. </note><textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="7" xml:id="MS_Fairfax_3-item7">
                     <locus from="194r">(fol. 194r)</locus>
                     <author key="person_120695167">John Gower</author>
                     <title type="desc">'Quia unusquisque'</title>
                     <incipit>Quia unusquisque</incipit>
                     <explicit>specialiter sortitus est </explicit>
                     <note>Later version, with condemnation of Richard Il and praise of Henry, earl
                        of Derby. Macaulay (ed.), <title>Works</title>, III.479-80, IV.360. </note>
                     <textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="8" xml:id="MS_Fairfax_3-item8">
                     <locus from="194v">(fol. 194v)</locus>
                     <author key="person_18781487">Ralph Strode (?)</author>
                     <title type="desc">'Eneidos Bucolis'</title>
                     <incipit>Carmen quod quidam Philosophus </incipit>
                     <explicit>gratanter transmisit </explicit>
                     <note>(prose rubric) </note>
                     <incipit>Eneidos Bucolis que Georgica </incipit>
                     <explicit>laus sit habendalocis </explicit>
                     <note>Macaulay (ed.), <title>Works</title>, IV.361. </note>
                     <textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <p><secFol><locus>(fol. 3 as now foliated)</locus> Be kept vpriht in such a wyse
                     </secFol></p>
                  <objectDesc form="codex">

                     <supportDesc material="perg">
                        <support>parchment</support>
                        <extent>ii (paper) + 1 + 193 + 1 + i (paper)  leaves <dimensions unit="mm" type="leaf">
                              <height>390</height>
                              <width>235</width>
                           </dimensions>
                        </extent>
                        <foliation>Foliated (modern) i-ii, 1-196 </foliation>
                        <collation>i-xxii(8) xxiii(8, fol. 185, cut away and replaced by a
                           singleton with stub following) xxiv(6) xxv(4) (wants 4, after fol. 194).
                              <catchwords>Catchwords regularly written by the scribe in lower
                              margins of last leaf verso of each quire.</catchwords> The leaves of
                           quire vii are disarranged, as Macaulay explains (ed. <title>Works</title>, II.clvii).
                           This disarrangement is noted by a contemporary hand at the foot of fols
                           5lv, 53v, 55v and 56v, as noted by A. I. Doyle, who commented that the
                           hand noting this disarrangement was 'a very neat secretary that could
                           well be Hoccleve's' (Doyle's handwritten note about the MS). </collation>
                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout columns="2" writtenLines="46">Written space <dimensions unit="mm" type="written">
                              <height>240</height>
                              <width>160</width>
                           </dimensions> In two columns, forty-six lines per column, except that
                           from fol. 186 onward the third scribe employs a single column layout (for
                           the Latin and French). Ruled in brown crayon for text blocks, but not for
                           marginal glosses and only occasionally for running titles. Running titles
                           across opening (Liber primus, etc.), except Prologus, Confessor, Amans,
                           etc. consistently in margin, without decoration or paraph. Paraphs are
                           never used in this MS. Latin verses pushed out when in the left column
                           into the left margin (to avoid running on the longer Latin lines into the
                           central column): where books begin in the left column (recto or verso),
                           the border is pushed out around the protruding Latin verses (III, VI,
                           VII, VIII), and in one case the whole border is pushed out left to
                           accommodate the Latin marginal gloss as well (V); in the right column,
                           the Latin verses are lined up with the regular margin, sometimes with a
                           lightly decorated vertical line in the central column to ensure the
                           correct line-up (e.g. fols 16v, 18v, 2lv, etc.). Sometimes this line
                           migrates to the left of the left column (perhaps to make sure decorated
                           initials are properly lined up? e.g. fols 148r, 156r, 164r, etc.). The
                           differentiation in the treatment of the Latin verses in left and right
                           columns is well illustrated in those groups of verses that run over the
                           two columns (e.g. fols 23ra and 23rb, 138vb and 139ra, 112va and 112vb,
                           etc.). Latin glosses are in the margins, placed in relation to the main
                           text in the exact positions observed by Macaulay: the long moralising
                           glosses often run out under one or both of the text-columns, e.g. fols
                           5vb, 14vb, 21v, 221, 25v (an extreme example, 1.3067). Latin glosses and
                           Latin verses are written in the same black ink as the Middle English
                           text, and even the textura quadrata headings and running titles are
                           written in black ink. </layout>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc hands="3">
                     <handNote script="cursivaAntiquior" execution="formata">One very good hand, with later interventions by two other hands, as
                        explained in the description of the text, above. Many corrections by
                        original hand, especially to correct the use of final -e (described in
                        detail by Macaulay (ed.), <title>Works</title>, II.clix). The principal
                        scribe writes in a late fourteenth-century anglicana formata hand showing
                        influence of the secretary script in its use of single compartment 'a'. The
                        second scribe writes in a similar style of anglicana formata of the
                        beginning of the fifteenth century, using the two-compartment 'a' and
                        writing in a less angular style than the principal. The third scribe uses
                        the most angular form of anglicana formata, with quadrata feet at the base
                        of minims and stalks of other letters, again datable to the early fifteenth
                        century. </handNote>
                     <handNote>Careful punctuation, including a raised point to mark a strong
                        caesural break after enjambement. There is detailed description by Macaulay
                        (ed., <title>Works</title>, II.clix). There is also arbitrary use of various
                        forms of punctuation at the ends of lines. The normal tyronian abbreviations
                        appear frequently in the Latin but sparingly in the English text; the scribe
                        prefers to write out and' rather than use the tyronian 'et'. Thorn is used
                        except as line-initial where the scribe spelled out 'Th'; and yogh is used
                        for the 'y' sound ('ȝet', 'ȝe', 'ȝou') but not for the 'gh' sound ('noght',
                        'briht', ynowh'). </handNote>
                  </handDesc>
                  <decoDesc>
                     <summary>Fine miniatures, borders, initials. (<ref target="https://catalog.hathitrust.org/Record/000468709">Pächt and
                           Alexander</ref> iii. 710, pl. LXXI)</summary>
                     <decoNote type="miniature">There are two miniatures. The first is the statue of
                        Nebuchadnezzar's dream ("The Dream of Precious Metals'), showing
                        Nebuchadnezzar in bed (with a splendid pink bedcover), and the image and a
                        hill beside, as is usual, but also showing the differentiation of metals (in
                        blue and gold), which is not. See Pächt and Alexander, <title>Illuminated
                           Manuscripts in the Bodleian Library</title>, III. pl. 71. The image
                        appears at the beginning of the poem, fol. 2ra, and occupies eighteen lines.
                        The other miniature occupies sixteen lines at the beginning of Book I, fol.
                        8rb, and shows the confession scene, Genius dressed in green with a wreath
                        of roses on his head, not much like a priest (Scott, <title>Later Gothic
                           Manuscripts</title>, II. 110), the penitent, kneeling, wearing a hood and
                        collar of SS (Gower was presented with a collar of SS by Henry Bolingbroke
                        in 1393) with a badge, probably a swan, hanging from it (see Figure 6). The
                        collar and badge, perhaps added later, are part of the Lancastrian livery,
                        as well as the livery colours of white and blue noted by Harris, "Ownership
                        and Readership', 121. S. Drimmer, <title>The Art of Allusion</title>, discusses
                        the collar of SS in relation to limhers' treatment of authorial identity
                        with Amans on p: 95 and Figure 38 on p. 98, illustrating the detail of the
                        collar in colour plate 11.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="border">Fairfax 3 was used by Macaulay as his copy-text, and
                        his division of the poem into paragraphs and chapters' corresponds exactly
                        to the hierarchy of the decorated initials. Six-line decorated initials,
                        combined with bar-borders, mark the beginnings of all books except the
                        Prologue (four-line). The borders consist of a single decorated column on
                        the left, alone (Prol.) or with lateral extensions the width of the page at
                        top and bottom (II, III, VI, VII) or at the bottom only (V); or a single
                        decorated column between the text-columns with lateral extensions to left
                        and right at top and bottom (IV, VIII) or at the bottom only (D). The
                        branches are variously decorated with little ball-ornaments, trefoils,
                        petals, sprays and occasionally thistles.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="decInit"> Four-line decorated initials in gold, blue and pink,
                        with pen-flourishing, mark major text-divisions, especially those that
                        follow Latin verses and are marked by Macaulay as 'chapters' with small
                        Roman numerals (e.g. 1.575, 1235, 1343).</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="flourInit"> Three-line initials, with flourishing, mark the
                        less important major text-divisions (Macaulay's line-spaces). One-line
                        decorated initials mark minor text-divisions (corresponding to Macaulay's
                        paragraphs), and are also used for the Latin verses. In the French and Latin
                        poems, the same kind of hierarchy of initials is observed, as appropriate to
                        the different structure of the poems, but with no borders. </decoNote>
                  </decoDesc>
                  <additions><list>
                        <item> Fol. 42r, across bottom, 'Dominus illuminacio mea et salus mea quem
                           timebo'. Psalm 27:1 (Vg. Ps. 26:1). In a good s.xv hand. Pale rusty-brown
                           ink. </item>
                        <item> Fol. 69r, top margin, 'Nota fabula pro mulieribus', referring to the
                           story of Rosiphelee, IV. 1245.</item>
                        <item> Fol. 100r, central space between text-columns, 'Thystory of Jason and
                           Medea', V.2232.</item>
                        <item> Fol. 109va, 'adryan and bardus', at V.4937, beside initial at
                           beginning of tale.</item>
                        <item> Fol. 194r, across bottom, 'Confessio Amantis'. Informal s.xv
                           hand.</item>
                     </list>
                     </additions>
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <binding notAfter="1825" notBefore="1700">
                        <p>On five bands, stippled calf with marbled paper endleaves and pastedowns,
                           probably s.xviii, maybe early s.xix. </p>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>

               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="1410" notBefore="1390">14th century,
                        late – 15th century, early</origDate>
                     <origPlace>
                        <country key="place_7002445">England</country>
                     </origPlace>
                  </origin>
                  <provenance notBefore="1511">  
                      Fol. 2r, top margin, 'The Ladie Isabell Fairfax <lb/> daughter and hare
                        of Thwates hir bouk'.
                      Fol. 8r, top margin, 'This boke be longythe to my lady farfax off
                        Steton'. <persName role="fmo" key="person_3545">Lady Isabel Fairfax</persName> (fol. 2r) was the granddaughter and heiress of
                     John Thwaites of Denton, in Yorkshire, who died in 1511. She was married to Sir
                     William Fairfax of Steeton (fol. 8r), also in Yorkshire.</provenance>
                  <provenance when="1588"> Fol. 1r, top margin, 'Sr Thomas fayrfax of Denton Knighte <lb/> true owner
                     of this booke, 1588'. <persName role="fmo" key="person_290699274">Sir Thomas Fairfax</persName>
                     (fol. 1r) was her grandson.</provenance>
                  <acquisition when="1675"> The book was bequeathed to the University of Oxford
                     by <persName role="fmo" key="person_74654593">Sir Thomas Fairfax</persName>, the parliamentary general, grandson of the above Sir
                     Thomas Fairfax, and was placed in the Bodleian Library in 1675. See Macaulay
                     (ed.), <title>Works</title>. II.clvii.</acquisition>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>Derek Pearsall and Linne Mooney, <title>A Descriptive Catalogue of the Manuscripts of John Gower's Confessio Amantis</title> (Cambridge: D. S. Brewer, 2021), reproduced by kind permission of Linne Mooney. Additional description of endleaf (fol. 195) by Matthew Holford, August 2022. Previously described in the Summary Catalogue. <listBibl>
                              <bibl facs="aaq0131.gif" type="SC">Summary Catalogue, Vol. 2 Part 2,
                                 p. 772</bibl>
                           </listBibl>
                        </source>
                     </recordHist>
                   <!--  <availability status="none">
                        <p>This item is on display in the exhibition "Chaucer Here and Now", Bodleian Libraries, Weston Library, 8 December 2023 – 28 April 2024. It will not be orderable between those dates or for a short period before or afterwards.</p>
                     </availability>-->
                  </adminInfo>
                  <surrogates>
                     <bibl type="digital-facsimile" subtype="full">
                        <ref target="https://digital.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/objects/b248e552-650b-47bc-aac2-e1184896f924/">
                           <title>Digital Bodleian</title></ref> <note>(full digital facsimile)</note>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl subtype="partial" type="digital-facsimile">
                        <ref target="https://digital.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/objects/d3376f6e-201d-4d7e-ae77-29ffbb94b28d/">
                           <title>Digital Bodleian</title></ref> <note>(3 images from 35mm slides)</note>
                     </bibl>
                  </surrogates>
                  <listBibl type="WRAPPER">
                     <listBibl type="INTERNET">
                        <head>Online resources:</head>
                        <bibl><ref target="http://jonas.irht.cnrs.fr/manuscrit/78072"><title>JONAS:
                                 Répertoire des textes et des manuscrits médiévaux d'oc et
                                 d'oïl</title></ref></bibl>
                        <bibl><ref target="https://www.medievalscribes.com/index.php?browse=manuscripts&amp;&amp;id=427&amp;nav=off"><title>Late Medieval English Scribes</title></ref></bibl>
                     </listBibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
               <msPart xml:id="MS_Fairfax_3-endleaf" type="fragment">
                  <msIdentifier>
                     <altIdentifier>
                        <idno>MS. Fairfax 3 - endleaf, fol. 195</idno>
                     </altIdentifier>
                  </msIdentifier>
                  
                  <msContents>
                     <textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>
                     <msItem>
                        <author key="person_95296771">Nicholas Lyra</author>
                        <title key="work_3316">Postilla litteralis</title><note>1 Cor. 5.6 - 7.3, 'subdicitur <quote>quia modicum fermentum</quote>' (fol. 195va) - 'circa primum dicit <quote>uxori</quote>' (fol. 195rb), as pr. Rome, 1471-2 (<ref target="https://data.cerl.org/istc/in00131000">ISTC in00131000</ref>), vol. V or Basle, 1498, vol. 6; Stegmüller, <title>Bibl.</title> 5903.</note>
                        <note>Misbound with recto as verso. In its current position in an earlier binding, as shown by wormholes.</note>
                     </msItem>
                  </msContents>
                  <physDesc>
                     <objectDesc form="codex">
                        <supportDesc material="perg">
                           <support>parchment</support>
                        </supportDesc>
                        <layoutDesc>
                           <layout columns="2" writtenLines="64">2 cols., 64 lines; column space <dimensions unit="mm" type="column">
                              <height>285</height>
                              <width quantity="88">c. 88</width>
                           </dimensions></layout>
                        </layoutDesc>
                     </objectDesc>
                     <handDesc>
                        <handNote script="textualisNorthern">Texualis libraria</handNote>
                     </handDesc>
                     <decoDesc>
                        <decoNote type="flourInit">3-line initials alternating red and blue with penwork in the contrasting colour.</decoNote>
                     </decoDesc>
                  </physDesc>
                  <history>
                     <origin>
                        <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notBefore="1390" notAfter="1410">14th century, late, or 15th century, early</origDate>
                        <origPlace><country key="place_7002445">England</country></origPlace>
                     </origin>
                  </history>
               </msPart>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2022-08">Description revised for publication on Digital Bodleian.</change>
         <change when="2017-07-01">First online publication.</change>
         <change when="2017-05-25"><persName>James Cummings</persName> Up-converted the markup using
               <ref target="https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl">https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl</ref></change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>