<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="manuscript_10023">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>MS. Germ. e. 23</title>
            <title type="collection">MSS. Germ. (German)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp when="2017-08">Cataloguer</resp>
               <persName>Stephen Mossman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp when="2021-05">Encoding</resp>
               <persName>Andrew Dunning</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </publisher>
            <idno type="msID">MS_Germ_e_23</idno>
            <idno type="collection">German</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="MS_Germ_e_23" xml:lang="en">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <region type="county">Oxfordshire</region>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <institution>University of Oxford</institution>
                  <repository>Bodleian Library</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">MS. Germ. e. 23</idno>
                  <idno type="ieArk">ark:29072/x0jw827b76ct</idno><idno type="crArk">ark:29072/x0js956f932z</idno><altIdentifier type="internal">
                     <idno type="SCN">Not in SC (late accession)</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
               <head><title>Andächtiges Myrrhenbüschlein</title>; Prayers, including texts by Johannes von Indersdorf and Johann von Neumarkt. Germany (Swabia), 16th century (c.1520–1550)</head>
               <msContents>
                  <summary>Personal <title key="work_16440" type="desc">prayerbook</title> of an individual nun, a member of a convent in eastern Swabia in the second quarter of the sixteenth century.</summary>
                  <textLang mainLang="gmh">Middle High German</textLang>
                  <msItem n="1">
                     <locus from="1r" to="9v">(fols. 1r–9v)</locus>
                     <title type="desc">Five prayers to Mary</title>
                     <rubric>Dacz send die finfzechen salue wer die all samsztag spricht der wirt nit verlasen von maria <sic>spirch</sic> triu salue</rubric>
                     <incipit>O du genedig vnd wirdige junckfraw maria bis ingedenck der grosen lieb vnd iberflissige gnad do mit du dein sún gottes von himel gezogen hast in deinen junckfrelichen keyschen ra<supplied>in</supplied> leyb ich bit dich vnd begere</incipit>
                     <note>Each to be followed by three recitations of the <title>Salve regina</title>, hence the total 15, calling on Mary to aid the petitioner at the hour of her death and to save her from tribulation (<title>Anfechtung</title>).</note>
                     <note>These prayers are also found in a second manuscript written in Eastern Swabian dialect that formed part of Schöber’s collection: now Augsburg, UB, Cod. III. 1. 8º 43, fols 19r–31v, a manuscript of c.1545 from a Swabian Dominican nunnery (Maria Medingen?). In that manuscript they are presented for recitation upon death, whereas here the rubric explains that Mary will not abandon the petitioner who recites them every Saturday.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="2">
                     <locus from="9v" to="24v">(fols. 9v–24v)</locus>
                     <title type="desc">Four Marian prayers</title>
                     <msItem>
                        <incipit>Eya du mutter aller genaden vnd barmhertzigkait ich erman dich des grosen <locus from="10r" to="10r">(fol. 10r)</locus> hertz laid das du enpfiengest in dein ersten aigen blick do du dein liebs kind also sachest auf gehenckt in sterbender not</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <incipit><locus from="13v" to="13v">(fol. 13v)</locus> O maria du betriebte mutter gotz ich bit dich bis ingedenck der klaglichen <locus from="14r" to="14r">(fol. 14r)</locus> wort ihesu do er verlauszen was von got vnd allen creaturen</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <rubric><locus from="14v" to="14v">(fol. 14v)</locus> Aain hailsam gebet zů ewerben ain selligs end vnd vnser lieben frawen maria</rubric>
                        <incipit>O maria du fil hocher nam ich armer sunder rief dich an durch deines kinds finf wunden die dir durch deines hertz drungen vnd durch deines hailigen kinds vrstend</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <rubric><locus from="17r" to="17r">(fol. 17r)</locus> Ain schens gebet <sic>gebet</sic> von vnser lieben frawen</rubric>
                        <incipit>O maria gegries seyestu ain junckfraw aller eren ich erman dich der wirdigkait vnd aller der frede <locus from="17v" to="17v">(fol. 17v)</locus> die dein sel vnd leyb enpfangen haben</incipit>
                        <explicit><locus from="24v" to="24v">(fol. 24v)</locus> vnd beschirm mich vor allem ibel an sol leib er vnd gut durch aller der froden willen die ich dich ermanen bin erhorr vnd gewer mich dar vmb ich dich bitten bin amen</explicit>
                     </msItem>
                     <note>Begins with three that continue the theme of the previous set. They call upon Mary’s intercession to aid the petitioner, explicitly identified in the female voice (fol. 11r), upon the instant of her death, as signalled explicitly by the rubric to the third in the set here. These first three prayers show evidence of intensive use, as does the set on fols. 1r–9v that precedes them, as is to be seen from the dirt and wear evident at the lower outer corners. The fourth and longest prayer in this set is of a different character. Here the penitent lists to Mary the sequence of her joys, and calls on her aid in protection. This text concludes the first section of the manuscript, which occupies the first three quires (fols. 1–24), and is copied entirely by the first hand.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="3">
                     <locus from="25r" to="26v">(fols. 25r–26v)</locus>
                     <title type="desc">Confessional text for recitation before going to bed</title>
                     <rubric>bekandtnus so du wilt schlauffen gan</rubric>
                     <incipit>O herr ihesu xpe ich bekenn mich schuldig das ich disen tag laider nit zů deinem lob vnd ere verzert hab bin dir nit danckber gewesen hab dein tod vnd bittere marter nit recht zů hertzen gefasset</incipit>
                     <note>With this short text a new section of the manuscript begins: the second hand enters the larger part of this text (fols. 25r–26r), with which a new quire is started. The two hands were working together, as demonstrated by the change between hands in the final line on fol. 26r.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="4">
                     <locus from="26v" to="35v">(fols. 26v–35v)</locus>
                     <title type="desc">Three prayers for recitation upon waking in the morning, the first presented as a supplication for blessing</title>
                     <msItem>
                        <rubric>Ain guter segen so du zů morgen auf stast</rubric>
                        <incipit>O ewiger got vatter geseg†ne mich der <locus from="27r" to="27r">(fol. 27r)</locus> mich beschafen hat ain verninftige creatur gesen†ne mich got sůn der vmb meiner erlesung willen erliten hat dem bittern tod an dein stam des hailligen creytz</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <rubric><locus from="29r" to="29r">(fol. 29r)</locus> dises gebet sprich all morgen so du auf stats damit magst du dir alle deine werck so du dein tag verbringst verdenlich</rubric>
                        <incipit><locus from="29v" to="29v">(fol. 29v)</locus> O du aller hailligister almechtigster ewiger got barmhertziger hymelischer vatter mein trwer got vnd schöpfer in ewigkait der aller in brinstiger lieb demyetigkait gehorszam arbeit schmertze vnd leyden deines aller liebsten sůn</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <author key="person_309715179">Johann von Neumarkt</author>
                        <rubric><locus from="33v" to="33v">(fol. 33v)</locus> ain gebet zů deinen engel so du des morgen auff stast</rubric>
                        <incipit>Ewige wirdiger vnd himlischer geist der mir von dem al<locus from="34r" to="34r">(fol. 34r)</locus>mechtigen got zů behietten geben ist ich rieff dich an vnd bit dich mit aller demutigkait in dem namen deines vnd meines heren</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <note>The conceptual link to the previous confessional formula, to be used prior to sleep, is evident. The third prayer (fols. 33v–35v), to the penitent’s guardian angel, is by Johann von Neumarkt (d. 1380), the long-serving imperial chancellor to Charles IV and noted humanist; the text ed. Joseph Klapper, <title>Schriften Johanns von Neumarkt. 4. Teil: Gebete des Hofkanzlers und des Prager Kulturkreises</title> (Berlin, 1935), no. 23, pp. 176–79. This prayer to the guardian angel was very widely transmitted, and is found in other East Swabian manuscripts from Schöber’s collection: Augsburg, Universitätsbibliothek, Cod. III. 1. 8º 11, fols. 328v–332r, a manuscript dated 1490, provenance unknown, and Cod. III. 1. 8º 50, fols. 191v–193r, a manuscript of the second quarter of the 16th c., from the same Dominican nunnery as Cod. III. 1. 8º 43 discussed above, and later in Kirchheim.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="5">
                     <locus from="35v" to="42v">(fols. 35v–42v)</locus>
                     <title type="desc">A pair of prayers to Christ</title>
                     <msItem>
                        <rubric>Ain scheins gebet zu sprechen als vnser her <locus from="36r" to="36r">(fol. 36r)</locus> ihesus xps an elperg gangen ist</rubric>
                        <incipit>O aller bester hirtt vnd gayttigister herr ihesu xpi du der nach dein abendessen bist mit deinen iungern yber den bach cedron vnd auff den perg oliueti gegangen</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <rubric><locus from="40r" to="40r">(fol. 40r)</locus> Aain kostlichs gebett zů gut dem sun</rubric>
                        <incipit>O himlischer barmhertziger got in der ewigkayt mein o herr ihesu xpe du gietiger vatter wie gar williklich hastu dich geben in dem bittern tod von vnsertt wegen vnd erman dich deiner vetterlichen lieb</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <note>Focusing in turn on Christ’s nocturnal prayer and inner suffering in Gethsemane as he submitted his human will to his divine father, and then on the suffering he experienced on his willing submission to suffering in his crucifixion. The two prayers are entered by the two different hands, but here working together on the same quire.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="6">
                     <locus from="42v" to="48r">(fols. 42v–48r)</locus>
                     <title type="desc">Prayers structured as supplications to receive the seven gifts of the Holy Spirit</title>
                     <msItem>
                        <rubric>Das send die siben gaub des hailigen geists Veni sancte</rubric>
                        <incipit>Hailiger geyst verleych mir rechte gettliche forcht in der ich gelassen mig folkumenlich alsind vnd vntugent das ich mich in allen wercken ieben mig Veni sancte</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <rubric><locus from="47r" to="47r">(fol. 47r)</locus> sprich daz gebet darauff</rubric>
                        <incipit>O hailiger geyst vnd ewiger gott vetterliche lieb trester aller betriebten hertzen ich lob dich ich ere dich vnd sag <locus from="47v" to="47v">(fol. 47v)</locus> dir danck deiner gettlichen lieb</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <note>Each prayer to be followed by recitation of the Latin sequence <title>Veni sancte spiritus</title>. This set of prayers is known from other late medieval prayerbooks from southern Germany, e.g. Munich, Bayerische Staatsbibliothek, Cgm 845, fols. 119r–121r, a manuscript from c. 1469–70 written in a central Bavarian dialect, and Cgm 4637, fols. 41v–44r, a manuscript copied in the 1490s in a south-eastern Bavarian dialect.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="7">
                     <locus from="48r" to="49v">(fols. 48r–49v)</locus>
                     <author key="person_100187025">Anselm of Canterbury</author>
                     <title>Antiphon from the Marian Psalter</title>
                     <msItem>
                        <rubric>Das send die finf fredt maria</rubric>
                        <incipit>Fre dich du gebererin gottes du vnbefleckte iunckfraw. Fre dich das du hast von dem engel fred enpfangen. Fre dich die du geboren hast die klarhait des ewigen liechts</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <rubric><locus from="49r" to="49r">(fol. 49r)</locus> sprich darauff also</rubric>
                        <incipit>Bis gegriest du klare gilg der scheynenden wunsamen trifaltikait bis gegriest du bliende ros himlischer wollustikait</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <note>in German translation</note>
                     <note>This text, initially an antiphon from the <title>Hymni et Psalterium de sancta virgine Maria</title> by Anselm, archbishop of Canterbury (d. 1109), was circulated in translation quite widely in late medieval prayerbooks from the German south-east. Six copies were already assembled by Georg Steer (see Steer, <q>Anselm von Canterbury</q>, <title>Verfasserlexikon</title>, vol. 1, Berlin/New York, 1978, cols 380–81); the text is edited from a single manuscript, in parallel to the Latin original, in Klapper, 1935, no. 119, p. 379. In this manuscript, it is coupled by means of a rubric to a second short Marian salutation.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="8">
                     <locus from="49v" to="50v">(fols. 49v–50v)</locus>
                     <author key="person_309715179">Johann von Neumarkt</author>
                     <title>Prayer to the Guardian Apostle</title>
                     <rubric>Von meinem lieben zwelf botten ain gebett</rubric>
                     <incipit>O ir wirdigen himel firsten mein liben zwelf botten vnd fir sprecher <note>[in margin: <q>S. filipi vnd iacobi</q>]</note> vor dem almechtigen got wan ir mit andern him(fol. 50r)el firsten an dem iungsten tag in gegenwirdigkait des himlischen kaisers vnd obristen richters vrtail geben werdent iber al menschen</incipit>
                     <note>ed. Klapper, 1935, no. 24, pp. 180–81.</note>
                     <note>The second prayer by the imperial chancellor and humanist Johann von Neumarkt (d. 1380) to be included in this manuscript, alongside the prayer to one’s guardian angel at fols. 33v–35v above, this is formulated as an address to one’s guardian apostle. This prayer enjoyed a very wide transmission, and the text in this manuscript shows the effect of multiple copying in its form when compared with the version in the critical edition. In the left-hand margin of fol. 49v, the nun who copied this prayer (our <q>second hand</q>) has entered the name of her own guardian apostles, SS. Philip and James, in red ink: an indication, perhaps, that the manuscript was intended for her personal use.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="9">
                     <locus from="51r" to="57v">(fols. 51r–57v)</locus>
                     <title type="desc">Prayers that begin with invocations of praise to God the Father, Son, and Holy Spirit, and the Virgin Mary</title>
                     <msItem>
                        <rubric>Am ersten soltu beten iii pater noster der aller gailigesten trifaltikait vnd sprich darnach zů dem vatter also</rubric>
                        <incipit>Lob ere vnd danck sey dir gott ewiger vatter das du mich beschaffen hast. Lob ere vnd danck sey dir <locus from="51v" to="51v">(fol. 51v)</locus> herr ihesu xpe das du mich erlest hast mit deinem bittern tod</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <rubric><locus from="52v" to="52v">(fol. 52v)</locus> Ain costlich gebet zů got dem sun ist gar halsam zů sprechen</rubric>
                        <incipit>O herr ihesu xpe ich sag dir von ganczem herczen lob ere vnd danck deines vnschuldigen todts den du vmb mich erlitten hast</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <incipit><locus from="57v" to="57v">(fol. 57v)</locus> O herr ich senck mich in die tieffin deiner wunden O herr wesch mich mit deinem minnigklichen rosen farben blůt</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <note>Prefacing a very short prayer to Christ to ask for his protection from erroneous belief and assistance at death. These are followed by a much longer prayer (fols. 52v–57v) to ask for Christ’s mercy and support, concluded by a request for his special attention to the souls of the petitioner’s parents and all of her lineage. The final text in this set, entered on the final verso of the seventh quire and immediately before a change from the second back to the first hand, asks for the petitioner to enter Christ’s wounds and be bathed in his redemptive blood to participate in his merits (fol. 57v). It is to be found in a second Swabian prayerbook from Schöber’s collection, Augsburg, Universitätsbibliothek, Cod. III. 1. 8º 53, fols. 37v–38r, in this case of the later 15th c.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="10">
                     <locus from="58r" to="66r">(fols. 58r–66r)</locus>
                     <title type="desc">Prayers to Christ</title>
                     <msItem>
                        <rubric>ain gutz gebet zů got dem heren zů bete</rubric>
                        <incipit>Herr ich bin der arm mensch den du beschaffen hast von deiner vetterlichen crafft nach dir selbs gebildet erzaig heutt dein vatterliche lieb an mir armen menschen</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <rubric><locus from="59r" to="59r">(fol. 59r)</locus> Das gebet sprich noch der busz so gebeychtet hast</rubric>
                        <incipit>O herr ihesu xpe ich opffer huit mein claine bus in die bittrikait deines willigen leidens vnd in deinen bittern dot vnd ich armer sunder bit dich</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <incipit><locus from="61r" to="61r">(fol. 61r)</locus> O her ich opffer dir huit mein klaine bůsz in dein reychtumb deines hochwirdigen verdenen vnd bitt dich durch deynen hailigen wirdigen tod das du mir vergebest</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <incipit><locus from="62r" to="62r">(fol. 62r)</locus>O herr ihesu xpe ich wirff die groshait meiner sind in die grosz vnd bittrikait deiner marter vnd deines leidens vnd bint mein klaine bůs an die groshait deines wirdigen verdenens</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <incipit><locus from="62v" to="62v">(fol. 62v)</locus> O aller gietigister vnd barmherczigister herr <locus from="63r" to="63r">(fol. 63r)</locus> ihesu xpe ich bitt dich vmb deinen hailigen namen das du die klaine gnug tuung meiner rui vnd bekantnus beycht vnd bůsz vmb mein sind wellest erfillen vnd volkumen machen</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <incipit><locus from="64r" to="64r">(fol. 64r)</locus> O almechtiger vnd barmhercziger gietiger gott du hast alweg berait dem menschen zů helffen ausz seynen sinden ich beken vnd ist mir laid das ich in meinen vergangen tagen</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <note>Commenced by the first hand returning to begin a new quire, but completed by the second hand from fol. 61r onwards. The initial prayer on fols. 58r–v is a tripartite petition to request mercy in recognition that man is created in God’s image. It is followed by a sequence of five prayers (fols. 59r–66r) for recitation after confession, as the petitioner offers her penance to Christ and seeks his merits in securing her salvation. This sequence of five prayers was printed at the start of the 1520 edition of the <title>Gilgengart</title> by Hans Schönsperger in Augsburg (the edition is unpaginated; see Online Resources below). Whether the text in this manuscript was copied from the printed edition, which would supply an important terminus post quem for this manuscript, or whether the <title>Gilgengart</title> drew on textual material that had earlier circulated in manuscript form, is uncertain.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="11">
                     <locus from="66r" to="92r">(fols. 66r–92r)</locus>
                     <title type="desc">25 eucharistic prayers</title>
                     <msItem n="i">
                        <rubric>wan du wilt gan zů dem hochwirgigen sacrament so sprich dise gebett mit andacht deines herczen</rubric>
                        <incipit>O herr ich sag dir danck <locus from="66v" to="66v">(fol. 66v)</locus> das du mich so hertiklich hast erarnet vnd bitt dich schick mir durch dein verdenst dich nach deinem wol gefallen zů enpfachen dan in dir ist alle gnad vnd enpfach ich meynen selig macher</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="ii">
                        <locus from="67v">(fol. 67v)</locus>
                        <incipit>Ach zarter herr gott ich bitt dich demietiklich <locus from="68r" to="68r">(fol. 68r)</locus> dein selbs ere mit tail mir dein gnad durch das ich mich mig schicken dich wirdiklich zů enpfachen mit danckberkait meines herczen</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="iii">
                        <locus from="68v">(fol. 68v)</locus>
                        <incipit>Zarter herr ihesu xpe du miniklicher herr vnd got <locus from="69r" to="69r">(fol. 69r)</locus> ich beger dich zů enpfachen vmb meiner besserung willen wan ich beken mich gancz gebrechlich vnd wolt mich geren bessern</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="iv">
                        <locus from="72r">(fol. 72r)</locus>
                        <incipit>O herr ihesu xpe ich armer sinder fall huit fir dich vnd naig mich fir dein gettlich fies vnd zaig deiner gruntlosen barmherczikait mein schuldigs gewissen das dir allain bekand ist</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="v">
                        <locus from="74v">(fol. 74v)</locus>
                        <incipit>O du wirdiges opffer wan von deiner crafft die hell zerbrochen wart vnd das gefangen folck erlestest vnd in das ewig leben gabest kum herr ihesu xpe vnd mach mich rain von allen meinen sinden</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="vi">
                        <locus from="75v">(fol. 75v)</locus>
                        <incipit>O herr ihesu xpe ain sun gottes hilf mir das ich dich entpfach das du lust habest zů mir zů kumen vnd <locus from="76r" to="76r">(fol. 76r)</locus> bey mir zů beleyben o du gruntloses gůtt das von himel herab kumen ist</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="vii">
                        <locus from="76v">(fol. 76v)</locus>
                        <incipit>O herr ich gang zů dir das ich arm bin vnd nun mir dein fasten deyn <locus from="77r" to="77r">(fol. 77r)</locus> wachen dein betten vnd alle deyne gůtte werck vnd alle deyn tugent zieren mich zů deiner wirdtschafft</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="viii">
                        <locus from="78r">(fol. 78r)</locus>
                        <incipit>Himlischer vatter mein sind send so fil das ich die nit ablegen kan da von wil ich huit dein ain geboren sun enpfachen dir zů lob vnd zů ainem opffer</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="ix">
                        <locus from="79r">(fol. 79r)</locus>
                        <incipit>O du ewige weyshait herr ihesu xpe du hast vns menschen hie auf erden die gnad verlichen das wir gespeyst sollen werden mit deinem zarten fronleychnam erher mich armen sinder</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="x">
                        <locus from="80r">(fol. 80r)</locus>
                        <incipit>O herr ihesu xpe du gna<locus from="80v" to="80v">(fol. 80v)</locus>den reycher schacz meiner sel lasz huit in mir erfilt werden das trostlich wort das du sprachest zů deinem iungern an dem lesten aubent</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="xi">
                        <locus from="81r">(fol. 81r)</locus>
                        <incipit>Eia du ewigs wort gefloszen ausz dem herczen deines himlischen vatters kum huit gnedi<locus from="81v" to="81v">(fol.81v)</locus>klich zů mir vnd verschmech mich nit dein creatur bin ich dein nit wirdig</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="xii">
                        <incipit>Ich bitt dich got himlisz<locus from="82r" to="82r">(fol. 82r)</locus>cher vatter du wellest mich gnediklich enpfachen vnd erheren in meinem gebet vnd alles das von mir nemen das mich krenckt an leyb vnd an sel</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="xiii">
                        <locus from="82v">(fol. 82v)</locus>
                        <incipit>O herr ihesu xpe naig dich zů mir seyt du deyn gietige barmherczikait dich geben wilt allen den die dich anrieffen</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="xiv">
                        <locus from="83r">(fol. 83r)</locus>
                        <incipit>Herr ihesu xpe ich stand vor dir als ain schuldiger mensch vor ainem gewaltigen richter der vrtail wart det vnd nit waisz wie esz im ergan wirt</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="xv">
                        <locus from="84r">(fol. 84r)</locus>
                        <incipit>O herr ihesu xpe du hast mich gebilt nach dir das vergis nit an mit herr du hast mich kaufft mit deinem rosen farben blůt</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="xvi">
                        <locus from="84v">(fol. 84v)</locus>
                        <incipit>Herr ihesu xpe du bist mein vatter ich bin dein kind wie gros mein schuld ist so ist doch dein barmherczigkait fil greser</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="xvii">
                        <locus from="85r">(fol. 85r)</locus>
                        <incipit>O herr ihesu xpe ich birg mich huit in dem bach deynes rosen farben blůts vor deinem zoren den ich verdent hab mit meinem sinden</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="xviii">
                        <locus from="85v">(fol. 85v)</locus>
                        <incipit>O herr ihesu xpe ich senck mich in die tief aller deiner wunden wesch mich mit deinem rosen farben blůt</incipit>
                        <rubric>wan du gleych hin zů wi<locus from="86r" to="86r">(fol. 86r)</locus>lt gan schprich also</rubric>
                        <msItem>
                           <incipit>O herr ich bin nit wirdig das du gangest vnder mein tach sprich nit mer dan ain word so wirt gesuntt mein arme sel,</incipit>
                           <rubric>nach der enpfachung</rubric>
                           <note>Adapted from Mt 8.8.</note>
                        </msItem>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="xix">
                        <incipit>O ewiger himlischer got wer bin ich oder wer hat mir die gnad erworben von dir vatter von himel reich</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="xx">
                        <locus from="87r">(fol. 87r)</locus>
                        <incipit>O du sieses himel brot herr ihesu xpe ain sun <locus from="87v" to="87v">(fol. 87v)</locus> gottes des himlischen vatters geboren ausz der iunckfrawen maria ich lob dich mit ganczen herczen</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="xxi">
                        <locus from="88v">(fol. 88v)</locus>
                        <incipit>Mein sel lobt got dem hailigen geyst durch das wircken des hailigen froleychnams xpi der gebildet vnd gemacht ist in dem rainen leyb marie</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="xxii">
                        <locus from="89v">(fol. 89v)</locus>
                        <incipit>O herr ihesu xpe gib mir ledigung meines hercz das es an kainer creatur hafft noch mein zeyt an kain creatur leg dan an dich</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="xxiii">
                        <locus from="90r">(fol. 90r)</locus>
                        <incipit>O herr dein hailiger froleychnam sey mir ain frid vnd ain fred in allen notten sei mir <locus from="90v" to="90v">(fol. 90v)</locus> ain trost</incipit>
                        <rubric>Zů vnser frawen sprich also</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="xxiv">
                        <incipit>O du aller rainiste můter vnsers herren hailige maria du ewige iunckfra die du den selben schepffer aller creatur wirdig gewesen bist</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="xxv">
                        <locus from="91v">(fol. 91v)</locus>
                        <incipit>O barmhercziger ewiger got <locus from="92r" to="92r">(fol. 92r)</locus> ich befilch mich arme sinderin in dein blůt farb seytten in der do lag dein truies rains hercz</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <note>The first 18 preparatory prayers for recitation prior to sacramental reception, followed by an adapted version of Mt 8,8 for recitation at the moment of reception, and a further seven prayers for recitation after reception, the final two addressed to Mary. Two blocks of prayers, nos. ix–xii and xix–xxi, are by the Augustinian canon <persName key="person_263144756">Johannes von Indersdorf</persName> (d. 1470), being nos. 1–4 and 7–9 of his cycle of ten eucharistic prayers from the so-called <q>Gebetbuch I. für Elisabeth Ebran</q>, written 1426 (see Franz Xaver Haimerl, <title>Mittelalterliche Frömmigkeit im Spiegel der Gebetbuchliteratur Süddeutschlands</title>, 1952, pp. 152–57, with incipits of the eucharistic prayers given at p. 153 n. 946; for the author see Bernhard D. Haage, <q>Johannes von Indersdorf</q>, <title>Verfasserlexikon</title>, vol. 4, Berlin/New York, 1983, cols 647–51, and on this prayerbook and its known manuscript transmission Haage, Bernhard, <title>Der Traktat <q>Von Dreierlei Wesen der Menschen</q></title> (Diss. Heidelberg, 1968), pp. 49–59, 64–97, and 533–34). Some others can be identified elsewhere, although this particular arrangement of 25 prayers appears to be unique to this manuscript.</note>
                     <note>No. xiv was presented in a critical edition by Klapper, 1935, no. 46, pp. 216–18, where it is termed a <q>Reuegebet vor Christus.</q> No. iv is transmitted in several late medieval manuscripts from southern Germany (e.g. Leipzig, Universitätsbibliothek, Ms. 0737, fols. 94v–96r; Munich, Bayerische Staatsbibliothek, Cgm 744, fols. 1v–2v; Munich, Universitätsbibliothek, 8º Cod. ms. 258, fols. 22r–24r and again at fols. 74r–78r). No. xviii, a prayer which begins with the petitioner asking to be washed in Christ’s blood as she enters the depths of his wounds, is known from two other manuscripts in Schöber’s collection (Augsburg, Universitätsbibliothek, Cod. III. 1. 8º 6, fol. 154v, this section written in an Eastern Swabian dialect and dated 1459; and Cod. III. 1. 8º 53, fols. 37v–38r, a late fifteenth-century manuscript in Swabian dialect) and elsewhere besides (see Haimerl, 1952, pp. 48–49 n. 247, p. 53 n. 267, and p. 143 n. 897). No. xxii, which follows the second block of prayers by Johannes von Indersdorf, is also known in other manuscripts (see Haimerl, 1952, pp. 48–49 n. 247, p. 53 n. 267, and p. 143 n. 897).</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="12">
                     <locus from="92r" to="96r">(fols. 92r–96r)</locus>
                     <rubric>Von der krenung vnsers herren</rubric>
                     <incipit>O herr ihesu xpe ich danck <locus from="92v" to="92v">(fol. 92v)</locus> dir mit dein selbs wirdigkait deiner bittern schmerczlichen peyn die du hast gelitten in deiner krenung vnd besunder der ellenden verserten fůsz trit</incipit>
                     <note>An extended prayer that focuses on Christ’s coronation with thorns, paying especial attention to the blood that ran down Christ’s body as the thorns penetrated his head, the damage inflicted on his brain as the thorns were pressed into his skull, and further despoliation afflicted upon his face in the course of his crucifixion. This prayer shows indications of intensive use; the lower outer corners of the pages are almost translucent from repeated handling. On the narrative elaboration of the coronation with thorns in later medieval texts from the German-speaking lands see Tobias A. Kemper, <title>Die Kreuzigung Christi. Motivgeschichtliche Studien zu lateinischen und deutschen Passionstraktaten des Spätmittelalters</title> (Tübingen, 2006), pp. 199–207.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="13">
                     <locus from="96r" to="98v">(fols. 96r–98v)</locus>
                     <rubric>uon allen zwelf botten ain gebet</rubric>
                     <incipit>O ir besundern ausserwelten von got ir hailige zwelffbotten vnsers lieben herren ihesu xpi der warhaftigen stim seliger bredig in alles ertrich auszgangen vnd zů end aller welten ir wort erhollen send</incipit>
                     <note>Prayer to the Apostles, which consists in large part of an extended praise of the apostles, expressed as a series of apostrophes (<q>O, you twelve gemstones on Aaron’s priestly robe</q>, etc.). This prayer is quite widely transmitted, and is also found in two other south-eastern German prayerbooks of a similar period: Augsburg, Universitätsbibliothek, Cod. III. 1. 8º 55, fols. 157r–160v, a late fifteenth-century manuscript in central Bavarian dialect with Eastern Swabian features, and Cod. I. 3. 8º 1, fols. 117r–121r, a manuscript of the first quarter of the sixteenth century from Nuremberg.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="14">
                     <locus from="99r" to="262r">(fols. 99r–262r)</locus>
                     <title key="work_16443">Andächtiges Myrrhenbüschlein</title>
                     <rubric>Fasciculus mirre dilectus meus michi interr vbera mea comorabitur conticorum</rubric>
                     <incipit>Zu machen ain gestlichs mirren büschelin auff daz hercz zů legen alz die lieb haberin des herren spricht mein geliebter ist mir ain mirren büschelin vnd wond in meinen herczen <locus from="99v" to="99v">(fol. 99v)</locus> dar iber spricht S bernhartus vmb daz mirren büschelin hab ich von iugennt auf nott vnd fleys gehabt</incipit>
                     <explicit><locus from="261v" to="261v">(fol. 261v)</locus> er sprach auch wo du dich finst da lasz dich vnd tracht das du ain sel habest die als gedurstig sey das si alle ding getir don vnd lassen durch den herren ob alle welt wider vns ist vnd auf vns vrtailt das schat vns nit <locus from="262r" to="262r">(fol. 262r)</locus> on wir mit got ains send so sol vns vnser aug hin zů im stan wan durch in sollen wir billich alle ding leyden amen.</explicit>
                     <note>This work, an extended Passion narrative known as the <title>Devout Bundle of Myrrh</title>, forms the quantitative core of the manuscript. It belongs to that medieval tradition of interpreting Christ’s Passion in relation to Ct 1,12 (<q>Fasciculus murrae dilectus meus mihi inter ubera mea commorabitur</q>), first developed at length by Bernard of Clairvaux in his 43rd sermon on the Song of Songs. Bernard’s approach to contemplation of Christ’s Passion by means of mental recapitulation of a series of episodes of suffering from the course of Christ’s life was highly influential for the later medieval tradition: as, for example, for the <title>Arbor vitae crucifixae</title> of the Franciscan Spiritual Ubertino da Casale (see Stephen Mossman, <q>Ubertino da Casale and the Devotio Moderna</q>, <title>Ons Geestelijk Erf</title> 80 (2009), pp. 229–34).</note>
                     <note>The <title>Andächtiges Myrrhenbüschlein</title> is one of a number of late medieval German and Dutch treatises that adopt the Bernardine premise of interpreting Ct 1,12 in relation to the contemplation of Christ’s Passion (for a conspectus see Kemper, 2006, pp. 161–63). It was hitherto known in just six other manuscripts (see Dietrich Schmidtke, <q>Myrrhenbüschel-(Fasciculus-myrrhae-)Texte</q>, <title>Verfasserlexikon</title>, vol. 6, Berlin/New York, 1987, col. 835 [his no. III. A. 2], and Online Resources below). To judge on this evidence, it is a later fifteenth-century composition from the German south-east, and one that has received no scholarly attention whatsoever. It begins with a short prologue, in which Bernard’s 43rd sermon on the Song of Songs is quoted directly and extensively, and then proceeds to narrate episodes of suffering from Christ’s life, beginning with Christ’s cognition of the weight of human sin while he was still as yet unborn in Mary’s womb (for this tradition of extending Christ’s suffering across the length of his life, see Stephen Mossman, <title>Marquard von Lindau and the Challenges of Religious Life in Late Medieval Germany. The Passion, the Eucharist, the Virgin Mary</title>, Oxford, 2010, pp. 67–102).</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="15">
                     <locus from="262r" to="270v">(fols. 262r–270v)</locus>
                     <title type="desc">Seven prayers to be accompanied by recitation of the Lord’s Prayer</title>
                     <rubric>Hie nach folgent die siben ausgeng vnsers lieben herren</rubric>
                     <incipit>O herr ihesu xpe ain scheyn der vetterlichen eren vnd seyner magestat diser pater noster <locus from="262v" to="262v">(fol. 262v)</locus> sey dir gesprochen zů lob ere vnd danckberkait vnd erman dich da mit des ausz gang ausz dem vetterlichen herczen in den iunckfrelichen leyb</incipit>
                     <note>Structured around the seven processions of Christ: the first is his emanation from his Father’s heart into Mary’s womb; the second is his birth, and so on. The text is known from a second prayerbook from Schöber’s collection, a manuscript of c. 1545 in Eastern Swabian dialect (Augsburg, Universitätsbibliothek, Cod. III. 1. 8º 43, fols. 1r–9v), noted earlier above in relation to the text on fols. 1r–9v of this manuscript. It is also found in Leipzig, Universitätsbibliothek, Ms. 0737, fols. 83r–89r, noted earlier above in relation to the prayer at fols. 72r–74v, a sixteenth-century manuscript in Bavarian dialect; and in the same collection also in Ms. 1568, fols. 74v–79r, a later fifteenth-century manuscript from Augsburg, potentially from the Dominican nunnery of St. Katharina. In both of those manuscripts this text is also accompanied by the following text in this manuscript (i.e. fols. 270v–272v), although in the reverse order.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="16">
                     <locus from="270v" to="272v">(fols. 270v–272v)</locus>
                     <title type="desc">Three prayers to be accompanied by recitation of the Lord’s Prayer</title>
                     <rubric>Das ist gar kostlich zů sprechen bey ainem sterbenden menschen vnd send die dry pater noster</rubric>
                     <incipit>O err <note>[sic]</note> ihesu xpe das gebet sey dir zů lob deinem lesten zigen vnd allen deinen <locus from="271r" to="271r">(fol. 271r)</locus> wunden sunderlichen deinem blůtigen schwais den du schwicztest vor angsten deiner marter</incipit>
                     <note>Specified in the rubric as particularly valuable for recitation by or for a dying person. This text travels as a pair with its predecessor: it is found, as noted above, in Leipzig, Universitätsbibliothek, Ms. 0737, fols. 81v–83r, and Ms. 1568, fols. 73v–74v, in both cases immediately preceding the same text that it follows in this present manuscript.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="17">
                     <locus from="272v" to="277r">(fols. 272v–277r)</locus>
                     <rubric>Item von disen nachgeschriben drey pater noster hat man iij <locus from="273r" to="273r">(fol. 273r)</locus> tausent jar applas vnd was tods der mensch begriffen wirt das er doch von got nit geschaiden wirt</rubric>
                     <incipit>O herr ihesu xpe dein ersten pater noster sey dir zů lob er vnd dancksagen dein grosen schmertzen vnd seufzen den du tetest da su zů ierusalem auszgiengest</incipit>
                     <note>A set of three prayers, each to follow recitation of the Lord’s Prayer, and associated with three <q>sighs</q> exhaled by Christ upon episodes associated with his Passion: his entrance into Jerusalem, his setting down of the cross at the site of his crucifixion, and his inspection of the nails that were to be used to crucify him. The rubric associates recitation of these prayers with the acquisition of a thousand years of indulgence, and God’s steadfast assistance at the hour of death.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="18">
                     <locus from="277v" to="278r">(fols. 277v–278r)</locus>
                     <rubric>Esz was ain geischlicher korher der selb het dise gewonhait an im wa er ain crucifyx hat gesechen oder dar fur gangen ist hat er all weg vnseren herren trulichen ermant vnd gebeten auch geeret mit disen noch geschriben gebet …</rubric>
                     <note>The final text is merely the rubric to a prayer that has not been entered, and the final leaves remain blank. The rubric takes the form of an edifying exemplum: a canon whose custom was to recite this prayer on encountering a crucifix, whereupon he would also call to mind the events of Christ’s Passion, was greeted at the moment of his death with a heavenly voice that told him his petitions would be granted.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem>
                     <locus from="278v" to="287v">(fols. 278v–287v)</locus>
                     <note>Blank</note>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="chart">
                        <support>Paper, in sedecimo; with a pair of watermarks, <watermark>a crown with a double-contoured hoop studded with pearls, above which is a double-contoured cross, above which is a single-contoured star, in use c.1520–c.1550 (Piccard-Online nos. 54278–54729). A more precise identification not possible on account of the multiple cuts produced by sedecimo format.</watermark></support>
                        <extent><measure type="leaf" quantity="287">287</measure> leaves <dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                              <height>105</height>
                              <width>70</width>
                           </dimensions>
                        </extent>
                        <foliation>Modern foliation.</foliation>
                        <collation>i–iii⁸ + iv¹⁰ + v–xxxv⁸ + xxxvi⁵ [where fol. 283 is contiguous with rear pastedown]</collation>
                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout columns="1" writtenLines="10 12">Normally on 10–12 unruled lines, on written space <dimensions type="ruled" unit="mm">
                              <height max="70" min="65">c. 65–70</height>
                              <width>55</width>
                           </dimensions>
                        </layout>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc>
                     <summary>Written in two, possibly three hands.</summary>
                     <handNote execution="currens" script="hybrida">An irregular hybrida currens, fols. 1r–24v, 26r–39v, 58r–60v, and 272v–278r.</handNote>
                     <handNote execution="currens" script="hybrida">Semihybrida currens, with unusually elongated ascenders, 25r–26r, 40r–57v, 61r–272v, where fols. 99r–139r might conceivably be written by a distinct, third hand.</handNote>
                  </handDesc>
                  <decoDesc>
                     <decoNote type="flourInit">One- and two-line red penwork initials.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="rubrication">Rubrication throughout.</decoNote>
                  </decoDesc>
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <binding contemporary="true">
                        <p>Bound in brown blind-tooled leather (binding stamps resist present identification) over wooden boards with paper pastedowns, sewn on three cords, with functional metal clasp. <dimensions type="binding" unit="mm">
                              <height>110</height>
                              <width>85</width>
                           </dimensions></p>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="1550" notBefore="1520">c.1520–c.1550</origDate>
                     <origPlace>
                        <region key="place_7017048">Swabia</region>, <country key="place_7000084">Germany</country>.</origPlace> The manuscript is copied in an East Swabian dialect, and so can be localized in that region, the area around the cities of Ulm and Augsburg. The paper stocks provide an approximate dating to the period c.1520–c.1550. Occasional prayers are presented in a female voice (e.g. <q>zu wem ich mich armen sünderin keren sol</q>, fol. 11r; <q>ich befilch mich arme sinderin</q>, fol. 92r); taken together with the evidence of two hands working together, this is very likely an institutional product of a female convent. It would require identification of the binding stamps, which has not yet proven possible, to propose an association with a particular convent in the region. Evidence of intensive use of fols. 1–15 and 92–98.</origin>
                  <provenance><persName key="person_3233054" role="fmo">David Gottfried Schöber</persName> (1696–1778), his inscription on front pastedown: <q>Dieses Ms. welches ungefehr Aº1480 von einer Nonne in einem Schwäbischen Kloster geschrieben, ist der Kirschkauischen Bibliothek gewidmet. / David Gottfried Schöber / Gera A. 11 September 1761</q>. Schöber, a merchant who was elected mayor of Gera in Thüringen in 1760, was a noted hymnologist with a significant collection of medieval and early modern manuscripts, on which he drew for his studies and textual editions (see Online Resources below). A set of some 30 German prayerbooks in small formats, mostly from Swabian and Franconian nunneries of the Dominican Order, were acquired from his collection at auction in 1779 by Prince Kraft Ernst zu Oettingen-Wallerstein (1748–1802), and are now held by the Universitätsbibliothek Augsburg (see Karin Schneider, <title>Deutsche Mittelalterliche Handschriften der Universitätsbibliothek Augsburg: die Signaturengruppen Cod. I. 3 und Cod. III. 1</title>, Wiesbaden, 1988, pp. 11–12).</provenance>
                  <provenance>Kirschkau, Thüringen, Bibliothek der <orgName key="org_242317182">Jesus-Kirche</orgName>. Schöber’s inscription of donation (see no. 2 above) indicates that the manuscript entered the library of the parish church in the village of Kirschkau, in Thüringen about 40 km south-south-east of Gera. That library can be documented with certainty from 1704, and the donation of this manuscript in 1761 was likely connected to the rebuilding of the church in the years 1751–53 by Count Heinrich XII Reuß zu Schleiz, who was also responsible for the copying and donation of manuscripts to the library in the years 1756–58.</provenance>
                  <provenance>Unidentified German collection, shelfmark in pencil on front pastedown: <q>Regal IX, Fach 3</q>.</provenance>
                  <acquisition>Purchased from Les Enluminures, April 2021.</acquisition>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>Adapted (May 2021) by Andrew Dunning from a description by Stephen Mossman for Les Enluminures, 2017.</source>
                     </recordHist>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <surrogates>
                     <bibl subtype="full" type="digital-facsimile">
                        <ref target="https://digital.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/objects/4fe29f7d-7d36-4c29-bae4-ac53d0013cdc/">
                           <title>Digital Bodleian</title></ref>
                        <note>(full digital facsimile)</note>
                     </bibl>
                  </surrogates>
                  <listBibl type="WRAPPER">
                     <listBibl type="INTERNET">
                        <head>Online resources:</head>
                        <bibl><ref target="https://hab.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/en/"><title>Manuscripts from German-Speaking Lands – A Polonsky Foundation Digitization Project</title></ref></bibl>
                     </listBibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2021-05-31"><persName>Andrew Dunning</persName> Encoded description.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>