<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="manuscript_2007">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>MS. Buchanan g. 3</title>
            <title type="collection">MSS. Buchanan</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Cataloguer</resp>
               <persName>Peter Kidd</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </publisher>
            <idno type="msID">MS_Buchanan_g_3</idno>
            <idno type="collection">Buchanan</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="MS_Buchanan_g_3">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <region type="county">Oxfordshire</region>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <institution>University of Oxford</institution>
                  <repository>Bodleian Library</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">MS. Buchanan g. 3</idno>
                  <idno type="ieArk">ark:29072/x0hd76s026bm</idno><idno type="crArk">ark:29072/x0h989r3431r</idno><altIdentifier type="SCN">
                     <idno>Not in Summary Catalogue (late accession)</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents>
                  <textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>
                  <msItem class="#liturgica #biblia" xml:id="MS_Buchanan_g_3-item1">
                     <title key="work_14114" type="desc">Psalter (ferial)</title>
                     <msItem xml:id="MS_Buchanan_g_3-item1-item1">
                        <note>[Items 1–2 occupy quire I]</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem xml:id="MS_Buchanan_g_3-item1-item2">
                        <locus from="1r" to="6v">(fols. 1r–6v)</locus>
                        <note>Calendar</note>
                        <note>about half-full; graded with commemorations, feasts of twelve lessons, and <hi rend="italic">duplex maius</hi> or <hi rend="italic">minus</hi> feasts, but no feasts of three or nine lessons; January headed by a note on the number of months, weeks, and days in the year, in red; each month headed by a note on the length of the calendar and lunar month, in red; the Golden Numbers given in arabic numerals; major feasts (in red) include: Benedict ('<hi rend="italic">Sanctissimi patris nostri Benedicti ... duplex maius</hi>') (21 Mar.), Placidus and his companions, '<hi rend="italic">duplex maius</hi>' (5 Oct.), Justina, '<hi rend="italic">duplex maius</hi>' (7 Oct.), Ambrose '<hi rend="italic">duplex minus</hi>' (7 Dec.); feasts of twelve lessons in ordinary ink include Simeon (26 July), Dominic (5 Aug.), Cyprian &amp; Justina (26 Sept.), Columban (21 Nov.); vigils are written as: 'Vigilia de precepto'; numerous erasures, regradings, and additions in January-June; contemporary additions include George, Felix, Fortunatus, and Achilleus (23 Apr., twelve lessons); regradings include some of three lessons, and others of twelve divided into eight and four lessons.</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem xml:id="MS_Buchanan_g_3-item1-item3">
                        <locus from="7r" to="10v">(fols. 7r–10v)</locus>
                        <note>Tables of the antiphons before Christmas (pr. S. J. P. van Dijk, ed., <title>Sources of the modern Roman liturgy: the ordinals of Haymo of Faversham and related documents (1243–1307)</title> (Studia et Documenta Franciscana: 2 vols., Leiden, 1963), II, 401–8).</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem xml:id="MS_Buchanan_g_3-item1-item4">
                        <note>[Items 3–6 occupy quires II-XII] </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem xml:id="MS_Buchanan_g_3-item1-item5">
                        <locus from="11r" to="92r">(fols. 11r–92r)</locus>
                        <note>Ferial Psalter</note>
                        <note>beginning imperfect in Ps. 6:9 (at '|| operamini iniquitatem ...'), due to the loss of a leaf before fol. 11; with Benedictine divisions (except Ps. 32; see under Decoration), and sub-divisions of psalms marked (e.g. Pss. 9:20, 17:26, 67:20, 103:25, fols. 13r, 16v, 46v, 68v, respectively).</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem xml:id="MS_Buchanan_g_3-item1-item6">
                        <locus from="92r" to="97r">(fols. 92r–97r)</locus>
                        <note>Canticles for Advent, Christmas, Quadragesima, and Easter; and <locus from="95v" to="97r">(fols. 95v–97r)</locus> for the Common of Saints.</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem xml:id="MS_Buchanan_g_3-item1-item7">
                        <locus from="97r" to="111r">(fols. 97r–111r)</locus>
                        <note>Hymnal</note>
                        <note>including hymns for major feasts of the Temporale, the Dedication of the Church, Sts. Benedict and <locus from="107v" to="108v">(fols. 107v–108v)</locus> Justina, and the Common of Saints. </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem xml:id="MS_Buchanan_g_3-item1-item8">
                        <locus from="111r" to="113v">(fols. 111r–113v)</locus>
                        <note>Litany and collects</note>
                        <note> The litany including Placidus and his companions, sixth among twelve martyrs; Benedict ('Sancte pater Benedicte') first among ten monks and hermits; and Justina second among fourteen virgins; followed <locus from="112r" to="112v">(fol. 112r–v)</locus> by petitions including:</note>
                        <msItem xml:id="MS_Buchanan_g_3-item1-item8-item1">
                           <incipit>Ut omnes nauigantes ad portum salutis perducere digneris</incipit>
                        </msItem>
                        <note>and <locus from="113r" to="113v">(fol. 113r–v)</locus> by the usual ten collects (see MS. Buchanan e. 5, where they are listed); the fifth mentioning '... famulo tuo presidenti nostro ...'; the tenth ending imperfect (at '... omniumque misere||[ris]'), due to the loss of a bifolium after fol. 113; fols. 114r-115v, ruled, otherwise blank.</note>
                     </msItem>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <p>
                     <secFol>
                        <locus>(Calendar, fol. 2r)</locus>KL Martius</secFol>
                     <secFol>
                        <locus>(tables, fol. 8r)</locus> Ad laudes</secFol>
                     <secFol>
                        <locus>(text, fol. 11r)</locus> operamini iniquitatem</secFol>
                     <secFol>
                        <locus>(text, fol. 12r)</locus> deducat Exurge</secFol>
                  </p>
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="perg">
                        <support>Parchment, rather water-stained at beginning and end; offsets indicate that the bifolium was already missing after fol. 113 when the water-damage occured.</support>
                        <extent>ii (paper, the first marbled and conjoint with the pastedown) + 115 + ii (paper, the second marbled and conjoint with the pastedown).<dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                              <height max="75" min="73">73–5</height>
                              <width max="105" min="104">104–5 mm.; the decoration cropped in all three outer margins.</width>
                           </dimensions>
                           <dimensions type="ruled" unit="mm">
                              <height max="77" min="76">76–7</height>
                              <width max="55" min="45">54–5</width>
                           </dimensions>
                        </extent>
                        <foliation>Foliated in modern pencil: i-ii, 1–117.</foliation>
                        <collation>In quires of 10 leaves, with some losses: I<hi rend="superscript">10</hi> (fols. 1–10) | II<hi rend="superscript">10–1</hi> (1st leaf excised, leaving a stub before fol. 11) (fols. 11–19), III-XI<hi rend="superscript">10</hi> (fols. 20–109), XII<hi rend="superscript">10–4</hi> (5rd and 6th leaves, a bifolium, missing, 9th and 10th leaves excised) (fols. 110–115) <catchwords>CATCHWORDS survive at the end of every quire except the first and last, written in the same script as the main text, horizontally in the lower margin, between the ruled vertical intercolumnar bounding lines, about two lines' height below the bottom line of text, surrounded in a saltire pattern by four designs in paler ink, each like a cross of St. Andrew on a quatrefoil.</catchwords>
                        </collation>
                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout columns="2" ruledLines="33" writtenLines="32">33 lines ruled in very pale brown ink, in two columns, each column between single vertical bounding lines extending the full height of the page; the inter-columnar space c.6 mm.; single PRICKINGS survive in the upper fore-edge margin, 4–5 mm. above the top ruled line. 32 lines of text per page; the written space of each column 74–6 × 23–4 mm. </layout>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc>
                     <handNote>Written in a neat rounded gothic bookhand</handNote>
                  </handDesc>
                  <decoDesc>
                     <decoNote type="rubrication">Headings in red.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="other">
                        <p>One eight-line initial in gold and colours, with a bar-extender running the whole height of the page, to Ps. 109 (fol. 83r; pl. 000); a similar six-line initial and extender to Ps. 101 <locus from="66v" to="66v">(fol. 66v)</locus>; a seven-line foliate initial on a gold ground, with foliate sprays and gold balls extending half the height of the page and into or towards the upper and lower margins, at the start of the hymnal <locus from="97r" to="97r">(fol. 97r)</locus>; similar four- to six-line initials, their extensions ranging from half to full height, to Pss. 20, 45, 59, 73, 85 (fols. 18v, 38r, 44v, 52r, 60r), the start of the canticles for Advent and Christmas (fols. 92r, 93r), the Common of Saints (fols. 95v, 96v), hymns for major feasts of the Sanctorale (fols. 97v, 98v, 101v, 103r, 104r, 108v), the Common of Saints (fols. 109r, 109v, 111r), and the litany <locus from="111r" to="111r">(fol. 111r)</locus>; four-line initial in red with purple penwork, the penwork extending almost the full height of the page, to Ps. 26 <locus from="21v" to="21v">(fol. 21v)</locus>; similar three-line initials alternately in red with purple penwork, or blue with red penwork, with similar penwork extenders, to psalms, canticles, etc. up to fol. 44r, thereafter two-line; one-line initials alternately in red or blue, to verses and other minor divisions; guide letters for coloured initials are visible throughout; paraphs in blue; simple red and blue line-fillers in the litany <locus from="111v" to="112v">(fols. 111v–112v)</locus>.</p>
                     </decoNote>
                  </decoDesc>
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <binding notAfter="1800" notBefore="1700">
                        <p>Sewn on three(?) cords (not clearly visible); bound in Italian 18th(?)-century mottled brown leather over pasteboards; rebacked, the old spine laid on, with gilt foliate ornament and a pale brown leather title-piece lettered: 'OFFIC | DELLA | B.V.M', slightly damaged along the side of the upper joint; marbled pastedowns and conjoint flyleaves; the edges of the leaves coloured red, later than the date of the binding, since the red also affects underlying corners of the pasteboards which are exposed by damage.</p>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origPlace cert="low">
                        <country key="place_1000080">Italian</country>, <region>Northeast</region>, <settlement key="place_7018159">Venice</settlement> (?)<!--ORIGINAL: Italian, Northeast, Venice(?)--></origPlace>
                     <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="1475" notBefore="1450">15th century, third quarter</origDate>
                  </origin>
                  <provenance>Made for a Benedictine House (as evidenced by the grading of feasts with twelve lessons in the calendar, the Benedictine divisions and sub-divisions of the psalms, and the wording of the 21 March feast of Benedict) of the Congregation of Sta. Giustina (as evidenced by the emphasis on St. Justina in the calendar, litany, and hymnal; the emphasis on St. Placidus in the calendar and litany; the wording of vigils 'de precepto'; and the collect mentioning 'presidenti nostro'); the petition for sailors might hint at a coastal origin, since it occurs also in manuscripts of the Congregation written for S. Giorgio Maggiore, Venice (e.g. MSS. Canon. Liturg. 204 and 210), but not in the Breviary of the Congregation printed in 1484; yet it also occurs in a breviary written for nuns of the Congregation in the diocese of Brescia (MS. Canon. Liturg. 164).</provenance>
                  <provenance>? <orgName key="org_152797746" role="fmo">Monastery of SS. Felice e Fortunata, Vicenza</orgName> (on which see Cottineau, <title>Répertoire topo-bibliographique</title>, II, col. 3360): according to van Dijk, and accepted by Pächt &amp; Alexander, the added feast of these two saints in the calendar may point to the monastery dedicated to them; it was incorporated into the Congregation of S. Giustina in 1462. The fact that the feast is graded with twelve lessons, however, rather than as a duplex, casts some doubt on this.</provenance>
                  <provenance>Unidentified 18th/19th-century owner; inscribed (fol. ii recto): 'Horae diurne'.</provenance>
                  <provenance>Unidentified 19th-century owner: inscribed in pencil: 'LB13[?] V15+[?]' at the top left of fol. i verso.</provenance>
                  <provenance>Raguin, Paris bookseller, by 1875 (see Introduction, and below); inscribed in pencil: 'Bu.or'(?) in the top left corner of fol. 117r.</provenance>
                  <provenance>
                     <persName key="person_44557546" role="fmo">Rt. Hon. T. R. Buchanan (1846–1911)</persName>, 1875: fol. ii recto with a slip of paper glued in vertically, inscribed in ink by Buchanan '[Ho]ræ B.V.M. MS. of 15th century. | Bought from Raguin Nov. 1875 -' (cf. especially MS. Buchanan d. 2, and the printed books, Buchanan e.65 and e.136)</provenance>
                  <acquisition when="1941">Given to the Bodleian by his widow, <persName key="person_886" role="dnr">Mrs. E. O. Buchanan</persName>, in 1941; traces of a rectangular paper label with at least one perforated edge in the lower left corner of the upper board are probably the remains of a Bodleian shelf-mark label.</acquisition>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>Adapted from Peter Kidd, <title>Medieval Manuscripts from the Collection of T. R. Buchanan in the Bodleian Library, Oxford</title> (Oxford, 2001)</source>
                     </recordHist>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <surrogates>
                     <bibl subtype="partial" type="digital-facsimile">
                        <ref target="https://digital.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/objects/2b9793ed-4b6f-4bd4-b2d3-1b919cbeceef/">
                           <title>Digital Bodleian</title>
                        </ref>
                        <note>(1 image from 35mm slides)</note>
                     </bibl>
                  </surrogates>
                  <listBibl type="WRAPPER">
                     <listBibl type="PRINT">
                        <head>Printed descriptions:</head>
                        <bibl>S. J. P. van Dijk, <title>Latin Liturgical Manuscripts in the Bodleian Library, Oxford, vol. 2: Office Books</title> (typescript, 1957), <citedRange unit="page" from="97" to="97">p. 97</citedRange>
                        </bibl>
                     </listBibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2017-07-01">First online publication.</change>
         <change when="2017-05-25">
            <persName>James Cummings</persName> Up-converted the markup using <ref target="https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl">https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl</ref>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>