<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="manuscript_2008">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>MS. Buchanan g. 4</title>
            <title type="collection">MSS. Buchanan</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Cataloguer</resp>
               <persName>Peter Kidd</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </publisher>
            <idno type="msID">MS_Buchanan_g_4</idno>
            <idno type="collection">Buchanan</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="MS_Buchanan_g_4">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <region type="county">Oxfordshire</region>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <institution>University of Oxford</institution>
                  <repository>Bodleian Library</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">MS. Buchanan g. 4</idno>
                  <idno type="ieArk">ark:29072/x0hm50tr92zs</idno><idno type="crArk">ark:29072/x0hh63sw09n7</idno><altIdentifier type="SCN">
                     <idno>Not in Summary Catalogue (late accession)</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
               <head> </head>
               <msContents>
                  <msItem class="#oratio #devotiones #liturgica" xml:id="MS_Buchanan_g_4-item1">
                     <title key="work_13997" type="desc">Private prayers and devotions (perhaps an imperfect Book of Hours)</title>
                     <textLang mainLang="la" otherLangs="it">Latin and Italian</textLang>
                     <msItem xml:id="MS_Buchanan_g_4-item1-item1">
                        <note>[Items 1–2 originally occupied quires II-III; the start of item 1 was later copied onto the added quire I]</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem xml:id="MS_Buchanan_g_4-item1-item2">
                        <locus>(fols. 2r-15r)</locus>
                        <note>The Seven Penitential Psalms</note>
                        <note> Fol. 1r-v ruled, otherwise originally blank; fol. 2 is a supply leaf containing Ps. 6:1–6 (to '... inferno autem ||'; see also under Decoration)</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem xml:id="MS_Buchanan_g_4-item1-item3">
                        <locus>(fols. 15r-24v)</locus>
                        <note>Litany and collects</note>
                        <note> The litany with 'Sancte pater' Benedict (1), Placidus (6), and Romuald ('Romuade') (8) among eight monks, hermits, priests, and deacons; followed <locus>(fols. 22r-24v)</locus> by the usual ten collects (listed under MS. Buchanan e. 5), the fifth mentioning '... famulo tuo .N. ...'; fols. 25r-26v ruled, otherwise blank.</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem xml:id="MS_Buchanan_g_4-item1-item4">
                        <note>[Items 3–13 originally occupied the present quires IV-VIII; the start of item 3 was later copied onto the last leaf of quire III]</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem xml:id="MS_Buchanan_g_4-item1-item5">
                        <locus>(fols. 27r-51v)</locus>
                        <note>Office of the Dead</note>
                        <note> Omitting Vespers, and thus beginning at Matins, with only three lessons, corresponding to those of the Use of Rome; the first leaf is a supply leaf containing Ps. 94:1–59 (to '... adoremus. Quoniam ||'; see also under Decoration) </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem xml:id="MS_Buchanan_g_4-item1-item6">
                        <locus>(fols. 52r-53r, rubric on fol. 51v)</locus>
                        <note>The Verses of St. Bernard</note>
                        <textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>
                        <rubric>Isti sunt <sic>uersibus</sic> sancti bernardi abbatis. O bone ihesu:-</rubric>
                        <incipit>Illumina oculos meos</incipit>
                        <note>The verses in the same order as in MS. Buchanan e. 9, fols. 118v-119r (q.v.) followed by a versicle, response, and (fol. 53r) the usual prayer, here incorporating the name of the original owner:</note>
                        <msItem xml:id="MS_Buchanan_g_4-item1-item6-item1">
                           <incipit>Omnipotens sempiterne deus qui ezechie regi iude ... concede mihi indignum famulum tuum. iohannem.</incipit>
                           <explicit>misericordiam consequi merear. Per ...</explicit>
                        </msItem>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem xml:id="MS_Buchanan_g_4-item1-item7">
                        <locus>(fols. 53v-54r)</locus>
                        <note>Indulgenced prayer, here attributed to <persName cert="low" key="person_16017787" role="aut">Pope Innocent [III (1198–1216)?]</persName>
                        </note>
                        <rubric>Innocentius papa concessit omni dicenti semel in die istam orationem. indulgentiam omnium peccatorum suorum</rubric>
                        <incipit>Deus qui uoluisti pro salute mundi ... <note>[masculine forms]</note>
                        </incipit>
                        <explicit>perduxisti latronem crucifixum. Qui uiuis</explicit>
                        <note>(cf. Leroquais, <title>Livres d'heures</title>, II, 344; Wordsworth, <title>Horae Eboracenses</title>, 83; de la Mare, <title>Lyell cat.</title>, 64 item e, where it is attributed to Boniface IV).</note>
                        <textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem xml:id="MS_Buchanan_g_4-item1-item8">
                        <locus>(fols. 54v-56r)</locus>
                        <note>Prayer to be said before Communion</note>
                        <rubric>Oratio deuota dicenda ante comunionem</rubric>
                        <incipit>Domine yhesu christe qui dixisti. qui manducat meam carnem et bibit meum sanguinem. ... <note>[masculine forms]</note>
                        </incipit>
                        <explicit>Ubi te semper uideam. cum deo patre et spiritu sancto in secula seculorum. Amen.</explicit>
                        <textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem xml:id="MS_Buchanan_g_4-item1-item9">
                        <locus>(fols. 56r-57r)</locus>
                        <note>Prayer to be said after Communion, carrying an indulgence of Pope Boniface</note>
                        <rubric>papa bonifatius concessit omni dicenti post perceptionem corporis christi indulgentiam .xl.ª dierum</rubric>
                        <incipit>Gratias tibi ago domine sancte pater qui me famulum tuum nullis mentis</incipit>
                        <explicit>et sempiternum gaudium. Per eundem christum ...</explicit>
                        <textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem xml:id="MS_Buchanan_g_4-item1-item10">
                        <locus>(fol. 57r-v)</locus>
                        <note>Hymn, here attributed to <persName cert="low" key="person_59875293" role="aut">St. Bernard</persName>
                        </note>
                        <rubric>Beatus bernardus conposuit infrascriptam orationem. affirmans quicumque eam flexis genibus dixerit omnibus diebus uite sue numquam in peccatis morietur. oratio</rubric>
                        <incipit>Ave caro christi cara. inmolata crucis ara. pro redemptis hostia. Morte tua nos amata.</incipit>
                        <explicit>pater misericordiarum. Amen.</explicit>
                        <note>(<ref target="http://webserver.erwin-rauner.de/php_ancarm/ancarm_refwerke.php?opus=1003&amp;var=Chev&amp;nr_char=1710">Chevalier 1710</ref>).</note>
                        <textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem xml:id="MS_Buchanan_g_4-item1-item11">
                        <locus>(fols. 58r-60r, rubric on fols. 57v-58r)</locus>
                        <note>Prayer, here attributed to <persName cert="low" key="person_66806872" role="aut">St. Augustine</persName>
                        </note>
                        <rubric>Oratio sancti augustini ualde utilis et deuota. Quicumque eam dixerit semel in die non peribit in igne. ... Et si quid iustum petierit a deo i[m]petrabit. oratio</rubric>
                        <incipit>Deus propitius esto mihi peccatori et custos omnibus diebus uite mee.</incipit>
                        <explicit>ad tuam sanctam gratiam facias peruenire. Amen.</explicit>
                        <note>(a shorter version is pr. in Wordsworth, <hi rend="italic">op. cit.</hi>, 125)</note>
                        <textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem xml:id="MS_Buchanan_g_4-item1-item12">
                        <locus>(fols. 60v-61r, rubric on fol. 60r-v)</locus>
                        <note>Prayer in Italian, here attributed to <persName cert="low" key="person_66806872" role="aut">St. Augustine</persName>
                        </note>
                        <rubric>Questa oratione fece sancto augustino laquale e molto utile et deuota. Incipit</rubric>
                        <incipit>Signor rodio mio misericordia mia refugio mio et desiderio mio atte rifuggo</incipit>
                        <explicit>raccomando lo spirito mio. Amen.</explicit>
                        <textLang mainLang="it">Italian</textLang>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem xml:id="MS_Buchanan_g_4-item1-item13">
                        <locus>(fols. 61v-62r, rubric on fol. 61r)</locus>
                        <note>Prayer to one's guardian angel</note>
                        <rubric>Oratio ad proprium angelum</rubric>
                        <incipit>Superne curie ciuis angele sancte. qui fragilis uite mee deputatus es custos</incipit>
                        <explicit>et presenta eam in uitam eternam. Amen.</explicit>
                        <textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem xml:id="MS_Buchanan_g_4-item1-item14">
                        <locus>(fol. 62r-v)</locus>
                        <note>Commemoration of the archangel Raphael</note>
                        <rubric>Conmemoratio beati raphaelis archangeli. antiphona</rubric>
                        <incipit>Angelum nobis medicum salutis</incipit>
                        <textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>
                        <note>with versicle, response, and the prayer</note>
                        <msItem xml:id="MS_Buchanan_g_4-item1-item14-item1">
                           <incipit>Deus qui raphaelem archangelum thobie famulo tuo properanti preuium direxisti.</incipit>
                           <explicit>.LAUS DEO.</explicit>
                           <note>(pr. J. Lemarié, 'Textes relatifs au culte de l'archange et des anges dans les bréviaires manuscrits du Mont-Saint-Michel', <title>Sacris Erudiri</title> 13 (1962), 113–52, at 141)</note>
                           <textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>
                        </msItem>
                        <note>fol. 63r ruled, otherwise originally blank; fol. 63v originally blank.</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem xml:id="MS_Buchanan_g_4-item1-item15">
                        <locus>(fol. 63r-v)</locus>
                        <note>(?) Pen trials, of uncertain date; inscribed: 'mapilon' or 'mopilon' at the start of the top line of fol. 63r, and '[T]ota die' at the top of the verso.</note>
                     </msItem>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <p>
                     <secFol>quis confitebitur</secFol>
                  </p>
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="perg">
                        <support>Parchment.</support>
                        <extent>i (modern paper, conjoint with the pastedown) + 63 + i (modern paper, conjoint with the pastedown).<dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                              <height max="94" min="93">93–4</height>
                              <width max="68" min="67">67–8</width>
                           </dimensions>
                           <dimensions type="ruled" unit="mm">
                              <height max="55" min="54">54–5</height>
                              <width max="36" min="35">35–6</width>
                           </dimensions>
                           <dimensions type="written" unit="mm">
                              <height max="53" min="52">52–3</height>
                              <width max="37" min="34">34–7</width>
                           </dimensions>
                        </extent>
                        <foliation>Foliated in modern pencil: i, 1–64.</foliation>
                        <collation>Mostly in quires of 10 leaves: I<hi rend="superscript">2</hi> (fols. 1–2) | II<hi rend="superscript">10–1</hi> (1st leaf excised, leaving a stub before fol. 3) (fols. 3–11), III<hi rend="superscript">10</hi> (fols. 12–21), IV<hi rend="superscript">6</hi> (fols. 22–27) | V<hi rend="superscript">10–1</hi> (1st leaf excised, leaving a stub before fol. 28) (fols. 28–36), VI-VII<hi rend="superscript">10</hi> (fols. 37–56), VIII<hi rend="superscript">8–1</hi> (with the stub of an excised leaf after fol. 58) (fols. 57–63)-the structure of the final quire is rather complicated, see the Note below. <catchwords>Each of the two main original scribes (see under Script) used a different system of CATCHWORDS: (i) written sideways vertically downwards, on the inner vertical bounding line, between a pair of dots (fols. 11v and 21v); (ii) written horizontally in the centre of the lower margin, surrounded by four short wavy lines (fols. 36v, 46v, and 56v).</catchwords> The rather tight and fragile binding makes for some uncertainty. The stub before fol. 59 has traces of pen-flourishing on its recto which correspond to the pen-flourishing of the initial on fol. 58; it therefore seems likely that what is now the stub was originally the second leaf of the quire, and that this was cancelled after it had been written and decorated; the text was then re-written on the conjugate half of the same bifolium (which would have been the ruled but otherwise blank penultimate leaf of the quire), and bound in its present position, as fol. 58. Another anomaly is the offset of purple penwork decoration in the gutter [sic] margin of fol. 47r, with no such decoration on the facing page, and no loss of a leaf: to produce an offset here, another leaf/quire must presumably have been laid head-to-tail on top of this one by the pen-flourisher before binding, and while the ink was still wet. </collation>
                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout ruledLines="14" writtenLines="13">14 lines ruled in very pale brown ink, sometimes almost invisible, between single vertical bounding lines extending the full height of the page; single PRICKINGS visible, often a Y-shaped puncture, in the fore-edge margin c.4 mm. below the bottom ruled line. 13 lines of text per page</layout>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc hands="3">
                     <handNote>Written in gothic bookhands by three scribes: (i) fols. 3r-24v; (ii) fols. 28r-62v (using a distinctive signe-de-renvoie to supply an omission, fol. 43v); and (iii) fols. 2r-v, and 27r-v (i.e. the supply leaves; somewhat clumsy, and perhaps artificial-see e.g. the unusual abbreviation 'do(m)ine' on fol. 2r).</handNote>
                  </handDesc>
                  <decoDesc>
                     <decoNote type="rubrication">Each scribe was responsible for his own headings, in red.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="other">
                        <p>Two historiated initials (9- and 7-line) on inserted leaves, perhaps late 15th century, or later, each on a square gold field with foliate tendrils extending into the margins: <list>
                              <item>
                                 <locus>(fol. 2r)</locus> Penitential Psalms. Initial D[omine]: a group of buildings (perhaps a monastery?), including a circular tower with three storeys, on top of which is a cross and pennant.</item>
                              <item>
                                 <locus>(fol. 27r)</locus> Office of the Dead. Initial U[enite] (but shaped more like an 'O' or 'D'): group of buildings, similar in some details to those on fol. 2r.</item>
                           </list>
                        </p>
                        <p>Two-line initials, alternately in blue with red penwork or red with purple penwork, the penwork extending almost the full height of the page, at the start of psalms, collects, lessons, etc.; one-line initials alternately in red or blue, at the start of verses and other minor textual divisions.</p>
                     </decoNote>
                  </decoDesc>
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <binding notAfter="1750" notBefore="1650">
                        <p>Sewn on two cords; bound in 17th/18th?-century brown leather over pasteboards; with a double gilt fillet framing the covers (largely obscured), five (or six?) similar horizontal double fillets dividing the spine (largely obscured); each cover with an applied panel of 19th-century enamelled glass (the upper panel badly cracked) with a semée of gold stars on a deep blue ground, and with gold and silver oak-leaf motifs around the edges; these panels each with an openwork gilt metal framing (originally attached with a nail in each corner; three of the nails on the upper cover are now detached) in the form of branches, foliage, flowers, and fruit(?); with a silver(?) clasp (fastening from bottom to top); the spine with a convex gilt metal panel (damaged and repaired) with fleurs-de-lis and scrolls in relief, attached with a nail at each corner; yellow wove paper flyleaves conjoint with the pastedowns; fol. 63 apparently the pastedown of a previous binding; the edges of the leaves gilt; boxed.</p>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origPlace>
                        <country key="place_1000080">Italian</country>
                     </origPlace>
                     <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="1500" notBefore="1450">15th century, second half</origDate>
                  </origin>
                  <provenance>Made for an Italian-speaker named <persName key="person_439" role="fmo"><!-- not found -->Giovanni/Iohannes</persName> (see text items 4 and 10); it is probable that the manuscript is the second half of a Book of Hours.</provenance>
                  <provenance>Unidentified owner: there is an erased ownership(?) inscription at the upper edge of fol. 1r, not legible even under UV light, probably added after the binding, since it appears to be offset onto the flyleaf, fol. i verso.</provenance>
                  <provenance>Thomas Arthur / William Ridler, London booksellers; inscribed in pencil on the upper pastedown with their characteristic price and pricecode: '£10–18-0' (the '10' altered from '11'), upper centre, with their price-code 'm/sd/-' (i.e. £8 15s), at the centre fore-edge, sloping upwards (cf. MSS. Buchanan b. 1 and d. 1).</provenance>
                  <provenance>
                     <persName key="person_44557546" role="fmo">Rt. Hon. T. R. Buchanan (1846–1911)</persName>, probably bought from Arthur or Ridler after 1874)</provenance>
                  <acquisition when="1941">Given to the Bodleian in 1941 by his widow, <persName key="person_886" role="dnr">Mrs. E. O. Buchanan</persName>.</acquisition>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>Adapted from Peter Kidd, <title>Medieval Manuscripts from the Collection of T. R. Buchanan in the Bodleian Library, Oxford</title> (Oxford, 2001)</source>
                     </recordHist>
                     <availability status="restricted">
                        <p>To ensure its preservation, access to this item is restricted, and readers are asked to work from reproductions and published descriptions as far as possible. If you wish to apply to see the original, please click the request button above. When your request is received, you will be asked to contact the relevant curator outlining the subject of your research, the importance of this item to that research, and the resources you have already consulted.</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <surrogates>
                     <bibl type="microfilm">Microfilm available in the open shelf collections in the Weston Library (R. Films 101)</bibl>
                  </surrogates>
                  <listBibl type="WRAPPER">
                     <listBibl type="PRINT">
                        <head>Printed descriptions:</head>
                        <bibl>S. J. P. van Dijk, <title>Latin Liturgical Manuscripts in the Bodleian Library, Oxford, vol. 4: Books of Hours</title> (typescript, 1957), <citedRange unit="page" from="332" to="332">p. 332</citedRange>
                        </bibl>
                     </listBibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2017-07-01">First online publication.</change>
         <change when="2017-05-25">
            <persName>James Cummings</persName> Up-converted the markup using <ref target="https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl">https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl</ref>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>