<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="manuscript_4701">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>MS. Douce 38</title>
            <title type="collection">MSS. Douce</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp when="2013">Cataloguer</resp>
               <persName>Elizabeth Solopova</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp when="2024">Encoding</resp>
               <persName>Matthew Holford</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </publisher>
            <idno type="msID">MS_Douce_38</idno>
            <idno type="collection">Douce</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="MS_Douce_38" xml:lang="en">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <region type="county">Oxfordshire</region>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <institution>University of Oxford</institution>
                  <repository>Bodleian Library</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">MS. Douce 38</idno>
                  <idno type="ieArk">ark:29072/x08c97kq892h</idno>
                  <idno type="crArk">ark:29072/x0hd76s026n1</idno>
                  <altIdentifier type="internal">
                     <idno type="SCN">21612</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
               <head>Portable Psalter; Flanders, Bruges (?), late 13th or early 14th century</head>
               <msContents>
                  <msItem class="#liturgica #biblia" n="1" xml:id="MS_Douce_38-item1">
                     <title key="work_14114" type="desc">Portable Psalter </title>
                     <note>Fols. i–ii are a paper bifolium with notes by Douce (see ‘Provenance’). </note>
                     <note>[item 1 occupies quire I]</note>
                     <msItem n="1">
                        <locus from="1r" to="6v">(fols. 1r–6v)</locus>
                        <note> Calendar (published and compared with the calendars of other psalters
                           from the Bruges–Ghent area by Carlvant, 1978, pp. 485–508), laid out one
                           month per page, written in red and brown, approximately one-third full,
                           not graded. Contains Donatianus in red (14 October), patron saint of an
                           important parish and collegiate church in Bruges, which served in early
                           modern times as cathedral of the archdiocese of Bruges, Boniface (5
                           June), patron of a church in Bruges (see Carlvant, 1978, pp. 122–6),
                           Egidius in red (1 September), Lambert, bishop of Liège in red (17
                           September), Remigius, Germanus, Vedast and Bavo of Ghent in red (1
                           October), Leodegar of Autun (2 October), Leonard of Limousin (6
                           November), Eligius in red (1 December) and Nicholas in red (6 December).
                           ‘Thomas e c’ (?) is added in a 14th-century English hand on 18 August and
                           ‘Thomas Jonet’ (?) on 21 November. Months are headed by verses on the
                           ‘Egyptian’ days and notes on the length of the solar and lunar month,
                           e.g. ‘Ianuarius habet dies xxxi luna xxx’. Most verses correspond to
                           Hennig’s (1955) set III, apart from the verses for January and
                           August–October, which roughly correspond to set I (‘Iani prima dies et
                           septima fine timetur’, etc.). There is no verse for June. </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <note>[item 2 occupies quire II]</note>
                     <msItem n="2">
                        <locus from="7r" to="9v">(fols. 7r–9v)</locus>
                        <note> Two prefatory miniatures and Beatus-initial, painted on the versos
                           with rectos left blank (see ‘Decoration’). The gathering, at present
                           containing three single leaves, may have originally contained more
                           miniatures, illustrating the life of Christ. </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <note> [items 3–6 occupy quires III–XXV]</note>
                     <msItem n="3">
                        <locus from="10r" to="210r">(fols. 10r–210r)</locus>
                        <note> Psalms 1–150, laid out with most verses starting on a new line,
                           without titles. The numbers of psalms 1–10 are added in the margins; and
                           at psalms 6 and 9 there is a note ‘morning prayer’ (fols. 13v, erased,
                           and 16v), probably in the same, later 16th- or 17th-century hand. The
                           numbers of psalms beginning with historiated initials are added in pencil
                           by Douce. Punctuated throughout with punctus elevatus used to mark metrum
                           and minor pauses, and punctus used to mark the ends of verses. The psalms
                           are in the biblical order, subdivisions within psalms are not indicated,
                           apart from psalm 118, subdivided into twenty-two 8-verse units. Psalm 21
                           ends imperfectly at verse 22, and the opening words of psalm 22 are
                           missing, because of the loss of one leaf after fol. 33 (note ‘deficit
                           folio’ is written on fol. 33v in a 14th-century (?) hand, contemporary
                           and possibly the same as that of the ‘Thomas’ additions in the calendar).
                           Psalm 52 is missing because of the loss of leaves after fol. 77. The text
                           contains corrections in medieval hands. Errors are marked with crosses in
                           the margins, and cancelled by striking through or erasure or left
                           uncorrected. There are textual divisions at psalms 26, 38, 68, 80, 97 and
                           109, marked with historiated initials and facing miniatures (see
                           ‘Decoration’). Psalm 52 originally also started with a historiated
                           initial and was preceded by a miniature (see ‘Physical description’
                           (‘Collation’)). </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="4">
                        <locus from="210r" to="222r">(fols. 210r–222r)</locus>
                        <note> Weekly canticles, without titles: <list>
                              <item>(1) Confitebor tibi domine (Isaiah 12);</item>
                              <item>(2) Ego dixi (Isaiah 38: 10–21);</item>
                              <item>(3) Exultauit cor meum (1 Samuel 2: 1–11);</item>
                              <item>(4) Cantemus domino (Exodus 15: 1–20);</item>
                              <item>(5) Domine audiui (Habakkuk 3);</item>
                              <item>(6) Audite celi (Deuteronomy 32: 1–44).</item>
                           </list>
                        </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="5">
                        <locus from="222r" to="229v">(fols. 222r–229v)</locus>
                        <note> Daily canticles, prayers and creeds, without titles: <list>
                              <item>(1) Te deum laudamus (fol. 222r);</item>
                              <item>(2) Benedicite omnia opera (fol. 223v);</item>
                              <item>(3) Benedictus dominus deus (fol. 225r);</item>
                              <item>(4) Magnificat (fol. 225v);</item>
                              <item>(5) Nunc dimittis (fol. 226v);</item>
                              <item>(6) Athanasian Creed (Quicumque uult ...) (fol. 226v).</item>
                           </list>
                        </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="6">
                        <locus from="229v" to="233r">(fols. 229v–233r)</locus>
                        <note> Litany, containing saints venerated in the Bruges–Ghent region
                           (published and compared with litanies of other psalters from this area by
                           Carlvant, 1978, pp. 509–12). Donatianus is the first among the
                           confessors, followed by Basil, who appears again towards the end of the
                           list of confessors. The litany also contains Leodegar and Julian (twice)
                           among the martyrs; and Macarius, Audomar, Medard, Eligius and Egidius
                           among the confessors. Followed by collects (fols. 232r–233r), including
                           one to St Nicholas (‘Deus qui beatum ...’): <list>
                              <item>(1) Concede nos famulos tuos quesumus domine deus perpetua
                                 mentis et corporis ...</item>
                              <item> (2) Exaudi quesumus domine deus supplicum preces ...</item>
                              <item> (3) Deus qui beatum nicholaum pontificem tuum innumeris
                                 decorasti miraculis ...</item>
                              <item> (4) Absolue domine animas famulorum famularumque tuarum ab omni
                                 uinculo delictorum ...</item>
                              <item> (5) Pretende domine famulis et famulabus tuis dexteram celestis
                                 auxilii ...</item>
                              <item> (6) Omnium sanctorum tuorum quesumus domine supplicatione
                                 placatus et ueniam nobis tribue ...</item>
                              <item> (7) Concede quesumus omnipotens deus fragilitati nostre
                                 subsidium ...</item>
                              <item> (8) Partem beate resurrectionis obtineant anime omnium fidelium
                                 defunctorum uitamque eternam ...</item>
                           </list> Fol. 233v is blank apart from modern notes. </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <p><secFol> predicans preceptum eius <locus>(psalter, fol.
                     11r)</locus></secFol></p>
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="perg">
                        <support> parchment; added paper bifolium (fols. i–ii); fols. 230–233 cut
                           with a knife and repaired with laid paper</support>
                        <extent> <measure type="leaf" quantity="237">237</measure> leaves <dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                              <height quantity="135">c. 135</height>
                              <width>95</width>
                           </dimensions>
                           <note>Leaves were trimmed in rebinding, occasionally causing the loss of
                              text and decoration. </note>
                        </extent>
                        <foliation> modern, in pencil; i–ii + 1–17a + 17b + 18–205a + 205b +
                           206–233.</foliation>
                        <collation> (fol. i–ii) paper bifolium | (fols. 1–6) I (6) | (fols. 7–9) II
                           (3) three singletons, containing full-page miniatures and the
                           Beatus-initial; more miniatures are probably missing | (fols. 10–28)
                           III–IV (10) | (fols. 29–37) V (10+1−2) missing 6 (the loss of text in
                           psalms 21–22) and 11 (the gathering originally contained at its end an
                           added leaf with a miniature, facing the initial of psalm 26; the
                           miniature was excised, but the stub remains) | (fols. 38–77) VI–IX (10) |
                           (fols. 78–85) X (10−2) missing 1 and 2; text page with psalm 52 and
                           facing miniature excised | (fols. 86–135) XI–XV (10) | (fols. 136–146)
                           XVI (10+1) fol. 142, containing a miniature, is an added singleton |
                           (fols. 147–156) XVII (10) | (fols. 157–165) XVIII (10−1) missing 10
                           (miniature, which originally faced the initial of psalm 109, is excised)
                           | (fols. 166–224) XIX–XXIV (10) | (fols. 225–233) XXV (10−1) missing 10,
                           but no loss of text. Catchwords, partly cropped off, survive</collation>
                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout columns="1" writtenLines="18" rulingMedium="leadpoint">Ruled in
                           plummet with two sets of double vertical and two sets of double
                           horizontal bounding lines, extending the full height and width of page;
                           18 lines per page; prickings visible on some leaves; written below the
                           top line; written space: <dimensions type="written" unit="mm">
                              <height quantity="80">c. 80</height>
                              <width>53</width>
                           </dimensions></layout>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc>
                     <handNote script="textualisNorthern" execution="formata">Formal Gothic book
                        hand, brown ink</handNote>
                  </handDesc>
                  <decoDesc>
                     <decoNote type="monogram">Gold KL monograms on blue and pink backgrounds, and
                        borders made of gold bars on pink and blue backgrounds at the beginning of
                        each month in the calendar. </decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="miniature">Miniatures of irregular shapes with the Labours of
                        the Months, often overlapping and obscuring the text. January: man warming
                        his open legs by the fire, next to a table with a jug and cup February:
                        nimbed woman with a candle, standing by an altar March: man pruning a tree
                        with an axe April: man carrying flowering branches May: man with a hawk
                        June: man carrying a bundle of wood on his back July: man mowing hay with a
                        scythe August: man reaping grain September: man picking grapes and putting
                        them in a basket October: man sowing November: man slaughtering an ox
                        December: man baking in an oven.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="miniature">Full-page miniatures on gold backgrounds (flaking)
                        in architectural frames and historiated initials, occupying most of the
                        page, at liturgical divisions. The prefatory miniature cycle is probably
                        incomplete. Miniatures preceding psalms 26, 52 and 109, and the text page
                        containing the beginning of psalm 52, have been excised (see ‘Physical
                        description’ (‘Collation’)). Prefatory miniatures and a miniature on a
                        single leaf (fol. 142) are painted on the versos, leaving rectos blank (see
                        Carlvant, 1985, p. 329 n. 14). Other miniatures, painted on leaves forming
                        parts of the ten-leaf gatherings, are on the versos with the psalter text on
                        the rectos. The miniatures and initials are on gold backgrounds (flaking) in
                        rectangular frames. <list>
                           <item>fol. 7v (miniature) Annunciation.</item>
                           <item>fol. 8v (miniature) Annunciation to the Shepherds.</item>
                           <item>fol. 9v Psalm 1 (initial B(eatus)) King David, seated, playing harp
                              in the upper part; David slaying Goliath in the lower part; coiled
                              tendrils and grotesques.</item>
                           <item>fol. 38r Psalm 26 (initial D(ominus)) The Last Supper; coiled
                              tendrils and a grotesque forming the tail of D.</item>
                           <item> fol. 58v (miniature) The Betrayal; St Peter cutting off Malchus’s
                              ear.</item>
                           <item>fol. 59r Psalm 38 (initial D(ixi)) Flagellation; coiled tendrils
                              and a grotesque forming the tail of D.</item>
                           <item>fol. 95v (miniature) Entombment: body of Christ embalmed by three
                              men.</item>
                           <item>fol. 96r Psalm 68 (initial S(aluum)) Resurrection: Christ steps out
                              of the tomb, the lid of which is lifted by an angel; guards asleep on
                              the ground; animal head and coiled tendrils, extending into the
                              margins.</item>
                           <item>fol. 119v (miniature) Noli me tangere.</item>
                           <item>fol. 120r Psalm 80 (initial (E(xultate)) Incredulity of St Thomas;
                              coiled tendrils, extending into the margins.</item>
                           <item>fol. 142v (miniature) Ascension.</item>
                           <item>fol. 143r Psalm 97 (initial C(antate)) Pentecost: seated apostles
                              and the Virgin Mary; nimbed white dove descending from above; coiled
                              tendrils, extending into the margins.</item>
                           <item>fol. 166r Psalm 109 (initial D(ixit)) Coronation of the Virgin
                              (rubbed); grotesque and coiled tendrils forming the tail of D.</item>
                        </list></decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="histInit">Historiated initials: see above.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="border">Borders: see above.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="decInit">3-line gold initials on blue and pink backgrounds,
                        with gold tendrils on blue and pink backgrounds, extending into margins, at
                        the beginnings of psalms, canticles and litany.</decoNote>

                     <decoNote type="decInit">Pink and blue panels in the left margins serving as
                        backgrounds to 1-line gold initials at the beginnings of verses and periods.
                        The litany is laid out in two columns with the panels and initials in the
                        left and central margins.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="flourInit"> Red and blue penwork line-endings on fols. 10r and
                        18v (the outer pages of a single bifolium).</decoNote>
                  </decoDesc>
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <binding notAfter="1825" notBefore="1300">
                        <p> Red leather, possibly as late as the 18th or early 19th century, over
                           medieval wood boards. Original (?) sewing on tawed thongs. The boards
                           retain under the leather the stations of two clasps at the fore-edge.
                           Three raised bands on spine. Fragmentary paper label on spine with
                           ‘PSALTERIVM’ written in ink; fragment of another label at the bottom of
                           the spine. Paper pastedowns. </p>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origPlace>
                        <country key="place_7024097">Flemish</country>, <settlement
                           key="place_7007867">Bruges</settlement> (?) </origPlace>
                     <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="1310" notBefore="1290">13th century,
                        late, or 14th century, early</origDate>
                  </origin>
                  <provenance>Made for the use of Bruges: evidence of the calendar and litany. The
                     simplicity of the textual contents and the absence of grading in the calendar
                     suggest a lay patron. St Nicholas appears in the litany and in red in the
                     calendar. The litany is followed by a collect to St Nicholas (compare MS. Douce
                     49). Carlvant notes that several psalters from the Bruges–Ghent area, probably
                     made for lay patrons, include images and prayers to St Nicholas of Myra (1978,
                     pp. 338–9). The psalter has many similarities in codicology, illumination and
                     textual contents with other contemporary psalters from the Bruges–Ghent area,
                     such as MS. Auct. D. 4. 2 (‘Tweede Groep’, Carlvant, 1978, pp. 140–57). </provenance>
                  <provenance>14th-century English (?) addition of ‘Thomas Jonet’ (?) in the
                     calendar. </provenance>
                  <provenance>Erased inscriptions in the margins, possibly of different dates, on
                     pages containing miniatures and historiated initials (fols. 7v, 8v, 9v, 38r,
                     58v–59r, 95v–96r, 119v–120r, 122v–123r, 142v–143r) and on fols. 16r, 146v–147r,
                     212r. Fragments of text are preserved in the upper margin on fol. 10r; an
                     erased inscription on fol. 212r left an offset on fol. 211v. </provenance>
                  <provenance>Added psalm numbers and short notes in English and Latin on fols. 13v
                     and 16v (see ‘Text’) and fol. 230r (‘archengle . . . Johannes’ (?)) in a later
                     16th- or 17th-century hand. </provenance>
                  <provenance notAfter="1834" notBefore="1757" resp="#MMM">
                     <persName key="person_69848690" role="fmo">Francis Douce, 1757–1834</persName>,
                     see ODNB: bookplate on the upper pastedown. His (?) shelfmark (?): ‘B. 7’ in
                     red ink on the upper pastedown (cf. MS. Douce 23, MS. Douce 24, MS. Douce 49). </provenance>
                  <acquisition when="1834">Bodleian Library: received in 1834 with bequest of Douce.
                  </acquisition>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>Elizabeth Solopova, <title>Latin Liturgical Psalters in the Bodleian
                              Library: A Select Catalogue</title> (Oxford, 2013), pp. 365–71.
                           Previously described in the Summary Catalogue. <listBibl>
                              <bibl facs="aaz0519.gif" type="SC">Summary Catalogue, vol. 4, p.
                                 500</bibl>
                           </listBibl>
                        </source>
                     </recordHist>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <surrogates>
                     <bibl subtype="partial" type="digital-facsimile">
                        <ref
                           target="https://digital.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/objects/035c5483-7202-4b24-863e-e23f3bb567b3/">
                           <title>Digital Bodleian</title>
                        </ref>
                        <note>(26 images from 35mm slides)</note>
                     </bibl>
                  </surrogates>
                  <listBibl type="WRAPPER">
                     <listBibl type="PRINT">
                        <head>Select bibliography to 2009:</head>

                        <bibl>Weale, W., ‘Liturgical manuscripts in the Bodleian Library,
                              Oxford’, <title>The Ecclesiologist</title> 3 (1 September 1888), p.
                           36.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Summary catalogue, vol. 4, no. 21612.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Frere, no. 440.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Willard, J. F., ‘Occupations of the months in medieval
                              calendars’, <title>BQR</title> 7 (1932), pp. 33–9, at pp. 34, 36.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Haseloff (1938), p. 67.</bibl>
                        <bibl><title>Flemish art, 1300–1700: Royal Academy of Arts, London, 1953–1954</title>
                           (London: Royal Academy of Arts, 1953), no. 557.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Diringer, D., <title>The illuminated book: its history and
                              production</title> (New York: Philosophical Library, 1958), p.
                           437.</bibl>
                        <bibl>S. J. P. van Dijk, <title>Latin Liturgical Manuscripts in the Bodleian
                           Library, Oxford, vol. 2: Office Books</title> (typescript, 1957),
                           <citedRange unit="page" from="92b" to="92b">p. 92b</citedRange>
                        </bibl>
                        <bibl>Pächt and Alexander (1966–73), vol. 1, no. 293, pls. XXI–XXII.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Carlvant (1978), pp. 134–5, 414–6, 474 and passim.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Carlvant, K. B. E., ‘Trends in Bruges illumination until 1260,
                              apropos a psalter connected with Oostkerke’, <title>Archives et bibliothèques
                              de Belgique</title> 56 (1985), pp. 321–63, at p. 351, n. 50.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Bräm, A., <title>Das Andachtsbuch der Marie de Gavre: Paris, Bibliothèque
                           nationale, Ms. nouv. acq. fr. 16251. Buchmalerei in der Diözese Cambrai im letzten Viertel des 13.
                           Jahrhunderts</title> (Wiesbaden: L. Reichert, 1997), p. 161.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Randall, L. M. C. et al., <title>Medieval and Renaissance manuscripts
                              in the Walters Art Gallery, vol. iii, Belgium, 1250–1530</title>, 2
                              parts (Baltimore; London: Johns Hopkins University Press in
                           association with the Walters Art Gallery, 1997), part 1, no. 216, p.
                           14.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Stones, A., ‘The full-page miniatures of the Psalter-Hours New York,
                           PML, MS M. 729. Programme and patron’ in Büttner (2004), pp. 281–307, at pp. 330, 306,
                           307.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Morgan (2009), p. 69.</bibl>
                     </listBibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2024-05-07">Encode full description from Solopova catalogue.</change>
         <change when="2018-10-14" xml:id="MMM">
            <persName>Mitch Fraas</persName> Provenance and acquisition information added using <ref
               target="https://github.com/littlegustv/oxfordupdates/blob/master/test_case_for_oxford_prov.rb"
               >https://github.com/littlegustv/oxfordupdates/blob/master/test_case_for_oxford_prov.rb</ref>
            in collaboration with the <ref target="http://mappingmanuscriptmigrations.org/">Mapping
               Manuscript Migrations</ref> project.</change>
         <change when="2017-07-01">First online publication.</change>
         <change when="2017-05-25">
            <persName>James Cummings</persName> Up-converted the markup using <ref
               target="https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl"
               >https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl</ref>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
