<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="manuscript_4612">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>MS. Douce 265</title>
            <title type="collection">MSS. Douce</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Description</resp>
               <persName>Elizabeth Solopova</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Revision</resp>
               <persName>Andrew Dunning</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </publisher>
            <idno type="msID">MS_Douce_265</idno>
            <idno type="collection">Douce</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="MS_Douce_265" xml:lang="en">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <region type="county">Oxfordshire</region>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <institution>University of Oxford</institution>
                  <repository>Bodleian Library</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">MS. Douce 265</idno>
                  <idno type="ieArk">ark:29072/x0dj52w4884s</idno><idno type="crArk">ark:29072/x06395w795gk</idno><altIdentifier type="internal">
                     <idno type="SCN">21839</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents>
                  <textLang mainLang="enm" otherLangs="la">Middle English with Latin</textLang>
                  <msItem n="1">
                     <locus from="i recto" to="1v">(fols. i recto–1v)</locus>
                     <note>Fol. i is a paper flyleaf (see Provenance).</note>
                     <note>Fols. ii–1 are an added bifolium from a Wycliffite table of lections (see Douce 265-a).</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem>
                     <note>Fols. 2–3 are parchment leaves ruled for two columns, but blank apart from early modern notes (see Provenance).</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="2">
                     <locus from="4r" to="13r">(fols. 4r–13r)</locus>
                     <note>[item 2 occupies quire I]</note>
                     <title type="desc">Table of lections of Type I</title>
                     <rubric>Here bigynneþ a rule þat telliþ in whiche chapiters of þe bible ȝe may fynde þe pistlis &amp; gospels þat ben rad in þe chirche aftir þe vss of salisbirie markid with lettris of þe a.b.c. at þe bigynnynge of þe chapiters or toward þe myddil or ende aftir þe ordre as þe lettris stonden in þe a.b.c. ffirst ben sett sondaies &amp; verials to gidere and after þat þe sanctorum comyn &amp; propre togider of al þe ȝeer ffirst is writun a clause of þe bigynnynge þerof and a clause of þe endinge þerof also</rubric>
                     <note>Contains New Testament lections only (cf. MS. Bodl. 183). Includes all feasts characteristic of the Later Version of the Wycliffite Bible (Forshall, J. and Madden, F. (eds), <title>The Holy Bible … in the earliest English versions made from the Latin Vulgate by John Wycliffe and his followers</title>, 4 vols (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1850), vol. 4, pp. 683, 690–6), apart from Giles (1 September). The readings consist of the name of the liturgical occasion in red, abbreviated reference to a book and chapter of the Bible, an indexing letter in red, the opening words of a reading, <q>ende</q> in red, the closing words of a reading and double strokes in red. Includes the temporal, followed by commemorations of the Virgin Mary, Trinity, Holy Ghost, Cross, angels, <q>ffor briþeren &amp; sustris &amp; salus populi</q>, peace, clear weather, rain, <q>in time of batlis</q>, <q>a man for him silf</q>, <q>for pestilence of bestes</q>, pilgrims, weddings, sinners, sick, <q>pistils for dede</q> and gospels for the dead. Commemorations are followed by the sanctoral (both proper and common according to the rubric, but only proper is present). Larger initials at Conversion of St Paul, Candlemas, Annunciation, Nativity of John the Baptist, Nativity of the Virgin Mary, St Luke and Halloween.</note>
                     <finalRubric>Thus endiþ þe kalender of þe newe testament</finalRubric>
                     <note>Title ‘pope’ is erased <locus from="10r" to="10r">(fol. 10r)</locus>. Fol. 13v is ruled for the table of lections, but blank apart from an added note (see Provenance); fol. 14r–v is ruled for two columns, but blank.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="3">
                     <locus from="15r" to="243v">(fols. 15r–243v)</locus>
                     <note>[item 3 occupies quires II–XXX]</note>
                     <title key="work_13437" type="desc">New Testament in the Later Version of the Wycliffite Bible with usual prologues</title>
                     <note>Usual rubrics at the beginning of all prologues and books, e.g., <q>here endiþ þe gospel of Matheu and bigynneþ þe prolog on þe gospel of mark</q>
                        <locus from="44r" to="44r">(fol. 44r)</locus>; <q>Ierom on his prologe seiþ þis on mark</q>
                        <locus from="44v" to="44v">(fol. 44v)</locus>. Chapter numbers as red Roman numerals or written out as words in English. Running titles in red with blue paraphs on both rectos and versos, consisting of an abbreviated title of the biblical book only.</note>
                     <finalRubric>Here endiþ þe apocalips of Ioon þe ende of þe newe testament</finalRubric>
                     <note>Corrections in a contemporary hand. No marginal glosses; added material within the text is not underlined. Indexing letters in the margins entered at the beginnings of lections, rather than consistently. The beginnings of lections are also highlighted with yellow wash within the text; the ends of lections are marked with double strokes in the margins and within the text. Crosses and <q>nota</q> added in the margins. Added notes in a 15th-century hand in the margins of the Apocalypse, briefly describing the content of the seven visions. Fols. 244–263v are ruled for two columns, but blank, apart from fol. 261r which contains an extract from <persName key="person_17218027" role="aut">Heinrich Suso</persName>, <title key="work_1975">Horologium Sapientiae</title>, <title key="work_6729">Cursus de aeterna sapientia</title>, added in a 15th-century hand. The extract contains the beginning of the <title>Cursus</title> up to the end of the third stanza of the <q>Hymnus</q> (<q>Iesu dulcis memoria…</q>), starting <q>Salutem mentis &amp; corporis…</q> and ending <q>…sed quid inuenientibus</q> (ed. Künzle (1977), pp. 606–7).</note>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="perg">
                        <support>parchment</support>
                        <extent>267 leaves, <foreign rend="italic">c.</foreign><dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                              <height>181</height>
                              <width>124</width>
                           </dimensions></extent>
                        <foliation>modern in pencil, i–ii + 1–265</foliation>
                        <collation><locus from="i" to="3">(fols. i–3)</locus> paper flyleaf, added bifolium and two parchment leaves | <locus from="4" to="13">(fols. 4–13)</locus> I (10) missing 1 | <locus from="14" to="261">(fols. 14–261)</locus> II–XXXII (8) | <locus from="262" to="263">(fols. 262–263)</locus> XXXIII (4–2 (?)) | <locus from="264" to="266">(fols. 264–266)</locus> paper flyleaves. <catchwords>Catchwords survive.</catchwords>
                           <signatures>Leaf signatures in New Testament run consecutively a–p in quires II–XVI <locus from="14" to="133">(fols. 14–133)</locus> and a–o in quires XVII–XXX <locus from="134" to="245">(fols. 134–245)</locus>.</signatures>
                           <secFol><q>ffriday romans xiiii</q>
                              <locus>(fol. 5r, table of lections)</locus></secFol>
                        </collation>
                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout columns="2" writtenLines="33">ruled for two columns with single vertical and double horizontal bounding lines extending the full height and width of page; 33 lines per page; written space: <foreign rend="italic">c.</foreign><dimensions type="ruled" unit="mm">
                              <height>115</height>
                              <width>80</width>
                           </dimensions></layout>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc>
                     <handNote script="textualisNorthern">textura, black ink; the table of lections is by a different scribe</handNote>
                  </handDesc>
                  <decoDesc>
                     <decoNote type="flourInit">4-line gold initials on blue and pink background, decorated with penwork sprays and gold leaves, at the beginnings of books.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="flourInit">2-line blue initials with red penwork at the beginnings of prologues and chapters.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="rubrication">Rubrics in red ink.</decoNote>
                  </decoDesc>
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <binding notAfter="1800" notBefore="1700">
                        <p>Red morocco over thick pasteboard, made for Thomas Rawlinson early in the 18th century. Gilt fillet lines and floral roll border round the outer edge of both covers. Gilt scallop shells in the four corners. A heraldic crest in the form of a bird with a scallop shell in its beak, surrounded by a wreath, at the centre of both covers. Six raised bands on spine edged with double gilt fillet lines. Gilt decoration on the panels between the raised bands. Gilt lettering ‘N. TESTAMENT IN ENGLISH’, ‘MSS.’ and paper label with ‘265’ on spine. Marbled paper pastedowns; laid paper flyleaves.</p>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origPlace>
                        <country key="place_7002445">England</country>
                     </origPlace>
                     <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="1459" notBefore="1440">15th century, middle</origDate>
                     <p>The table of lections and New Testament are codicologically separate and are the work of two different scribes, but the table of lections was written to accompany a New Testament since it omits all Old Testament readings.</p>
                     <p>Dialect survey: <list>
                           <item>ony(10), ech(5)/eche(5), fier(9)/fire(1), ȝouun(10), lyf(9)/lif(1), lijk(10), myche(10), siȝ(8)/syȝ(1) (sg.), saien(5)/siȝen(1)/seien(1) (pl.), silf(10), sich(4)/ siche(6), þouȝ(8), þurȝ(2)/þourȝ(7)/þouȝr(1), birie (bury), verials (‘ferials’, table of lections, rubric)</item>
                           <item>-iþ(9)/-eþ(1) (pres.ind.3sg.), -en(10) (pres.ind.pl.), -ynge(3)/-inge(7) (pres. part.), sche(10) (3sg fem.pronoun, nom.), þei(10) (3pl.pronoun, nom.), hem(10) (3pl.pronoun, oblique), her(10) (3pl.pronoun, possessive)</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                  </origin>
                  <provenance>Extract from Heinrich Suso’s <title>Horologium Sapientiae</title> added on empty leaves in a 15th-century hand.</provenance>
                  <provenance>Note by <persName>Robart Hornbe</persName> on fol. 13v recording that his mother gave him this book on 17 March 1543: <q>memorandum (?) yt my mother hathe gyvin to me Robart Hornbe herfore this newe testament yn xvij day of marche ye yere of ower lord god xliij in ye yere of ower soverayne lord king henry ye viij xxxiiij</q>. Followed by more text in the same hand, crossed out.</provenance>
                  <provenance>Title ‘pope’ erased in the table of lections, presumably at Reformation.</provenance>
                  <provenance><persName key="person_1203" role="fmo">Thomas Rawlinson</persName> (1681–1725); see <title>Oxford Dictionary of National Biography</title>: binding; fol. i verso.</provenance>
                  <provenance><persName key="person_90543170" role="fmo">Sir Peter Thompson</persName> (1698–1770), merchant and book collector; see <title>Oxford Dictionary of National Biography</title>: bought at Rawlinson’s sale in 1733 (lot 365) for £4 (note on fol. 3v).</provenance>
                  <provenance>May have been owned by <persName key="person_41944166" role="fmo">William Herbert</persName> (1718–1795); see <title>Oxford Dictionary of National Biography</title>: notes on fol. 1r–v. He is known to have bought books from Peter Thompson and to have collected bibles (see <title>Oxford Dictionary of National Biography</title>).</provenance>
                  <provenance><persName key="person_56951183" role="fmo">Gustavus Brander</persName> (1719/20–1787), merchant and antiquary; see <title>Oxford Dictionary of National Biography</title>: lot 1096 in his sale 13 February, 1790.</provenance>
                  <provenance><persName key="person_69848690" role="fmo">Francis Douce</persName> (1757–1834); see <title>Oxford Dictionary of National Biography</title>: bought at Brander’s sale for £3 13<foreign rend="italic">s</foreign>. 6<foreign rend="italic">d</foreign>.; bookplate on the upper pastedown, notes on fols. i verso, 2r, 3v, stamp on fol. 4r. Added a bifolium from a Wycliffite table of lections (?).</provenance>
                  <acquisition when="1834">Bodleian Library: received in 1834 with the bequest of Douce.</acquisition>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>Elizabeth Solopova, <title><ref target="https://jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1gn6cmr">Manuscripts of the Wycliffite Bible in the Bodleian and Oxford College Libraries</ref></title>, Exeter Medieval Texts and Studies (Liverpool: Liverpool University Press, 2016), no. 15. Previously described: <listBibl>
                              <bibl facs="aaz0591.gif" type="SC">Summary Catalogue, vol. 4, p. 572</bibl>
                              <bibl facs="aaz0592.gif" type="SC">Summary Catalogue, vol. 4, p. 573</bibl>
                           </listBibl>
                        </source>
                     </recordHist>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <surrogates>
                     <bibl subtype="partial" type="digital-facsimile">
                        <ref target="https://digital.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/objects/7638a3a5-dfd1-4d3d-9adc-4007b1b47582/">
                           <title>Digital Bodleian</title>
                        </ref>
                        <note>(1 image from 35mm slides)</note>
                     </bibl>
                  </surrogates>
                  <listBibl type="WRAPPER">
                     <listBibl type="PRINT">
                        <bibl>Forshall, J. and Madden, F. (eds), <title>The Holy Bible … in the earliest English versions made from the Latin Vulgate by John Wycliffe and his followers</title>, 4 vols (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1850), vol. 1, p. l.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Madan, F., <title>Summary catalogue of western manuscripts in the Bodleian Library at Oxford</title>, vol. 4 <title>(collections received during the first half of the 19th century) nos. 16670–24330</title> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1897), no. 21839.</bibl>
                        <bibl>May, S. W., ‘William Hunnis and the 1577 <title>Paradise of Dainty Devices</title>, <title>Studies in Bibiliography</title> 28 (1975), pp. 63–80 at p. 63 n. 2.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Rogers, D., ‘Francis Douce’s manuscripts: some hitherto unrecognised provenances’, in Hunt, R. W., Philip, I. G. and Roberts, R. J. (eds), <title>Studies in the book trade in honour of Graham Pollard</title> (Oxford: Oxford Bibliographical Society, 1975), pp. 315–40 at p. 319.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Künzle, Pius (ed.), <title>Heinrich Seuses Horologium sapientiae</title>, Spicilegium Friburgense 23 (Freiburg/Schweiz: Universitätsverlag, 1977).</bibl>
                        <bibl><title>The Douce legacy: an exhibition to commemorate the 150th anniversary of the bequest of Francis Douce (1757–1834)</title> (Oxford: Bodleian Library, 1984), no. 200.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Hudson, A., ‘Lollard book production’, in Griffiths, J. and Pearsall, D. A. (eds), <title>Book production and publishing in Britain 1375–1475</title> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1989), pp. 125–42, p. 140.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Dove, M., <title>The first English Bible: the text and context of the Wycliffite versions</title> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2007), p. 299.</bibl>
                     </listBibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
               <msPart>
                  <msIdentifier>
                     <altIdentifier type="partial">
                        <idno type="part">MS. Douce 265-a</idno>
                     </altIdentifier>
                  </msIdentifier>
                  <msContents>
                     <textLang mainLang="enm" otherLangs="la">Middle English with Latin</textLang>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="ii" to="1">(fols. ii–1)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Wycliffite table of lections of Type I with Old Testament readings written out in full</title>
                        <note>A bifolium bound with MS. Douce 265.</note>
                        <note>Contains the end of the temporal and most of the commemorations; probably written to accompany a New Testament. Starts with the Ember Saturday before the 18th Sunday after Trinity and ends with the commemoration of the sick. New Testament readings consist of the name of a liturgical occasion in red, abbreviated reference to a book and chapter of the Bible, an indexing letter in red, the opening words of a reading, <q>ende</q> in red, the closing words of a reading and double strokes in red. Old Testament readings are written out in full with added material within the text underlined in red, each preceded by a rubric stating the liturgical occasion. Some Old Testament readings derive from the Earlier Version of the Wycliffite Bible (e.g., Ecclesiasticus 24, Genesis 24), whereas others from the Later Version of the Wycliffite Bible (e.g., Jeremiah 14, Jeremiah 23, Ecclesiasticus 44) (see the description of a similar table in MS. Bodl. 531). Does not include Wednesday after the 25th Sunday after Trinity, an entry characteristic of the Later Version of the Wycliffite Bible (Forshall, J. and Madden, F. (eds), <title>The Holy Bible … in the earliest English versions made from the Latin Vulgate by John Wycliffe and his followers</title>, 4 vols (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1850), vol. 4, pp. 683–98). Commemorations are in the following order: the Virgin Mary, Trinity, Holy Ghost, Cross, angels, <q>ffor breþeren &amp; sistris &amp; salus populi</q>, peace, clear weather, rain, <q>In tyme of bateils</q>, <q>a man for him silf</q>, <q>ffor pestilence of beestis</q>, pilgrims, weddings, sinners and sick. Shares variants with Forshall and Madden’s (1850) manuscripts EMRXk, including a rubric <q>treno<ex>rum</ex> ii</q> for an Old Testament reading for ‘clear weather’; the presence of the entry <q>Commemoracioun of oure ladi in alle oþire tymes of þe ȝeer</q>; and the order of commemorations, e.g., angels after the Cross (Forshall, J. and Madden, F. (eds), <title>The Holy Bible … in the earliest English versions made from the Latin Vulgate by John Wycliffe and his followers</title>, 4 vols (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1850), vol. 4, pp. 697–8). Running titles in red with blue paraphs written across a two-leaf opening.</note>
                     </msItem>
                  </msContents>
                  <physDesc>
                     <objectDesc form="codex">
                        <supportDesc material="perg">
                           <support>parchment</support>
                           <extent><foreign rend="italic">c.</foreign><dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                                 <height>213</height>
                                 <width>147</width>
                              </dimensions></extent>
                           <collation>a single bifolium from the centre (?) of a quire; <catchwords>catchwords in red on the verso of both leaves.</catchwords>
                           </collation>
                        </supportDesc>
                        <layoutDesc>
                           <layout columns="1" writtenLines="36">ruled in ink with double vertical and double horizontal (upper margin) bounding lines extending the full height and width of page; the lower margin has a single horizontal bounding line and an additional set of two bounding lines; 36 lines per page; written space: <foreign rend="italic">c.</foreign><dimensions type="ruled" unit="mm">
                                 <height>117</height>
                                 <width>95</width>
                              </dimensions></layout>
                        </layoutDesc>
                     </objectDesc>
                     <handDesc>
                        <handNote script="textualisNorthern">textura, black ink</handNote>
                     </handDesc>
                     <decoDesc>
                        <decoNote type="flourInit">1-line blue initials with red penwork at the beginning of Old Testament readings.</decoNote>
                        <decoNote type="rubrication">Rubrics in red ink.</decoNote>
                     </decoDesc>
                  </physDesc>
                  <history>
                     <origin>
                        <origPlace>
                           <country key="place_7002445">England</country>
                        </origPlace>
                        <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="1425" notBefore="1400">15th century, first quarter</origDate>
                        <p>A leaf from a Wycliffite New Testament with a table of lections (?).</p>
                        <p>Dialect survey: <list>
                              <item>biried(1), lijc(1), wijs(1) -eþ(3) (pres.ind.3sg.), -en(10) (pres.ind.pl.), -yng(2)/ynge(1)/-inge(2)/-ing(1) (pres.part.),</item>
                              <item>þei(5) (3pl.pronoun, nom.), hem(8) (3pl.pronoun, oblique), her(3) (3pl. pronoun, possessive)</item>
                           </list>
                        </p>
                     </origin>
                     <provenance>Bound with MS. Douce 265 by Francis Douce (?).</provenance>
                  </history>
                  <additional>
                     <adminInfo>
                        <recordHist>
                           <source>Elizabeth Solopova, <title><ref target="https://jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1gn6cmr">Manuscripts of the Wycliffite Bible in the Bodleian and Oxford College Libraries</ref></title>, Exeter Medieval Texts and Studies (Liverpool: Liverpool University Press, 2016), no. 17.</source>
                        </recordHist>
                     </adminInfo>
                  </additional>
               </msPart>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2023-03-24">Add Solopova description.</change>
         <change when="2022-04-04">Add binding information from Summary Catalogue.</change>
         <change when="2018-10-14" xml:id="MMM">
            <persName>Mitch Fraas</persName> Provenance and acquisition information added using <ref target="https://github.com/littlegustv/oxfordupdates/blob/master/test_case_for_oxford_prov.rb">https://github.com/littlegustv/oxfordupdates/blob/master/test_case_for_oxford_prov.rb</ref> in collaboration with the <ref target="http://mappingmanuscriptmigrations.org/">Mapping Manuscript Migrations</ref> project.</change>
         <change when="2017-07-01">First online publication.</change>
         <change when="2017-05-25">
            <persName>James Cummings</persName> Up-converted the markup using <ref target="https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl">https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl</ref>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
