<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="manuscript_4691">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>MS. Douce 369</title>
            <title type="collection">MSS. Douce</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Description</resp>
               <persName>Elizabeth Solopova</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Revision</resp>
               <persName>Andrew Dunning</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </publisher>
            <idno type="msID">MS_Douce_369</idno>
            <idno type="collection">Douce</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="MS_Douce_369" xml:lang="en">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <region type="county">Oxfordshire</region>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <institution>University of Oxford</institution>
                  <repository>Bodleian Library</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">MS. Douce 369</idno>
                  <idno type="ieArk">ark:29072/x04b29b673gh</idno><idno type="crArk">ark:29072/x0gb19f6107j</idno><altIdentifier type="internal">
                     <idno type="SCN">21944</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <p n="composite">Composite: fols. 1–250 || fols. 251–485</p>
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <binding notAfter="1834" notBefore="1800">
                        <p>Nineteenth-century binding made for Douce (Gillam (1984)), red velvet over boards. Six raised bands on spine. Gilt (flaking) decorations (vases) and lettering on spine ‘ANTIENT <lb/> ENGLISH <lb/> BIBLE’ and ‘MSS 14 CENT’. Pastedowns and flyleaves made from blue paper with white floral designs; further flyleaves of laid paper with watermarks. Edges of textblock speckled red.</p>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <provenance>Biblical books in both parts are numbered in the upper right corner in medieval hands; see fols. 100r, 101r, 109r, 146r, 357r, 463r. The first clearly visible number is ‘5’ on fol. 16r, which shows that the books were numbered before the beginning was lost. The prologues are not numbered separately, but have the same number as the preceding or following book (e.g., the prologue to psalms has number 21 <locus from="150r" to="150r">(fol. 150r)</locus>, the same as preceding <title>Job</title>). On fol. 78v (4 Kings) number 12 is accompanied by the word <q>ezechie</q>, referring to the beginning of chapter 21 <q>And ezechie…</q>. On fol. 146r the number is outlined in red. The first clearly visible number in the second part is ‘29’ <locus from="275r" to="275r">(fol. 275r)</locus> for <title>Jeremiah</title>.</provenance>
                  <provenance>Notes in a 16th-century hand, recording the loss of leaves at the beginning and end: <q>Thar be thes man<ex>y</ex> leves conteyned in this book in all <note>[space]</note> s(?) xxv cor lacking j lefe</q>
                     <locus from="1r" to="1r">(fol. 1r)</locus>; <q>Better it is to trus(?)</q>
                     <locus from="147r" to="147r">(fol. 147r)</locus>; <q>Thar be so man<ex>y</ex> lefese contained in this book in all s(?) xxv cor laking j lefe</q>
                     <locus from="486v" to="486v">(fol. 486v)</locus>. Pious note in the margin on fol. 203v in a different 16th-century hand: <q>Helth is þe gefte of god…</q>.</provenance>
                  <provenance><persName key="person_69848690" role="fmo">Francis Douce</persName> (1757–1834); see <title>Oxford Dictionary of National Biography</title>: recorded in his accession notebook (MS. Douce e. 67, fol. 32r) under November 1818: ‘Wicliffe’s Testament MS… Triphook’ (Rogers (1975)). Initials ‘FD’ in a red circular frame <locus from="1r" to="1v">(fol. 1r–v)</locus>. Notes by Douce throughout <locus>(fols. i verso, ii recto, 170v, 250r, etc.)</locus>.</provenance>
                  <acquisition when="1834">Bodleian Library: received in 1834 with the bequest of Douce.</acquisition>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>Elizabeth Solopova, <title><ref target="https://jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1gn6cmr">Manuscripts of the Wycliffite Bible in the Bodleian and Oxford College Libraries</ref></title>, Exeter Medieval Texts and Studies (Liverpool: Liverpool University Press, 2016), no. 17. Previously described: <listBibl>
                              <bibl facs="aaz0628.gif" type="SC">Summary Catalogue, vol. 4, p. 609</bibl>
                           </listBibl>
                        </source>
                     </recordHist>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <surrogates>
                     <bibl subtype="partial" type="digital-facsimile">
                        <ref target="https://digital.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/objects/52b725a6-eb3e-40e4-b125-a137a5aed11b/">
                           <title>Digital Bodleian</title>
                        </ref>
                        <note>(2 images from 35mm slides)</note>
                     </bibl>
                  </surrogates>
                  <listBibl type="WRAPPER">
                     <listBibl type="PRINT">
                        <bibl>Forshall, J. and Madden, F. (eds), <title>The Holy Bible … in the earliest English versions made from the Latin Vulgate by John Wycliffe and his followers</title>, 4 vols (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1850), vol. 1, pp. xvii, xxxiv–xxxvi, l–li, base text for the Earlier Version of the Wycliffite Bible from Ezra to Baruch 3:20; sigla <title>C</title> – first part; <title>K</title> – second part.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Madan, F., <title>Summary catalogue of western manuscripts in the Bodleian Library at Oxford</title>, vol. 4 <title>(collections received during the first half of the 19th century) nos. 16670–24330</title> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1897), no. 21944.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Skeat, W. W., ‘On the dialect of Wycliffe’s Bible’, <title>Transactions of the Philological Society</title> (1895), pp. 212–19 at pp. 217–18.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Deanesly, M., <title>The Lollard Bible and other medieval biblical versions</title> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1920), p. 253.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Pope, H. and Bullough, S., <title>English versions of the Bible</title> (St Louis, Mo.: Herder, 1952).</bibl>
                        <bibl>Fristedt, S. L., <title>The Wycliffe Bible</title>, 3 vols (Stockholm: Almquvist &amp; Wiksells, 1953–73), <foreign rend="italic">passim</foreign>; sigla C and K.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Hargreaves, H., ‘The Latin text of Purvey’s Psalter’, <title>Medium Aevum</title> 24 (1955), pp. 73–90 at p. 74.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Fristedt, S. L., ‘The authorship of the Lollard Bible’, <title>Stockholm Studies in Modern Philology</title> 18 (1956), pp. 28–41, <foreign rend="italic">passim</foreign>.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Hargreaves, H., ‘The Middle English primers and the Wycliffite Bible’, <title>Modern Language Review</title> 51 (1956), pp. 215–17 at p. 217.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Lindberg, C. (ed.), <title>The earlier version of the Wycliffite Bible,</title> 8 vols (Stockholm: Almqvist &amp; Wiksell, 1959–97), vol. 8 (1997), pp. 24, 29, 70, 374, sigla ‘C’, ‘K’, ‘O’.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Danielsson, B., review of Fristedt, <title>The Wycliffe Bible</title>, part II, <title>Studia Neophilologica</title> 44 (1972), pp. 190–5.</bibl>
                        <bibl>David, R., ‘Francis Douce’s manuscripts: some hitherto unrecognised provenances’, <title>Studies in the book trade in honour of Graham Pollard</title>, Oxford Bibliographical Society Publications, n.s. 18 (Oxford, 1975), pp. 315–40 at p. 339.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Lambert, M. D., <title>Medieval heresy: popular movements from Bogomil to Hus</title> (London: E. Arnold, 1977), p. 234.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Gillam, S. G. (ed.), <title>The Douce legacy: an exhibition to commemorate the 150th anniversary of the bequest of Francis Douce (1757–1834)</title> (Oxford: Bodleian Library, 1984), no. 203.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Hudson, A., <title>Lollards and their books</title> (London: Hambledon Press, 1985), p. 104.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Brake, D. L. (ed.), <title>The New Testament in English translated by John Wycliffe MCCCLXXXII; revised by John Purvey MCCCLXXXVIII</title> (facsimile of MS. Rawl. C. 259) (Portland, Oreg.: International Bible Publications, 1986), pp. xxi–ii.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Tanabe, H., ‘On some English renderings in the vocabulary of the Wycliffite Bible’ in Oshitari K. et al. (ed.), <title>Philologia Anglica: essays presented to Professor Yoshio Terasawa on the occasion of his sixtieth birthday</title> (Tokyo: Kenkyusha, 1988), pp. 389–402 at pp. 389 n. 1.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Catto, J. I., ‘Wyclif and Wycliffism at Oxford’ in Catto, J. I. and Evans, R. (eds), <title>The history of the University of Oxford</title>, vol. 2, <title>Late medieval Oxford</title> (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1992), pp. 175–261 at p. 225.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Lindberg, C. (ed.), <title>King Henry’s Bible, MS. Bodley 277: the revised version of the Wyclif Bible</title>, 4 vols (Stockholm: Almqvist &amp; Wiksell, 1999–2004), vol. 3, p. 5. Scott, K. L. (gen. ed.), <title>An index of images in English manuscripts from the time of Chaucer to Henry VIII, c.1380–c.1509: the Bodleian Library, Oxford</title>, 3 vols (Turnhout: Harvey Miller Publishers, 2000–02), vol. 2, p. 41, no. 493. de Hamel, C., <title>The book: a history of the Bible</title> (London: Phaidon, 2001), pp. 170–3, fig. 120. Dove, M., <title>The first English Bible: the text and context of the Wycliffite versions</title> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2007), pp. 256–7, 299 and <foreign rend="italic">passim</foreign>.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Peikola M., ‘Aspects of mise-en-page in manuscripts of the Wycliffite Bible’, in Caie G. and Renevey D. (eds.), <title>Medieval texts in context</title> (London: Routledge, 2008), pp. 28–67 at p. 40.</bibl>
                     </listBibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
               <msPart xml:id="MS_Douce_369-part1">
                  <msIdentifier>
                     <altIdentifier type="partial">
                        <idno type="part">MS. Douce 369, fols. 1r–250v</idno>
                     </altIdentifier>
                  </msIdentifier>
                  <msContents>
                     <textLang mainLang="enm" otherLangs="la">Middle English with Latin</textLang>
                     <msItem>
                        <note>Fols. i–ii are paper flyleaves, blank apart from Douce’s notes on Wyclif.</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem class="#biblia" n="1">
                        <locus from="1r" to="250r">(fols. 1r–250r)</locus>
                        <title key="work_15600" type="desc">Numbers 20:2–Baruch 3:20 in the Earlier Version of the Wycliffite Bible with usual prologues</title>
                        <note>Imperfect at the beginning because of the loss of leaves. Prologues to psalms appear at the end of quire XVIII. The second of the two prologues occupies three-quarters of the first column on the last page of this quire <locus from="150v" to="150v">(fol. 150v)</locus>, the rest of the page is left blank and psalms start on a new quire. The books are numbered in a contemporary hand as shown in brackets after each title (see also Provenance). Running titles in black in the upper left margin, usually only on the versos, consisting of abbreviated titles of books without chapter numbers. Occasionally rubrics in red or black, in English or Latin, by the scribes, rubricator or added in contemporary hands (see below). Chapter numbers in black (occasionally in red) in the margins at the beginning of each chapter in Arabic numerals, preceded by <q>c<ex>apitulu</ex>m</q>. The contents of the chapters are summarised in Latin verses (two for each chapter) in the lower margins of pages containing the beginnings of chapters. The verses are laid out in long lines and rhyme at the end and at caesura. Such two-line verse summaries are in a smaller, more informal script, in a hand different from those of the main scribes, and are preceded by chapter numbers in Arabic numerals. The ruling for the verses (thick brown plummet) is similar to the ruling elsewhere in the manuscript (e.g., fols. 6v, 15v–16r, 189r, 193r). Occasionally the ruling is provided where the verses are absent (e.g., fols. 42v, 121r, 122r, etc.). Starting with fol. 132v the chapter numbers that accompany the verses are in red, and the verses are enclosed in red brackets. The verse summaries are absent in psalms and after fol. 206r (from chapter 47 of Ecclesiasticus onwards), though the ruling is provided up to fol. 208r. The lections are occasionally marked with a red bracket in the margin and sometimes with the opening and final letters of the passage written in red in the margins. Added material within the text is occasionally underlined faintly in brown ink (e.g., Jeremiah 8:7, fol. 230r).</note>
                        <note>Many corrections in the margins in contemporary hands, including cancellations, additions and substitutions of words or short phrases. Some corrections are stylistic or grammatical; particularly frequent are the substitution of <q>þe whiche</q> for <q>þe</q> or <q>þat</q>, the insertion of the article <q>þe</q> and the future modal <q>schal</q> (e.g., fols. 193r, 198r–v, 200r, 202r, 203r, 224v). Other examples are <q>resteyȝede</q> for <q>restide</q>
                           <locus from="65r" to="65r">(fol. 65r)</locus>, <q>hadde taken</q> for <q>tok</q>
                           <locus from="80r" to="80r">(fol. 80r)</locus>, <q>made of nou3t</q> for <q>foormede</q>
                           <locus from="219v" to="219v">(fol. 219v)</locus>. Other contemporary marginal additions include: cross-references between biblical books (e.g., fols. 117r–v, 222r, 223v); notes providing the Latin version of a phrase (e.g., <q>optaui et datus</q>, fol. 187v; <q>melior est iniquitas…</q>, fol. 205r; <q>clama ne cesses</q>, fol. 224r) and <q>nota</q>
                           <locus>(fols. 184r, 185r, 194v, 223r, 229r etc.)</locus>. Contemporary pointing hands and ‘hedera’ signs in the margins, some in red ink <locus from="146v" to="146v">(fol. 146v)</locus>, occasionally accompanied by notes referring to the content of passages (e.g., <q>heritage of prestis</q>, fol. 206r), or drawing attention to them (<q>noteþ weel</q>, fol. 230r; <q>marke weel</q>, fol. 230v). Some notes are on scrolls or outlined in red ink <locus from="68r" to="68r">(fol. 68r)</locus>; many partially cropped off.</note>
                        <note>[quires I–XVIII]</note>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="1r">(fol. 1r)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Numbers 20:2 (4?)</title>
                           <note>Imperfect at the beginning.</note>
                           <incipit defective="true">whanne the puple nedede water</incipit>
                           <note>17th-century note concerning the loss of leaves (see Provenance).</note>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="8v">(fol. 8v)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Deuteronomy (5)</title>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="22v">(fol. 22v)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Prologue to Joshua</title>
                           <incipit>At þe laste ended þe fyue bookis of moises</incipit>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="23r">(fol. 23r)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Joshua (6)</title>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="32v">(fol. 32v)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Judges (7)</title>
                           <note>Missing 1:21–4:4, because of the loss of a leaf after fol. 32</note>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="41r">(fol. 41r)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Ruth (8)</title>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="42v">(fol. 42v)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Prologue to 1 Kings</title>
                           <incipit>Þe tunge forsoþe</incipit>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="43v">(fol. 43v)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">1 Kings (9)</title>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="56v">(fol. 56v)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">2 Kings (10)</title>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="67r">(fol. 67r)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">3 Kings (11)</title>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="78v">(fol. 78v)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">4 Kings (12 and <q>ezechie</q>)</title>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="89v">(fol. 89v)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Prologue to 1 Chronicles</title>
                           <rubric>Prologus paralipomenon</rubric>
                           <incipit>Iff þe making of þe seuenti</incipit>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="89v">(fol. 89v)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Prologue to 1 Chronicles</title>
                           <incipit>Þe boc of paralipomenon</incipit>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="89v">(fol. 89v)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">1 Chronicles (13)</title>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="99v">(fol. 99v)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Prologue to 2 Chronicles</title>
                           <incipit>Evsebeus ierome senden</incipit>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="100r">(fol. 100r)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">2 Chronicles (14)</title>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="112r">(fol. 112r)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Prayer of Manasseh</title>
                           <note>(note, added by the original scribe: <q>þis preȝeere of manasse is not in ebrue</q>, fol. 112v)</note>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="112v">(fol. 112v)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Prologue to 1 Ezra</title>
                           <incipit>Wheþer it be hardere</incipit>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="113r">(fol. 113r)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Prologue to 1 Ezra</title>
                           <incipit>Esdras et Neemye</incipit>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="113r">(fol. 113r)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Commendation of Ezra</title>
                           <rubric>Here folewiþ þe comendacioun of esdre</rubric>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="113r">(fol. 113r)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">1 Ezra (15)</title>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="116v">(fol. 116v)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">2 Ezra (16)</title>
                           <rubric>Explicit liber primus. Incipit liber secundus</rubric>
                           <finalRubric>Explicit liber secundus esdre <locus from="121r" to="121r">(fol. 121r)</locus></finalRubric>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="121r">(fol. 121r)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">3 Ezra (17)</title>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="126v">(fol. 126v)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Prologue to Tobit</title>
                           <incipit>To cromacio</incipit>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="126v">(fol. 126v)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Tobit (18)</title>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="130r">(fol. 130r)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Prologue to Judith</title>
                           <incipit>Anentus þe ebrues</incipit>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="130r">(fol. 130r)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Prologue to Judith</title>
                           <incipit>Jvdith widewe</incipit>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="130r">(fol. 130r)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Judith (19)</title>
                           <rubric>Explicit liber iudith <locus from="134v" to="134v">(fol. 134v)</locus></rubric>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="134v">(fol. 134v)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Prologue to Esther</title>
                           <incipit>Þe boc of ester to be maad vicious</incipit>
                           <note>Rubrics concerning the differences between the Latin and English texts in brown ink.</note>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="134v">(fol. 134v)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Esther (20)</title>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="139v">(fol. 139v)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Prologue to Job</title>
                           <rubric>Incipit prologus in libro Iob</rubric>
                           <incipit>I am constreyned</incipit>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="140">(fol. 140)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Prologue to Job</title>
                           <incipit>Iff forsoþe a Iunket wiþ resshe</incipit>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="140r">(fol. 140r)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Job (21)</title>
                           <rubric>Incipit liber Iob</rubric>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="149v">(fol. 149v)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Prologue to psalms</title>
                           <incipit>Whan it is knowe</incipit>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="150r">(fol. 150r)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Prologue to psalms</title>
                           <rubric>Explicit prologus super psalterium</rubric>
                           <incipit>Dauyd þe sone of Iesse</incipit>
                        </msItem>
                        <note>[quires XIX–XXX]</note>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="151r">(fol. 151r)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Psalms (22)</title>
                           <note>Laid out as prose with verses starting with alternating red or blue initials.</note>
                           <rubric>þe boc begynneþ of ympnes &amp; solitarie spechis of þe profete dauyd of cryst</rubric>
                           <note>A leaf is missing before the start of psalms, but there is no obvious loss of text. Liturgical divisions are not marked. English titles in red. Numbers and Latin incipits in the margins in a contemporary hand, but not by the main scribe. Verses on the psalter (9 lines) are added in the lower margin in the hand responsible for Latin verse chapter summaries: <quote>
                                 <l>Post Iob psalmorum codex debet stituari</l>
                                 <l>Dic sibi iunguntur prouerbia quam salomonis…</l>
                              </quote>
                           </note>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="174v">(fol. 174v)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Prologue to Proverbs</title>
                           <incipit>To Cromacye</incipit>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="174v">(fol. 174v)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Proverbs (23)</title>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="182v">(fol. 182v)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Prologue to Ecclesiastes</title>
                           <rubric>Heere gynneþ þe prologe in þe boc of eclesiates þat is to sey boc of talker to þe puple or togidere clepere</rubric>
                           <incipit>Þis almost þe fifte</incipit>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="182v">(fol. 182v)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Ecclesiastes (24?)</title>
                           <rubric>heer gynneþ þe boc</rubric>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="185r">(fol. 185r)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Song of Songs (25)</title>
                           <rubric>heer gynneþ þe booc þat is clepid song of songis of þe bridalis of crist &amp; of þe chirche þe chirche of þe comyng of crist spekiþ seiende</rubric>
                           <note>Speakers identified in red.</note>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="186v">(fol. 186v)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Prologue to Wisdom</title>
                           <rubric>heer gynneþ þe prolog in þe booc of wisdam</rubric>
                           <incipit>Þe booc of wisdam anent ebrues noȝher is</incipit>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="187r">(fol. 187r)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Wisdom (26)</title>
                           <rubric>heer gynneþ þe booc</rubric>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="191v">(fol. 191v)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Prologue to Ecclesiasticus</title>
                           <incipit>Off manye &amp; grete bi þe lawe and profetes</incipit>
                           <note><q>explicit</q> and <q>prologus</q> added by the hand which corrected the text.</note>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="191v">(fol. 191v)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Ecclesiasticus (27)</title>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="208r">(fol. 208r)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Prologue to Isaiah</title>
                           <rubric>prologus</rubric>
                           <incipit>No man whan</incipit>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="208v">(fol. 208v)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Isaiah (28)</title>
                           <rubric><note>(in chapter 38)</note> þe scripture of ezechie king of iuda whan he hadde be syc &amp; hadde couered of hys sycnesse</rubric>
                           <note>Preceding <q>I seide in þe myddel of my daȝes…</q>.</note>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="226v">(fol. 226v)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Prologue to Jeremiah</title>
                           <incipit>Jeremye þe profete</incipit>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="227r">(fol. 227r)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Prologue to Jeremiah</title>
                           <incipit>God is redi</incipit>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="227r">(fol. 227r)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Jeremiah (29)</title>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="247v">(fol. 247v)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Lamentations of Jeremiah (30?)</title>
                           <rubric>her gynneþ þe lamintacoun of ieremye þat is in title cenoþ with þe soylinge out of ebru lettris</rubric>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="249r">(fol. 249r)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Prayer of Jeremiah</title>
                           <rubric>þe orisoun of Ieremye profete</rubric>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="249r">(fol. 249r)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Prologue to Baruch</title>
                           <rubric>her endeþ ieremye &amp; ginneþ þe prolog in þe boc clepid baruch</rubric>
                           <incipit>Þis boc þat baruch bi name is befor notid</incipit>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="249r">(fol. 249r)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Baruch (31?)</title>
                           <rubric>heer gynneþ þe boc</rubric>
                        </msItem>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <note>Note concerning the authorship of Nicholas Hereford at the end (see Provenance). Fol. 250v is blank.</note>
                     </msItem>
                  </msContents>
                  <physDesc>
                     <objectDesc form="codex">
                        <supportDesc material="perg">
                           <support>parchment, generally thin, white and high quality, but sometimes rough, with tears repaired by sowing</support>
                           <extent>253 leaves, <foreign rend="italic">c.</foreign><dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                                 <height>365</height>
                                 <width>250</width>
                              </dimensions>; leaves were trimmed in rebinding, frequently causing the loss of text in the margins</extent>
                           <foliation>foliated by Douce in brown ink; 1–74 + 75a + 75b + 76–180 + 180* + 181–187 + 187* + 188–250</foliation>
                           <collation><locus from="i" to="ii">(fols. i–ii)</locus> fol. i is a paper flyleaf conjoint with the upper pastedown; fol. ii is a paper flyleaf | <locus from="1" to="32">(fols. 1–32)</locus> I–IV (8) | <locus from="33" to="39">(fols. 33–39)</locus> V (8–1) missing 1 | <locus from="40" to="150">(fols. 40–150)</locus> VI–XVIII (8) | <locus from="151" to="157">(fols. 151–157)</locus> XIX (8–1) missing 1 | <locus from="158" to="243">(fols. 158–243)</locus> XX–XXIX (8) | <locus from="244" to="250">(fols. 244–250)</locus> XXX (8–1) missing 8. <catchwords>Catchwords survive;</catchwords>
                              <signatures>quire signatures occasionally survive (more than one set).</signatures>
                              <secFol><q>puple shal</q>
                                 <locus from="2r" to="2r">(fol. 2r)</locus></secFol>
                           </collation>
                        </supportDesc>
                        <layoutDesc>
                           <layout columns="2" writtenLines="47 56">ruled in plummet for two columns with single vertical and horizontal bounding lines extending the full height and width of page; 47–56 lines per page; written space: variable, <foreign rend="italic">c.</foreign><dimensions type="ruled" unit="mm">
                                 <height>245–280</height>
                                 <width>150–160</width>
                              </dimensions>. Occasionally the ruling is visible above the horizontal bounding lines at the top of the page (e.g., fols. 63r–65r)</layout>
                        </layoutDesc>
                     </objectDesc>
                     <handDesc>
                        <handNote script="textualisNorthern">textura. According to Forshall, J. and Madden, F. (eds), <title>The Holy Bible … in the earliest English versions made from the Latin Vulgate by John Wycliffe and his followers</title>, 4 vols (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1850), the work of three scribes, first scribe: Numbers 20:2–Judith 6, fols. 1r–131v; second scribe: Judith 7–Esther 2:4, fols. 132r–134v; third scribe: Esther 2:5–Baruch 3:30, fols. 134v–250r. Possibly two scribes: 1r–134v and 134v–250r. Forshall and Madden believed that the last hand was identical to the last hand of MS. Bodl. 959 (1850, vol. 1, p. l), but this was questioned by Fristedt, S. L., <title>The Wycliffe Bible</title>, 3 vols (Stockholm: Almquvist &amp; Wiksells, 1953–73), vol. 1, p. 88, R. W. Hunt (cited by Fristedt), and de Hamel, C., <title>The book: a history of the Bible</title> (London: Phaidon, 2001), p. 172. de Hamel pointed out that only the added note naming Hereford is likely to be by the last scribe of MS. Bodl. 959</handNote>
                     </handDesc>
                     <decoDesc>
                        <decoNote type="flourInit">Roughly executed initials alternating deep blue with red penwork and lighter blue with red penwork. Occasionally decorated with human faces. The initials are larger at the beginnings of books (4 lines or higher) and smaller at the beginnings of chapters (most 3 lines high). The initials at the beginnings of prologues vary in size, some are similar to chapter, other to book initials. Unusual style; according to de Hamel, C., <title>The book: a history of the Bible</title> (London: Phaidon, 2001) the work of an Italian artist.</decoNote>
                        <decoNote type="rubrication">Rubrics in red ink; instructions to rubricator survive (e.g., fols. 22v, 113r, etc.).</decoNote>
                     </decoDesc>
                  </physDesc>
                  <history>
                     <origin>
                        <origPlace>
                           <country key="place_7002445">England</country>
                        </origPlace>
                        <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="1399" notBefore="1390">1390s (?)</origDate>
                        <p>Dialect survey: <list>
                              <item><locus from="1" to="131v">(fols. 1–131v)</locus>
                                 <list>
                                    <item>any(10), eche(9)/ech(1), fijr(8)/fyir(2), ȝiue(6)/ȝiuen(1)/ȝoue(1)/ȝouen(1)/ ȝeuen(1), lif(10), lic(10), myche(10), saȝ(7) (sg.), seȝen(5) (pl.), self(9)/silf(1), such(9)/suche(1), þurȝ(8)</item>
                                    <item>-iþ(2)/-eþ(8) (pres.ind.3sg.), -en(8)/-e(2) (pres.ind.pl.), -ende(8)/-onde(1)/ande(1) (pres.part.), she(10) (3sg.fem.pronoun, nom.), þei(9)/þey(1) (3pl. pronoun, nom.), þem(6)hem(4) (3pl.pronoun, oblique), þer(10) (3pl. pronoun, possessive)</item>
                                    <item>Also: birieþ/biried (‘buried’), ha (‘have’)’, sloȝ (‘slew’)</item>
                                 </list>
                              </item>
                              <item><locus>(fols. 132r–134v, Judith 7–Esther 2:4)</locus>
                                 <list>
                                    <item>any(1), fijr(1), ȝiuen(1)/ȝiue(6), lif(10), myche(8)/miche(1), self(10), such(2)/ suche(1), þurȝ(2)</item>
                                    <item>-eþ(6) (pres.ind.3sg.), -en(5) (pres.ind.pl.), -ende(10) (pres.part.), she(10) (3sg.fem.pronoun, nom.), þei(10) (3pl.pronoun, nom.), þem(2)hem(8) (3pl. pronoun, oblique), þer(5) (3pl.pronoun, possessive)</item>
                                 </list>
                              </item>
                              <item><locus from="135r" to="250r">(fols. 135r–250r)</locus>
                                 <list>
                                    <item>any(10), eche(10), fyr(10), ȝiue(3)/ȝiuen(2), lif(10), lic(10), myche(10), saȝ(3) (sg.), seȝen(8) (pl.), self(9)/silf(1), such(9)/suche(1), þoȝ(1), þurȝ(10)</item>
                                    <item>-ith(1)/-eþ(9) (pres.ind.3sg.), -en(9)/-e(1) (pres.ind.pl.), -ende(10) (pres.part.), she(10) (3sg.fem.pronoun, nom.), þei(10) (3pl.pronoun, nom.), þem(4) hem(6) (3pl.pronoun, oblique), þer(10) (3pl.pronoun, possessive) Also: knewȝ/kneȝ (‘knew’)</item>
                                 </list>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </p>
                     </origin>
                     <provenance><q>Expliciᵗ translacōm Nicholay de herford</q>, added in a contemporary hand, fol. 250r. This hand may have been responsible for other additions in part I, such as the chapter numbers and corrections to the English text, e.g., those on fols. 249v–250r (de Hamel, C., <title>The book: a history of the Bible</title> (London: Phaidon, 2001), p. 172). It may also be identical to the last hand in MS. Bodl. 959 (de Hamel, C., <title>The book: a history of the Bible</title> (London: Phaidon, 2001), p. 172). The text in MS. Bodl. 959 may have been checked against MS. Douce 369, or a version similar to it, and corrected to bring it in conformance with this version. A break at the same point in the text occurs in MS. Bodl. 959 and Cambridge University Library MS. Ee. 1. 10.</provenance>
                  </history>
               </msPart>
               <msPart xml:id="MS_Douce_369-part2">
                  <msIdentifier>
                     <altIdentifier type="partial">
                        <idno type="part">MS. Douce 369, fols. 251r–485v</idno>
                     </altIdentifier>
                  </msIdentifier>
                  <msContents>
                     <textLang mainLang="enm" otherLangs="la">Middle English with Latin</textLang>
                     <msItem>
                        <title key="work_10461" type="desc">Isaiah–Acts 28:15 in the Earlier Version of the Wycliffite Bible</title>
                        <note>Missing Ezekiel 1:27–22:22 because of the loss of leaves. The books are numbered in the same way as in the first part, in the same contemporary hand, as shown in brackets after each title (see Provenance).</note>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="251r">(fol. 251r)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Prologue to Isaiah</title>
                           <rubric>Prologue to Isaye þe prophete þe firste chapl’ of Isaye</rubric>
                           <incipit>No man when</incipit>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="251r">(fol. 251r)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Isaiah (28)</title>
                           <rubric>Here endiþ þe prolog and bigynneþ þe book of Isaye</rubric>
                           <rubric><note>(in chapter 38)</note> þe scripture of ezechie kyng of Iuda whane he hadde be syk &amp; hadde keuerid his syknesse</rubric>
                           <note>Preceding <q>I seide in þe midel of my days…</q>
                              <locus from="263r" to="263r">(fol. 263r)</locus>.</note>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="273r">(fol. 273r)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Prologue to Jeremiah</title>
                           <rubric>Her endiþ þe book of Isaye &amp; bigynneþ þe prolog to Ieremie</rubric>
                           <incipit>Jeremy þe profete</incipit>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="273r">(fol. 273r)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Prologue to Jeremiah</title>
                           <rubric>anoþer prolog</rubric>
                           <incipit>God is redy</incipit>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="273v">(fol. 273v)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Jeremiah (29)</title>
                           <rubric>Here endiþ þe prolog &amp; bigynneþ þe book</rubric>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="300v">(fol. 300v)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Lamentations of Jeremiah (30)</title>
                           <rubric>heer begynneþ þe lamentacioun of Ieremye þat is in title cenoth wiþ þe soilinge out of Ebrew lettris of reed</rubric>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="302v">(fol. 302v)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Prayer of Jeremiah</title>
                           <rubric>here begynneþ þe orisoun of Ieremye þe profete</rubric>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="303r">(fol. 303r)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Prologue to Baruch</title>
                           <rubric>Prologe in baruch</rubric>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="303r">(fol. 303r)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Baruch (31)</title>
                           <rubric>Here endiþ þe prolog &amp; bigynneþ þe book of Baruch</rubric>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="305r">(fol. 305r)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Epistle of Jeremiah</title>
                           <rubric>heer begynneþ ensaumple of þe same pistle whiche Ieremye sente to þe caitifs led aweie in to babiloyne of þe kyng of men of <sic>men</sic> of babiloyne: þat he shulde shewe to hem after þat it is comaundid to him of god</rubric>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="306v">(fol. 306v)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Ezekiel (32)</title>
                           <rubric>Here bigynneþ þe book of Ezechiel þe prophete</rubric>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="316v">(fol. 316v)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Daniel (33)</title>
                           <rubric>Here endiþ þe book of Ezechiel and bigynneþ þe book of Daniel</rubric>
                           <note>In chapter 3 <q>And þei walkiden in mydil…</q> (3:24) is preceded by a rubric <q>þe se þingis þat suen I foond not in Ebrew tunge <note>[<q>tunge</q> underdotted and crossed out]</note> bookis</q> in red, in the hand of the rubricator <locus from="118r" to="118r">(fol. 118r)</locus>.</note>
                           <note>On fol. 319r a rubric underlined in red with a blue paraph, preceding <q>þanne kyng nabugodonosor…</q> (3:91): <q>Hiderto is not h<ex>a</ex>d in ebrue &amp; what þinges we han putte ben translatid of þe makyng of teodosion</q>.</note>
                           <note>On fol. 325r a rubric underlined in red: <q>Hidre to we reeden danyel in ebru oþer þingis that suen til in to þe eende of þe boke: ben translatid of þe making of theodosyon</q>, preceding <q>A man was in babiloyne…</q> (13:1).</note>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="326v">(fol. 326v)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Hosea (34)</title>
                           <rubric>Here endiþ þe book of Danyel þe prophete and bigynneþ þe book of Osee þe prophete þe firste chaptl</rubric>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="330r">(fol. 330r)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Joel (35)</title>
                           <rubric>Here endiþ þe book of Osee: and bigynneþ þe book of Joel prophete</rubric>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="331r">(fol. 331r)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Amos (36?)</title>
                           <rubric>Here endiþ þe book of Joel and bigyn þe book of Amos prophete</rubric>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="334r">(fol. 334r)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Obidiah (37)</title>
                           <rubric>Here endiþ þe book of Amos prophete: &amp; bigynneþ þe book of Abdias prophete</rubric>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="334v">(fol. 334v)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Jonah (38?)</title>
                           <rubric>Here endiþ þe book of abdias prophete: &amp; bigynneþ þe book of Ionah þe prophete</rubric>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="335r">(fol. 335r)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Micah (39)</title>
                           <rubric>Here endiþ þe book Ionas: &amp; bigynneþ þe book of Micheas</rubric>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="335r">(fol. 335r)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Nahum (40?)</title>
                           <rubric>Ende of þe book of Micheas: &amp; bigynneþ þe book of Naum prophete</rubric>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="338r">(fol. 338r)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Habakkuk (41?)</title>
                           <rubric>Here endiþ <sic>þe</sic> of Naum prophete: and bigynneþ þe book of Abacuk prophete</rubric>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="339r">(fol. 339r)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Zephaniah (42?)</title>
                           <rubric>Here endiþ þe book of Abacuk þe prophete &amp; bigynneþ þe book of Sophonye prophete</rubric>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="340r">(fol. 340r)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Haggai (43?)</title>
                           <rubric>Here endiþ þe book of Sophonye prophete and bigynneþ þe book of Aggey þe prophete</rubric>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="341r">(fol. 341r)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Zechariah (44?)</title>
                           <rubric>Here endiþ þe book of Aggey þe prophete and bigynneþ þe book of Zacharie sone of Barachias</rubric>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="345r">(fol. 345r)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Malachi (45?)</title>
                           <rubric>Here endiþ þe book of Zacharias þe prophete and bigynneþ þe book of Malachie prophete</rubric>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="346r">(fol. 346r)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">1 Maccabees (46)</title>
                           <rubric>Here endiþ þe book of Malachie &amp; bigynneþ þe firste book of Machabeorum</rubric>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="361v">(fol. 361v)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">2 Maccabees (47?)</title>
                           <rubric>Here endiþ þe book of þe firste Iudas machabeus &amp; bigynneþ þe book of secunde Iudas Machabeus</rubric>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="372v">(fol. 372v)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Prologue to Matthew</title>
                           <rubric>Here endiþ þe storie of machabeus þe which is þe laste book of þe olde testament And now bigynneþ þe newe testament ffirst is þe prologu of Matheu apostle &amp; euangelist</rubric>
                           <incipit>Mathew of Iewerye</incipit>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="372v">(fol. 372v)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Matthew (48)</title>
                           <rubric>Here endiþ þe prolog &amp; begynnᵗ þe gospel</rubric>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="389r">(fol. 389r)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Prologue to Mark</title>
                           <rubric>Here endiþ þe gospel of Mᵗ &amp; bigynneþ þe prolog of mark</rubric>
                           <incipit>Mark þe euangelist</incipit>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="389r">(fol. 389r)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Mark (49)</title>
                           <rubric>Here endiþ þe prolog &amp; bigynneþ þe gospel</rubric>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="399v">(fol. 399v)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Prologue to Luke</title>
                           <rubric>Here endiþ þe gospel of mark &amp; bigynneþ þe prolog of luk</rubric>
                           <incipit>Lvcas of antyoche</incipit>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="400v">(fol. 400v)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Luke (50)</title>
                           <rubric>Here endiþ þe prolog and bigynneþ þe gospel</rubric>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="418r">(fol. 418r)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Prologue to John</title>
                           <rubric>Here endiþ þe gospel of luk &amp; bigynneþ þe prolog of Iohn</rubric>
                           <incipit>This is John</incipit>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="418r">(fol. 418r)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">John (51)</title>
                           <rubric>Here endiþ þe prolog and bigynneþ þe gospel</rubric>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="429v">(fol. 429v)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Prologue to Romans</title>
                           <rubric>Here endiþ þe gospel of Iohn And now bigynneþ þe prolog of seint poul to romayns</rubric>
                           <incipit>Fvrst vindirstond</incipit>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="430r">(fol. 430r)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Romans (52)</title>
                           <rubric>Here endiþ þe prolog and bigynneþ epistle to romyns</rubric>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="437r">(fol. 437r)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Prologue to 1 Corinthinas</title>
                           <rubric>Here endiþ þe epistle to romayns and now bigynneþ þe prolog to þe firste epistle to corinthies</rubric>
                           <incipit>Corinthies ben</incipit>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="437r">(fol. 437r)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">1 Corinthinas (53)</title>
                           <rubric>Here endiþ þe prolog and bigynneþ þe epistele</rubric>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="444r">(fol. 444r)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Prologue to 2 Corinthians</title>
                           <rubric>Here endiþ þe firste pistle to corinthis &amp; now bigynneþ þe prolog to þe secunde</rubric>
                           <incipit>Aftir penaunce</incipit>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="444r">(fol. 444r)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">2 Corinthians (54)</title>
                           <rubric>Ende of þe prolog bigynnynge þe secunde pistle</rubric>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="448v">(fol. 448v)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Prologue to Galatians</title>
                           <rubric>Here endiþ þe secunde pistle to corinthis and now bigynneþ þe prolog to galathies</rubric>
                           <incipit>Galathies ben greekis</incipit>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="448v">(fol. 448v)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Galatians (55)</title>
                           <rubric>Here endiþ þe prolog &amp; bigynneþ þe <sic>epitstle</sic></rubric>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="451r">(fol. 451r)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Prologue to Ephesians</title>
                           <rubric>Here endiþ þe epistle to Galathies &amp; now bigynneþ þe prolog to Ephesyes</rubric>
                           <incipit>Ephecyes soþli ben</incipit>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="451r">(fol. 451r)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Ephesians (56?)</title>
                           <rubric>Ende of prolog bigynnyng capitulum primum</rubric>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="453r">(fol. 453r)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Prologue to Philippians</title>
                           <rubric>Here endiþ þe epistle to Ephecies &amp; bigynneþ þe prolog to Philipencis</rubric>
                           <incipit>Philipencis ben</incipit>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="453v">(fol. 453v)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Philippians (57?)</title>
                           <rubric>Ende of prolog bigynnyng þe epitstle þe firste chaptl</rubric>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="455r">(fol. 455r)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Prologue to Colossians</title>
                           <rubric>Here endiþ þe epistle to philipensis &amp; bigynneþ prolog to Colocenses</rubric>
                           <incipit>To colocensis also</incipit>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="455r">(fol. 455r)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Colossians (58?)</title>
                           <rubric>Ende of þe prolog bigynnynge þe epistle</rubric>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="456v">(fol. 456v)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Prologue to 1 Thessalonians</title>
                           <rubric>Here endiþ þe epistle to Colocensis &amp; bigynneþ þe prolog to tessalonycensis</rubric>
                           <incipit>Tessalonycensis ben men</incipit>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="456v">(fol. 456v)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">1 Thessalonians (59?)</title>
                           <rubric>Ende of prolog bigynnyng þe firste pistle</rubric>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="458r">(fol. 458r)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Prologue to 2 Thessalonians</title>
                           <rubric>Here endiþ þe firste pestle to tessalonycensis and bigynneþ þe prolog to þe secunde pistle</rubric>
                           <incipit>To tessalonycensis</incipit>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="458r">(fol. 458r)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">2 Thessalonians (60?)</title>
                           <rubric>Here endiþ þe prolog &amp; bigynneþ þe secunde pistle to tessalonycensis</rubric>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="458v">(fol. 458v)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Prologue to 1 Timothy</title>
                           <rubric>Here endiþ þe secunde pistle to tessalonycensis &amp; bigynneþ þe prolog to þe firste pistle to tymothe</rubric>
                           <incipit>Tymothe þe apostle</incipit>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="459r">(fol. 459r)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">1 Timothy (61)</title>
                           <rubric>Here endiþ þe prolog &amp; bigynneþ þe firste pistle</rubric>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="460v">(fol. 460v)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Prologue to 2 Timothy</title>
                           <rubric>Here endiþ þe firste pistle to Tymothe &amp; bigynneþ þe prolog to secunde pistle</rubric>
                           <incipit>Also he wrytiþ</incipit>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="460v">(fol. 460v)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">2 Timothy (62?)</title>
                           <rubric>Here endiþ þe prolog &amp; bigynneþ þe pistle</rubric>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="462r">(fol. 462r)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Prologue to Titus</title>
                           <rubric>Here endiþ þe secunde pistle to Tymothe &amp; bigynneþ þe prolog to Tyte</rubric>
                           <incipit>Tyte he counceiliþ</incipit>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="462r">(fol. 462r)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Titus (63?)</title>
                           <rubric>Here endiþ þe prolog &amp; bigynneþ þe epistle to Tyte</rubric>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="462v">(fol. 462v)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Prologue to Philemon</title>
                           <rubric>Here endiþ þe epistle to Tyte &amp; bygynneþ þe prolog to ffilomon</rubric>
                           <incipit>To ffilomon he makiþ</incipit>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="463r">(fol. 463r)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Philemon (64)</title>
                           <rubric>Here endiþ þe prolog and bigynneþ þe epistle to filomon</rubric>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="463r">(fol. 463r)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Prologue to Hebrews</title>
                           <rubric>Here endiþ þe epistle to ffilomon &amp; bigynneþ þe prolog to þe pistle to Ebrews</rubric>
                           <incipit>In þe firste</incipit>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="463r">(fol. 463r)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Hebrews (65)</title>
                           <rubric>Here endiþ þe prolog &amp; bigynneþ þe epistle</rubric>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="468v">(fol. 468v)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Prologue to Acts</title>
                           <rubric>Here enden þe epistlis of poul and now bigynneþ þe prolog to actus apostolorum</rubric>
                           <incipit>Lvk of sirye</incipit>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="468v">(fol. 468v)</locus>
                           <title type="desc">Acts (66)</title>
                           <rubric>Here endiþ þe prolog &amp; bigynneþ þe lessoun</rubric>
                        </msItem>
                        <note>Ends imperfectly at 28:15 (<q>…þre tauernes whom whanne</q>). Fols. 486–488 are paper flyleaves, containing notes by Douce, including a list of contents of the manuscript with folio numbers.</note>
                        <note>The text contains corrections, most over erasures, in contemporary hands. Chapter numbers and running titles with chapter numbers in red by the original rubricator. Lections outlined in red and/or marked in the margins with the opening and final letters of each passage, possibly by the original rubricator. Added material within the text is consistently underlined in red. English notes in the margins in the original hand referring to the subject matter of passages (e.g., fols. 433r, 434r, 435v, 436r, etc.). Occasionally glosses in the margins in a contemporary hand providing Latin versions of phrases <locus>(fols. 288r, 392r)</locus>; cross-references among biblical books (e.g., fols. 313r, 378r); and <q>nota</q>
                           <locus>(fols. 435v, 439r, etc.)</locus>. Pointing hands added in the margins, 16th century (?) (e.g., fols. 270r–v, 272r, etc.).</note>
                     </msItem>
                  </msContents>
                  <physDesc>
                     <objectDesc form="codex">
                        <supportDesc material="perg">
                           <support>parchment</support>
                           <extent>239 leaves, <foreign rend="italic">c.</foreign><dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                                 <height>365</height>
                                 <width>250</width>
                              </dimensions>; leaves were trimmed in rebinding, frequently causing the loss of text in the margins</extent>
                           <foliation>foliated by Douce in brown ink; 251–429 + 429* + 430–488</foliation>
                           <collation><locus from="251" to="298">(fols. 251–298)</locus> I–IV (12) | <locus from="299" to="306">(fols. 299–306)</locus> V (12–4) missing 9–12 | <locus from="307" to="307">(fol. 307)</locus> VI (12–11) missing 1–11 | <locus from="308" to="474">(fols. 308–474)</locus> VII–XX (12) | <locus from="475" to="485">(fols. 475–485)</locus> XXI (12–1) missing 12 | <locus from="386" to="388">(fols. 386–388)</locus> fols. 386–387 are paper flyleaves; fol. 388 is a paper flyleaf conjoint with the lower pastedown. <catchwords>Catchwords survive;</catchwords>
                              <signatures>quire signatures often survive: a–e before fol. 307, starting with g afterwards.</signatures>
                              <secFol><q>hei3t of stronge</q>
                                 <locus from="252r" to="252r">(fol. 252r)</locus></secFol>
                           </collation>
                        </supportDesc>
                        <layoutDesc>
                           <layout columns="2" writtenLines="48">ruled in ink for two columns with single horizontal and vertical bounding lines, extending the full height and width of page; 48 lines per page in the first scribe’s section and 45 in the second scribe’s section; written space: variable, <foreign rend="italic">c.</foreign><dimensions type="ruled" unit="mm">
                                 <height>250–255</height>
                                 <width>165–170</width>
                              </dimensions>; prickings occasionally visible (e.g., fol. 274)</layout>
                        </layoutDesc>
                     </objectDesc>
                     <handDesc>
                        <handNote script="textualisNorthern">textura; the work of two scribes, first scribe: Isaiah–Mark 5:30 <locus from="251r" to="391v">(fols. 251r–391v)</locus>; second scribe: the rest, fols. 392r–485v (quires XIV–XXI) and possibly most of the text on fols. 385v, 389r and corrections elsewhere in the stint of the first scribe; black and brown ink</handNote>
                     </handDesc>
                     <decoDesc>
                        <decoNote type="flourInit">3- to 6-line red and blue initials with red, blue and purple penwork and penwork borders at the beginnings of books; 2- to 4-line blue initials with red penwork at the beginnings of chapters and prologues. Some initials are decorated with human and animal masks, and other zoomorphic and anthropomorphic designs (e.g., fols. 372v, 385r, 444r, 451r, 453v, 456v, 459v). Simple red line-fillers at the end of texts. Drawings of human faces in the lower margin (e.g., fols. 278v, 280v) and catchwords decorated with grotesques in the section written by the first scribe.</decoNote>
                     </decoDesc>
                  </physDesc>
                  <history>
                     <origin>
                        <origPlace>
                           <country key="place_7002445">England</country>
                        </origPlace>
                        <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="1400" notBefore="1375">14th century, last quarter (?)</origDate>
                        <p>Dialect survey: <list>
                              <item><locus from="251r" to="391v">(fols. 251r–391v)</locus><list>
                                    <item>any(1)/eny(9), eche(8)/ech(2), fijr(9)/fire(1), ȝouen(10), lijf(4)/lif(2)/lyf(4), liche(3)/lic(4)/like(2)/liik(1), myche(6)/moche(4), seiȝ(1)/seeȝ(2)/say(3) (sg.), sayen(2)/syȝen(1)/seien(2) (pl.), self(9)/silf(1), siche(4), þorwȝ(1)</item>
                                    <item>-iþ(7)/-eþ(3) (pres.ind.3sg.), -en(9)/-e(1) (pres.ind.pl.), -ande(1)/-yng(1)/inge(2)/-ynge(6) (pres.part.), she(10) (3sg.fem.pronoun, nom.), þei(10) (3pl. pronoun, nom.), hem(10) (3pl.pronoun, oblique), her(10) (3pl.pronoun, possessive) Also: slowȝ (‘slow’)</item>
                                 </list>
                              </item>
                              <item><locus from="392r" to="485v">(fols. 392r–485v)</locus>
                                 <list>
                                    <item>ony(10), ech(10), fier(2)/fyer(7), ȝouun(9)/ȝouen(1), lyf(10), lychi(1)/liche(1)/ lich(1)/lyk(4), moche(10), syȝ(3) (sg.), seye(1) (pl.), silf(10), such(3)/suche(3)/ sich(2)/siche(2), þouȝ(5), þorw(5)/þorwȝ(1)</item>
                                    <item>-iþ(9)/-eþ(1) (pres.ind.3sg.), -en(10) (pres.ind.pl.), -ynge(7)/-inge(3) (pres. part.), she(6)/sche(4) (3sg.fem.pronoun, nom.), þei(10) (3pl.pronoun, nom.), hem(10) (3pl.pronoun, oblique), her(10) (3pl.pronoun, possessive)</item>
                                    <item>Also: slowȝ/slouȝ (‘slew’)</item>
                                 </list>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </p>
                     </origin>
                  </history>
               </msPart>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2023-03-24">Add Solopova description.</change>
         <change when="2022-04-04">Add binding information from Summary Catalogue.</change>
         <change when="2018-10-14" xml:id="MMM">
            <persName>Mitch Fraas</persName> Provenance and acquisition information added using <ref target="https://github.com/littlegustv/oxfordupdates/blob/master/test_case_for_oxford_prov.rb">https://github.com/littlegustv/oxfordupdates/blob/master/test_case_for_oxford_prov.rb</ref> in collaboration with the <ref target="http://mappingmanuscriptmigrations.org/">Mapping Manuscript Migrations</ref> project.</change>
         <change when="2017-07-01">First online publication.</change>
         <change when="2017-05-25">
            <persName>James Cummings</persName> Up-converted the markup using <ref target="https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl">https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl</ref>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>