<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="manuscript_4495">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>MS. Douce 118</title>
            <title type="collection">MSS. Douce</title>
            <respStmt xml:id="ES">
               <resp when="2013">Cataloguer</resp>
               <persName>Elizabeth Solopova</persName>
            </respStmt>
            
            <respStmt xml:id="MH">
               <resp when="2024">Encoding</resp>
               <persName>Matthew Holford</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </publisher>
            <idno type="msID">MS_Douce_118</idno>
            <idno type="collection">Douce</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="MS_Douce_118" xml:lang="en">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <region type="county">Oxfordshire</region>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <institution>University of Oxford</institution>
                  <repository>Bodleian Library</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">MS. Douce 118</idno>
                  <idno type="ieArk">ark:29072/x09w032338pn</idno>
                  <idno type="crArk">ark:29072/x0s4655g24t3</idno>
                  <altIdentifier type="internal">
                     <idno type="SCN">21692</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
               <head>Psalter ('The Aspremont Psalter'), Companion Volume to a Book of Hours; France, Lorraine (?), late 13th or early 14th century</head>
               <msContents>
                  <msItem class="#liturgica #biblia" n="1" xml:id="MS_Douce_118-item1">
                     <title key="work_14114" type="desc">Psalter</title>
                     <note>('The Aspremont Psalter')</note>
                    
                     <note> Fols. i–ii are parchment fly-leaves, blank apart from early modern and
                        modern notes (see ‘Provenance’). A modern paper leaf is pasted to fol. i
                        recto, containing notes by Eric Millar, 1926, on the provenance of the
                        manuscript.</note>
                     <note> [item 1 occupies quire I]</note>
                     <msItem n="1">
                        <locus from="1r" to="6v">(fols. 1r–6v)</locus>
                        <note> Calendar, laid out one month per page, with feasts in black and
                           rubrics in pink and red, approximately one-third full, not graded, vigils
                           included for June– December. The calendar contains saints venerated in
                           north-eastern France, particularly in the dioceses of Metz, Toul and
                           Verdun, including Serena, relics at Metz (29 January), Arnold, bishop of
                           Metz (17 April), Gangulf, relics at Langres (11 May), Arnulf, bishop of
                           Metz (16 August), Aper, bishop of Toul (15 September) and Agericus,
                           bishop of Verdun (1 December). The presence of Lambert (17 September) and
                           Hubert (3 November) suggests a link with Liège (cf. Manion and Vines,
                           1984, p. 174). Months are headed with notes on the length of the solar
                           and lunar month. </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <note> [items 2–5 occupy quires II–XXIV]</note>
                     <msItem n="2">
                        <locus from="7r" to="163r">(fols. 7r–163r)</locus>
                        <note> Psalms 1–150, written with each verse starting on a new line, without
                           numbers, with titles ‘psalmus dauid’. Punctuated throughout with punctus
                           used to mark the ends of verses, punctus or punctus elevatus used to mark
                           metrum and minor pauses. The psalms are in the biblical order,
                           subdivisions within psalms are not indicated, apart from psalm 118,
                           subdivided into twenty-two 8-verse units. There are liturgical divisions
                           at psalms 26, 38, 52, 68, 80, 97 and 109 (see ‘Decoration’). Psalm 109
                           starts on a new quire; a bifolium is inserted immediately before, to
                           finish psalm 108. The text contains many corrections in contemporary
                           hands, probably executed in the original scriptorium, such as the
                           readings entered over erasures in a light brown ink, or a verse omitted
                           by the original scribe, and inserted in the margins on fols. 50r, 55r,
                           60v, 170r, etc. </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="3">
                        <locus from="163r" to="172r">(fols. 163r–172r)</locus>
                        <note> Weekly canticles, the first three with the title ‘canticum’: <list>
                              <item>(1) Confitebor tibi domine (Isaiah 12);</item>
                              <item>(2) Ego dixi (Isaiah 38: 10–21);</item>
                              <item>(3) Exultauit cor meum (1 Samuel 2: 1–11);</item>
                              <item>(4) Cantemus domino (Exodus 15: 1–20);</item>
                              <item>(5) Domine audiui (Habakkuk 3) (‘Canticum abacuc
                                 prophete’);</item>
                              <item>(6) Audite celi (Deuteronomy 32: 1–44) (‘Canticum
                                 deuteronomij’).</item>
                           </list>
                        </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="4">
                        <locus from="172r" to="178r">(fols. 172r–178r)</locus>
                        <note> Daily canticles, prayers and creeds, with titles: <list>
                              <item>(1) Benedicite omnia opera (fol. 172r) (‘Canticum
                                 puerorum’);</item>
                              <item>(2) Benedictus dominus deus (fol. 173r) (‘canticum’);</item>
                              <item>(3) Magnificat (fol. 174r) (‘Canticum’);</item>
                              <item>(4) Nunc dimittis (fol. 174r) (‘Canticum symeonis’);</item>
                              <item>(5) Te deum laudamus (fol. 174v) (‘Laus angelorum’);</item>
                              <item>(6) Athanasian Creed (Quicumque uult... .) (fol. 176r) (‘Fides
                                 catholica’).</item>
                           </list>
                        </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="5">
                        <locus from="178v" to="180r">(fols. 178v–180r)</locus>
                        <note> Litany, containing saints venerated in France, including Martin
                           (first), Germanus of Auxerre, Medard, bishop of Noyon and Tournai, Amand,
                           bishop of Maastricht, and Remigius, bishop of Reims among the confessors,
                           and Gertrude (of Nivelles (?)) among the virgins. Two leaves missing
                           after fol. 179. Followed by collects with a rubric ‘collecta’ (fol.
                           180r): <list>
                              <item>(1) Omnipotens sempiterne deus dirige actus nostros in
                                 beneplacito tuo... .</item>
                              <item> (2) Fidelium deus omnium conditor et redemptor animabus
                                 famulorum famularumque tuarum remissionem... .</item>
                           </list> Fols. 180v–181r are blank. </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <note> [item 6 occupies quire XXV]</note>
                     <msItem n="6">
                        <locus from="181v" to="182r">(fols. 181v–182r)</locus>
                        <note> Three added prayers in honour of Giles in a 15th- or 16th-century
                           hand, with a long title in French, beginning ‘Saint gile commanda Charles
                           le Roy de fraunce ... ’. Invocation (?) in the same hand in the lower
                           margin on fol. 182r: ‘h. h. Ga. te. de. p’ (?). Fol. 182v is blank.
                        </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <p><secFol> Tunc loquetur <locus>(psalter, fol. 8r)</locus></secFol></p>
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="perg">
                        <support> parchment; added paper leaves at the front and back</support>
                        <extent><measure type="leaf" quantity="276">276</measure> leaves <dimensions unit="mm" type="leaf">
                              <height quantity="227">c. 227</height>
                              <width>152</width>
                           </dimensions><note>Leaves were trimmed in rebinding, occasionally causing
                              the loss of text and decoration.</note></extent>
                        <foliation>Modern, in pencil; i–ii + 1–184.</foliation>
                        <collation> (fols. i–ii) parchment bifolium with a modern paper leaf pasted
                           to the recto of fol. i | (fols. 1–6) I (6) | (fols. 7–30) II–IV (8) |
                           (fols. 31–36) V (6) no loss of text | (fols. 37–124) VI–XVI (8) | (fols.
                           125–126) XVII (2) | (fols. 127–174) XVIII–XXIII (8) | (fols. 175–180)
                           XXIV (8−2) missing 6 and 7 (two stubs after fol. 179) | (fols. 181–182)
                           XXV (4−1) missing 3 (first leaf conjoint with the pastedown) | (fols.
                           183–184) laid 18th-century paper bifolium with notes by Douce.
                           Catchwords, some decorated with penwork grotesques, many partly cropped
                           off, survive; leaf signatures occasionally survive (e.g. fols. 15–18,
                           117–120)</collation>
                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout writtenLines="18" columns="1" rulingMedium="leadpoint"
                           topLine="below">Ruled in plummet with double vertical and single
                           horizontal bounding lines, extending the full height of page; a second
                           set of double vertical and horizontal bounding lines in the margins; 18
                           lines per page; written below the top line; written space: <dimensions
                              type="written" unit="mm">
                              <height quantity="135">c. 135</height>
                              <width>91</width>
                           </dimensions></layout>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc>
                     <handNote script="textualisNorthern" execution="formata">Formal Gothic book
                        hands, often with calligraphic descenders on the bottom line of the page,
                        black and brown ink.</handNote>
                  </handDesc>

                  <decoDesc>

                     <decoNote>The style of illumination is related to manuscripts produced in
                        Lorraine in the late 13th and early 14th century, such as the book of hours
                        (Baltimore, Walters Art Museum MS. W. 93); the two-volume breviary of Renaud
                        de Bar, provost of St Madeleine in Verdun in 1301 (London, British Library,
                        Yates-Thompson MS. 8 and Verdun, Bibliothèque municipale MS. 107), and his
                        pontifical, dating to the time when he was bishop of Metz (1301–1316)
                        (Cambridge, Fitzwilliam Museum MS. 298) (see Oliver, 1988, vol. 1, p. 181;
                        Randall et al., 1989). Signed by an illuminator on fol. 142r: a bird holding
                        in its beak a small bearded figure, a cripple (?), holding a scroll with
                        lettering ‘<persName key="person_908" role="art">nicolaus</persName> me
                        fecit qui illuminat librum’. </decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="monogram">Calendar: Blue and pink KL monograms on gold
                        backgrounds with white tracery, and borders of gold, blue and pink bars,
                        decorated with coiled tendrils, foliage and gold discs.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="miniature">Labours of the Months and the Signs of the Zodiac,
                        set in cusped medallions with gold borders or backgrounds on the right side
                        of each page: January: Janus feasting; Aquarius February: man warming by the
                        fire; Pisces March: man pruning trees; Aries April: man carrying flowering
                        branches; Taurus May: man on horseback with a hawk and a flower; Gemini
                        (naked twins behind a shield) June: man mowing hay with a scythe; Cancer
                        July: man reaping grain; Leo August: man threshing grain; Virgo (a woman
                        with a flower and a staff with fleur-de-lis) September: man treading and
                        eating grapes, and another carrying grapes in a basket; Libra (a woman with
                        scales) October: man sowing; Scorpio November: man knocking down acorns for
                        pigs; Sagittarius December: man slaughtering a pig; Capricorn.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="histInit">Historiated initials and borders at liturgical
                        divisions, accompanied, apart from psalm 26 (fol. 31v), by decorative panels
                        with the opening words of each psalm in gold. On all panels, apart from
                        psalm 1, the text alternates with the arms of the patrons. Most initials are
                        over half a page tall, decorated with foliage, on blue, pink and gold
                        backgrounds. The pages with the initials have full borders of pink, blue and
                        gold bars, decorated with coiled tendrils, foliage, human and animal figures
                        and inset panels with religious and secular scenes. There are also smaller,
                        3-line historiated initials at the beginnings of the canticles and litany. <list>
                           <item>fol. 7r Psalm 1 (initial B(eatus)) King David playing harp in the
                              upper part, David and Goliath in the lower part.</item>
                           <item>(full border) Panels containing the Virgin and Child, Crucifixion,
                              St Margaret emerging from a dragon, mounted Joffroy and kneeling
                              Isabelle wearing their respective arms (see ‘Provenance’); dog chasing
                              a hare; grotesque.</item>
                           <item>fol. 31v Psalm 26 (initial D(ominus)) King David pointing to his
                              eyes, kneeling before an image of the Virgin on an altar.</item>
                           <item>(full border) Ape with a shield and stick confronting a stork; hare
                              blowing a trumpet; man with a sword and shield; bird; ape;
                              hare.</item>
                           <item>fol. 47v Psalm 38 (initial D(ixi)) The Anointing of David; God
                              above.</item>
                           <item>(full border) Hounds chasing a stag; bird; squirrel.</item>
                           <item>fol. 60v Psalm 52 (initial D(ixit)) The Fool with a stick and
                              bread, nude apart from a cloak; the head of Christ with cruciform halo
                              in clouds above.</item>
                           <item>(full border) Jousting grotesques; apes blowing trumpets;
                              squirrel.</item>
                           <item>fol. 74r Psalm 68 (initial S(aluum)) King David praying in waters
                              in the lower part; half-figure of Christ with cruciform halo, holding
                              a book and blessing in the upper part.</item>
                           <item>(full border) Hounds chasing a stag; hare.</item>
                           <item>fol. 92r Psalm 80 (initial E(xultate)) King David playing five
                              bells.</item>
                           <item>(full border) Two men jousting; bird; lion; hare.</item>
                           <item>fol. 108r Psalm 97 (initial C(antate)) Five clerics singing from a
                              book open on a lectern.</item>
                           <item>(full border) Hunter blowing horn and a dog chasing a stag;
                              owl.</item>
                           <item> fol. 127r Psalm 109 (initial D(ixit)) Trinity: two seated figures
                              with cruciform halos, blessing, one holding a book, another an orb;
                              nimbed white dove descending from clouds above.</item>
                           <item>(full border) Panels with kneeling Joffroy wearing his arms, a
                              kneeling woman (Isabelle (?)) and St Margaret emerging from a dragon;
                              two jousting knights bearing the arms of Kievraing and Châtillon in
                              the bas-de-page; man blowing a trumpet; grotesque; lion.</item>
                           <item>fol. 163r Canticles (initial C(onfitebor)) 3-line initial infilled
                              with a prophet holding a scroll with the words ‘Dauid propheta’ on
                              gold background.</item>
                           <item>fol. 178v Litany (initial K(yrie)) Clerics singing from a book open
                              on a lectern.</item>
                           <item>2-line historiated initials at the beginnings of psalms and
                              canticles, decorated with heraldic insignia, figures of prophets with
                              scrolls and books, saints, men and women in prayer, grotesques, animal
                              figures and masks, coiled tendrils and foliage on gold
                              background.</item>
                           <item>1-line initials at the beginnings of verses and periods, decorated
                              with human heads, animal figures and masks, and floral designs on gold
                              background.</item>
                        </list></decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="border">Borders: see above. Every page has a full or
                        three-quarter border of blue, pink and gold bars, decorated with coiled
                        tendrils, leaves and gold discs, grotesques, animal and human
                        figures.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="decInit">Decorated initials.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="bas-de-page">Many pages contain scenes, usually in bas-de-page,
                        featuring the patrons in prayer, saints, knights, hunts and theatrical
                        performances. Several scenes illustrate subjects from the Bestiary, such as
                        a unicorn with its head in the lap of a virgin, killed by a hunter (fol.
                        32v), a fox pretending to be dead to attract the birds of prey (fols. 56v,
                        102v, 121r), a pelican feeding its young with its blood (fols. 66r, 142v)
                        and a beaver castrating itself to escape from hunters (fol. 107v). Other
                        subjects include: St Margaret emerging from a dragon (fol. 23r); St
                        Catherine (fols. 27v, 103v, 121r); the Fool with a club and bread (fol.
                        42v); a female saint with a book, a palm and the Lamb of God (fol. 63r); St
                        Stephen (fol. 66v); a figure with a scroll inscribed ‘zacharias propheta’
                        (fol. 173r); a man beating a dog to tame a chained lion (fols. 124r,
                        173v–174r); St Athanasias writing (fol. 176r); nimbed prophets (?) and a
                        king, each with a scroll inscribed ‘vere languores nostras ipse tulit’
                        (Isaiah 53: 4) (fols. 39r, 130v , 177v), ‘tv es devs christvs’ (fol. 90v),
                        etc.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="lineFill">Line-endings, decorated with floral designs, animal
                        figures and heads, grotesques and arms of the patrons.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="rubrication"> Rubrics in red ink</decoNote>
                  </decoDesc>
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <binding notAfter="1500" notBefore="1300">
                        <p> Blind stamped brown leather over boards, French, 14th or 15th century.
                           On the upper cover a central column of small stamps, c. 10 × 8 mm (‘a
                           pelican in her piety’); surrounded by a border of stamps, c. 13 × 13 mm
                           (an animal with long horns); surrounded by two further borders of stamps,
                           the first c. 20 × 20 mm (three flowers and four leaves), the second c. 9
                           × 16 mm (vine). The first three stamps are also used on the lower cover
                           together with another stamp, c. 12 × 38 mm (coiled tendrils, flowers and
                           leaves). Sewn on six stations. Rebacked, probably in the Bodleian. Gilt
                           lettering on spine ‘MS. || Douce. || 118’. Fragments of the fittings of
                           two straps on the upper cover and impressions left by the fittings of two
                           pins on the lower cover. Gilt edges of textblock. Parchment pastedowns.
                        </p>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="1310" notBefore="1290">c.
                        1290–1310</origDate>
                     <origPlace>
                        <country key="place_1000070">French</country>, <region>Lorraine</region> (?)
                        <!--ORIGINAL: French, Verdun-->
                     </origPlace>
                  </origin>
                  <provenance>A companion of the book of hours, Melbourne, National Gallery of
                     Victoria MS. Felton 173/1, produced by the same team of scribes and
                     illuminators and possibly originally bound together (described in Manion,
                     2005). Probably made for <persName role="pat" key="person_4865">Isabelle of Kievraing</persName>, wife of
                     <persName role="pat" key="person_4866">Joffroy d’Aspremont (d. 1302)</persName>: their arms, correspondingly, gules
                     a cross argent, and or a chief bendy of six argent and gules, appear throughout
                     (Manion, 2005, pp. 114–19). The companion volume in Melbourne uses feminine
                     grammatical forms. The arms of other noble families to which Isabelle and
                     Joffroy were related are occasionally depicted. Thus jousting knights in
                     bas-de-page of fol. 127r bear the arms of Kievraing and Châtillon
                     (Châtillon-Porcien, a branch of the Châtillon-Marne family in the Champagne;
                     see Morgan, 2003, pp. 8 and n. 29, 19, and Manion, 2005, pp. 114–15). Some arms
                     have not been identified (see Morgan, 2003, pp. 7–8; Manion, 2005, p. 115). The
                     borders and 2-line initials also contain images of a woman wearing Aspremont
                     arms, and of nuns in a grey-brown, Franciscan (?), habit and in a black,
                     Benedictine, habit. These images may represent the members of the patrons’
                     family. </provenance>
                  <provenance>A list in a 14th-century hand on the upper pastedown, containing the
                     opening words of psalms and canticles followed by (incorrect) running numbers.
                     The psalms at liturgical divisions in the psalter, but also some other psalms,
                     are marked with paragraph marks. An ownership (?) inscription is cut from the
                     lower pastedown. </provenance>
                  <provenance>Abbaye du Perray (<orgName role="fmo" key="org_350">Cistercian nunnery, Abbaye du Perray-aux-Nonnains,
                     diocese of Angers</orgName> (?)): erased 16th-century (?) ownership inscriptions of
                     ‘Madame l’abesse du Perray’ (fols. 69r and 182r). An erased inscription,
                     possibly in the same hand, on fol. i recto. 16th-century addition of prayers in
                     honour of St Giles (fols. 181v–182r). </provenance>
                  <provenance>The companion volume of the hours belonged in the 16th century to
                     Walter Cramer, physician of King Henry VIII (Manion and Vines, 1984, p. 176). </provenance>
                  <provenance>Thomas Payne (?) (1752–1831), London bookseller and publisher, see
                     ODNB: ‘Payne’ (?), written by Douce in pencil on the upper pastedown. Price
                     ‘10. 10. 0’ in pencil (fol. i recto). </provenance>
                  <provenance notAfter="1834" notBefore="1757" resp="#MMM">
                     <persName key="person_69848690" role="fmo">Francis Douce, 1757–1834</persName>,
                     see ODNB: bookplate on the upper pastedown; notes on fol. 183r. </provenance>
                  <acquisition resp="#MMM" when="1834">Bodleian Library: received in 1834 with
                     bequest of Douce.</acquisition>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>Summary description based on Elizabeth Solopova, <title>Latin
                              Liturgical Psalters in the Bodleian Library: A Select
                              Catalogue</title> (Oxford, 2013), pp. 297–305. Previously described in
                           the Summary Catalogue. <listBibl>
                              <bibl facs="aaz0546.gif" type="SC">Summary Catalogue, vol. 4, p.
                                 527</bibl>
                           </listBibl>
                        </source>
                     </recordHist>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <surrogates>
                     <bibl subtype="partial" type="digital-facsimile">
                        <ref
                           target="https://digital.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/objects/01979694-9663-472b-97d5-3ed575dd89b2/">
                           <title>Digital Bodleian</title>
                        </ref>
                        <note>(225 images from 35mm slides)</note>
                     </bibl>
                  </surrogates>
                  <listBibl type="WRAPPER">
                     <listBibl type="PRINT">
                        <head>Select bibliography to 2009:</head>

                        <bibl>Frere, no. 445.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Millar, E. G., ‘Livre d’heures executé pour Joffroy d’Aspremont
                              et pour sa femme Isabelle de Kievraing’, <title>Bulletin de la Société
                              française de reproductions de manuscrits à peintures</title> 9 (1925),
                           pp. 20–32.</bibl>
                        <bibl>S. J. P. van Dijk, <title>Latin Liturgical Manuscripts in the Bodleian
                           Library, Oxford, vol. 2: Office Books</title> (typescript, 1957),
                           <citedRange unit="page" from="77" to="77">p. 77</citedRange>
                        </bibl>
                        <bibl>Randall, L. M. C., <title>Images in the margins of Gothic
                              manuscripts</title> (Berkeley: University of California Press, 1966),
                           figs. 133, 222, 401, 551, 626, 705 and refs. in ‘Index of
                           Subjects’.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Pächt and Alexander (1966–73), vol. 1, no. 554, pl. XLII.</bibl>
                        <bibl><title>Heraldry: catalogue of an exhibition held in connection with the
                           English Heraldry Society 1967</title> (Oxford: Bodleian Library, 1967), no.
                           3.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Einhorn, J. W., <title>Spiritalis unicornis: das Einhorn als
                              Bedeutungsträger in Literatur und Kunst des Mittelalters</title>
                           (Munich: W. Fink, 1976), pp. 345, 434.</bibl>
                        <bibl> de Winter, P. M., ‘Une réalisation exceptionnelle
                              d’enlumineurs français et anglais: le bréviaire de Renaud de Bar,
                              évêque de Metz’ in <title>La Lorraine: études archéologiques, Actes du 103e
                              congrès national des Sociétés savantes</title> (Nancy-Metz, 1978), Section
                              d’archaeologie et d’histoire de l’art (Paris: Bibliothèque
                           nationale, 1980), pp. 27–62, at p. 33 n. 9.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Collin-Roset, S., <title>Ecriture et enluminure en Lorraine au Moyen
                              Age: catalogue de l’exposition ‘La plume et le parchemin’ organisé par
                              la Société Thierry Alix du 29 mai au 29 juillet 1984 en la chapelle
                              des Cordeliers, Musée historique lorrain, Nancy</title> (Nancy:
                           Société Thierry Alix, 1984), no. 79.</bibl>
                        <bibl><title>The Douce legacy: an exhibition to commemorate the 150th anniversary
                           of the bequest of Francis Douce</title> (1757– 1834) (Oxford: Bodleian Library,
                           1984), no. 71</bibl>
                        <bibl> Manion, M. M. and Vines, V. F., <title>Medieval and
                              Renaissance illuminated manuscripts in Australian collections</title>
                           (Melbourne; New York: Thames and Hudson, 1984), pp. 173–6, figs.
                           163–74.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Neale, R., ‘The Fool and his loaf’, <title>Medium Aevum</title> 54
                           (1985), pp. 104–9, at pp. 106, 109.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Oliver (1988), vol. 1, pp. 78 n. 72, 87, 181–2; vol. 2, pl.
                           182.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Southworth, J., <title>The English medieval minstrel</title>
                           (Woodbridge: Boydell, 1989), p. 140.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Sautmann, F., ‘Fileuse, fée, sorcière: images du sacré et de
                              l’interdit’ in <title>L’Image au Moyen Age: actes du colloque, Amiens, 19–23
                              mars 1986</title>, WODAN Recherches en littératures médiévales 15 (Amiens:
                              Centre d’études médiévales, Université de Picardie, 1992), pp. 281–90,
                              at p. 281 n. 4 (fol. 7v).</bibl>
                        <bibl>Manion, M. M., Knowles, L. and Payne, J., ‘The Aspremont
                              Psalter-Hours: the making of a manuscript’, <title>Art Bulletin of
                              Victoria</title> 34 (1994), pp. 25–34.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Canadé Sautman, F., <title>La religion du quotidien: rites et
                              croyances populaires de la fin du Moyen Âge</title> (Florence:
                           Olschki, 1995), p. 203.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Gathercole, P. M., <title>Animals in medieval French manuscript
                              illumination</title> (Lewiston, NY; Lampeter: Edwin Mellen Press,
                           1995), p. 20.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Carroll, C. W., ‘Text and image: the case of Erec et Enide’ in
                              Keith Busby (ed.), <title>Word and image in Arthurian literature</title> (New
                           York; London: Garland, 1996), pp. 58–78, at p. 70 n. 17.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Randall, L. M. C. et al., <title>Medieval and Renaissance manuscripts
                              in the Walters Art Gallery</title> (Baltimore; London: Johns Hopkins
                           University Press in association with the Walters Art Gallery, 1989– 97),
                           vol. 1, France, 975–1420, no. 57, p. 151, cols. 1–2.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Kolve, V. A., ‘God-denying fools and the medieval “religion of
                              love”’, <title>Studies in the Age of Chaucer</title> 19 (1997), pp. 3–59,
                           fig. 12.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Oosterwijk, S., ‘Kint ende kinne, man ende wijf. De plaats van
                              het kind in de middeleeuwse kunst’, <title>De wereld van het middeleeuwse
                              kind, Madoc: Tijdschrift over de Middeleeuwen</title> 11, no. 4
                           (1997), pp. 214–25, at p. 223.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Salmen, W., <title>Spielfrauen im Mittelalter</title> (Hildesheim: G. Olms,
                              2000), Abb. 43 (fol. 43).</bibl>
                        <bibl>Sprunger, D. A., ‘Depicting the insane: a thirteenth-century case
                           study’ in T. S. Jones and D. A. Sprunger (eds.), <title>Marvels, monsters, and miracles: studies in the
                           medieval and early modern imaginations</title>, Studies in Medieval Culture 42
                           (Kalamazoo, MI: Medieval Institute Publications, 2002), pp. 223–41, at
                           pp. 231–3 and fig. 4 (fol. 60v, detail).</bibl>
                        <bibl>Morgan, N., ‘Gendered devotions and social rituals: the
                              Aspremont Psalter-“Hours” and the image of the patron in late
                              thirteenth and early fourteenth-century France’, <title>Melbourne Art
                              Journal</title> 6 (2003), pp. 5–24.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Smith, K. A., <title>Art, identity and devotion in fourteenth-century
                              England: three women and their books of hours</title> (London: British
                           Library and University of Toronto Press, 2003), p. 144 n. 70.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Wirth, J., ‘Les marges à drôleries des manuscrits gothiques:
                              problèmes de méthode’ in A. Bolvig and P. Lindley (eds.), <title>History and
                              images: towards a new iconology</title> (Turnhout: Brepols, 2003),
                           pp. 277–300, at pp. 296 fig. 8 (fol. 101v, detail), 297.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Wirth, J. (with I. Jeger), ‘La femme qui bénit’ in J.-C. Schmitt
                           (ed.), <title>Femmes, art et religion au Moyen Âge</title> (Strasbourg: Presses
                           Universitaires de Strasbourg, 2004), pp. 157–79, at pp. 167–8; 169 ill.
                           10.12; 219.</bibl>
                        <bibl> Manion, M. M., <title>The Felton illuminated manuscripts in the
                              National Gallery of Victoria</title> (Melbourne: Macmillan Art
                           Publishing and the National Gallery of Victoria, 2005), pp. 98–203 and
                           passim.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Morgan, N. and Binski, P., ‘Private devotion: humility and splendor’
                           in P. Binski and S. Panayotova (eds.), <title>The Cambridge illuminations: ten centuries of book production in the medieval west</title> [exhibition catalogue] (London: H.
                           Miller, 2005), pp. 163–233, cited at no. 52.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Nishimura, M. M. and Nishimura, D., ‘Rabbits, warrens, and
                              Warenne: the patronage of the Gorleston Psalter’ in K. A. Smith and C.
                              H. Krinsky (eds.), <title>Tributes to Lucy Freeman Sandler: studies in
                              manuscript illumination</title> (London: H. Miller, 2007), pp. 205–18,
                           at pp. 212 n. 60, 213 n. 64.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Morgan (2009), pp. 64, 65, 67.</bibl>
                      
                     </listBibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2024-05">Encode full description from Solopova catalogue.</change>
         
         <change when="2022-04-04">Add binding information from Summary Catalogue.</change>
         <change when="2018-10-14" xml:id="MMM">
            <persName>Mitch Fraas</persName> Provenance and acquisition information added using <ref
               target="https://github.com/littlegustv/oxfordupdates/blob/master/test_case_for_oxford_prov.rb"
               >https://github.com/littlegustv/oxfordupdates/blob/master/test_case_for_oxford_prov.rb</ref>
            in collaboration with the <ref target="http://mappingmanuscriptmigrations.org/">Mapping
               Manuscript Migrations</ref> project.</change>
         <change when="2017-07-01">First online publication.</change>
         <change when="2017-05-25">
            <persName>James Cummings</persName> Up-converted the markup using <ref
               target="https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl"
               >https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl</ref>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
