<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="manuscript_4720">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>MS. Douce 49</title>
            <title type="collection">MSS. Douce</title>

            <respStmt xml:id="ES">
               <resp when="2013">Cataloguer</resp>
               <persName>Elizabeth Solopova</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="MH">
               <resp when="2024">Encoding</resp>
               <persName>Matthew Holford</persName>
            </respStmt>

         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </publisher>
            <idno type="msID">MS_Douce_49</idno>
            <idno type="collection">Douce</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="MS_Douce_49" xml:lang="en">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <region type="county">Oxfordshire</region>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <institution>University of Oxford</institution>
                  <repository>Bodleian Library</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">MS. Douce 49</idno>
                  <idno type="ieArk">ark:29072/x02r36tz40d7</idno>
                  <idno type="crArk">ark:29072/x0k930bx09jg</idno>
                  <altIdentifier type="internal">
                     <idno type="SCN">21623</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
               <head>Portable Psalter; French Flanders, Diocese of Thérouanne, region of St-Omer (?); c. 1270–1290</head>
               <msContents>

                  <msItem class="#liturgica #biblia" n="1" xml:id="MS_Douce_49-item1">
                     <title key="work_14114" type="desc">Psalter (portable)</title>
                     <note>Fols. i and 1–3 are fly-leaves with added notes (see
                        ‘Provenance’).</note>
                     <note> [item 1 occupies quire I]</note>
                     <msItem n="1">
                        <locus from="4r" to="9v">(fols. 4r–9v)</locus>
                        <note> Calendar, written in red and black, laid out one month per page,
                           approximately one-third full, not graded. Includes saints venerated in
                           the diocese of Thérouanne, such as Audomar (9 September) and Maximus,
                           bishop of Riez (27 November), both in red, Bertin (5 September) and
                           Winnoc (6 November). Other saints in red are Vincent of Saragossa (22
                           January), Basil (14 June), Lawrence (10 August) with octave, Egidius (1
                           September), Remigius, Germanus and Bavo of Ghent (1 October), Vedast (6
                           February and 1 October), Denis (9 October), Martin (11 November) with
                           octave and his translation (4 July), Bricius of Tours (13 November),
                           Clement of Metz (23 November), Catherine (25 November), Nicholas (6
                           December) and his translation (9 May), Stephen (26 December) and Thomas
                           Becket (29 December). The calendar also includes Amand (6 February),
                           Lambert, bishop of Liège (17 September), Francis (4 October), Donatianus
                           (14 October) and Eligius (1 December). The months are headed by notes on
                           the length of the solar and lunar month (e.g. ‘Januarius habet dies xxxi.
                           luna xxx’) and by verses on the ‘Egyptian’ days, different from all the
                           sets published by Hennig (1955), but close to his sets I and III. Hebrew
                           names of the months in Latin transliteration are added in the top margin
                           in a 16thcentury hand, including ‘TISRI . HIC INCIPIVNT ANNVM HAEBREI .’
                           on the page for September.  </note>
                     </msItem><note>[items 2–6 occupy quires II–XXIII]</note>
                     <msItem n="2">
                        <note> (fols. ii recto–clxxxv recto) Psalms 1–150, written with each verse
                           starting on a new line, without titles. The leaf which originally
                           contained the Beatus-initial is missing, so that the first psalm begins
                           with ‘Qui non abiit ...’. There is an offset of an illuminated border and
                           the opening words of psalm 1 in capitals (‘...ATVS VIR’) (fol. ii recto).
                           The psalms are in the biblical order; subdivisions within psalms are not
                           indicated, apart from psalm 118, subdivided into twenty-two 8-verse
                           units. Punctuated throughout, with punctus used to mark the ends of
                           verses, and occasionally punctus elevatus used to mark metrum. There are
                           textual divisions at psalms 26, 38, 51, 52, 68, 80, 97, 101 and 109 (see
                           ‘Decoration’). Psalm numbers in Roman numerals are added in a
                           16th-century hand (pink ink). The same hand wrote the running titles in
                           the upper margin to indicate the subdivision of psalms into five books in
                           Jewish usage, and added short rubrics at the beginning of psalms,
                           referring to their ‘authorship’ and use (e.g. ‘david’, ‘asaph’, ‘canticum
                           graduum’, ‘aggei et zacharie’, ‘oratio’, etc.). The letters of the Hebrew
                           alphabet added in black ink at the beginning of sections of psalm 118
                           (fol. cli verso) are probably in the same hand, as well as the names of
                           some of the letters in Latin transliteration (e.g. ‘aleph’, ‘beth’, etc.)
                           and their translation into Latin (e.g. ‘doctrina’, ‘domus’, etc.).
                           ‘Alleluya’ is written in Greek in the margin at the beginning of psalm
                           118. There are post-medieval corrections to the text of psalms on fols.
                           lxxiii verso, lxxiiii recto, lxxxvii recto, lxxxv verso, clv verso,
                           clxxiiii recto, clxxxv verso, etc. The numbers of psalms that have
                           historiated initials are added in pencil by Douce (see ‘Provenance’).
                        </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="3">
                        <note> (fols. clxxxv recto–clxxxxv recto) Weekly canticles, with numbers
                           i–vi and titles added in a 16th-century hand: <list>
                              <item>(1) Confitebor tibi domine (Isaiah 12) (‘Cantica Esaie’);</item>
                              <item>(2) Ego dixi (Isaiah 38: 10–21) (‘Cantica Ezechiae’);</item>
                              <item>(3) Exultauit cor meum (1 Samuel 2: 1–11) (‘Cantica
                                 Anne’);</item>
                              <item>(4) Cantemus domino (Exodus 15: 1–20) (‘Cantica Moysi’);</item>




                              <item>(5) Domine audiui (Habakkuk 3) (‘Cantica Abacuch’);</item>
                              <item>(6) Audite celi (Deuteronomy 32: 1–44) (‘Moysi’).</item>
                           </list>
                        </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="4">
                        <note> (fols. clxxxxv recto–ccii recto) Daily canticles, prayers and creeds,
                           with numbers vii–xii and titles added in a 16th-century hand: <list>
                              <item>(1) Te deum laudamus (‘Augustini Ambrosii’) (fol. clxxxxv
                                 recto);</item>
                              <item>(2) Benedicite omnia opera (‘Trium puerorum’) (fol. clxxxxvi
                                 verso);</item>
                              <item>(3) Benedictus dominus deus (‘Zacharie’) (fol. clxxxxvii
                                 verso);</item>
                              <item>(4) Magnificat (‘Cantica dive˛ virginis Marie’) (fol. clxxxxviii
                                 verso);</item>
                              <item>(5) Nunc dimittis (‘Simeonis’) (fol. clxxxxix recto);</item>
                              <item> (6) Athanasian Creed (Quicumque uult ...) (‘Symbolum
                                 Athanasii’) (fol. clxxxxix verso).</item>
                           </list>
                        </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="5">
                        <note> (fols. ccii recto–ccvi recto) Litany, including Martin, Remigius,
                           Vedast, Amand, Bavo, Benedict, Medard, Gildard and Maximus last among the
                           confessors. The litany is followed by versicles and responses, and
                           collects (fols. cciv verso–ccvi recto); the last two are to Sts Catherine
                           and Nicholas (compare MS. Douce 38): <list>
                              <item> (1) Deus cui proprium est misereri semper et parcere suscipe
                                 ...</item>
                              <item> (2) Deus cui omne cor patet et omnis uoluntas loquitur et quem
                                 nullum latet secretum ...</item>
                              <item> (3) Deus a quo sancta desideria recta consilia et iusta sunt
                                 ...</item>
                              <item> (4) Concede nos famulos tuos quesumus domine deus noster
                                 perpetua mentis et corporis ...</item>
                              <item> (5) Fidelium deus omnium conditor et redemptor animabus
                                 famulorum famularumque tuarum remissionem ...</item>
                              <item> (6) Deus qui dedisti legem moysi in summitate montis ...</item>
                              <item> (7) Deus qui beatum nicholaum pontificem tuum in numeris
                                 decorasti miraculi ...</item>
                           </list> More collects and other texts may have been included originally,
                           as two leaves are missing after fol. ccv. The collect ‘Fidelium deus ...’
                           ends with ‘Amen’ at the end of fol. ccv verso and is followed by
                           versicles and responses on fol. ccvi. </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="6">
                        <note> (fols. ccvi verso–ccxiiii verso) Office of the Dead, beginning
                           without a title or capital letter; responsories correspond to nos. 83,
                           25, 1, 38, 58, 29, 93, 82, 38 in Ottosen (1993). The Office is followed
                           on fols. ccxiii verso–ccxiiii verso by collects without titles: <list>
                              <item> (1) Adiuua nos domine deus noster et beatissime dei genetricis
                                 marie precibus ...</item>
                              <item> (2) Deus indulgentiarum da animabus famulorum tuorum N.
                                 refrigerii sedem quietis beatitudinem eterni luminis
                                 claritatem</item>
                              <item> (3) Deus in cuius miseratione anime fidelium requiescunt
                                 famulis et famulabus tuis ...</item>
                              <item> (4) Actiones nostras quesumus domine aspirando preueni
                                 ...</item>
                              <item> (5) Deus qui nos patrem et matrem honorare precepisti miserere
                                 clementer animabus ...</item>
                              <item> (6) Inclina domine aurem tuam ad preces nostras quibus
                                 misericordiam tuam supplices ...</item>
                           </list> The last collect has feminine grammatical forms (‘anime famule
                           tue’, fol. ccxiiii verso). Fols. ccxv–ccxix are blank apart from Douce’s
                           notes (see ‘Provenance’). </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>
                     <msItem>
                        <note>16th-century additions in Hebrew: see Provenance.</note>
                        <textLang mainLang="he">Hebrew</textLang>
                     </msItem>
                  </msItem>

               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <p><secFol> reditatem tuam et possessionem <locus>(psalter, fol. iii
                           recto)</locus></secFol></p>
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="perg">
                        <support> parchment; paper fly-leaves</support>
                        <extent> <measure type="leaf" quantity="228">228</measure> leaves <dimensions unit="mm" type="leaf">
                              <height quantity="136">c. 136</height>
                              <width>93</width>
                           </dimensions>
                           <note> Leaves were trimmed in rebinding, occasionally causing the loss of
                              text and decoration.</note>
                        </extent>
                        <foliation> Modern, in pencil and 16th-century in red ink; 1–9 + i–ccxix.
                           The 16thcentury foliation begins with ii on the leaf containing the
                           imperfect beginning of the first psalm, suggesting that the page with the
                           Beatus-initial was still present when the manuscript was foliated. Modern
                           folio numbers i and ccxvi–ccxix were added in pencil before the start and
                           after the end of the 16th-century foliation.</foliation>
                        <collation> (fols. 1–2) fol. 1 is a paper fly-leaf, conjoint with the upper
                           pastedown; fol. 2 is a paper fly-leaf | (fols. 3–i) I (6+2) the outer
                           bifolium (fols. 3 and i) is made from a different, much more speckled
                           parchment than the rest of the manuscript (the same as fol. ccxvi, an
                           empty fly-leaf at the end of the manuscript) and may have been added by
                           the 16th-century owner; the missing Beatus-initial page was probably a
                           single leaf | (fols. ii–li) II–VI (10) | (fols. lii–lxii) VII (12−1)
                           missing 2 (stub remains after fol. lii, but no loss of text) | (fols.
                           lxiii–ccii) VIII–XXI (10) | (fols. cciii–ccviii) XXII (8−2) missing 4 and
                           5 (two stubs in the middle of the quire, but no loss of text) | (fols.
                           ccix–ccxv) XXIII (8−1) missing 8 (?), no loss of text | (fols.
                           ccxvi–ccxix) fol. ccxvi is an added parchment fly-leaf; fols.
                           ccxvii–ccxviii are paper fly-leaves; fol. ccxix is a paper fly-leaf
                           conjoint with the lower pastedown</collation>
                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout writtenLines="18" columns="1" topLine="above"
                           rulingMedium="leadpoint"> Ruled in plummet, with double vertical and
                           horizontal bounding lines, extending the full height and width of page;
                           the ruling for lines 9–10, occupying the centre of the page, also extends
                           the full width of page; 18 lines per page; written above the top line
                           (see Oliver, 1985, p. 139, n. 27 and compare MS. Liturg. 396 and MS.
                           Auct. D. 4. 3); written space: variable, <dimensions type="written"
                              unit="mm">
                              <height quantity="85">c. 85</height>
                              <width>49</width>
                           </dimensions></layout>
                     </layoutDesc>

                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc>
                     <handNote script="textualisNorthern" execution="formata">Formal Gothic book
                        hand, black ink.</handNote>
                  </handDesc>
                  <decoDesc resp="#PA">
                     <decoNote type="monogram">Gold KL monograms on blue and pink backgrounds in the
                        calendar (cut out on fol. 5). </decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="miniature">Miniatures with the Labours of the Months, on gold
                        backgrounds, in frames pointed at the top, by a different artist from that
                        of the historiated initials in the psalter (Pächt and Alexander, 1966–73):
                        January: man warming one bare foot by the fire, holding his shoe in one hand
                        and drinking out of a bowl (rubbed) February: woman holding a lighted candle
                        and a book March: man digging with a spade April: man holding a glove and
                        branches (?) May: man with a hawk June: man carrying a bundle of wood on his
                        back July: man mowing hay with a scythe August: man reaping grain September:
                        man cutting grapes; a basket with grapes on his back October: man sowing
                        November: man knocking down acorns for pigs December: man baking bread in an
                        oven.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="histInit">Nine historiated initials in the psalter (the
                        Beatus-page is missing) on gold backgrounds, occupying two-thirds of a page,
                        and borders decorated with grotesques, hybrids and animals. The iconography
                        of the initials is related to other Franco- Flemish psalters of the second
                        half of the 13th century, which have a Christological cycle at the eight
                        divisions, and saints at psalms 51 and 101 (see Carlvant, 1978, pp. 473–4). <list>
                           <item>fol. xxx verso: Psalm 26 (initial D(ominus)). The Betrayal; Christ
                              healing Malchus’s ear. Hybrid figure with a shield and a sword.</item>
                           <item>fol. xlviii verso Psalm 38 (initial D(ixi)). Christ before Pilate;
                              dragon forms the tail of Q.</item>
                           <item>fol. lxiiii verso: Psalm 51 (initial Q(vid)).St Francis preaching
                              to birds, Brother Leo (?) sitting behind him. Grotesque and a
                              crouching dog form the tail of Q.</item>
                           <item> fol. lxv verso: Psalm 52 (initial D(ixit)). Flagellation. Ape
                              riding a dog.</item>
                           <item>fol. lxxxii verso: Psalm 68 (initial S(aluum)). Christ carrying the
                              Cross.</item>
                           <item>fol. ciii recto: Psalm 80 (initial E(xultate)).Crucifixion, with
                              Longinus pointing to his eye, piercing Christ’s side, and Stephaton
                              with the sponge on a reed. Ape with a trumpet.</item>
                           <item>fol. cxxiii verso: Psalm 97 (initial C(antate)). Descent from the
                              Cross: the Virgin holding Christ’s hand, Joseph of Arimathea
                              supporting his body, and Nicodemus removing the nail from his feet;
                              the sun and moon above.</item>
                           <item>fol. cxxvi verso: Psalm 101 (initial D(omine)). St Clare of Assisi
                              (?) in a habit tied with a rope with three knots, giving boots to
                              beggars.</item>
                           <item>fol. cxliiii verso: Psalm 109 (initial D(ixit)) The body of Christ
                              embalmed by three men.</item>
                        </list></decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="border">Borders: see above.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="decInit">3-line gold initials on blue and pink backgrounds, and
                        borders made of gold, blue and pink bars, some ending with animal heads, at
                        the beginnings of psalms, canticles, litany and prayers.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="flourInit">2-line gold and blue initials, decorated with
                        contrasting blue and red penwork at the beginnings of verses and
                        periods.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="lineFill">Line-endings with gold, white, red and blue geometric
                        and floral designs.</decoNote>
                  </decoDesc>
                  <bindingDesc>

                     <binding notAfter="1800" notBefore="1700">
                        <p> Brown leather (calf (?)) over pasteboard, 18th century. Gilt floral
                           border round the outer edge of both covers. Rebacked in the Bodleian,
                           with the original, fragmentary spine pasted to the lower pastedown.
                           Panels decorated with gilt floral and geometric designs on the original
                           spine. One of the fragmentary panels has gilt lettering: ‘[PSALTE]RIVM ||
                           MS. SÆC. XIV’. Discoloration left by a (Bodleian (?)) paper label at the
                           bottom of the spine. Gilt fillet lines on the edges of covers, gilt
                           decorations on turn-ins. Pastedowns and fly-leaves made of blue marbled
                           paper with white floral designs. Gilt edges of textblock with gauffering.
                        </p>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="1290" notBefore="1270"><hi
                           rend="italic">c</hi>. 1270–1290</origDate>
                     <origPlace>
                        <country key="place_7024097">Flanders</country>, <region>diocese of
                           Thérouanne</region>, region of <settlement key="place_7011062">St.
                           Omer</settlement>
                     </origPlace>
                  </origin>
                  <provenance>Probably made for use of the diocese of Thérouanne: evidence of the
                     calendar and litany. Perhaps made for a female patron with Franciscan
                     connections. The final prayer in the original hand has feminine grammatical
                     forms (fol. ccxiiii verso), Francis appears in the calendar and there are
                     Franciscan saints in the initials. </provenance>
                  <provenance>Many 16th-century additions by an owner with an interest in the Jewish
                     usage of psalms. The additions are in majuscules, Hebrew, or a cursive
                     humanist, Italian (?) hand (see fols. lxiii verso–lxiiii recto). The erased
                     text in the lower margins of fols. lx recto and lxii recto, which preserve
                     fragments of reddish ink, was probably by the same hand. </provenance>
                  <provenance notAfter="1834" notBefore="1757" resp="#MMM">
                     <persName key="person_69848690" role="fmo">Francis Douce, 1757–1834</persName>,
                     see ODNB: bookplate on the upper pastedown, notes on fols. 2r–v and ccxvii
                     recto–verso, his (?) shelfmark (?): ‘B iiij’ in red ink (upper pastedown and
                     fol. 1v, cf. MS. Douce 23, MS. Douce 24, MS. Douce 38). </provenance>
                  <acquisition resp="#MMM" when="1834">Bodleian Library: received in 1834 with
                     bequest of Douce. </acquisition>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>Elizabeth Solopova, <title>Latin Liturgical
                              Psalters in the Bodleian Library: A Select Catalogue</title> (Oxford,
                           2013), pp. 341–347. Previously described: <listBibl>
                              <bibl facs="aaz0523.gif" type="SC">Summary Catalogue, vol. 4, p.
                                 504</bibl>
                           </listBibl>
                        </source>
                     </recordHist>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <surrogates>
                     <bibl subtype="partial" type="digital-facsimile">
                        <ref
                           target="https://digital.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/objects/b7ba958e-ca38-4b77-a564-fb9ef9cbfcec/">
                           <title>Digital Bodleian</title>
                        </ref>
                        <note>(26 images from 35mm slides)</note>
                     </bibl>
                  </surrogates>
                  <listBibl type="WRAPPER">
                     <listBibl type="PRINT">
                        <head>Select bibliography to 2009</head>

                        <bibl>‘Liturgical manuscripts in the Bodleian Library, Oxford’, <title>The
                           Ecclesiologist</title> 3 (1 September 1888), pp. 34–5.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Summary catalogue, vol. 4, no. 21623.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Frere, no. 442.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Vitzthum von Eckstaedt, B. G., <title>Die Pariser Miniaturmalerei von
                              der Zeit des hl. Ludwig bis zu Philipp von Valois und ihr Verhältnis
                              zur Malerei in Nordwesteuropa</title> (Leipzig: Verlag von Quelle
                           &amp; Meyer, 1907), p. 108.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Nordenfalk, C., ‘Insulare und kontinentale
                              Psalterillustrationen aus dem XIII. Jahrhundert’, <title>Acta
                              archaeologica</title> 10 (1939), pp. 107–20.</bibl>
                        <bibl>S. J. P. van Dijk, <title>Latin Liturgical Manuscripts in the Bodleian
                           Library, Oxford, vol. 2: Office Books</title> (typescript, 1957),
                           <citedRange unit="page" from="95" to="95">p. 95</citedRange>
                        </bibl>
                        <bibl>Randall, L. M. C., <title>Images in the margins of Gothic
                              manuscripts</title> (Berkeley: University of California Press, 1966),
                           p. 40.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Pächt and Alexander (1966–73), vol. 1, no. 287, pl. XXI.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Carlvant (1978), pp. 443–4, 471–4.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Oliver, J. H., ‘Medieval alphabet soup: reconstruction of a
                              Mosan psalter-hours in Philadelphia and Oxford and the cult of St
                              Catherine’, <title>Gesta</title> 24/2 (1985), pp. 129–40.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Bräm, A., <title>Das Andachtsbuch der Marie de Gavre: Paris, Bibliothèque
                           nationale, Ms. nouv. acq. fr. 16251. Buchmalerei in der Diözese Cambrai im letzten Viertel des 13.
                           Jahrhunderts</title> (Wiesbaden: L. Reichert, 1997), p. 17.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Gil, M. and Nys, L., <title>Saint-Omer gothique. Les arts figuratifs à
                              Saint-Omer à la fin du Moyen Âge, 1250–1550: peinture, vitrail,
                              sculpture, arts du livre</title> (Valenciennes: Presses Universitaires
                           de Valenciennes, 2004), pp. 65, 69, 76 n. 163.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Bräm, A., ‘“Fratrum minorum mater”. Heiligenbilder als
                              Angleichung und zum Patronat in Frankreich und Flandern und in der
                              Anjou-Hofkunst Neapels’ in D. Blume and M. Werner (eds.), <title>Elisabeth
                              von Thüringen: eine europäische Heilige</title> (Petersberg: Imhof,
                           2007), pp. 309–24, at p. 312.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Morgan (2009), pp. 64, 66, 68–9.</bibl>

                       
                     </listBibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2024-05">Encode full description from Solopova catalogue.</change>
         <change when="2023-11-09">Description revised to incorporate all the information in the
            Summary Catalogue (1897)</change>
         <change when="2018-10-14" xml:id="MMM">
            <persName>Mitch Fraas</persName> Provenance and acquisition information added using <ref
               target="https://github.com/littlegustv/oxfordupdates/blob/master/test_case_for_oxford_prov.rb"
               >https://github.com/littlegustv/oxfordupdates/blob/master/test_case_for_oxford_prov.rb</ref>
            in collaboration with the <ref target="http://mappingmanuscriptmigrations.org/">Mapping
               Manuscript Migrations</ref> project.</change>
         <change when="2017-07-01">First online publication.</change>
         <change when="2017-05-25">
            <persName>James Cummings</persName> Up-converted the markup using <ref
               target="https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl"
               >https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl</ref>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
