<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="manuscript_4721">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>MS. Douce 50</title>
            <title type="collection">MSS. Douce</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp when="2013">Cataloguer</resp>
               <persName>Elizabeth Solopova</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp when="2024">Encoding</resp>
               <persName>Matthew Holford</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </publisher>
            <idno type="msID">MS_Douce_50</idno>
            <idno type="collection">Douce</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="MS_Douce_50" xml:lang="en">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <region type="county">Oxfordshire</region>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <institution>University of Oxford</institution>
                  <repository>Bodleian Library</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">MS. Douce 50</idno>
                  <idno type="ieArk">ark:29072/x02b88qd073g</idno>
                  <idno type="crArk">ark:29072/x0kd17cs92vx</idno>
                  <altIdentifier type="internal">
                     <idno type="SCN">21624</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
               <head>Portable Psalter; France, Paris (?), 13th century, 1240s (?)</head>
               <msContents>
                  <msItem class="#liturgica #biblia" n="1" xml:id="MS_Douce_50-item1">
                     <title key="work_14114" type="desc">Portable Psalter</title>
                     <note>Pp. i–viii are paper fly-leaves with modern and early modern notes (see
                        ‘Provenance’).</note>
                     <note> [item 1 occupies quire I]</note>
                     <msItem n="1">
                        <locus from="ix" to="xvi">(pp. ix–xvi)</locus>
                        <note> Calendar, laid out one month per page, written in red, blue and
                           black, not graded, leaves for January–February and November–December
                           missing. The calendar includes English, Scottish and Irish saints. The
                           following feasts are in red: four feasts of John the Baptist (see
                           ‘Provenance’), the translation of Edmund (29 April), Augustine of
                           Canterbury (26 May), Benedict (11 July), Christina of Bolsena (24 July)
                           and Mundus (21 October, the feast day of the Irish Fintan Munnu). Brendan
                           (16 May) was originally written in black, but was overwritten in red,
                           presumably in the original workshop; Columba, originally in red, is
                           erased on 9 June. The feasts in blue include Edward (18 March) and
                           Elphege (19 April). The calendar also contains Patrick (17 March),
                           Cuthbert (20 March) and his translation (4 September), Melrune
                           (‘Maelrubha’, 21 April), Mellitus (24 April), Alban (22 June), Kentigern
                           (7 July), Oswald (5 August), Wilfrid (12 October) and Frideswide (21
                           October). Errors in the calendar, such as ‘Edmund’ instead of ‘Edward’
                           (18 March), suggest the lack of familiarity with English saints (Branner,
                           1977, p. 107).</note>
                        <note> The absence of Margaret of Scotland, canonized and translated in 1250
                           (feasts 10 June and 16 November, translation 19 June), supports an
                           earlier date for the manuscript (dated by Pächt and Alexander (1966–73)
                           to the third quarter of the 13th century, but by Branner (1969) to 1240s;
                           see also Glenn (1998)). Thomas Becket’s translation on 7 July 1220 is
                           also absent, although he appears very highly placed in the litany.
                        </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <note>[item 2 occupies quire II]</note>
                     <msItem n="2">
                        <locus from="xvii" to="xxii">(pp. xvii–xxii) </locus>
                        <note>Three full-page miniatures, painted on one side of each leaf with the
                           other side blank (see ‘Decoration’). </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <note>[items 3–6 occupy quires III–XXVII]</note>
                     <msItem n="3">
                        <locus from="1" to="472">(pp. 1–472) </locus>
                        <note>Psalms 1–150, written with each verse starting on a new line, without
                           titles or numbers. The psalms are in the biblical order; subdivisions
                           within psalms are not indicated, apart from 17: 26 (Cum sancto ...) (p.
                           51) and psalm 118 subdivided into twenty-two 8-verse units. Punctuated
                           throughout, with punctus elevatus used to mark metrum, punctus or punctus
                           elevatus used to mark minor pauses, and punctus used to mark the ends of
                           verses. Initials ‘I’ at the beginnings of psalms 10 (p. 30) and 30 (p.
                           91) were never executed, presumably because of an oversight. Psalm 85,
                           also beginning with ‘I’ (‘Inclina ...’), starts with a 1-line, rather
                           than 2-line, initial (p. 277). There are textual divisions at psalms 26,
                           38, 51, 52, 68, 80, 97, 101, 109 and 119 (see ‘Decoration’). The initials
                           mark psalms appointed first for Matins during the week, psalm 109
                           appointed first for Sunday Vespers, the division into ‘three fifties’,
                           and psalm 119, the first of the Gradual Psalms. Psalm 109 starts on a new
                           page and is singled out with a larger historiated initial. The Latin
                           alphabet is written in the original hand on p. 367, left partially blank
                           before the start of psalm 109 on the next page. </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="4">
                        <locus from="472" to="499">(pp. 472–499)</locus>
                        <note> Weekly canticles, without titles: <list>
                              <item>(1) Confitebor tibi domine (Isaiah 12);</item>
                              <item>(2) Ego dixi (Isaiah 38: 10–21);</item>
                              <item>(3) Exultauit cor meum (1 Samuel 2: 1–11);</item>
                              <item>(4) Cantemus domino (Exodus 15: 1–20);</item>
                              <item>(5) Domine audiui (Habakkuk 3);</item>
                              <item>(6) Audite celi (Deuteronomy 32: 1–44).</item>
                           </list>
                        </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="5">
                        <locus from="500" to="516">(pp. 500–516) </locus>
                        <note>Daily canticles, prayers and creeds, without titles: <list>
                              <item>(1) Te deum laudamus (p. 500);</item>
                              <item>(2) Benedicite omnia opera (p. 503);</item>
                              <item>(3) Benedictus dominus deus (p. 506);</item>
                              <item>(4) Magnificat (p. 508);</item>
                              <item>(5) Nunc dimittis (p. 509);</item>
                              <item>(6) Athanasian Creed (Quicumque uult ...) (p. 510).</item>
                           </list>
                        </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="6">
                        <note> (pp. 516–535)</note>
                        <note> Litany, including English as well as Scottish and Irish saints:
                           Thomas Becket (second), Alban, Edmund and Oswald among the martyrs;
                           Maglorius, Cuthbert, Fintan Munnu (Mundus), Patrick, Malachy (?), Blane,
                           Bean, Berchan, Columba and Fechian among the confessors; Columba and
                           Brigid (of Kildare (?)) among the virgins. Followed by collects (pp.
                           533–535): <list>
                              <item> (1) Deus qui corda fidelium sancti spiritus illustratione
                                 docuisti ...</item>
                              <item> (2) Deus cui proprium est misereri semper et parcere suscipe
                                 ...</item>
                              <item> (3) Omnipotens sempiterne deus qui facis mirabilia magna solus
                                 ...</item>
                              <item> (4) Pretende domine famulis et famulabus tuis omnibus
                                 benefactoribus nostris dexteram celestis auxilii ut de toto corde
                                 ...</item>
                              <item> (5) Deus a quo sancta desideria recta consilia et iusta sunt
                                 ...</item>
                              <item> (6) Adesto domine supplicationibus nostris et uiam famulorum
                                 tuorum in salutis tue ...</item>
                           </list> Pp. 536–41 are blank apart from modern notes. </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <p><secFol>lio iustorum <locus>(psalter, fol. 3r)</locus></secFol></p>
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="perg">
                        <support> parchment; paper fly-leaves</support>
                        <extent> <measure type="leaf" quantity="564">564</measure> pages <dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                              <height quantity="140">c. 140</height>
                              <width>100</width>
                           </dimensions>
                           <note>Leaves were trimmed in rebinding, frequently causing the loss of
                              decoration.</note></extent>
                        <foliation> modern pagination in pencil and ink; i–xxii + 1–100 + 101a +
                           101b + 102–541.</foliation>
                        <collation> (pp. i–viii) pp. i–ii are a paper fly-leaf, conjoint with the
                           upper pastedown, with a small modern paper bifolium pasted to the recto;
                           pp. iii–iv and vii–viii are a paper bifolium; pp. v–vi are a small paper
                           leaf pasted to p. vii | (pp. ix–xvi) I (6−2) missing 1 and 6 | (pp.
                           xvii–xxii) II (3) pp. xvii–xviii are a singleton; pp. xix–xxii are a
                           bifolium | (pp. 1–20) III (10) | (pp. 21–100) IV–VIII (8) | (pp. 101–363)
                           IX–XIX (12) | (pp. 364–367) XX (2) | (pp. 368–535) XXI–XXVII (12) | (pp.
                           536–541) pp. 536–539 are a paper bifolium; p. 541 is a paper fly-leaf
                           conjoint with the lower pastedown. Leaf signatures survive in quires III
                           and XXV–XXVI</collation>

                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout columns="1" writtenLines="13 14">Ruled in plummet for tops and bottoms of minims, with double
                           vertical and triple horizontal bounding lines, extending the full height
                           and width of page (e.g. p. 51); 13 lines per page up to p. 68 (quires
                           III–VI) and 14 lines per page afterwards; written below the top line;
                           written space: <dimensions type="written" unit="mm">
                              <height quantity="82">c. 82</height>
                              <width>55</width>
                           </dimensions> up to p. 68 and <dimensions type="written" unit="mm">
                              <height quantity="89">c. 89</height>
                              <width>60</width>
                           </dimensions> afterwards.</layout>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc>
                     <handNote script="textualisNorthern" execution="formata">Formal Gothic book
                        hand, black ink.</handNote>
                  </handDesc>
                  <decoDesc>

                     <summary>Illumination is by an artist responsible for psalter illustrations in
                        MS. Douce 381, fols. 122–124, and is closely related in style to the
                        Wenceslas Psalter (Los Angeles, J. Paul Getty Museum MS. Ludwig VIII. 4); Le
                        roman de la poire (Paris, Bibliothèque nationale MS. fr. 2186); the Old
                        Testament scenes in New York, Morgan Library MS. M.638 and the ‘Missal of St
                        Louis’ in the treasury of San Francesco, Assisi (Pächt and Alexander,
                        1966–73; Branner, 1977).</summary>
                     <decoNote type="monogram">Blue and pink KL monograms on pink, blue and gold
                        backgrounds, decorated with coiled tendrils, foliage and animal heads, in
                        the calendar (fragmentary, more than a half cropped off during
                        rebinding).</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="miniature">Full-page prefatory miniatures (pp. xvii–xxii), each
                        with scenes set in two medallions, a layout characteristic of Parisian
                        psalters of the first half and middle of the thirteenth century (Oliver,
                        1988; Maekawa, 2000, p. 66). <list>
                           <item>p. xvii The Last Judgement (?), or Heaven and Hell (?): (above)
                              Christ enthroned, holding souls in a cloth, the heads of ten kings
                              seen through windows on either side; (below) two demons forcing souls
                              into a cauldron in a hell-mouth (cf. a similar composition in MS.
                              Douce 381, fol. 124v).</item>
                           <item>p. xix Adoration of the Magi; Presentation in the Temple.</item>
                           <item>p. xxii Ascension, with the Virgin Mary and Peter (?); Pentecost
                              with Peter and Paul (?), but not the Virgin Mary.</item>
                        </list></decoNote>

                     <decoNote type="histInit"> 6- to 8-line initials at liturgical divisions in the
                        psalter, decorated with coiled tendrils, foliage, grotesques and animal
                        heads, and infilled with miniatures on gold backgrounds. The initials for
                        psalms 1 and 109 occupy over half a page each. <list>
                           <item>p. 1 Psalm 1 (initial B(eatus)) David with a sling and armed
                              Goliath in the upper part of the initial; David beheading Goliath in
                              the lower part.</item>
                           <item>p. 81 Psalm 26 (initial D(ominus)) The Anointing of David: Saul
                              sits next to David holding and blessing a phial.</item>
                           <item>p. 126r Psalm 38 (initial D(ixi)) King David standing, pointing to
                              his mouth, facing standing Christ, who is holding a book and raising
                              his hand in a gesture of teaching or blessing (defaced).</item>
                           <item>p. 169 Psalm 52 (initial D(ixit)) King David speaks to the Fool,
                              naked apart from a cloak, eating bread and holding a club.</item>
                           <item>p. 212 Psalm 68 (initial S(aluum)) Half-figure of nude King David
                              praying in waters; half-figure of Christ above, holding an orb and
                              blessing (defaced).</item>
                           <item>p. 265 Psalm 80 (initial E(xultate)) Two seated kings, one playing
                              bells, the other harp.</item>
                           <item>p. 314 Psalm 97 (initial C(antate)) Three tonsured clerics, singing
                              from an open book before a lectern.</item>
                           <item>p. 368 Psalm 109 (initial D(ixit)) Trinity: God-the-Father and Son,
                              holding books and blessing; white dove with halo descending from
                              above.</item>
                        </list></decoNote>

                     <decoNote type="decInit">3-line initials, decorated with animal heads, coiled
                        tendrils and foliage, on gold backgrounds, at the beginnings of psalms 51
                        (p. 167), 101 (p. 320), 119 (p. 415) and the beginning of weekly canticles
                        (p. 472).</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="decInit">2-line initials, decorated with grotesques, beasts,
                        human and animal heads and masks, coiled tendrils and foliage, on gold
                        backgrounds, at the beginnings of psalms, canticles and prayers.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="flourInit">1-line alternating blue and gold initials, decorated
                        with contrasting red and blue penwork, extending into the margins, at the
                        beginnings of verses and periods.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="lineFill">Gold, and red and blue penwork line-endings with
                        floral and geometric designs.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="border">Diagonal marginal extensions in red, blue and gold, on
                        the versos throughout, except the outer bifolium of quire III, where they
                        are on the rectos.</decoNote>
                  </decoDesc>
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <binding notAfter="1825" notBefore="1775">
                        <p> Late 18th-century or early 19th-century French (?) binding, olive
                           morocco over pasteboard. Gilt roll border round the outer edge of both
                           covers. Five panels on spine separated by borders with gilt Greek key
                           design. Gilt lettering on the second panel from the top: ‘HEURES MSS :
                           SUR || VELIN AVEC MIN :’. Flat lozenge-shape design made of flowers,
                           crosses and circles with a floral centre-piece on other panels. Fragment
                           of a (Bodleian (?)) paper label on spine. Gilt edges of textblock.
                           Endbands of gold-coloured thread. Gilt stripe design on turn-ins.
                           Pastedowns and fly-leaves of marbled paper; further fly-leaves of laid
                           paper. </p>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="1249" notBefore="1240">1240s
                        (?)</origDate>
                     <origPlace>
                        <country key="place_1000070">French</country>, <settlement
                           key="place_7008038">Paris</settlement> (?) 
                     </origPlace>
                  </origin>
                  <provenance>Made probably in Paris for a Scottish patron, perhaps associated with
                     Ardchattan Priory in Argyllshire, dedicated to the Virgin Mary and John the
                     Baptist. The calendar contains four feasts of John the Baptist (24 June with
                     octave, 29 August and 24 September), all in red. The Irish saint Fintan Munnu,
                     prominent in the calendar and litany, was venerated in Scotland and may have
                     founded Kilmun in Argyll. Ardchattan was founded in 1230 or 1231 and was one of
                     three Valliscaulian priories in Scotland, directly dependent on Val des Choux,
                     diocese of Langres in France (see Cowan and Easson, 1976, pp. 83–4). The
                     absence of grading in the calendar, an alphabet (p. 376) and the simplicity of
                     the textual contents of the psalter suggest that it was made for a lay patron,
                     or for private use. </provenance>
                  <provenance>Corrections to the text in a 15th-century (?) hand (pp. 127, 512,
                     etc.). </provenance>
                  <provenance>An erased two-line inscription on p. 535, probably late medieval and
                     apparently over an earlier erasure, partly readable as ‘... Liber ...
                     lis/prioris ... cha ...’ (The Douce legacy, 1984). </provenance>
                  <provenance>Letter ‘S’ on a foliage and floral background of overall square shape,
                     in light brown ink, apparently stamped from a printer’s block, 16th century (?)
                     (p. xviii). </provenance>
                  <provenance><persName key="person_69848690" role="fmo">Francis Douce,
                        1757–1834</persName>, see ODNB: bookplate on the upper pastedown; notes (pp.
                     v, vii, viii). </provenance>
                  <acquisition resp="#MMM" when="1834">Bodleian Library: received in 1834 with
                     bequest of Douce. </acquisition>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>Adapted (April 2024) from Elizabeth Solopova, <title>Latin
                              Liturgical Psalters in the Bodleian Library: A Select
                              Catalogue</title> (Oxford, 2013), pp. 280–6. Previously described in
                           the Summary Catalogue. <listBibl>
                              <bibl facs="aaz0523.gif" type="SC">Summary Catalogue, vol. 4, p.
                                 504</bibl>
                           </listBibl>
                        </source>
                     </recordHist>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <surrogates>
                     <bibl subtype="partial" type="digital-facsimile">
                        <ref
                           target="https://digital.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/objects/a052a35a-4876-4257-b79a-ee98bb21fe56/">
                           <title>Digital Bodleian</title>
                        </ref>
                        <note>(15 images from 35mm slides)</note>
                     </bibl>
                  </surrogates>
                  <listBibl type="WRAPPER">
                     <listBibl type="PRINT">
                        <head>Select bibliography to 2006:</head>
                        <bibl>Summary catalogue, vol. 4, no. 21624.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Frere, no. 443.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Vitzthum von Eckstaedt, B. G., <title>Die Pariser Miniaturmalerei von
                              der Zeit des hl. Ludwig bis zu Philipp von Valois und ihr Verhältnis
                              zur Malerei in Nordwesteuropa</title> (Leipzig: Verlag von Quelle
                           &amp; Meyer, 1907), p. 89.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Haseloff (1938), pp. 28, 84.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Boase, T. S. R., <title>English illumination of the thirteenth and
                              fourteenth centuries</title>, Bodleian Library Picture Books 10
                           (Oxford: Bodleian Library, 1954), no. 5a </bibl>
                        <bibl>S. J. P. van Dijk, <title>Latin Liturgical Manuscripts in the Bodleian
                              Library, Oxford, vol. 2: Office Books</title> (typescript, 1957),
                              <citedRange unit="page" from="72" to="72">p. 72</citedRange>
                        </bibl>
                        <bibl>Metzger, M., ‘Les illustrations bibliques d’un manuscrit hébreu du
                           Nord de la France (1278– 1340 environ)’ in P. Gallais and Y.-J. Riou
                           (eds.), <title>Mélanges offerts à René Crozet à l’occasion de son
                              soixante-dixième anniversaire par ses amis, ses collègues, ses élèves
                              et les membres du C.É.S.C.M</title>, 2 vols. (Poitiers: Société
                           d’Études Médiévales, 1966), vol. 2, pp. 1237–53, at p. 1242 n. 47.</bibl>
                        <bibl><ref target="https://catalog.hathitrust.org/Record/000468709">Pächt
                              and Alexander</ref> (1966–73), vol. 1, no. 535, pl. XLI.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Branner, R., ‘The Copenhagen “Corpus”’, <title>Konsthistorisk
                              tidskrif</title>t 38 (1969), pp. 97–119, at pp. 110–11 (figs. 22–4),
                           115–16.</bibl>
                        <bibl> Pächt, O. and Thoss, D., <title>Französische Schule I,
                              Österreichische Nationalbibliothek. Illuminierten Handschriften und
                              Inkunabeln der Österreichischen Nationalbibliothek</title>, Band 1, 2
                           vols. (Wien: Verlag der Österreichischen Akademie der Wissenschaften,
                           1974), p. 126 and fig. 28.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Cowan, I. B. and Easson, D. E., <title>Medieval religious houses,
                              Scotland, with an appendix on the houses in the Isle of Man, 2nd
                              edn.</title> (London: Longman, 1976).</bibl>
                        <bibl>McKinnon, J. W., ‘Canticum novum in the Isabella book’,
                              <title>Medievalia</title> 2 (1976), pp. 207–22, at p. 211 and fig.
                           3.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Branner, R., <title>Manuscript painting in Paris during the reign of
                              Saint Louis: a study of styles</title> (Berkeley: University of
                           California Press, 1977), pp. 107–8, 110–20, 139, 228, figs. 301–5.</bibl>
                        <bibl><title>The Douce legacy: an exhibition to commemorate the 150th
                              anniversary of the bequest of Francis Douce (1757– 1834)</title>
                           (Oxford: Bodleian Library, 1984), no. 70.</bibl>
                        <bibl><title>French connections: Scotland and the arts of France</title>
                           [exhibition catalogue] (Edinburgh: HMSO; Royal Scottish Museum, 1985), p.
                           15 (fig. 3) and no. 4 on p. 141.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Assirelli, M. et al., <title>I libri miniati di età romanica e gotica:
                              saggi e catalogo, Miracolo di Assisi 7.1</title> (Assisi: Cassa di
                           Risparmio di Perugia; Sacro convento di Assisi; Casa editrice
                           francescana, 1988), p. 154.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Krieger, M. (commentary), <title>Gotische Bilderbibel: Faksimile der
                              Handschrift Cod. Ser. n. 2611, fol. 1– 22 der Österreichischen
                              Nationalbibliothek</title>, 2 vols. (Stuttgart: Verlag Müller &amp;
                           Schindler, 1988), vol. 2, pp. 31, 33, fig. 6.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Oliver (1988), vol. 1, p. 151 n. 23.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Randall, L. M. C., <title>Medieval and Renaissance manuscripts in the
                              Walters Art Gallery, vol. 1, France 875–1420</title> (Baltimore: Johns
                           Hopkins University Press, 1989), pp. 74, 78.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Bossier, F., ‘Le problème des lemmes du De caelo dans la traduction
                           latine du Commentaire In De caelo de Simplicius’ in J. Hamesse (ed.),
                              <title>Les problèmes posés par l’édition critique des textes anciens
                              et médiévaux</title>, vol. 13 (Louvain-la-Neuve: Institut d’études
                           médiévales, 1992), pp. 361–97, at p. 365 n. 5.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Sauer, C. (with U. Kuder) (ed.), <title>Die gotischen Handschriften
                              der Württembergischen Landesbibliothek Stuttgart</title> (Katalog der
                           illuminierten Handschriften der Württembergischen Landesbibliothek
                           Stuttgart, Band 3), Teil 1, Vom späten 12. bis zum frühen 14. Jahrhundert
                           (Stuttgart: A. Hiersemann, 1996), p. 140.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Glenn, V., ‘Court patronage in Scotland 1240–1340’ in R. Fawcett
                           (ed.), <title>Medieval art and architecture in the diocese of
                              Glasgow</title>, British Archaeological Association Conference
                           Transactions 23, Historic Scotland (England: British Archaeological
                           Association, 1998), pp. 111–21, at pp. 111–14, pls. XXVIIA–B,
                           XXVIIIA.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Higgitt, J., ‘Manuscripts and libraries in the diocese of Glasgow
                           before the Reformation’ in ibid., pp. 102–10, at pp. 105, 109 n.
                           24.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Maekawa, K., <title>Narrative and experience: innovations in
                              thirteenth-century picture books</title> (Frankfurt am Main: Peter
                           Lang, 2000).</bibl>
                        <bibl>Bennett, A., ‘The transformation of the Gothic psalter in
                           thirteenth-century France’ in Büttner (2004), pp. 211–21, at p. 215 n.
                           23.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Büttner, F. O., ‘Der illuminierte Psalter im Westen’ in Büttner
                           (2004), pp. 1–106, at p. 15 n.</bibl>
                        <bibl>25.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Boardman, S. I., ‘The Gaelic world and the early Stewart court’ in D.
                           Broun and M. MacGregor (eds.), <title>Miorun Mor nan Gall, the great ill-will of
                           the Lowlander: Lowland perceptions of the Scottish Highlands</title> (Chippenham,
                           Wilts.: Antony Rowe, 2006), pp. 83–109, at pp. 89 n. 16, 90 n. 17, 91 n.
                           22, 97 n. 40.</bibl>



                     </listBibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2024-04-17">Adapt full description from Solopova catalogue.</change>
         <change when="2018-10-14" xml:id="MMM">
            <persName>Mitch Fraas</persName> Provenance and acquisition information added using <ref
               target="https://github.com/littlegustv/oxfordupdates/blob/master/test_case_for_oxford_prov.rb"
               >https://github.com/littlegustv/oxfordupdates/blob/master/test_case_for_oxford_prov.rb</ref>
            in collaboration with the <ref target="http://mappingmanuscriptmigrations.org/">Mapping
               Manuscript Migrations</ref> project.</change>
         <change when="2017-07-01">First online publication.</change>
         <change when="2017-05-25">
            <persName>James Cummings</persName> Up-converted the markup using <ref
               target="https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl"
               >https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl</ref>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
