<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xml:id="manuscript_10028" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>MS. Douce 311 adds. 1</title>
            <title type="collection">MSS. Douce</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Description</resp>
               <persName>Andrew Dunning</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </publisher>
            <idno type="msID">MS_Douce_311 adds. 1</idno>
            <idno type="collection">Douce</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="MS_Douce_311" xml:lang="en">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <region type="county">Oxfordshire</region>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <institution>University of Oxford</institution>
                  <repository>Bodleian Library</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">MS. Douce 311 adds. 1</idno>
                  <idno type="ieArk">ark:29072/x05t34sk82wc</idno>
                  <idno type="crArk">ark:29072/x05x21tg666k</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <head>Elevation of the Host, miniature from the Hours of Louis Quarré</head>
               <msContents>
                  <textLang mainLang="zxx">No linguistic content</textLang>
                  <msItem>
                     <locus>(recto)</locus>
                     <title type="desc">Elevation of the Host</title>
                     <note>Miniature cut from MS. Douce 311 between fols. 49 and 50.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem>
                     <locus>(verso)</locus>
                     <note>Blank</note>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="leaf">
                     <supportDesc material="perg">
                        <support>parchment</support>
                        <extent>
                           <measure>1 leaf</measure>
                           <dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                              <height>163</height>
                              <width>90</width>
                           </dimensions>
                        </extent>
                     </supportDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <decoDesc>
                     <decoNote type="miniature">Full-page miniature, attributed to the workshop of the <persName key="person_56525922" role="art">Master of the Prayer Book of Maximilian</persName>, who is likely to be identified with <persName key="person_95781970" role="art">Alexander Bening (died 1519)</persName>.</decoNote>
                  </decoDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="1499" notBefore="1490">1490s</origDate>
                     <origPlace>
                        <country key="place_7024097">Flemish</country>
                     </origPlace>
                  </origin>
                  <provenance><persName key="person_4808" role="fmo">Louis Quarré (died 1519)</persName>, seigneur de la Haye en Hainaut: his overpainted coats of arms (MS. Douce 311, fols. 122v, 130r). One of the escutcheons accompanies a commemoration of St Barbara (fol. 119r), reflecting his marriage to Barbara Croesinck (died 1531).</provenance>
                  <provenance notAfter="1818"><persName key="person_64021324" role="fmo">Dominique Vivant, baron Denon (1747–1825)</persName>: according to the <ref target="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/nyp.33433057513875?urlappend=%3Bseq=120">Williams sale catalogue</ref>, <quote>This most splendid Book of Offices is known as the celebrated Missal belonging to the Baron Denon, late President of the French Institute, who possessed greater advantages than any other person of securing articles of Vertu of the choicest description, from the unlimited confidence placed in him by Bonaparte, in selecting and securing works of art for the National Museum. […] It is undoubtedly one of the most sumptuous Missals ever offered to the public, and was considered by the Baron as one of the gems in his collection.</quote> This was presumably before 1818, when a description of a handful of manuscripts still in his collection does not show any that match the Quarré Hours: <ref target="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/gri.ark:/13960/t24b69w8j?urlappend=%3Bseq=496">Thomas F. Dibdin, <title>A Bibliographical, Antiquarian and Picturesque Tour in France and Germany</title> (London: Shakspeare Press, 1821), 2:454</ref>. Sold to:</provenance>
                  <provenance notAfter="1823"><persName key="person_4809" role="fmo">Robert Heathcote (died 1823)</persName>: according to the Williams catalogue, <quote>purchased from [Denon] by the late Robert Heathcote, esq. a gentleman well known for his distinguished taste.</quote> As-Vijvers (¶ 65) notes that Heathcote purchased another book of hours at Paris in 1816. Heathcote sold both books and art from 1802 onwards: <ref target="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/gri.ark:/13960/t4gn3hr3f"><title>A catalogue of a magnificent, truly superbe, and valuable collection of Italian, French, Flemish and Dutch pictures</title> (London: Philips, 1805)</ref>; <ref target="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/uc2.ark:/13960/t14m92f31?urlappend=%3Bseq=576"><title>Repertorium bibliographicum; or, Some account of the most celebrated British libraries</title> (London: Clarke, 1819), 470–73</ref>; Seymour de Ricci, <title>English Collectors of Books and Manuscripts (1530–1930)</title> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1930), 99. Heathcote sold some books through an intermediary, <quote>Mr Farmer</quote>: David Rogers, <quote>Francis Douce’s Manuscripts: Some Hitherto Unrecognised Provenances</quote>, in <title>Studies in the Book Trade in Honour of Graham Pollard</title>, ed. Richard W. Hunt, Ian G. Philip, and Richard J. Roberts (Oxford: Oxford Bibliographical Society, 1975), 334.</provenance>
                  <provenance notAfter="1827"><persName key="person_35164295405908412379" role="fmo">Theodore Williams (1785–1875)</persName>, vicar of Hendon: it is unclear whether the missing miniatures were still in the volume when he purchased it. Williams, born in Jamaica, was also an avid cactus collector. Sale of his library, <ref target="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/nyp.33433057513875?urlappend=%3Bseq=120"><title>A catalogue of the library of the Rev. Theodore Williams […] which will be sold by auction, by Messrs. Stewart, Wheatley, and Adlard</title> (London: Adlard, 1827), lot 1030 (p. 104)</ref>, 24 April 1827. The description mentions <quote>twelve Large Paintings</quote>, showing that the missing miniatures had been removed by this point.</provenance>
                  <provenance><persName key="person_8323092" role="fmo">John Rushout, second Baron Northwick (1769–1859)</persName>.</provenance>
                  <provenance>Sotheby’s, 21 May 1928, lot 11, sold along with three other miniatures from MS. Douce 311: the Visitation, the Annunciation to the Shepherds, and the Rest on the Flight into Egypt.</provenance>
                  <provenance>Christie’s, 6 December 1989, lot 6; sold to:</provenance>
                  <provenance><persName key="person_4810" role="fmo">Roger De Kesel (1922–2023)</persName>; sold to:</provenance>
                  <acquisition when="2022">Bodleian Library: purchased in 2022 through a Christie’s private treaty sale with the support of Art Fund, the Friends of the Bodleian, and the Friends of the National Libraries.</acquisition>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>Description by Andrew Dunning (2023), drawing extensively on Anne Margreet As-Vijvers, ‘<ref target="https://doi.org/10.5092/jhna.2018.10.1.2">The Missing Miniatures of the Hours of Louis Quarré</ref>’, <title>Journal of Historians of Netherlandish Art</title> 10, no. 1 (March 2018).</source>
                     </recordHist>
                     <availability status="restricted">
                        <p>To ensure its preservation, access to this item is restricted, and readers are asked to work from reproductions and published descriptions as far as possible. If you wish to apply to see the original, please click the request button above. When your request is received, you will be asked to contact the relevant curator outlining the subject of your research, the importance of this item to that research, and the resources you have already consulted.</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <surrogates>
                     <bibl type="digital-facsimile" subtype="full">
                        <ref target="https://digital.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/objects/72a36d00-1321-48e7-9cad-e45a1c85fdbc/">
                           <title>Digital Bodleian</title></ref> <note>(full digital facsimile)</note>
                     </bibl>
                  </surrogates>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2023-12-04"><persName>Andrew Dunning</persName>: new description.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
