<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="manuscript_4632">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>MS. Douce 293</title>
            <title type="collection">MSS. Douce</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp when="2013">Cataloguer</resp>
               <persName>Elizabeth Solopova</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp when="2024">Encoding</resp>
               <persName>Matthew Holford</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </publisher>
            <idno type="msID">MS_Douce_293</idno>
            <idno type="collection">Douce</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="MS_Douce_293" xml:lang="en">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <region type="county">Oxfordshire</region>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <institution>University of Oxford</institution>
                  <repository>Bodleian Library</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">MS. Douce 293</idno>
                  <idno type="ieArk">ark:29072/x02514nm40nt</idno>
                  <idno type="crArk">ark:29072/x08910jv289q</idno>
                  <altIdentifier type="internal">
                     <idno type="SCN">21867</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
               <head>Secular Psalter; England, North, 12th century, third quarter</head>
               <msContents>
                  <msItem class="#liturgica #biblia" n="1" xml:id="MS_Douce_293-item1">
                     <title key="work_14114" type="desc">Secular Psalter</title>
                     <note> Fols. i–ix are paper fly-leaves, blank apart from early modern and
                        modern notes.</note>



                     <note>[item 1 occupies quire I]</note>
                     <msItem n="1">
                        <locus from="1v" to="7r">(fols. 1v–7r)</locus>
                        <note> Calendar (published by Temple, 1985, pp. 36–8), laid out one month
                           per page, approximately half full, not graded. The calendar is written
                           alternately in red, green and blue, used decoratively, rather than for
                           the grading of feasts. Vigils are included from June to December. The
                           calendar contains many Flemish saints and largely corresponds to the
                           calendar of Bruges (Temple, 1985). Among the saints particularly
                           venerated in Bruges are Donatianus (14 October), titular saint of the
                           parish and collegiate church in Bruges, which served as a cathedral in
                           early modern times, and Basil (14 June), patron of the chapel of St Basil
                           and the Holy Blood in Bruges. The calendar contains other saints
                           venerated in the Bruges–Ghent region, such as Amand and Vedast (6
                           February), Ansbertus (9 February) and Macarius of Ghent (Antioch) (9
                           May). The Feast of the Transfiguration is on 26 July (according to
                           Temple, 1985, p. 13, the celebration of this feast on this uncommon date
                           is found in only three other 12th- and 13th-century English calendars,
                           London, British Library, Cotton MS. Tiberius E. IV; Durham, University
                           Library MS. Sel. 6; and Oxford, Bodleian Library MS. Douce 270, all
                           produced for private patrons in the north of England and the Scottish
                           borderland). The calendar also contains several English saints,
                           particularly those venerated in the north of England, such as Wilfrid (24
                           April), John of Beverley (7 May), Paulinus (31 August) and Oswald (5
                           August). Cuthbert is commemorated twice (20 March and 4 September);
                           Kentigern of Glasgow is on 13 January. The calendar also includes Alban
                           (22 June), Edmund (20 November) and Swithin (2 July). The absence of
                           Thomas Becket suggests a date before his canonization in 1173. Botulph
                           and Etheldreda (17 and 23 June) are added in a contemporary hand. The
                           titles ‘papae’ are erased and replaced with ‘episcopi’ in a 16th-century
                           (?) hand. </note>
                     </msItem><note>[item 2 occupies quire II] </note>
                     <msItem n="2">
                        <locus from="8r" to="15v">(fols. 8r–15v)</locus>
                        <note> Prefatory miniatures, painted on both sides of each leaf,
                           illustrating the life of Christ (see ‘Decoration’). </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <note>[items 3–7 occupy quires III–IX]</note>
                     <msItem n="3">
                        <locus from="16r" to="125v">(fols. 16r–125v)</locus>
                        <note> Psalms 1–150, without titles or numbers, written with each verse
                           starting on a new line. The colour of ink changes with each line (see
                           ‘Physical description’ (‘Script’)). Punctuated throughout with punctus
                           elevatus used to mark metrum, and punctus used to mark the ends of verses
                           and minor pauses. The psalms are in the biblical order; the subdivisions
                           within the psalms are not indicated, apart from psalm 118, subdivided
                           into eleven 16-verse units. The unit beginning with ‘Iniquos’ (118: 113)
                           is further subdivided into two 8-verse units (‘Feci iudicium’, 118: 121,
                           begins with a 3-line initial). Fol. 16r is occupied by a full-page
                           Beatus-initial, but the first verse was never filled in (psalm 1 starts
                           on fol. 16v with verse 2, ‘Sed in lege ...’). Many other omitted verses
                           are added between the lines and in the margins in a contemporary hand
                           (e.g. fols. 69r, 123v). Various errors are corrected throughout, probably
                           in the same hand (e.g. substitution on fol. 71r, erasures on fols. 71v
                           and 72r, etc.). Psalms 89–91 are omitted and there is a drypoint note in
                           a 13th-century hand pointing this out in the lower margin on fol. 84r.
                           These psalms are added on fols. 137v–139v in a contemporary hand which
                           corrected the psalter. Psalms 148–150 are written as a single text,
                           though the initial ‘L’ at the beginning of psalm 150 (fol. 125v) is
                           indented, unlike other initials at the beginning of verses. There are
                           textual divisions at psalms 21, 26, 38, 51, 52, 68, 80, 97, 109, 114,
                           121, 126, 131, 137 and 143 (see ‘Decoration’). The initials mark psalms
                           appointed to be read first at Matins during the week in the secular use
                           and, unusually, psalms appointed to be read first at Vespers during the
                           week in the secular use (psalms 114, 121, 126, 131, 137 and 143). Psalm
                           51 is marked with an illuminated initial as is common in psalters from
                           England and the Netherlands (see Carlvant, 1978, pp. 457–72). Psalm 21
                           was also sometimes marked with an illuminated initial in psalters from
                           the Bruges–Ghent region, though this is found in later, 13th- and
                           14th-century psalters, such as MSS. Douce 5–6 (see Carlvant, 1985, p.
                           332, n. 21). </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="4">
                        <locus from="126r" to="131v">(fols. 126r–131v)</locus>
                        <note> Weekly canticles, without titles:<list>
                              <item> (1) Confitebor tibi domine (Isaiah 12);</item>
                              <item> (2) Ego dixi (Isaiah 38: 10–21);</item>
                              <item> (3) Exultauit cor meum (1 Samuel 2: 1–11);</item>
                              <item> (4) Cantemus domino (Exodus 15: 1–20);</item>
                              <item> (5) Domine audiui (Habakkuk 3);</item>
                              <item> (6) Audite celi (Deuteronomy 32: 1–44).</item>
                           </list></note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="5">
                        <locus from="132r" to="136r">(fols. 132r–136r)</locus>
                        <note> Daily canticles, prayers and creeds, without titles:<list>
                              <item> (1) Benedicite omnia opera (fol. 132r);</item>
                              <item> (2) Benedictus dominus deus (fol. 132v);</item>
                              <item> (3) Te deum laudamus (fol. 133r);</item>
                              <item> (4) Magnificat (fol. 134r);</item>
                              <item> (5) Nunc dimittis (fol. 134r);</item>
                              <item> (6) Athanasian Creed (Quicumque uult ...) (fol. 134v).</item>
                           </list></note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="6">
                        <locus from="136r" to="137r">(fols. 136r–137r)</locus>
                        <note> Litany (published by Temple, 1985, p. 18), based on a Continental,
                           northern French (?) model, rather than a litany from Bruges or Ghent. It
                           includes Martial (last) among the apostles; Martin (first), Audomar,
                           Bertin, Remigius, Vedast, Amand and Eligius among the confessors;
                           Benedicta and Eusebia (last) among the virgins. The litany also includes
                           insular saints: Oswald (in third place), Alban and Edmund (last) among
                           the martyrs; Cuthbert (fourth) among the confessors; Brigid (of Kildare
                           (?)) among the virgins. Followed by invocations (not a normal English
                           series) and two collects (fol. 137r): <list>
                              <item> (1) Omnipotens sempiterne deus dirige actus nostros in
                                 beneplacito tuo ...</item>
                              <item> (2) Deus cui omne cor patet et omnis uoluntas loquitur et quem
                                 nullum latet secretum ...</item>
                           </list>
                        </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="7">
                        <locus from="137v" to="139r">(fols. 137v–139r)</locus>
                        <note> Omitted psalms 89–91added in red ink in a contemporary hand. </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <p><secFol> conturbabit eos <locus>(psalter, fol. 17r)</locus></secFol></p>
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="perg">
                        <support> parchment; laid paper fly-leaves</support>
                         <extent> 157 leaves<dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                            <height quantity="258">c. 258</height><width>171</width></dimensions><note>Leaves were trimmed,
                               occasionally causing the loss of decoration </note></extent>
                       
                        <foliation> modern, in pencil; i–ix + 1–82 + 83a–83b + 84–87 + 88a–88b +
                           89–120 + 120* + 121 + 121* + 122–130 + 130* + 131–135 + 136a + 136b +
                           137–142.</foliation>
                        <collation> (fols. i–ix) fols. i and viii are a paper bifolium; fols. ii–vii
                           are paper leaves pasted to i–viii; fol. ix is a paper fly-leaf | (fols.
                           1–7) I (8−1) missing 1 | (fols. 8–123) II–XVI (8) | (fols. 124–129) XVII
                           (6) no loss of text | (fols. 130–136a) XVIII (8) | (fols. 136b–139) XIX
                           (4) | (fols. 140–142) fol. 140 is a paper fly-leaf; fols. 141–142 are a
                           paper bifolium</collation>
                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout columns="1" writtenLines="22"> Ruled in plummet with single vertical and horizontal bounding
                           lines, extending the full height and width of page; prickings often
                           survive; written above the top line; 22 lines per page; written space:
                           <dimensions type="written" unit="mm">
                              <height quantity="185">c. 185</height>
                              <width>106</width>
                           </dimensions></layout>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc>
                     <handNote script="textualisNorthern" execution="formata"> Formal proto-Gothic book script. The colour of ink changes at
                        each line throughout, alternating between red, green and blue, or red,
                        green, blue and brown on some leaves (fols. 96v, 109r). The colour of
                        initials contrasts with the colour of each line and also alternates
                        between red, green and blue. Temple (1985, p. 23), gives London,
                        British Library, Cotton MS. Tiberius E. IV from Winchcombe Abbey near
                        Gloucester as another example of a psalter with colour used
                        decoratively in the calendar, and interprets it as an artistic
                        development within the context of the Anglo- Saxon tradition of
                        inscribing pages with coloured inks</handNote>
                  </handDesc>
                  <decoDesc>
                     <decoNote type="miniature">Prefatory miniatures have English iconographical subjects, but the
                        artist may have also used a Continental model of the 11th century
                        (Kauffmann, 1975; Temple, 1984). Some iconography is untraditional, e.g. the
                        angel holding a book in the Annunciation scene.
                     The miniature cycle is related to the cycles in two other northern
                     English psalters, MS.
                     Gough Liturg. 2 and Copenhagen, Kongelige Bibliotek MS. Thott 143 2o,
                     though it differs considerably in detail (Kauffmann, 1975; Temple, 1984).
                    
                     <list>
                        <item>fol. 8r Annunciation: an angel pointing to a book which he holds in
                           his left hand; the Virgin Mary stretches out her hands to receive the book;
                           architectural background.</item>
                        <item>fol. 8v Nativity: an angel swings censer over the Virgin Mary, who is
                           lying on a bed; a midwife sits by her side; the infant with cruciform halo
                           lies in the manger; heads of an ox and ass; sky with a star.</item>
                        <item>fol. 9r Annunciation to the Shepherds: a barefoot angel with crossed
                           wings appears to three shepherds with staffs, a goat and a sheep.</item>
                        <item>fol. 9v Adoration of the Magi: three crowned kings with gifts walk
                           towards the seated Virgin; the Child is in her lap with cruciform halo, one
                           hand raised in blessing, the other holding a book; architectural
                           background.</item>
                        <item>fol. 10r Flight to Egypt: the Virgin and Child on a donkey; Joseph
                           leading the way; stylized landscape in the background.</item>
                        <item>fol. 10v Presentation in the Temple: the Virgin Mary giving the Child
                           to Simeon; a male attendant (or Joseph?) stands by her side, holding two
                           doves.</item>
                        <item>fol. 11r The Last Supper: Christ and disciples at the table in the
                           upper half of the miniature; Christ washing the feet of St Peter in the
                           lower half.</item>
                        <item>fol. 11v The Betrayal of Christ: Judas embraces Christ; two soldiers
                           with a sword, axe and pike approach.</item>
                        <item>fol. 12r Christ crowned with Thorns: the crown of thorns is placed on
                           Christ’s head by two armed soldiers.</item>
                        <item>fol. 12v Flagellation: Christ tied to a column, blindfolded; two
                           soldiers with scourges on either side.</item>
                        <item> fol. 13r Crucifixion: Christ on the Cross; the Virgin, arms crossed,
                           and St John with beard, holding a book, stand on either side; above the arms
                           of the Cross are two smaller half-figures holding the palms of
                           martyrdom.</item>
                        <item>fol. 13v Disciples at Christ’s Tomb: three apostles standing before
                           the closed tomb; three soldiers in chainmail sleeping on the
                           ground.</item>
                        <item>fol. 14r The Harrowing of Hell: Christ, holding the Cross, stands
                           before Hell’s mouth; naked souls emerge, stretching their arms towards him;
                           Christ holds one of the souls by the hand; an angel appears from the clouds
                           above.</item>
                        <item>fol. 14v Resurrection: the holy women with ointments stand before an
                           angel, seated on an open tomb.</item>
                        <item>fol. 15r The Virgin enthroned: the Virgin, holding a lily, is seated
                           on a throne (decorated with two animal figures); the Child on her lap,
                           holding a book and blessing.</item>
                        <item>fol. 15v Christ enthroned: Christ seated, holding a book and
                           blessing; the symbols of the evangelists in the corners.</item>
                     </list>
                     </decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="border"> Most miniatures are rectangular frames, decorated with acanthus leaves, a
                        few with dragons or grotesques.</decoNote>
                    
                     <decoNote type="histInit">6-line to full-page initials at liturgical divisions. Psalm 97 has an early
                        example of the Annunciation to the Shepherds, though the iconography (the
                        presence of the prophets) is unusual.
                     <list>
                        <item>Psalm 1 fol. 16r (initial B(eatus)) Full-page initial, decorated with
                           interlace, acanthus-leaf and floral designs, a bird, a beast, an animal mask
                           and animal heads; gold rectangular frame.</item>
                        <item>Psalm 21 fol. 29r (initial D(evs)) Gold initial, decorated with plant
                           scrolls and animal mask.</item>
                        <item>Psalm 26 fol. 33r (initial D(ominus)) A young man seated under an
                           arch flanked by two towers; gold background, interlace, animal
                           heads.</item>
                        <item>Psalm 38 fol. 44r (initial D(ixi)) Red initial, decorated with plant
                           scrolls, a beast and a bird on gold background.</item>
                        <item> Psalm 51 fol. 54r (initial Q(vid)) Pink initial, decorated with
                           geometric and acanthus-leaf designs; a winged dragon forming the tail of
                           Q.</item>
                        <item>Psalm 52 fol. 54v (initial D(ixit)) Gold initial, decorated with
                           plant scrolls, acanthus-leaf and floral designs.</item>
                        <item>Psalm 68 fol. 65r (initial S(alvum)) Gold initial, decorated with
                           plant scrolls, acanthus-leaf and floral designs, beasts and a
                           bird.</item>
                        <item>Psalm 80 fol. 78r (initial E(xultate)) Gold initial, decorated with
                           plant scrolls, a beast, acanthus-leaf and floral designs
                           (flaking).</item>
                        <item>Psalm 97 fol. 87v (initial C(antate)) Annunciation to the Shepherds:
                           an angel speaks from above to two shepherds, one holding a staff, flanked by
                           two men, one young, one old, each holding books.</item>
                        <item>Psalm 109 fol. 100v (initial D(ixit)) Christ, naked to the waist,
                           holding the Cross, seated next to the Father, holding a book and blessing;
                           their feet rest on a prostrate nude figure (‘enemies thy
                           footstool’).</item>
                        <item>Psalm 114 fol. 103r (initial D(ilexi)) Blue initial, decorated with
                           plant scrolls, floral designs and animal mask on gold background.</item>
                        <item>Psalm 121 fol. 113v (initial L(etatus)) Body of a winged dragon
                           forming the initial.</item>
                        <item>Psalm 126 fol. 115r (initial N(isi)) Gold initial, decorated with
                           plant scrolls and floral designs.</item>
                        <item> Psalm 131 fol. 116v (initial M(emento)) Gold initial, decorated with
                           plant scrolls, acanthus-leaf and floral designs, and a winged
                           dragon.</item>
                        <item>Psalm 137 fol. 119v (initial C(onfitebor)) Gold initial, decorated
                           with plant scrolls, a beast and a winged grotesque.</item>
                        <item>Psalm 143 fol. 121*v (initial B(enedictus)) Gold initial, decorated
                           with floral designs.</item>
                     </list></decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="decInit">Minor
                        initials at the beginning of psalms and verses. </decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="flourInit">3-line gold initials, with red, blue and green penwork, at the
                        beginning of psalms, canticles and litany.</decoNote>
                    <decoNote type="colInit">1-line alternating red, blue and green initials at the beginning of
                        periods and verses.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="other">Run-over signs in the form of animal heads (fols. 24r,
                        137v).</decoNote>
                  
                   
                   
                  </decoDesc>
                  <bindingDesc>

                     <binding notAfter="1800" notBefore="1700">
                        <p> Red diced calf over pasteboards, 18th century. Single gilt fillet border
                           round the outer edge of covers. Rebacked in the Bodleian in 1983 (‘L. J.
                           L. 12/83’ on fol. 142r). The original spine is pasted to the lower
                           pastedown (brown leather, five bands, five panels with double gilt
                           borders and gilt floral decorations between the bands, gilt lettering
                           ‘ANTIENT || PSALTER’). Marbled paper pastedowns and laid paper
                           fly-leaves. </p>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="1175" notBefore="1150">12th century,
                        third quarter</origDate>
                     <origPlace>
                        <country key="place_7002445">English</country>, <region>North</region>
                        <!--ORIGINAL: English, North-->
                     </origPlace>
                  </origin>
                  <provenance>Written in the north of England and modelled on both English and
                     Continental exemplars: evidence of the calendar, litany and decoration (Temple,
                     1971, 1984, 1985). Produced in a well-organized scriptorium which had access to
                     multiple exemplars and where the scribes’ work was checked and corrected.
                     Probably made for a lay person: the calendar does not represent a liturgical
                     use of any house or diocese, and the litany does not agree with the calendar;
                     decorative approach to the presentation of the text and the calendar; psalms
                     are subdivided according to the secular use. The manuscript is related to two
                     other luxury psalters, the Hunterian Psalter (Glasgow, University Library MS.
                     Hunter U. 3. 2) and the Copenhagen Psalter (Copenhagen, Kongelige Bibliotek MS.
                     Thott 143 2o) (Kauffmann, 1975; Temple, 1984). All three psalters were produced
                     around the same time (Thomas Becket is missing from all three calendars),
                     probably in the north of England. The calendars and litanies are not identical,
                     but similar, and all include saints venerated in the north, such as Cuthbert,
                     Wilfrid, John of Beverley, Paulinus and Oswald. Most of the initials in the
                     Hunterian Psalter are by an artist responsible for some of the initials in the
                     Copenhagen Psalter. The iconography of the principal initials is similar in the
                     Hunterian and Copenhagen psalters, whereas the miniature cycle in Douce 293 is
                     related to that of the Hunterian Psalter. Temple (1985) compares MS. Douce 293
                     with London, British Library, Cotton MS. Tiberius E. IV from Winchcombe Abbey
                     near Gloucester (Worcester diocese). It shares with Douce 293 the decorative
                     use of colour in the calendar, the unusual date for the Feast of the
                     Transfiguration and the presence of northern saints in the calendar, introduced
                     when Worcester and York had the same bishop (972–1010 and again at intervals up
                     to 1062). </provenance>
                  <provenance>Erasure of titles ‘papae’ from the calendar, presumably at the
                     Reformation. </provenance>
                  <provenance notAfter="1834" notBefore="1757" resp="#MMM">
                     <persName key="person_69848690" role="fmo">Francis Douce, 1757–1834</persName>, see ODNB: bookplate on the upper pastedown;
                     autograph on fol. i verso; notes on fols. ii–ix. Watermark ‘1808’, fol. ii. ‘A
                     12’ on the upper pastedown. 
                  </provenance>
                  <acquisition resp="#MMM" when="1834">Bequeathed to the Bodleian in
                     1834</acquisition>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>Elizabeth Solopova, <title>Latin
                              Liturgical Psalters in the Bodleian Library: A Select
                              Catalogue</title> (Oxford, 2013), pp. 30–39. Previously described in
                           the Summary Catalogue. <listBibl>
                              <bibl facs="aaz0602.gif" type="SC">Summary Catalogue, vol. 4, p.
                                 583</bibl>
                           </listBibl>
                        </source>
                     </recordHist>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <surrogates>
                     <bibl subtype="partial" type="digital-facsimile">
                        <ref
                           target="https://digital.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/objects/fe7c6cf9-6a23-4ec4-bb6c-692e36852f6e/">
                           <title>Digital Bodleian</title>
                        </ref>
                        <note>(41 images from 35mm slides)</note>
                     </bibl>
                  </surrogates>
                  <listBibl type="WRAPPER">
                     <listBibl type="PRINT">
                        <head>Select bibliography to 2004:</head>
                        <bibl>Douce catalogue, p. 49.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Summary catalogue, vol. 4, no. 21867.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Frere, no. 447.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Mynors, R. A. B., <title>Durham Cathedral manuscripts to the end of
                              the twelfth century</title> (Oxford: Printed for the Dean and Chapter
                           of Durham Cathedral at the University Press, 1939), p. 47.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Nordenfalk, C., <title>‘Insulare und kontinentale
                              Psalterillustrationen aus dem XIII. Jahrhundert’, Acta Archaeologica
                              10</title> (1939), pp. 107–20, at p. 116.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Latin liturgical manuscripts (1952), no. 44.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Boase, T. S. R., <title>English art, 1100–1216</title> (Oxford:
                           Clarendon Press, 1953), p. 245.</bibl>
                        <bibl>S. J. P. van Dijk, <title>Latin Liturgical Manuscripts in the Bodleian
                           Library, Oxford, vol. 2: Office Books</title> (typescript, 1957),
                           <citedRange unit="page" from="41" to="41">p. 41</citedRange></bibl>
                        <bibl>Temple, E., ‘The twelfth-century psalter in the Bodleian Library, Ms.
                           Douce 293’, unpublished Ph.D. thesis, London University, 1971.</bibl>
                        <bibl><ref target="https://catalog.hathitrust.org/Record/000468709">Pächt
                           and Alexander</ref> (1966–73), vol. 3, no. 168, pl. XVII.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Sandler (1974), p. 169.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Kauffmann, C. M., <title>Romanesque manuscripts, 1066–1190, Survey of
                              Manuscripts Illuminated in the British Isles 3</title> (London: H.
                           Miller, 1975), no. 94.</bibl>
                        <bibl>McKinnon, J. W., ‘Canticum novum in the Isabella book’,
                              <title>Medievalia</title> 2 (1976), pp. 207–22, at p. 209 and fig. 1.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Alexander, J. J. G., ‘Scribes as artists: the arabesque initial
                              in twelfth-century English manuscripts’ in M. B. Parkes and A. G.
                              Watson (eds.), <title>Medieval scribes, manuscripts and libraries: essays
                              presented to N. R. Ker</title> (London: Scolar Press, 1978), pp.
                           87–116, at p. 90 n. 15.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Temple, E., ‘Some aspects of the iconography of MS. Douce 293’,
                              <title>BLR</title> 11 (1984), pp. 211–19.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Wormald, F., ‘The miniatures in the Gospels of St. Augustine’ in J. J.
                           G. Alexander, T. J. Brown and J. Gibbs (eds.), <title>Francis Wormald: collected writings</title>
                           (London; New York: H. Miller in conjunction with OUP, 1984), vol. 1,
                           Studies in medieval art from the sixth to the twelfth centuries, pp.
                           13–35, at p. 17 n. 31.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Zarnecki, G., Holt, J. and Holland, T. (eds.), <title>English
                              Romanesque art 1066–1200: catalogue of an exhibition held at Hayward
                              Gallery, London, 5 April–8 July 1984</title> (London: Arts Council of
                           Great Britain in association with Weidenfeld &amp; Nicolson, 1984), no.
                           74.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Carlvant, K. B. E., ‘Trends in Bruges illumination until 1260,
                              a propos a psalter connected with Oostkerke’, <title>Archives et
                              bibliothèques de Belgique 56</title> (1985), pp. 321–63.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Temple, E., ‘The calendar of the Douce psalter’, <title>BLR</title> 12
                           (1985), pp. 13–38.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Gibson, Heslop and Pfaff (1992), p. 28 n. 9.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Riedmaier, J., <title>Die ‘Lambeth-Bibel’: Struktur und Bildaussage
                              einer englischen Bibelhandschrift</title> (Frankfurt am Main: Peter
                           Lang, 1994), p. 342.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Bynum, C. W., <title>The resurrection of the body in Western
                              Christianity, 200–1336</title> (New York: Columbia University Press,
                           1995), p. 193 n. 121.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Martin, N. G., <title>Reading the Huntingfield Psalter (Pierpont
                              Morgan Library manuscript M. 43): devotional literacy and an English
                              psalter</title> (Ann Arbor, MI: UMI, 1995), pp. 111, 196–9.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Henry, A., ‘Daring conflation? A difficult image in the Genesis
                              sequence of the Eton roundels (Eton College, Ms 177, f. 2r)’ in C.
                              Hourihane (ed.), <title>Image and belief: studies in celebration of the
                              eightieth anniversary of the Index of Christian Art</title>
                           (Princeton, NJ: Index of Christian Art, Dept. of Art and Archaeology,
                           Princeton University, 1999), pp. 169–203, at p. 180.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Wolter-von dem Knesebeck, H., <title>Der Elisabethpsalter in Cividale
                              del Friuli: Buchmalerei für den Thüringer Landgrafenhof zu Beginn des
                              13. Jahrhunderts</title> (Berlin: Deutscher Verlag für
                           Kunstwissenschaft, 2001), p. 184.</bibl>
                        <bibl> Bennett, A., <title>‘The transformation of the Gothic Psalter in
                              thirteenth-century France’ in Büttner</title> (2004), pp. 211–21, 211
                           n. 3.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Büttner, F. O., <title>‘Der illuminierte Psalter im Westen’ in
                              Büttner</title> (2004), pp. 1–106, at p. 29 n. 146.</bibl>
                        <bibl/>
                     </listBibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2024-03-06">Encode full description from Solopova catalogue.</change>
         <change when="2018-10-14" xml:id="MMM">
            <persName>Mitch Fraas</persName> Provenance and acquisition information added using <ref
               target="https://github.com/littlegustv/oxfordupdates/blob/master/test_case_for_oxford_prov.rb"
               >https://github.com/littlegustv/oxfordupdates/blob/master/test_case_for_oxford_prov.rb</ref>
            in collaboration with the <ref target="http://mappingmanuscriptmigrations.org/">Mapping
               Manuscript Migrations</ref> project.</change>
         <change when="2017-07-01">First online publication.</change>
         <change when="2017-05-25">
            <persName>James Cummings</persName> Up-converted the markup using <ref
               target="https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl"
               >https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl</ref>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
