<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/msDesc/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/msDesc/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xml:id="manuscript_000000" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Brasenose College MS. 10</title>
            <title type="collection">Brasenose College MSS.</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Description</resp>
               <persName>Elizabeth Solopova</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Revision</resp>
               <persName>Andrew Dunning</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </publisher>
            <idno type="msID">Brasenose_College_MS_10</idno>
            <idno type="collection">Brasenose_College</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="Brasenose_College_MS_10" xml:lang="en">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <repository>Brasenose College</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">Brasenose College MS. 10</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents>
                  <textLang mainLang="enm" otherLangs="la">Middle English with Latin</textLang>
                  <msItem>
                     <note>Fols. 1–2 are paper flyleaves, blank apart from early modern and modern notes (see Provenance).</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="1">
                     <locus from="3r" to="12v">(fols. 3r–12v)</locus>
                     <note>[item 1 occupies quires I–II]</note>
                     <title type="desc">Table of lections of Type II</title>
                     <rubric>Here bigynneþ a rule þat telliþ in whiche chapitris of þe bible ȝe [m]oun fynde þe lessons pistlis &amp; gospels þat ben rad bi al þe ȝeer a[.]oute <note>[aloute (?)]</note> in holi chirche aftir þe vss of Salisbiry.</rubric>
                     <note>Comprises the temporal, the proper, common and commemorations. The proper is short, the only non-biblical saints included are Nicholas, George, Seven Brothers, the translation of Thomas Becket, Lawrence and Clement. The entries consist of a date in red, abbreviated reference to a book and chapter of the Bible, an indexing letter in red, the opening words of a reading, <q>ende</q> in red, the closing words of a reading and double strokes. Commemorations are in the following order Our Lady, Trinity, the Holy Ghost, cross, angels, <q>ffor briþeren and sistren and for salus populi</q>, peace, clear weather, rain, <q>In tyme of bateils</q>, <q>for him silf</q>, <q>ffor pestilence of beestis</q>, <q>for weifering and pilgrimis</q>, weddings, dead, sick and sinners. Readings omitted by the original scribe are added in the margins in a contemporary hand.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="2">
                     <locus from="13r" to="254r">(fols. 13r–254r)</locus>
                     <note>[item 2 occupies quires III–XXXII]</note>
                     <title type="desc">New Testament in the <title key="work_13437" type="desc">Later Version of the Wycliffite Bible</title>, with James and 1 Peter in the <title key="work_13434" type="desc">Earlier Version of the Wycliffite Bible</title></title>
                     <note>Contains the usual prologues, apart from the prologue to James that is not included. James is also the only book that does not have a penwork border (see Decoration). Usual rubrics, e.g., <q>Here endiþ þe gospel of mathu &amp; bigynniþ þe prolog on mark</q>, <q>þis seiþ Ierom in his prolog on mark &amp; bigynniþ þe gospel of mark</q>
                        <locus from="45v" to="46r">(fols. 45v–46r)</locus>. John ends on fol. 125rb and the rest of the second column on this leaf is left blank; Romans continues on fol. 125v. Running titles on both rectos and versos consisting of abbreviated titles of books in red. Chapter numbers as Roman numerals preceded by blue paraphs. Many corrections in the original or contemporary hands. Indexing letters in the margins entered at the beginnings of lections rather than consistently; the ends of lections are marked with double strokes in the margins. Red paraphs mark sections within the text, often the beginnings of lections. The beginnings and ends of lections are also highlighted with yellow wash.</note>
                     <note>Added material within the text is occasionally underlined in red. No glosses in the margins with rare exceptions (e.g., fol. 154r). Pointing hand at <q>Blessid be pore men in spiryt…</q> (Matthew 5, fol. 6v).</note>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="perg">
                        <support>poor quality parchment with holes and repairs, paper flyleaves</support>
                        <extent>258 leaves, <foreign>c.</foreign><dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                              <height>182</height>
                              <width>130</width>
                           </dimensions>; leaves were trimmed in rebinding, occasionally causing the loss of text and decoration in the margins</extent>
                        <foliation>modern in pencil, 1–258</foliation>
                        <collation><locus from="1" to="2">(fols. 1–2)</locus> paper flyleaves | <locus from="3" to="8">(fols. 3–8)</locus> I (6) | <locus from="9" to="10">(fols. 9–10)</locus> II (4) | <locus from="11" to="244">(fols. 11–244)</locus> III–XXXI (8) | <locus from="245" to="256">(fols. 245–256)</locus> XXXII (12) | <locus from="257" to="258">(fols. 257–258)</locus> paper flyleaves. <catchwords>Catchwords survive;</catchwords>
                           <signatures>quire signatures run consistently starting on fol. 11 (the beginning of Matthew): a–z, &amp;, (con-), a–e.</signatures>
                           <secFol><q>mt .ij.</q>
                              <locus from="4r" to="4r">(fol. 4r)</locus></secFol>
                        </collation>
                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout columns="2" writtenLines="33">ruled for two columns, with single vertical and horizontal bounding lines extending the full height and width of page; another set of double bounding lines in all margins; 33 lines per page; written space: <foreign>c.</foreign><dimensions type="ruled" unit="mm">
                              <height>135</height>
                              <width>87</width>
                           </dimensions></layout>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc>
                     <handNote script="textualisNorthern">textura, brown ink</handNote>
                  </handDesc>
                  <decoDesc>
                     <decoNote type="flourInit">3- to 5-line blue initials with red penwork and one-sided penwork borders at the beginnings of books.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="flourInit">2-line blue initials with red penwork at the beginnings on prologues and chapters.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="rubrication">Rubrics in red ink.</decoNote>
                  </decoDesc>
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <binding notAfter="1700" notBefore="1600">
                        <p>Worn dark leather over pasteboard, 17th century (?), with an added (?) 18th-century (?) blind roll border round the outer edge of both covers. Rebacked with the original spine relaid. Red label on spine with gilt fillet-line border and gilt lettering ‘TINDALL’S <lb/> TRANSLATION <lb/> OF N. TEST. MS.’. The label was added in Brasenose College (other college manuscripts have a similar label, e.g., Brasenose College MS. f. 2 and Brasenose College MS. f. 3). Brasenose paper label on spine with ‘MS. <lb/> Brasenose Coll. <lb/> E 10’. Flyleaves of laid paper with watermark (unicorn standing on a cartouche with letters ‘FD’). Similar watermarks in Briquet (1907), nos 10313–10346, date from 1496–1600, most from the second half of the 16th century. Edges of textblock speckled red (18th-century addition (?)).</p>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origPlace>
                        <country key="place_7002445">England</country>
                     </origPlace>
                     <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="1425" notBefore="1400">15th century, first quarter</origDate>
                     <p>Mixed the Earlier Version of the Wycliffite Bible and the Later Version of the Wycliffite Bible text, poor quality parchment, modest decoration.</p>
                     <p>Dialect survey: <list>
                           <item>oni(10), ech(10), fier(10), ȝoue(1)/ȝouun(9), lif(10), lik(10), miche(10), sai(9) (sg.), saien(6) (pl.), silf(10), sich(3)/siche(5)/suche(1), þouȝ(8), þoruȝ(10)</item>
                           <item>-iþ(8)/-eþ(2) (pres.ind.3sg.), -en(10) (pres.ind.pl.), -inge(5)/-ynge(5) (pres. part.), she(10) (3sg.fem.pronoun, nom.), þei(10) (3pl.pronoun, nom.), hem(10) (3pl.pronoun, oblique), her(4)/here(6) (3pl.pronoun, possessive)</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                  </origin>
                  <provenance>Erased, presumably medieval, ownership inscription on fol. 256v: <q>L[iber] (?)…[de](?)…</q>.</provenance>
                  <provenance>Sixteenth-century (?) owner interested in Eucharist. Notes in the margin, partially cropped off and therefore predating the present binding: <q>Institucion … [o]f Christe</q>
                     <locus>(fol. 41v, next to a description of Eucharist at the Last Supper in Matthew 26)</locus>, <q>…he Supper [o]f yᵉ lorde</q>
                     <locus>(fol. 95v, next to <q>where I shal eete pask with my disciplis</q> in a description of the Last Supper in Luke 22)</locus>. Verse numbers added on fols. 13v–19r in an early modern hand.</provenance>
                  <provenance>Translation of Thomas Becket erased, presumably at Reformation.</provenance>
                  <provenance>Seventeenth-century binding, possibly altered in the 18th century.</provenance>
                  <provenance><persName key="person_26951736" role="fmo">Edward Hill</persName> (1589–1669), Vicar of Huddersfield, Yorkshire, from 2 September 1619, see Dale (1910), pp. 76–7. Listed by Baines (1871), vol. 2, p. 433, as the only vicar with this name. Foster, J., <title>Alumni Oxonienses: the members of the University of Oxford, 1715–1886</title>, 4 vols (London: Joseph Foster; Oxford: Parker and Co., 1887–88) records an entry for his son: ‘Hill, John – s. Edward, of Huddersfield, Yorks, sacerd. Brasenose Coll., matric. 16 Oct., 1635, aged 16; perhaps B.A. from Gloucester Hall 18 June, 1639’.</provenance>
                  <acquisition when="1635">Brasenose College: given by Edward Hill, presumably after 1635, when his son entered Brasenose. <q>Liber Aulæ Regiæ &amp; Collegij de Brasenose. Ex dono Edvardi Hill Vicarij de Huddersfield in Comitat’ Ebor:</q>
                     <locus from="2r" to="2r">(fol. 2r)</locus>, 17th century, added in Brasenose (other college manuscripts have donors recorded on flyleaves in Latin in a similar way). Bookplate with Brasenose arms on the upper pastedown. Fragments of an earlier paper bookplate on the upper pastedown with ‘T’(?) at the end of a line (Brasenose bookplate of a different design (?)). ‘Will: Tindalls translation’ on fol. 1r, 17th century, probably added in Brasenose (other college manuscripts have similar descriptions of contents on flyleaves). Brasenose shelfmarks: ‘X’ (upper pastedown); ‘J. 2. 15’ <locus>(fol. 1r and edge of textblock)</locus>; ‘East Closet 1.’ <locus from="1r" to="1r">(fol. 1r)</locus>. Not listed in Bernard’s catalogue of 1697 which may not have been exhaustive.</acquisition>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>Elizabeth Solopova, <title><ref target="https://jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1gn6cmr">Manuscripts of the Wycliffite Bible in the Bodleian and Oxford College Libraries</ref></title>, Exeter Medieval Texts and Studies (Liverpool: Liverpool University Press, 2016), no. 47.</source>
                     </recordHist>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>Bernard, E., <title>Catalogi librorum manuscriptorum Angliae et Hiberniae in unum collecti cum indice alphabetico</title> (Oxford, 1697).</bibl>
                     <bibl>Forshall, J. and Madden, F. (eds), <title>The Holy Bible … in the earliest English versions made from the Latin Vulgate by John Wycliffe and his followers</title>, 4 vols (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1850), vol. 1, p. li.</bibl>
                     <bibl>Coxe, H. O., <title>Catalogus codicum mss. qui in collegiis aulisque Oxoniensibus hodie adservantur</title>, 2 vols (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1852), vol. 2, <title>Catalogus codicum MSS. Collegii Aenei Nasi</title>, pp. 2–3.</bibl>
                     <bibl>Baines, T., <title>Yorkshire, past and present: a history and a description of the three ridings of the great county of York, from the earliest ages to the year 1870</title>, 2 vols (London: W. Mackenzie, 1871).</bibl>
                     <bibl>Dale, B., <title>Yorkshire puritanism and early nonconformity, illustrated by the lives of the ejected ministers</title> (Bradford, 1910).</bibl>
                     <bibl>Ogilvie-Thomson, S. J., <title>Index of Middle English prose</title>, 18 vols (Cambridge, 1984– ), Handlist VIII (1991), p. 15. Dove, M., <title>The first English Bible: the text and context of the Wycliffite versions</title> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2007), p. 301.</bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2023-04-19">Add Solopova description.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
