<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/msDesc/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/msDesc/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xml:id="manuscript_00000" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Corpus Christi College MS. 4</title>
            <title type="collection">Corpus Christi College MSS.</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Description</resp>
               <persName>Elizabeth Solopova</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Revision</resp>
               <persName>Andrew Dunning</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </publisher>
            <idno type="msID">Corpus_Christi_College_MS_4</idno>
            <idno type="collection">Corpus Christi College</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="Corpus_Christi_College_MS_4" xml:lang="en">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <repository>Corpus Christi College</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">Corpus Christi College MS. 4</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents>
                  <textLang mainLang="enm" otherLangs="la">Middle English with Latin</textLang>
                  <msItem>
                     <note>Fols. i–ii are originally blank parchment flyleaves (see Provenance).</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="1">
                     <locus>(fols. 1r–6r)</locus>
                     <note>[items 1–2 occupy quire I]</note>
                     <title type="desc">Table of lections of Type II</title>
                     <note>Without a rubric. Includes the temporal, proper, common and commemorations. The entries consist of a liturgical occasion in red, abbreviated reference to a book and chapter of the Bible, an indexing letter in red, the opening words of a reading, <q>ende</q> in red and the closing words of a reading. The proper is short, and includes, apart from the biblical saints, Nicholas, George, the Translation of Martin, Seven Brothers, Abdon, Cyriac and his fellows, the Eve, Day and Octave of Lawrence, Denis and Clement. Penwork initials at Epiphany, Easter, Ascension, Pentecost, Trinity, Corpus Christi, Candlemas, John the Baptist, Assumption, Nativity of our Lady and All Saints. Does not include Wednesday after the 25th Sunday after Trinity and the feast of the relics. Commemorations are in the following order: Trinity, Holy Ghost, cross, Our Lady, <q>ffor breþeren &amp; sisters &amp; good doers</q>, peace, clear weather, rain, <q>ffor batel &amp; pestilence</q>, angels, <q>A prest for hym seif</q>, <q>ffor pestilence of beestis</q>, <q>ffor weie ferynge men</q>, <q>ffor oure synnes</q>, sick, weddings, pilgrims and dead. The feast of Thomas Becket in December is erased.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="2">
                     <locus>(fol. 6v)</locus>
                     <note>A list of Old Testament and New Testament books in English, in the hand of the original scribe, in the usual order, with a rubric <q>þese be þe names of þe bokis of þe bible</q>. New Testament has a further rubric <q>þese ben þe names of þe bokis of þe newe lawe</q>. Includes 1 and 2 Ezra only, followed by Tobit; <q>Corynth</q>’ presumably represents both 1 and 2 Corinthians, and <q>Tessalonicences</q> both 1 and 2 Thessalonians. Genesis–Deuteronomy are joined by a bracket with a heading <q>v bokis of moyses lawe</q>, Proverbs–Ecclesiasticus with a heading <q>Salomon</q>, Matthew–John with a heading <q>iiij euang</q>’, Romans–Hebrews with a heading <q>Paul</q>.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="3">
                     <locus>(fols. 7r–386v)</locus>
                     <note>[item 3 occupies quires II–XLIX]</note>
                     <title key="work_10458" type="desc">Old and New Testaments in the Earlier Version of the Wycliffite Bible</title>
                     <note>With Jerome’s prefatory epistles, <q>Broþer ambrose to me…</q> and <q>I haue takun desired epistlis…</q>, and usual prologues. Includes a second prologue to Job, <q>Forsoþe if I shulde make a iounket…</q>. No prologues in New Testament. The prologue to Joshua <q>At þe last endid þe fyue…</q> is preceded by a rubric <q>Here endiþ þe book of deuteronomi And nowe bigyneþ þe prolog of iosue &amp; of iudicum &amp; of ruth</q>
                        <locus>(fol. 68r)</locus>; the prologue to 1 Kings is preceded by a rubric <q>Here bigynneþ þe prolog of þe foure bokis of kyngis</q>
                        <locus>(fol. 84v)</locus>. The following rubrics occur at other prologues: <q>Here endiþ þe fourþ book of kyngis and now bigynneþ þe prolog of twey bookis of paralipomenon</q> (the first prologue to 1 Chronicles, fol. 124r); <q>Here eendiþ þe first book of paralipomenon and now bigynneþ þe proloog of þe secounde book</q> (prologue to 2 Chronicles, fol. 133v); <q>þe proloog of þe þree bookis of esdre</q> (the first prologue to 1 Ezra, fol. 145r); <q>Here begynneþ þe proloog in þe book of ecclesiastes þat is to seye þe book of talker to þe puple or to gidre cleper</q> (prologue to Ecclesiastes). The prayer of Manasseh follows chapter 36 of 2 Chronicles without a break; a rubric <q>þis preyer of manasses not in ebrew</q> is in black and not underlined <locus>(fol. 145r)</locus>.</note>
                     <note>Running titles in red (not in psalms), on both rectos and versos, consisting of abbreviated titles of books only. In New Testament starting with fol. 343r running titles are in black, most underlined in red. Rubrics in red (in New Testament often in black underlined in red), e.g., <q>Here endiþ genesis and now bigynne exodus</q>
                        <locus>(fol. 24r)</locus>. The prefatory epistles have no rubrics. Chapter numbers in red as Roman numerals and in the margins in black by the scribe. Alternating red and blue paragaphs at the start of sections within the text on fols. 7r–30r and in New Testament; only occasionally elsewhere in Old Testament. Added material within the text is consistently underlined in red or black starting with Baruch 3 and until the end of New Testament; before Baruch 3 it is underlined only very rarely (the first underlining occurs at 2 Kings 24:25, fol. 104r). Corrections in the margins and over erasures in the text in the original or contemporary hands. Names of Hebrew letters in red in Proverbs 31 and Lamentations of Jeremiah. Speakers identified in red in the Song of Song. No marginal glosses in the original hand with very few exceptions. Added glosses <q>of images</q> in the margins Deuteronomy 7, 8, 13, 27; Wisdom 13, 15; Isaiah 40, 44; Jeremiah 8, 10; Baruch 6; Ezekiel 7, 14, 16, 20; Micah 5; and Habakkuk 2. Added glosses <q>of idols</q> in the margins of Isaiah 1, 2; Jeremiah 32; and Ezekiel 18 in the same 15th-century hand. Latin incipits of passages occasionally written out in the margins in the original or contemporary hand, some at the beginnings of lections, e.g., <q>ab initio &amp; ante secula</q>
                        <locus>(fol. 222v)</locus> at the start of the reading for the Eve of the Assumption (Ecclesiasticus 24) and commemorations of Our Lady. Occasionally crossreferences to other books of the Bible and <q>nota</q> in the margins in the original hand. Rubrics concerning the differences between the Latin and Hebrew texts in Daniel.</note>
                     <note>Psalms are preceded with a rubric <q>The <sic>boob</sic> bygynneth of ympnys and solitarie spechis of dauyd þe profete of crist</q> and begin with 3-line initials. Laid out with verses starting on a new line with alternating red or blue 1-line initials. Decorative line endings in red and blue ink. The psalms are preceded by titles in red, Latin incipits in black, underlined in red, and numbers in red or black Roman or Arabic numerals. The Latin incipits are longer than usual, sometimes comprising a whole verse and are written out as part of the text, rather than in the margins; the psalm numbers are in the margins. The initials are those of the Latin text. There are larger ‘puzzle’ initials and penwork borders at psalms 26, 38, 52, 68, 80, 97, 109. The names of Hebrew letters in red are at the beginnings of sections of psalm 118. Psalms 119–132 have a rubric <q>þe songe of grees</q>.</note>
                     <note>Old Testament ends on fol. 310v where the end of the first column and the second column are left blank; the New Testament starts on a new leaf of a new quire and ends in the middle of the first column on fol. 386v; the rest of this folio was originally blank (see Provenance).</note>
                     <finalRubric>Here endiþ apocalips</finalRubric>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem>
                     <note>Fols. 387–8 are ruled, but originally blank (see Provenance).</note>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="perg">
                        <support>parchment</support>
                        <extent>390 leaves, <foreign>c.</foreign><dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                              <height>440</height>
                              <width>300</width>
                           </dimensions>; 130 mm thick; leaves were trimmed in rebinding occasionally causing the loss of decoration</extent>
                        <foliation>modern in pencil: i–ii + 1–388</foliation>
                        <collation><locus>(fols. i–ii)</locus> paper and parchment flyleaves | <locus>(fols. 1)</locus> I (6) | <locus>(fols. 7–382)</locus> II–XLVIII (8) | <locus>(fols. 383-lower pastedown)</locus> XLIX (8–1(?)) the 7th leaf is the lower pastedown, the 8th leaf cancelled. <catchwords>Catchwords survive;</catchwords>
                           <signatures>quire signatures often survive and run consecutively a–z + ? + 1 + aa-nn; a new series starts in New Testament <locus>(fol. 311)</locus>, [a]-k.</signatures>
                           <secFol><q>Exodi cciiij</q> (table of lections, fol. 2r); <q>erþe of</q> (prefatory epistle, fol. 8r)</secFol>
                        </collation>
                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout columns="2" writtenLines="59 60">ruled for two columns, with single vertical and horizontal bounding lines extending the full height and width of page; 59–60 lines per page; written space: <foreign>c.</foreign><dimensions type="ruled" unit="mm">
                              <height>315</height>
                              <width>205</width>
                           </dimensions></layout>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc>
                     <handNote script="textualisNorthern">textura, black and brown ink</handNote>
                  </handDesc>
                  <decoDesc>
                     <decoNote type="flourInit">7- to 9-line red and blue ‘puzzle’ initials decorated with penwork and red, and blue and purple penwork borders at the beginnings of books.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="flourInit">3-line blue initials with red penwork at the beginnings of prologues and chapters.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="rubrication">Rubrics in red ink.</decoNote>
                  </decoDesc>
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <binding notAfter="1700" notBefore="1600">
                        <p>Brown leather over wood boards, 17th century. Gilt and blind fillet-line border round the outer edge of both covers. Rectangular figure at the centre of both covers with gilt corner-pieces and gilt panel in the middle. Brass panels with bosses at the centre and originally at the outer corners of both covers, only one surviving on the lower cover. Originally two brass clasps, one now missing. Rebacked with a modern spine. Sewn on nine bands. Parchment pastedowns and flyleaves. Gilt edges of textblock (a later addition?). Formerly chained.</p>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origPlace>
                        <country key="place_7002445">England</country>
                     </origPlace>
                     <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="1425" notBefore="1400">15th century, first quarter</origDate>
                     <p>Dialect survey: <list>
                           <item>Exodus, Psalms, Isaiah <list>
                                 <item>eny(10), ech(4)/eche(6), fier(9)/fyer(1), ȝouun(5)/ȝouen(1)/ȝeuen(3)/ȝeue(1), lijf(10), lijk(5)/lyik(1)/liyk(2)/like(1)/liic(1), myche(10), sawȝ(9)/seeȝ(1) (sg.), seen(5)/seyn(1) (pl.), self(3)/silf(5)/seluen(2), siche(1), þurȝ(10)</item>
                                 <item>-iþ(5)/eþ(5) (pres.ind.3sg.), -en(10) (pres.ind.pl.), -ynge(10) (pres.part.), she(10) (3sg.fem.pronoun, nom.), þei(10) (3pl.pronoun, nom.), hem(10) (3pl.pronoun, oblique), her(10) (3pl.pronoun, possessive) Also <foreign>slewȝ</foreign> ‘slew’, <foreign>snowȝ</foreign> ‘snow’, <foreign>ȝow</foreign> ‘you’.</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                           <item>Matthew <list>
                                 <item>any(1)/ony(9), ech(8)/eche(2), fier(10), ȝouun(10), lijf(8)/lyif(1)/lif(1), lijk(4)/ like(1)/liche(5), myche(9)/miche(1), say(5)/saie(1) (sg.), saien(5) (pl.), silf(10), such(1)/suche(4)/sich(2)/siche(2), þouȝ(2)/þowȝ(1), þurȝ(2)/þuruȝ(1)/þuroȝ(1)/ þurou(4)/þurow(1)</item>
                                 <item>-iþ(5)/eþ(5) (pres.ind.3sg.), -en(10) (pres.ind.pl.), -ynge(9)/-inge(1) (pres. part.), she(9)/sche(1) (3sg.fem.pronoun, nom.), þei(10) (3pl.pronoun, nom.), hem(10) (3pl.pronoun, oblique), her(10) (3pl.pronoun, possessive) Also <foreign>knew<ex>e</ex></foreign> ‘knew’, <foreign>ȝou</foreign> ‘you’, <foreign>narouȝ</foreign> ‘narrow’.</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                  </origin>
                  <provenance>Lower margin of fol. 1 is cut away, probably to remove an ownership inscription.</provenance>
                  <provenance><q><persName>Thomas Reuely</persName></q>, early 16th century <locus>(fol. i recto)</locus>, see Hope (1997), pp. 260–4.</provenance>
                  <provenance><q>Nunc dimittis</q> and <q>Ecce nunc benedici te dominum</q> with music for four parts added in a 16th-century hand on the upper pastedown. Lyric <q>The sight which ferst my hart did strayne</q> (<title>IMEV</title> 3461.8, <title>NIMEV</title> 3461.8, <ref target="http://dimev.net/record.php?recID=5462"><title>DIMEV</title> 5462</ref>) in the same hand, seven lines, ed. Robbins (1968) <locus>(fol. i verso)</locus>; text written three times, each with musical notation for a different part.</provenance>
                  <provenance>A list entitled <q>The Interpretation of certaine harde wordes in this booke</q> containing 48 Middle English words with English translation in a 16th-century hand.</provenance>
                  <provenance><persName>Thomas Moulder</persName>, 16th century (upper pastedown, fol. 387r). At the end of the Apocalypse in his hand: <q>Anime eorum et Omnium fidelium defunctorum per universam dei misericordiam in pace requiescant Amen So be it</q>
                     <locus>(fol. 386v)</locus>. Imperfect transcript of a deed mentioning William Mason of Leighton Buzzard: <q>…Willelmus Mason nuper de Leighton Bussard in coun. Bedd’ yeman…</q>. Pen trials on fols. 386v, 387r, 388r.</provenance>
                  <provenance><persName>Anthony Langford</persName>: <q>Liber collegij Corporis Christi Oxon’ ex dono Magistri Antonij Langford Generosi, et Reverendi in Christo Patris Thomae /Bilson Episcopi Wintoniensis Secretarij. December 8 1615</q>
                     <locus>(fol. 1r)</locus>; for <persName key="person_37264693">Thomas Bilson</persName> (1546/7–1616), bishop of Winchester; see <title>Oxford Dictionary of National Biography</title>.</provenance>
                  <acquisition when="1615">Corpus Christi College, Oxford: donated by Langford in 1615. Earlier shelfmarks: ‘Nº. 1471. 4.’; ‘W. A 4.5’ <locus>(fol. ii verso)</locus>.</acquisition>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>Elizabeth Solopova, <title><ref target="https://jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1gn6cmr">Manuscripts of the Wycliffite Bible in the Bodleian and Oxford College Libraries</ref></title>, Exeter Medieval Texts and Studies (Liverpool: Liverpool University Press, 2016), no. 51.</source>
                     </recordHist>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>Forshall, J. and Madden, F. (eds), <title>The Holy Bible … in the earliest English versions made from the Latin Vulgate by John Wycliffe and his followers</title>, 4 vols (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1850), vol. 1, p. li; siglum <title>A</title>.</bibl>
                     <bibl>Coxe, H. O., <title>Catalogus codicum mss. qui in collegiis aulisque Oxoniensibus hodie adservantur</title>, 2 vols (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1852), vol. 2, <title>Catalogus codicum MSS. Collegii Corporis Christi</title>, p. 2.</bibl>
                     <bibl>Skeat, W. W., ‘On the dialect of Wycliffe’s Bible’, <title>Transactions of the Philological Society</title> (1895), pp. 212–19 at p. 216.</bibl>
                     <bibl>Lindberg, C. (ed.), <title>The earlier version of the Wycliffite Bible,</title> 8 vols (Stockholm: Almqvist &amp; Wiksell, 1959–97), vol. 1 (1959), pp. 15–16; vol. 2 (1961), p. 18; vol. 3 (1963), pp. 18–19; vol. 4 (1965), pp. 16–17; vol. 8 (1997), p. 29.</bibl>
                     <bibl>Brown, C., Robbins, R. H., Cutler, J. L., <title>Supplement to the index of Middle English verse</title> (Lexington: University of Kentucky Press, 1965), no. 3461.8.</bibl>
                     <bibl>Robbins, R. H., ‘Mirth in manuscripts’, <title>Essays and Studies</title> 21 (1968), pp. 1–28 at p. 7.</bibl>
                     <bibl>Samuels, M. L., ‘The dialects of MS. Bodley 959’ [1969], reprinted in McIntosh, A., Samuels, M. L. and Laing, M. (eds), <title>Middle English dialectology: essays on some principles and problems</title> (Aberdeen: Aberdeen University Press, 1989), pp. 136–49, pp. 12, 147.</bibl>
                     <bibl>Ogilvie-Thomson, S. J., <title>Index of Middle English prose</title>, 18 vols (Cambridge, 1984– ), Handlist VIII (1991), p. 19.</bibl>
                     <bibl>Hope, A., ‘The lady and the bailiff: Lollardy among the gentry in Yorkist and Tudor England’, in Aston, M. and Richmond, C. (eds), <title>Lollardy and the gentry in the later Middle Ages</title> (Stroud and New York: Sutton/St Martin’s Press, 1997), pp. 250–77.</bibl>
                     <bibl>Dove, M., <title>The first English Bible: the text and context of the Wycliffite versions</title> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2007), pp. 17, 59, 65, 87, 88, 95, 99, 105, 142, 193, 199, 214, 260–1, 302.</bibl>
                     <bibl>Thomson, R. M., <title>A descriptive catalogue of the medieval manuscripts of Corpus Christi College Oxford</title> (Cambridge: D. S. Brewer, 2011), pp. 8–9.</bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2023-04-19">Add Solopova description.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
