<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/msDesc/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/msDesc/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xml:id="manuscript_00000000" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>New College MS. 67</title>
            <title type="collection">New College MSS.</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Description</resp>
               <persName>Elizabeth Solopova</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Revision</resp>
               <persName>Andrew Dunning</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </publisher>
            <idno type="msID">New_College_MS_67</idno>
            <idno type="collection">New_College</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="New_College_MS_67" xml:lang="en">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <repository>New College</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">New College MS. 67</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents>
                  <textLang mainLang="enm" otherLangs="la">Middle English with Latin</textLang>
                  <msItem n="1">
                     <locus from="1r" to="2v">(fols. 1r–2v)</locus>
                     <note>[item 1 occupies quire I]</note>
                     <note>Short tracts in the hand of the main scribe:</note>
                     <msItem>
                        <title>The sixteen conditions of charity</title>
                        <note>(Severs, J. B., Hartung, A. E., Beidler, P. G., <title>A manual of the writings in Middle English, 1050–1500</title>, 11 vols (New Haven: Connecticut Academy of Arts and Sciences, 1967– ), vol. 7, p. 2518, no. 58; Jolliffe, P. S., <title>A check-list of Middle English prose writings of spiritual guidance</title> (Toronto: Pontifical Institute of Mediaeval Studies, 1974), G. 4)</note>
                        <rubric>on charite</rubric>
                        <incipit>Seynt poule spekiþ &amp; seiþ on þis wise if y speke with mannus tunge</incipit>
                        <note>Lists sixteen conditions of charity (based on 1 Corinthians 13:1–8), each followed by a short explanation.</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <title type="desc">A tract on the ten commandments</title>
                        <note>(Severs, J. B., Hartung, A. E., Beidler, P. G., <title>A manual of the writings in Middle English, 1050–1500</title>, 11 vols (New Haven: Connecticut Academy of Arts and Sciences, 1967– ), vol. 7, p. 2495, no. 24)</note>
                        <incipit>These ben þe x comaundementis of god þe whiche euereche man mot kepe</incipit>
                        <note>The commandments are numbered in red Roman numerals in the margins, each followed by a short explanation; the first three are accompanied by references to biblical books and chapters in the margins. Also includes the lists of seven virtues, five bodily wits and five ghostly wits. Most of fol. 2v is left blank.</note>
                     </msItem>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="2">
                     <locus from="1r" to="172r">(fols. 1r–172r)</locus>
                     <note>[items 2–3 occupy quires II–XXIII]</note>
                     <title key="work_13434" type="desc">New Testament in the Earlier Version of the Wycliffite Bible</title>
                     <note>With usual prologues. Includes two prologues to Romans and a second prologue to Luke, found in only two other manuscripts (see Dove, M., <title>The first English Bible: the text and context of the Wycliffite versions</title> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2007), p. 233): <q>Forsothe for many men enforsiden to ordeyne þe telling of þingis. whiche ben fillid in us. as þei þat sayen at þe begynnyng. &amp; weren mynystris of þe word bytooken: it seyn also to me hauynge fro þe bygynnyng alle þingis deligently bi ordre to write to þee þu best teofile þat þu knowe þe treuþe of þoo wordis of whiche þu art lernd</q>.</note>
                     <note>Some prologues appear to have been added in spaces left for them after the biblical text was copied. Two prologues to Romans, <q>First us bihoueþ vndirstonde…</q> and <q>Romayns þe whiche lyueden in þe citee…</q>, are written in a very small script by the main scribe to fit on fol. 92r–v. The prologue to 1 Thessalonians is written in the margin by the main scribe. The prologue to the Apocalypse occupies about one third of fol. 164r; the rest of the page is left blank and the Apocalypse starts on fol. 164v. According to Lindberg (1994), p. 24, the text is very much revised and strongly influenced by the Later Version of the Wycliffite Bible. Extensive glosses in the margins from 1 Corinthians 6:4 to Jude, some unique, according to Forshall, J. and Madden, F. (eds), <title>The Holy Bible … in the earliest English versions made from the Latin Vulgate by John Wycliffe and his followers</title>, 4 vols (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1850), most found only in this copy and London, British Library, Harley MS. 5017. Fewer glosses in the Apocalypse. The introduction of glosses coincides with the use of a much smaller script for the biblical text (from fol. 109v, 1 Corinthians 7) which remains small in the rest of the volume. Added material within the text is consistently underlined in red throughout.</note>
                     <note>Rubrics in red or black, usually at the start of prologues, though sometimes also at the beginnings of books, e.g., <q>Here endiþ marc and bygynneþ luc þe prologe</q>; <q>luc þe first chapitre</q>
                        <locus from="45v" to="46r">(fols. 45v–46r)</locus>. Running titles consisting of the name of a book and chapter number, usually on both rectos and versos, sometimes preceded by red or blue paraphs. Many corrections in a contemporary hand, over erasures or in the margins; some text crossed out in red ink, particularly glosses within the text and alternative translations at the beginning of Matthew. Some deletions at the beginning of Matthew suggest stylistic editing (see Forshall, J. and Madden, F. (eds), <title>The Holy Bible … in the earliest English versions made from the Latin Vulgate by John Wycliffe and his followers</title>, 4 vols (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1850), vol. 1, p. lii).</note>
                     <note>Chapter numbers in black ink by the scribe in the margins, most as Arabic numerals, some underlined in red or preceded by paraphs; chapter numbers in Roman numerals added in a darker ink. The same hand (15th century, second half (?)) also added indexing letters in the margins at the beginnings of lections, double strokes at the ends of lections, and sometimes notes concerning liturgical occasions when the lections were appointed to be read (e.g., <q>S Andrew day</q>, fol. 5v). Added <q>nota</q> and pointing hands in the margins.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="3">
                     <locus from="172v" to="174v">(fols. 172v–174v)</locus>
                     <title type="desc">Short table of lections in Latin</title>
                     <rubric>Hic incipiunt cotaciones evangeliorum et epistolarum tocius anni legende</rubric>
                     <note>Starting with the first Sunday in Advent and consisting of the temporal and sanctoral. Imperfect at the end, ending at All Souls (2 November). Laid out in two columns with the names of liturgical occasions written in the margins. Entries consist of the opening words of readings followed by an abbreviated reference to a book and chapter of the Bible. No indexing letters.</note>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="perg">
                        <support>poor quality parchment with holes; paper flyleaves</support>
                        <extent>174 leaves + unnumbered paper flyleaves at the beginning and end, <foreign>c.</foreign><dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                              <height>195</height>
                              <width>144</width>
                           </dimensions></extent>
                        <foliation>modern in pencil, 1–174</foliation>
                        <collation>three unnumbered paper flyleaves | <locus from="1" to="2">(fols. 1–2)</locus> I (2) single bifolium (?) | <locus from="3" to="167">(fols. 3–167)</locus> II–XXII (8) | <locus from="168" to="174">(fols. 168–174)</locus> XXIII (8–1) missing 8. <catchwords>Catchwords survive;</catchwords>
                           <signatures>quire signatures partially survive and appear to run consecutively a–y.</signatures>
                           <secFol><q>pisen her…</q>
                              <locus from="2r" to="2r">(fol. 2r)</locus></secFol>
                        </collation>
                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout columns="2" writtenLines="38 52">ruled for a single column, with single vertical and double horizontal bounding lines extending the full height and width of page; a second set of double bounding lines in all margins; 38–52 lines per page; written space: <foreign>c.</foreign><dimensions type="ruled" unit="mm">
                              <height>117</height>
                              <width>75</width>
                           </dimensions></layout>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc>
                     <handNote script="textualisNorthern">textura, black and brown ink; the size and style of script vary</handNote>
                  </handDesc>
                  <decoDesc>
                     <decoNote type="flourInit">3- to 6-line ‘puzzle’ initials with red and purple penwork or blue initials with red penwork at the beginnings of books; 2- to 3-line similar initials at the beginnings of chapters and prologues; some initials omitted (e.g., fol. 83v).</decoNote>
                  </decoDesc>
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <binding notAfter="1900" notBefore="1800">
                        <p>Modern binding. Gilt lettering on spine ‘NEW TEST. <lb/> ENGLISH’. Parchment slip attached to the upper cover with handwritten ‘New Testament <lb/> Engl[…]’.</p>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origPlace>
                        <country key="place_7002445">England</country>
                     </origPlace>
                     <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="1425" notBefore="1400">15th century, first quarter</origDate>
                     <p>Some prologues were added after the text was completed in spaces left for them. Glosses were added after the text was completed and flourished – they avoid penwork initials and chapter numbers in the margins, but the decision to include them was probably made when the volume was planned – the scribe uses a much more compressed script starting with 1 Corinthians 7, the first book to include extensive glosses.</p>
                     <p>Dialect survey: <list>
                           <item>According to Forshall and Madden copied from an original that had the present participle terminating in -ende, which has led to frequent mistakes, ‘and particularly to the occurrence of the preterite where the participle should stand, as <foreign>puttede</foreign> for <foreign>puttende</foreign> (Forshall, J. and Madden, F. (eds), <title>The Holy Bible … in the earliest English versions made from the Latin Vulgate by John Wycliffe and his followers</title>, 4 vols (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1850), vol. 1, p. lii).</item>
                           <item>eny(10), eche(3)/ech(7), fyier(1)/fijer(6)/fijr(3), ȝouen(8)/ȝiuen(2), lijf(10), lijk(9)/lijche(1), myche(10), say(4)/seiȝe(1) (sg.), sayen(1)/siȝen(2)/seiȝen(2)/ seien(1) (pl.), self(8)/silf(2), such(1)/suche(7)/sich(1), þouȝ(3), þourȝ(9)</item>
                           <item>-iþ(7)/-eþ(3)/-ith(1) (pres.ind.3sg.), -en(10) (pres.ind.pl.), -ing(2)/-inge(6)/yng(2) (pres.part.), she(3)/sche(7) (3sg.fem.pronoun, nom.), þei(10) (3pl. pronoun, nom.), hem(10) (3pl.pronoun, oblique), her(10) (3pl.pronoun, possessive)</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                  </origin>
                  <provenance><persName role="fmo">Thomas Martin</persName>, fellow of New College 1538–1553 (Coxe, 1852; Foster, 1891–92, p. 980).</provenance>
                  <acquisition when="1558">New College, Oxford: given by Martin in 1558.</acquisition>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>Elizabeth Solopova, <title><ref target="https://jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1gn6cmr">Manuscripts of the Wycliffite Bible in the Bodleian and Oxford College Libraries</ref></title>, Exeter Medieval Texts and Studies (Liverpool: Liverpool University Press, 2016), no. 57.</source>
                     </recordHist>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>Coxe, H. O., <title>Catalogus codicum mss. qui in collegiis aulisque Oxoniensibus hodie adservantur</title>, 2 vols (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1852), vol. 1, <title>Catalogus codicum MSS. Collegii Novi</title>, p. 19; siglum <title>V</title>.</bibl>
                     <bibl>Fristedt, S. L., <title>The Wycliffe Bible</title>, 3 vols (Stockholm: Almquvist &amp; Wiksells, 1953–73), vol. 1, p. 16.</bibl>
                     <bibl>Hargreaves, H., ‘The marginal glosses to the Wycliffite New Testament’, <title>Studia Neophilologica</title> 33 (1961), pp. 285–300.</bibl>
                     <bibl>Hargreaves, H., ‘Popularising biblical scholarship: the role of the Wycliffite Glossed Gospels’, in Lourdaux, W. and Verhelst, D. (eds), <title>The Bible and medieval culture</title> (Louvain: Leuven University Press, 1979) pp. 171–89 at p. 175.</bibl>
                     <bibl>Gillespie, V., ‘Vernacular books of religion’, in Griffiths, J. and Pearsall, D. A. (eds), <title>Book production and publishing in Britain 1375–1475</title> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1989), pp. 317–44 at p. 319.</bibl>
                     <bibl>Ogilvie-Thomson, S. J., <title>Index of Middle English prose</title>, 18 vols (Cambridge, 1984– ), Handlist VIII (1991), p. 54.</bibl>
                     <bibl>Lindberg, C. (ed.), <title>The earlier version of the Wycliffite Bible,</title> 8 vols (Stockholm: Almqvist &amp; Wiksell, 1959–97), vol. 7 (1994), p. 24.</bibl>
                     <bibl>Dove, M., <title>The first English Bible: the text and context of the Wycliffite versions</title> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2007), pp. 142, 152, 165, 166, 169–70, 179–80, 221, 223, 234, 248, 302.</bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2023-04-19">Add Solopova description.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
