<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/msDesc/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/msDesc/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xml:id="manuscript_0000000" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>New College MS. 320</title>
            <title type="collection">New College MSS.</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Description</resp>
               <persName>Elizabeth Solopova</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Revision</resp>
               <persName>Andrew Dunning</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </publisher>
            <idno type="msID">New_College_MS_320</idno>
            <idno type="collection">New_College</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="New_College_MS_320" xml:lang="en">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <repository>New College</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">New College MS. 320</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents>
                  <textLang mainLang="enm" otherLangs="la">Middle English with Latin</textLang>
                  <msItem n="1">
                     <locus from="1r" to="2r">(fols. 1r–2r)</locus>
                     <title type="desc">The Earlier Version of the Wycliffite Bible prologues to psalms</title>
                     <incipit>Whan it is knowen alle þe prophetys</incipit>
                     <incipit>Dauiþ þe son of iesse</incipit>
                     <note>See Dove, M., <title>The first English Bible: the text and context of the Wycliffite versions</title> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2007), p. 202).</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="2">
                     <locus from="2r" to="41r">(fols. 2r–41r)</locus>
                     <title key="work_14082" type="desc">Psalms 1–150 in the Later Version of the Wycliffite Bible</title>
                     <note>Laid out as prose in two columns. The psalms are separated by fairly large spaces which suggests that the titles were planned to be included. Latin incipits are written out in black ink by the main scribe in the margins at the start of most psalms. There are textual divisions at psalms 26, 38, 52, 68, 82, 97 and 109.</note>
                     <note>Punctuated throughout with <foreign>punctus</foreign> used to mark the ends of verses and <foreign>punctus</foreign> or colon used to mark minor pauses. No running titles or marginal glosses; added material within the text is not underlined. Corrected occasionally with omissions written out in the margins (e.g., fols. 26v, 39v) and text crossed out in red ink (e.g., fols. 13r, 27r). Psalm numbers (Hebrew) are added in a later hand.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="3">
                     <locus from="41r" to="43v">(fols. 41r–43v)</locus>
                     <note>Weekly canticles with Latin incipits in the margins (<foreign>Confitebor</foreign>, <foreign>Ego dixi</foreign>, <foreign>Exultauit</foreign>, <foreign>Cantemus</foreign>, <foreign>Domine audiui</foreign>, <foreign>Audite celi</foreign>).</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="4">
                     <locus from="43v" to="45r">(fols. 43v–45r)</locus>
                     <note>Daily canticles with Latin incipits in the margins (<foreign>Benedicite omnia opera</foreign>, <foreign>Te deum laudamus</foreign>, <foreign>Magnificat</foreign>, <foreign>Benedictus dominus deus</foreign>, <foreign>Nunc dimittis</foreign>); Athanasian Creed (<foreign>Quicumque vult</foreign>…).</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="5">
                     <locus from="45v">(fol. 45v)</locus>
                     <title type="desc">Poem to the Virgin Mary</title>
                     <bibl type="repertory">(<title>IMEV</title> 3228, <ref target="http://dimev.net/record.php?recID=5064"><title>DIMEV</title> 5064</ref>)</bibl>
                     <note>In the same hand as the psalter.</note>
                     <incipit>Swete and benyngne moder &amp; may <lb/> Turtell trew flowr of women alle</incipit>
                     <note>Each of the seven stanzas rhyme royal is an acrostic on the name ‘stanlei’ (possibly Thomas, first baron Stanley, 1406–1459; see <title>Oxford Dictionary of National Biography</title>; Furnivall (1866)). Preceded by a title in red <q>Spero lucem</q>. Followed by a Marian antiphon (1), versicle (2) and collect (3) (see Harper, J., <title>The forms and orders of Western liturgy from the tenth to the eighteenth century: a historical introduction and guide for students and musicians</title> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1991), pp. 131–3): <list>
                           <item>
                              <q>Aue regina celorum mater regis Angelorum O maria flos virginum velut rosa <sic>velilium</sic> ffunde preces ad filium pro salute fidelium</q>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <q>Ora pro nobis sancta dei genitrix Ut digni efficiamur promissionibus christi.</q>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <q>Famulorum tuorum quesumus domine delictis ignosce et qui tibi placere…</q>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </note>
                     <note>At the end <q>By Will<ex>ia</ex>m Huchen</q> in red ink.</note>
                     <note>Bound with printed material. Fols. 47r–94v are quires and leaves from Caxton’s translation of Jacobus de Voragine’s <title>Legenda Aurea</title> (de Worde (1498), ‘folio. vi’ to ‘folio. lij’), containing lives of Old Testament figures: <q>The lyf of Abraham</q>, followed by the lives of Isaac, Joseph, Moses, Saul, David, Solomon, Job, Tobit and Judith. Fol. 94r is another leaf from de Worde (1498), containing Caxton’s printer’s device on the recto and woodcuts of the Annunciation and Crucifixion on the verso. ‘Hedera’ signs in the margins of the lives of David, Solomon, Judith and at the start of Tobit, next to a rubric declaring that it ‘is redde on the thyrde sondaye of Septembre’.</note>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="chart">
                        <support>paper</support>
                        <extent>46 leaves + unnumbered flyleaves at the beginning and end, <foreign>c.</foreign><dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                              <height>272</height>
                              <width>206</width>
                           </dimensions>; leaves were cropped occasionally causing the loss of psalm incipits in the upper margin</extent>
                        <foliation>modern in pencil, 1–46; medieval in Arabic numerals, probably identical to modern</foliation>
                        <collation><locus from="1" to="16">(fols. 1–16)</locus> I (16) | <locus from="17" to="30">(fols. 17–30)</locus> II, structure unclear; catchwords at fols. 27v, 30v | <locus from="31" to="46">(fols. 31–46)</locus> III (16). <secFol><q>men chosyn…</q>
                              <locus from="2r" to="2r">(fol. 2r)</locus></secFol>
                        </collation>
                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout columns="2" writtenLines="36 39">ruled for two columns, with single vertical and horizontal bounding lines extending the full height and width of page; 36–9 lines per page; written space: <foreign>c.</foreign><dimensions type="ruled" unit="mm">
                              <height>235</height>
                              <width>165</width>
                           </dimensions></layout>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc>
                     <handNote script="cursiva">Secretary, black ink</handNote>
                  </handDesc>
                  <decoDesc>
                     <decoNote type="flourInit">3- to 4-line red initials, some with simple penwork, at textual divisions; 2-line similar initials at the beginnings of psalms and prologues. 1-line initials at the beginnings of verses.</decoNote>
                  </decoDesc>
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <binding notAfter="1800" notBefore="1700">
                        <p>Brown leather over pasteboard, 18th century. Blind fillet-line border round the outer edge of both covers; blind fillet-line rectangular figure with floral corner-pieces at the centre of both covers. Paper label on spine with typewritten ‘MS. <lb/> New Col. <lb/> D. 320’. Edges of textblock speckled red. Paper flyleaves and pastedowns.</p>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origPlace>
                        <country key="place_7002445">England</country>
                     </origPlace>
                     <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="1509" notBefore="1490"><foreign>c.</foreign>1500</origDate>
                     <p>Poem in the same hand as the psalter with acrostic ‘stanlei’, conjectured by Furnivall (1866) to be <persName ref="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q456361" role="fmo">Thomas, first baron Stanley, 1406–1459</persName>. Signature ‘<persName>William Huchen</persName>’ in the hand of the scribe responsible for the poem and psalter. Anthony à Wood (1813–20) believed that the manuscript contained a translation of psalms by William Tyndale, because of the similarity of the name ‘William Huchen’ to Tyndale’s pseudonym. Mombert (1884), however, pointed out that the manuscript contained a Wycliffite translation of psalms. The psalms are in a format similar to the Old Testament material from de Worde (two columns and similar written space) and may have been copied to supplement this material.</p>
                     <p>Dialect survey: <list>
                           <item>ony(2)/any(1), ich(1)/iche(2)/ech(2)/eche(1), fiyr(1)/fijr(9), ȝoue(3)/ȝouen(2), lijf(9)/lyfe(1), lyk(1)/lyke(3)/lijk(2), myche(5), seiȝ(2) (sg.), syȝen(2)/siȝen(2)/ sien(1)/syen(2) (pl.), self(8), þorou(1)</item>
                           <item>-yþ(2)/-iþ(9) (pres.ind.3sg.), -en(9)/-(1) (pres.ind.pl.), -ynge(3)/-yng(7) (pres. part.), sche(1) (3sg.fem. pronoun, nom.), þei(8)/þey(2) (3pl.pronoun, nom.), hem(10) (3pl.pronoun, oblique), her(10) (3pl.pronoun, possessive)</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                  </origin>
                  <provenance><q><persName>Thomas Smyth of london</persName></q>, 16th century <locus from="46r" to="46r">(fol. 46r)</locus>.</provenance>
                  <provenance>Inscription recording that <persName>Thomas Philpott</persName> (Foster, J., <title>Alumni Oxonienses: the members of the University of Oxford, 1500–1714</title>, 4 vols (London: Joseph Foster; Oxford: Parker and Co., 1891–92), p. 1160), fellow of New College, was created D.D. in June 1646 <locus from="46v" to="46v">(fol. 46v)</locus> (see a full transcription in Coxe, H. O., <title>Catalogus codicum mss. qui in collegiis aulisque Oxoniensibus hodie adservantur</title>, 2 vols (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1852)).</provenance>
                  <acquisition>New College, Oxford: <q>Liber Novi Collegij in Oxon</q>’ <locus from="1r" to="1r">(fol. 1r)</locus>.</acquisition>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>Elizabeth Solopova, <title><ref target="https://jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1gn6cmr">Manuscripts of the Wycliffite Bible in the Bodleian and Oxford College Libraries</ref></title>, Exeter Medieval Texts and Studies (Liverpool: Liverpool University Press, 2016), no. 58.</source>
                     </recordHist>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>Wood, Anthony à, <title>Athenæ oxonienses: an exact history of all the writers and bishops who have had their education in the University of Oxford</title>, a new edition, with additions, and a continuation by Philip Bliss, 4 vols (London, 1813–20), vol. 1, col. 97.</bibl>
                     <bibl>Forshall, J. and Madden, F. (eds), <title>The Holy Bible … in the earliest English versions made from the Latin Vulgate by John Wycliffe and his followers</title>, 4 vols (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1850), vol. 1, p. lii.</bibl>
                     <bibl>Coxe, H. O., <title>Catalogus codicum mss. qui in collegiis aulisque Oxoniensibus hodie adservantur</title>, 2 vols (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1852), vol. 1, <title>Catalogus codicum MSS. Collegii Novi</title>, p. 115.</bibl>
                     <bibl>Furnivall, F. J. (ed.), <title>Political, religious and love poems, from Lambeth MS. 306 and other sources,</title> EETS o.s. 15 (1866), pp. 291–2.</bibl>
                     <bibl>Mombert, J. I., <title>William Tyndale’s five books of Moses, called the Pentateuch, being a verbatim reprint of the edition of M.CCCCC.XXX</title> (New York: A. D. F. Randolph, London: S. Bagster, 1884), p. liv.</bibl>
                     <bibl>Hargreaves, H., ‘The Latin text of Purvey’s psalter’, <title>Medium Aevum</title> 24 (1955), pp. 73–90 at p. 88.</bibl>
                     <bibl>Hudson, A., ‘Contributions to a history of Wycliffite writings’, in Hudson, A., <title>Lollards and their books</title> (London: Hambledon Press, 1985), pp. 1–12 at p. 11.</bibl>
                     <bibl>Ogilvie-Thomson, S. J., <title>Index of Middle English prose</title>, 18 vols (Cambridge, 1984– ), Handlist VIII (1991), pp. 73–5. de Hamel, C., <title>The book: a history of the Bible</title> (London: Phaidon, 2001), p. 179. Dove, M., <title>The first English Bible: the text and context of the Wycliffite versions</title> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2007), p. 302.</bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2023-04-19">Add Solopova description.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
