<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/msDesc/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/msDesc/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xml:id="manuscript_000000" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Queen’s College MS. 369</title>
            <title type="collection">Queen’s College MSS.</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Description</resp>
               <persName>Elizabeth Solopova</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Revision</resp>
               <persName>Andrew Dunning</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </publisher>
            <idno type="msID">Queens_College_MS_369</idno>
            <idno type="collection">Queen’s_College</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="Queens_College_MS_369" xml:lang="en">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <repository>Queen’s College</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">Queen’s College MS. 369</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents>
                  <textLang mainLang="enm" otherLangs="la">Middle English with Latin</textLang>
                  <msItem>
                     <note>Fol. i is a parchment flyleaf.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="1">
                     <locus from="1r" to="7v">(fols. 1r–7v)</locus>
                     <note>[item 1 occupies quire I]</note>
                     <title type="desc">Table of lections of Type I</title>
                     <rubric>Here begynneþ a reule þat telliþ in whiche chapitris of þe bible ȝe may fynde þe lessouns pistlis. gospels þat ben red in þe chirche at masse aftir þe vse of salesbery. markid wiþ lettris of þe a. b. c. at þe bigynnyng of þe chapitris toward þe myddil or ende after þe ordre as þe lettris stonden in the. a. b. c. first ben set sundaies &amp; ferials togidere &amp; after þe sanctorum comyn and propre togidere of al þe ȝeer. first written a clause of þe bigynnyng þerof. &amp; a clause of þe ending þerof also</rubric>
                     <note>The entries consist of the name of a liturgical occasion in red, abbreviated reference to a book and chapter of the Bible, an indexing letter in red, the opening words of a reading, <q>ende</q> in red, and the closing words of a reading. Includes the temporal, commemorations and the sanctoral. Commemorations are in the following order: Our Lady, Trinity, Holy Ghost, cross, angels, brothers and sisters and <q>salus populi</q>, peace, clear weather, rain, <q>In tyme of batels</q>, <q>A man for him self</q>, <q>pestilence of beestes</q>, pilgrims, weddings, sinners, sick and dead. Includes all feasts characteristic of the Later Version of the Wycliffite Bible, apart from Giles (1 September) (Forshall, J. and Madden, F. (eds), <title>The Holy Bible … in the earliest English versions made from the Latin Vulgate by John Wycliffe and his followers</title>, 4 vols (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1850), vol. 4, pp. 683, 690–6). Conception of our Lady, Candlemas, Annunciation, Nativity of John the Baptist, Peter and Paul, Assumption, Nativity of our Lady, Exaltation of the Cross (September) and Halloween start with blue initials. About two-thirds of fol. 7v are ruled for the table of lections but blank; fol. 8r–v is originally blank (see Provenance).</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="2">
                     <locus from="9r" to="449v">(fols. 9r–449v)</locus>
                     <note>[item 2 occupies quires II–LVI]</note>
                     <title key="work_10451" type="desc">Old and New Testaments in the Later Version of the Wycliffite Bible</title>
                     <note>Imperfect at the beginning, starting at Genesis 1:20 (<q>…þe erþe vndur þe firmament</q>). Unique prologues to all books from Exodus to Proverbs (except 2 Chronicles which originally must have had a prologue but lacks the beginning because of the loss of a leaf after fol. 152; missing 1 Chronicles, 29:7–2 Chronicles, 3:1) and to Jeremiah and 1 Maccabees. The prologues to Ezekiel and Daniel are shared with Cambridge, University Library, MS. Dd. I. 27. The unique prologues are listed in Dove, M., <title>The first English Bible: the text and context of the Wycliffite versions</title> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2007), pp. 200–4 (siglum M), apart from the prologue to Joshua <q>This book of iosue makiþ mynde how þe lord…</q>
                        <locus from="77v" to="77v">(fol. 77v)</locus>, and printed in Forshall, J. and Madden, F. (eds), <title>The Holy Bible … in the earliest English versions made from the Latin Vulgate by John Wycliffe and his followers</title>, 4 vols (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1850). The books from Ecclesiastes to Ecclesiasticus have longer than usual rubrics, some explaining that they do not need prologues: <q>Here endiþ þe book of prouerbis &amp; here bigynneþ þe book of ecclesiastes þat tretiþ also of wisdom &amp; prudence &amp; nediþ noon oþer prologe</q> (Ecclesiastes, fol. 228v); <q>Here endiþ þe book of ecclesiastes &amp; here bigynneþ þe book of song of songis þat weren maad of salomon to be sungen in þe temple of þe lord in to euerelastinge wurschiping &amp; nediþ noon þe prologe</q> (Song of Songs, fol. 231v); <q>Here endiþ þe book of songis &amp; here bigynneþ þe book of wisdom which is red in holi cherche in lessouns of þe masse for þe mater þerof is goostli &amp; profecie of þingis to comynge</q> (Wisdom, fol. 233r); <q>Here endiþ þe book of wisdom and here bigynneþ þe book of ecclesiasticus þat tretiþ also of wisdom and prudence in many degrees of þe world</q> (Ecclesiasticus, fol. 238v). Usual the Later Version of the Wycliffite Bible prologues to Isaiah and Baruch; no prologues to Hosea-Malachi and 2 Maccabees.</note>
                     <note>Rubrics in red, e.g., <q>Here endiþ þe book of genesis &amp; here bigynneþ a prologe on þe book of exodi</q>, <q>Here endiþ þe prologe &amp; here biginneþ þe book of Exodi</q>. Running titles above each column in red preceded by blue paraphs, consisting of book titles only. Chapter numbers in red Roman numerals. Added material within the text is underlined in black. No marginal glosses; includes a few of a series of glosses in Pentateuch written within the text (see Dove, M., <title>The first English Bible: the text and context of the Wycliffite versions</title> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2007), p. 264). Indexing letters occasionally appear in the margins placed at the beginnings of lections rather than consistently; double strokes in the margins at the ends of lections. Corrections in the original or contemporary hands, those in the margins are sometimes in red boxes. Red and blue paraphs within the text. Rubrics in Esther and Daniel pointing out the differences between the Latin and Hebrew texts.</note>
                     <note>Psalms written as prose with verses starting with alternating 1-line red or blue initials. Each psalm is preceded by a title in red ink. Latin incipits are added in a later cursive hand in the margins. Larger initials at the beginnings of psalms 26, 38, 52, 68, 80, 97 and 109. Psalm 118 has 3-line initials at the beginning of 11-verse units. At the end of psalms: <q>Here endiþ þe sauter but more salmes suwen þat ben writen in þe sauter whiche ben writen in diuerse <sic>chapitles</sic> of þe bible <sic>bible</sic> bifore &amp; after whiche it is no nede to writen hem twies þer for we enden here &amp; here bigynneþ a prologe vpon prouerbis of salomon</q>.</note>
                     <note>New Testament starts on a new quire <locus from="361r" to="361r">(fol. 361r)</locus> following a larger than usual 10-leaf quire at the end of Old Testament and ends with a 10-leaf quire; books have usual the Later Version of the Wycliffite Bible prologues. The Apocalypse ends in the first column on fol. 449v; the second column and fol. 250 are blank.</note>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="perg">
                        <support>parchment</support>
                        <extent><measure type="leaf" quantity="451">451</measure> leaves, <foreign>c.</foreign><dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                              <height>432</height>
                              <width>300</width>
                           </dimensions>, trimmed in rebinding</extent>
                        <foliation>modern in pencil, i + 450</foliation>
                        <collation><locus from="i" to="i">(fol. i)</locus> parchment flyleaf conjoint with the upper pastedown | <locus from="1" to="8">(fols. 1–8)</locus> I (8) | <locus from="9" to="15">(fols. 9–15)</locus> II (8–1) missing 1 | <locus from="16" to="151">(fols. 16–151)</locus> III–XIX (8) | <locus from="152" to="158">(fols. 152–158)</locus> XX (8–1) missing 2 | <locus from="159" to="350">(fols. 159–350)</locus> XXI–XLIV (8) | <locus from="351" to="360">(fols. 351–360)</locus> XLV (10) | <locus from="361" to="440">(fols. 361–440)</locus> XLVI–LV (8) | <locus from="441" to="449">(fols. 441–449)</locus> the Later Version of the Wycliffite BibleI (10) missing 10 | <locus from="450" to="450">(fol. 450)</locus> parchment flyleaf conjoint with the lower pastedown. <catchwords>Catchwords survive;</catchwords>
                           <signatures>medieval quire signatures occasionally survive.</signatures>
                           <secFol><q>Mt. v. &amp; vi.</q> (table of lections, fol. 10r); <q>dide a sone</q> (Old Testament, fol. 10r)</secFol>
                        </collation>
                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout columns="2" writtenLines="60">ruled for two columns with single vertical and horizontal bounding lines extending the full height and width of page; a second set of double bounding lines in all four margins; 60 lines per page; written space: <foreign>c.</foreign><dimensions type="ruled" unit="mm">
                              <height>325</height>
                              <width>210</width>
                           </dimensions></layout>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc>
                     <handNote script="textualisNorthern">textura, black ink</handNote>
                  </handDesc>
                  <decoDesc>
                     <decoNote type="decInit">7-line gold initials on blue and pink background, decorated with sprays of foliage and gold disks at the beginning of Leviticus, Joshua, 3 Kings, 1 Chronicles (cut out), psalms (cut out), Proverbs (cut out), Isaiah, Ezekiel, Hosea, I Maccabees, Matthew (cut out), other gospels, Romans, 2 Corinthians, 1 Thessalonians, Hebrews, Acts and James.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="flourInit">6- to 7-line red and blue ‘puzzle’ initials decorated with red and blue penwork foliage, and sometimes penwork borders at the beginnings of other books. An initial is cut out on fol. 97 at the beginning of 1 Kings.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="flourInit">3- to 4-line blue initials with red penwork at the beginnings of chapters and prologues.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="rubrication">Rubrics in red.</decoNote>
                  </decoDesc>
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <binding notAfter="1900" notBefore="1800">
                        <p>Brown leather over pasteboard. Blind fillet-line and roll decoration on both covers. Ten raised bands on spine. Two paper labels on spine with typewritten ‘1’ and handwritten ‘388’. Writing in faded ink on the fore-edge of textblock. Parchment pastedowns and flyleaves.</p>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origPlace>
                        <country key="place_7002445">England</country>
                     </origPlace>
                     <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="1425" notBefore="1400">15th century, first quarter</origDate>
                     <p>Dialect survey: <list>
                           <item>ony(10), ech(10), fijr(10), ȝouen(10), lijf(10), lijk(10), myche(10), seȝ(5)/sawȝ(2) (sg.), saien(4)/seiȝen(2) (pl.), self(10), suche(7)/such(2), þouȝ(7), þoruȝ(10) Also: knewȝ, slowȝ, snowȝ.</item>
                           <item>-iþ(8)/-eþ(2) (pres.ind.3sg.), -en(10) (pres.ind.pl.), -ynge(6)/-inge(4) (pres. part.), sche(10) (3sg.fem.pronoun, nom.), þei(10) (3pl.pronoun, nom.), hem(10) (3pl.pronoun, oblique), her(10) (3pl.pronoun, possessive)</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                  </origin>
                  <provenance><persName role="fmo">William Smyth</persName>, 1561–1563: <q>Ego Will<ex>el</ex>mus Smyth seruiens scutellie dominae reginae elezabethae incepi legere 2º die Octob. anº 1561 et finem feci 10 die Junii aº 1563 iterum relegere incepi 12º Junii anº praedicto</q>
                     <locus from="8v" to="8v">(fol. 8v)</locus>.</provenance>
                  <provenance>Loaned to Forshall, 9 July 1831 <locus from="i-verso" to="i-verso">(fol. i verso)</locus>.</provenance>
                  <acquisition>Queen’s College, Oxford; bookplate on the upper pastedown.</acquisition>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>Elizabeth Solopova, <title><ref target="https://jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1gn6cmr">Manuscripts of the Wycliffite Bible in the Bodleian and Oxford College Libraries</ref></title>, Exeter Medieval Texts and Studies (Liverpool: Liverpool University Press, 2016), no. 61.</source>
                     </recordHist>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>Forshall, J. and Madden, F. (eds), <title>The Holy Bible … in the earliest English versions made from the Latin Vulgate by John Wycliffe and his followers</title>, 4 vols (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1850), vol. 1, p. liii; siglum <title>M</title>.</bibl>
                     <bibl>Coxe, H. O., <title>Catalogus codicum mss. qui in collegiis aulisque Oxoniensibus hodie adservantur</title>, 2 vols (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1852), vol. 1, <title>Codices MSS. Collegii Reginensis</title>, p. 89.</bibl>
                     <bibl>Alexander, J. J. G. and Temple, E., <title>Illuminated manuscripts in Oxford College libraries, the University Archives and the Taylor Institution</title> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1985), no. 397.</bibl>
                     <bibl>Ogilvie-Thomson, S. J., <title>Index of Middle English prose</title>, 18 vols (Cambridge, 1984– ), Handlist VIII (1991), p. 84.</bibl>
                     <bibl>Dove, M., <title>The first English Bible: the text and context of the Wycliffite versions</title> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2007), pp. 17, 59, 62, 65, 96, 99, 100, 106, 107, 127, 129, 156, 193, 200, 201, 202, 203, 204, 263–4, 302.</bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2023-04-19">Add Solopova description.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
