<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="manuscript_6106">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>MS. Hatton 9</title>
            <title type="collection">MSS. Hatton</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp when="2013">Cataloguer</resp>
               <persName>Elizabeth Solopova</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp when="2024">Encoding</resp>
               <persName>Matthew Holford</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </publisher>
            <idno type="msID">MS_Hatton_9</idno>
            <idno type="collection">Hatton</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="MS_Hatton_9" xml:lang="en">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <region type="county">Oxfordshire</region>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <institution>University of Oxford</institution>
                  <repository>Bodleian Library</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">MS. Hatton 9</idno>
                  <idno type="ieArk">ark:29072/x0gt54kn2761</idno>
                  <idno type="crArk">ark:29072/x0gq67jr43wt</idno>
                  <altIdentifier type="internal">
                     <idno type="SCN">4123</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
               <head>Secular Choir, Partially Ferial, Psalter with Antiphons, Use of Sarum; England,
                  Diocese of Norwich; 15th century, second quarter</head>
               <msContents>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS_Hatton_9-item1">
                     <title key="work_14145" type="desc">Ferial Choir Psalter, Use of Sarum</title>
                     <note>Fols. 1 and 2 are blank paper fly-leaves. </note>
                     <note>[item 1 occupies quire I]</note>
                     <msItem n="1">
                        <locus>(fols. 3r–8v)</locus>
                        <note> Sarum–Norwich calendar, written in black and red, laid out one month
                           per page, approximately three-quarters full, graded up to 9 lessons and
                           ‘festum principale’, with short instructions concerning the celebration
                           of feasts. The feasts include Felix of Dunwich (8 March) and the
                           dedication of Norwich Cathedral (24 September), both in red, David and
                           Chad (1 and 2 March), Benedict in red (21 March) and his translation in
                           black (11 July), John of Beverley (7 May), Anne in red (26 July),
                           Augustine in red (28 August), Winifred (3 November) and Leonard in red (6
                           November). The feasts marked as synodal (non-Sarum), all in red, are
                           Felix (8 March), the translation of Edward (29 April) and Francis (4
                           October). A verse on the ‘Egyptian’ days heads the page for January only
                           (‘Iani prima dies et septima a fine terminetur’). There are twelve added
                           obits from 1472 to 1480, several mentioning West Wycombe,
                           Buckinghamshire, and Rickmansworth (about 15 miles east of West Wycombe),
                           including ‘Obitus domini Thome Stheuenyssone vicarii iiijti de
                           westwycomb’ (10 January 1472) and ‘Obitus domini Iohannis Wynton vicarii
                           de Rykmynswurth’ (14 November 1480). Four obits are for women. The
                           dedication of the parish church of West Wycombe is added on 27 July.
                           There are also added feasts of Apollonia (8 February), Osyth (3 June),
                           whose shrine was at St Mary’s Church in Aylesbury, about 20 miles north
                           of West Wycombe, and Osmund (translation, 16 July, and deposition, 4
                           December). Osmund was canonized in 1457, and the feasts were probably
                           added around this time, possibly by the hand which added the obits,
                           writing more formally. The same hand also wrote the names of the months
                           in the lower margins (many very faded), followed by the number of days in
                           each month in Roman numerals. The feasts of Thomas Becket and the titles
                           ‘pape’ are crossed out. </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <note> [items 2–6 occupy quires II–XV]</note>
                     <msItem n="2">
                        <locus>(fol. 9r–9v)</locus>
                        <note> Hymns for Matins on the 1st Sunday in Advent and the 1st Sunday after
                           the octave of Epiphany with rubrics and musical notation (square notation
                           on four red staves): <list>
                              <item>Uerbum supernum prodiens ... (Chevalier, no. 21391);</item>
                              <item> Primo dierum omnium ... (Chevalier, no. 15450);</item>
                              <item> Nocte surgentes uigilemus omnes ... (Chevalier, no. 12035) (two
                                 settings).</item>
                           </list>
                        </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="3">
                        <locus>(fols. 9v–101v)</locus>
                        <note> Psalms 1–150, without titles or numbers, written as prose. Punctuated
                           throughout, with punctus used to mark the ends of verses and minor
                           pauses, and punctus elevatus used to mark metrum. Psalms are mostly in
                           the biblical order, but with some deviations, reflecting the order in
                           which they were recited in the secular use (see below). Subdivisions
                           within psalms are not indicated, apart from 118, subdivided into eleven
                           16-verse units in accordance with secular use. The psalms are accompanied
                           by chapters, antiphons and hymns with rubrics and musical notation. The
                           weekly canticles and Athanasian Creed appear at major liturgical
                           divisions: <list>
                              <item> (1) Confitebor tibi domine (Isaiah 12), fol. 28r, after psalm
                                 37;</item>
                              <item> (2) Ego dixi (Isaiah 38: 10–21), fol. 34v, after psalm
                                 51;</item>
                              <item> (3) Exultauit cor meum (1 Samuel 2: 1–11), fol. 41v, after
                                 psalm 67;</item>
                              <item> (4) Cantemus domino (Exodus 15: 1–20), fol. 50r, after psalm
                                 79;</item>
                              <item> (5) Domine audiui (Habakkuk 3), fol. 58r, after psalm
                                 96;</item>
                              <item> (6) Audite celi (Deuteronomy 32: 1–44), fol. 67r, after psalm
                                 108;</item>
                              <item> (7) Athanasian Creed (Quicumque uult ...), fol. 77v, after
                                 psalm 118, verse 32.</item>
                           </list> Psalm 113, fols. 70v–72r, is accompanied by musical notation, and
                           is followed by the opening lines of the hymn ‘Iam lucis orto sydere’
                           (Chevalier, no. 9272) with music for different days of the year. Psalms
                           114–116, read at Vespers on Monday in the secular use, follow psalm 118
                           on fols. 89r–v. This creates an unbroken sequence of all five psalms
                           appointed for Monday Vespers in secular use (psalms 114–116, 119–120).
                           Psalms 148–150, recited at Lauds on all days of the week in both monastic
                           and secular use, are written as a single text without breaks on fols.
                           100v–101r. Psalm 66 follows psalm 62 (fol. 39r). These two psalms were
                           also recited at all Lauds during the week in the secular use.</note>
                        <note> There are textual divisions at psalms 26, 38, 51, 52, 68, 80, 97 and
                           109 (see ‘Decoration’). Psalm 109 starts on a new page (the scribe left
                           four lines blank on the preceding page) and has a more prominent border
                           than other psalms at liturgical divisions. Some leaves have parchment
                           bookmarks sewn to their edges, made from a medieval manuscript written in
                           a formal Gothic style (the text is visible on bookmarks at fols. 55 and
                           97). The bookmarks indicate: <list>
                              <item>– the beginnings of the Penitential Psalms 31 (fol. 34r) and 101
                                 (fol. 97v);</item>
                              <item> – some of the liturgical divisions (psalm 97, fol. 59v; psalm
                                 109, fol. 69v; and psalm 118, fol. 76v);</item>
                              <item> – some psalms appointed for Lauds, i.e. psalm 62, recited at
                                 all Lauds (fol. 39r), and psalm 90, recited second at Thursday
                                 Lauds (fol. 55r);</item>
                              <item> – the sequence of psalms for Monday Vespers 114–116 (fol. 89r),
                                 which follow psalm 118, deviating from the biblical order;</item>
                              <item> – canticle Benedicite omnia opera (fol. 103r);</item>
                              <item> – a few other psalms, i.e. 44 (?), fol. 31r, and 74 (?), fol.
                                 46r.</item>
                           </list> Some psalm initials are defaced by wet smudging, possibly in
                           order to make them more noticeable. </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="4">
                        <locus>(fols. 101v–104v)</locus>
                        <note> Daily canticles, prayers and creeds, without titles: (1) Te deum
                           laudamus with musical notation (fol. 101v); (2) Benedicite omnia opera
                           (fol. 103r); (3) Benedictus dominus deus (fol. 103v); (4) Magnificat
                           (fol. 103v); (5) Nunc dimittis (fol. 104r) followed by antiphons with
                           musical notation. There is a parchment bookmark on fol. 103. </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="5">
                        <locus>(fols. 104v–108v)</locus>
                        <note> Sarum litanies for each day of the week. Thomas Becket is erased on
                           fol. 105r. The litanies are followed by collects with rubrics (fols.
                           107v–108v): <list>
                              <item> (1) Deus cui proprium est misereri semper et parcere suscipe
                                 ...</item>
                              <item> (2) Omnipotens sempiterne deus qui facis mirabilia magna solus
                                 ...</item>
                              <item> (3) Deus qui caritatis dona per gratiam sancti spiritus tuorum
                                 cordibus fidelium infundis ...</item>
                              <item> (4) Deus a quo sancta desideria recta consilia et iusta sunt
                                 ...</item>
                              <item> (5) Ineffabilem misericordiam tuam nobis domine quesumus
                                 clementer ostende ut simul nos ...</item>
                              <item> (6) Fidelium deus omnium conditor et redemptor animabus omnium
                                 fidelium defunctorum ...</item>
                              <item> (7) Pietate tua quesumus domine nostrorum solue omnia uincula
                                 ...</item>
                           </list>
                        </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="6">
                        <locus>(fols. 108v–117r)</locus>
                        <note> Office of the Dead, use of Sarum, with musical notation. </note>
                        <note>Fol. 117v is ruled but blank. </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <p><secFol> quod fructum suum dabit <locus>(psalter, fol.
                     10r)</locus></secFol></p>
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="perg">
                        <support> parchment; paper fly-leaves; some leaves repaired with pieces of
                           parchment, probably at the time when the present binding was made; fol.
                           21 is repaired with a parchment fragment of a document with a faded text
                           in a cursive early modern (?) hand</support>
                        <extent> 119 leaves<dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                              <height quantity="327">c. 327</height>
                              <width>225</width>
                           </dimensions></extent>
                        <foliation> modern, in pencil; 1–119.</foliation>
                        <collation> (fols. 1–2) paper fly-leaves, fol. 1 conjoint with the upper
                           pastedown | (fols. 3–8) I (6) | (fols. 9–96) II–XII (8) | (fols. 97–103)
                           XIII (8−1) missing 8 (?), no loss of text, catchword on fol. 103v |
                           (fols. 104–111) XIV (8) | (fols. 112–117) XV (6) the quire is now perhaps
                           composed of single leaves, the original composition is unclear | (fols.
                           118–119) paper fly-leaves, fol. 119 conjoint with the upper pastedown.
                           Most catchwords and leaf signatures survive</collation>
                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout columns="1" writtenLines="30">Ruled in ink with single vertical
                           bounding lines, single horizontal bounding lines at the top of the page
                           and double horizontal bounding lines at the bottom of the page, all
                           extending the full height and width of page; written below the top line;
                           30 lines per page; prickings often survive; written space: <dimensions
                              type="written" unit="mm">
                              <height quantity="210">c. 210</height>
                              <width>135</width>
                           </dimensions></layout>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc>
                     <handNote execution="formata" script="textualisNorthern"> Large formal Gothic
                        book hand</handNote>
                  </handDesc>
                  <musicNotation>
                     <p>Notation on staves.</p>
                  </musicNotation>
                  <decoDesc>
                     <decoNote type="monogram">Blue KL monograms with red penwork in the
                        calendar.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="decInit">7-line Beatus-initial (fol. 9v) on gold background,
                        decorated with foliage and coiled tendrils, with a full border made of gold,
                        green, blue and pink bars, decorated with foliage, flowers and gold
                        discs.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="decInit">4- to 6-line gold initials, decorated with coiled
                        tendrils, leaves and flowers, and partial borders, formed of sprays of
                        leaves, flowers and gold discs at liturgical divisions at psalms 26 (fol.
                        22r), 38 (fol. 28r), 51 (fol. 34r), 52 (fol. 35v), 68 (fol. 42v), 80 (fol.
                        51r), 97 (fol. 59v) and 109 (fol. 69v). </decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="border">Psalm 109 has a full border made of gold, green, blue
                        and pink bars, decorated with foliage, flowers and gold discs.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="flourInit">2-line blue initials with red penwork, some with
                        human and animal figures and heads (fols. 14r, 20v, 63v, 96v, 99v and 109v)
                        at the beginnings of psalms, hymns, canticles, prayers and
                        litany.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="colInit">1-line plain alternating red and blue initials at the
                        beginnings of verses.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="cadel">Black cadels, some with human and animal profiles and
                        heads, at the beginnings of verses accompanied by musical
                        notation.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="rubrication">Rubrics in red ink.</decoNote>
                  </decoDesc>
                  <bindingDesc>

                     <binding notAfter="1800" notBefore="1700">
                        <p> Brown speckled leather over pasteboard, 18th century (?). Double blind
                           fillet border round the outer edge of both covers. Blind roll border with
                           arabesque designs next to the spine on both covers. Sewn on five cords,
                           five raised bands on spine. Gilt lettering on spine: ‘HATTON || 98’. ‘9’
                           painted white at the top of the spine. Bodleian paper label on spine with
                           handwritten ‘M.S. || Hatton || 9.’. The covers are rubbed and worn, and
                           fragments of leather are missing on the lower cover. Fly-leaves made of
                           laid paper, no watermarks. </p>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="1450" notBefore="1425">15th century,
                        second quarter</origDate>
                     <origPlace cert="low">
                        <country key="place_7002445">English</country>, <region>Norwich
                           diocese</region>
                        <!--ORIGINAL: English, Norwich (?)-->
                     </origPlace>
                  </origin>
                  <provenance>Made for a secular church in the diocese of Norwich: liturgical
                     evidence. </provenance>
                  <provenance>In <placeName key="place_7011903">West Wycombe, Buckinghamshire</placeName>, in the third and fourth quarters of
                     the 15th century: additions to the calendar. </provenance>
                  <provenance>‘By me <persName role="sgn" key="person_3969">Hew Darrell</persName>’, 16th century, fol. 107r. </provenance>
                  <provenance>‘<persName role="sgn" key="person_3970">Wyllyam Clarke</persName>’ (faded, upper margin), 16th century, fol. 101v. Faded
                     inscription in English probably in the same hand on fol. 42r. </provenance>
                  <provenance><persName role="fmo" key="person_37729288">Christopher, first Baron Hatton (bap. 1605, d. 1670)</persName>, see ODNB. On
                     fol. 3r ‘Psalterium’. </provenance>
                  <provenance>Robert Scott, London bookseller (b. in or before 1632, d. 1709/10),
                     see ODNB: bought as part of the library of Christopher, first Baron Hatton. </provenance>
                  <acquisition when="1671">Bodleian Library: bought in 1671 from Scott; came to the Library in
                     September 1671 (see Summary catalogue, vol. 2, part 2, pp. 801–2). Former
                     shelfmark: ‘Hatton 98’ (fol. 3r and binding). </acquisition>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>Elizabeth Solopova, <title>Latin
                              Liturgical Psalters in the Bodleian Library: A Select
                              Catalogue</title> (Oxford, 2013), pp. 237–41. Previously described in
                           the Summary Catalogue. <listBibl>
                              <bibl facs="aaq0211.gif" type="SC">Summary Catalogue, Vol. 2 Part 2,
                                 p. 852</bibl>
                           </listBibl>
                        </source>
                     </recordHist>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <surrogates>
                     <bibl subtype="partial" type="digital-facsimile">
                        <ref
                           target="https://digital.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/objects/19e893f4-d3b1-4d4f-ad5c-34929b4e6679/">
                           <title>Digital Bodleian</title>
                        </ref>
                        <note>(2 images from 35mm slides)</note>
                     </bibl>
                  </surrogates>
                  <listBibl type="WRAPPER">
                     <listBibl type="PRINT">
                        <head>Select bibliography to 2002:</head>
                        <bibl>Frere, no. 143.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Summary catalogue, vol. 2, part 2, no. 4123.</bibl>
                        <bibl>S. J. P. van Dijk, <title>Latin Liturgical Manuscripts in the Bodleian
                           Library, Oxford, vol. 2: Office Books</title> (typescript, 1957),
                           <citedRange unit="page" from="132" to="132">p. 132</citedRange>
                        </bibl>
                        <bibl><ref
                           target="https://catalog.hathitrust.org/Record/000468709">Pächt and
                           Alexander</ref> (1966–73), vol. 3, no. 931.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Scott (1996), vol. 2, p. 107.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Scott (2000–02), vol. 2, no. 544.</bibl>
                       
                     </listBibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2024-04-08">Encode full description from Solopova catalogue.</change>
         <change when="2017-07-01">First online publication.</change>
         <change when="2017-05-25">
            <persName>James Cummings</persName> Up-converted the markup using <ref
               target="https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl"
               >https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl</ref>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
