<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="manuscript_6064">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>MS. Hatton 4</title>
            <title type="collection">MSS. Hatton</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp when="2013">Cataloguer</resp>
               <persName>Elizabeth Solopova</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp when="2024">Encoding</resp>
               <persName>Matthew Holford</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </publisher>
            <idno type="msID">MS_Hatton_4</idno>
            <idno type="collection">Hatton</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="MS_Hatton_4" xml:lang="en">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <region type="county">Oxfordshire</region>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <institution>University of Oxford</institution>
                  <repository>Bodleian Library</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">MS. Hatton 4</idno>
                  <idno type="ieArk">ark:29072/x06h440t2940</idno>
                  <idno type="crArk">ark:29072/x06d56zx45tk</idno>
                  <altIdentifier type="internal">
                     <idno type="SCN">4133</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
               <head>Secular Choir Psalter with Antiphons and Hours, Use of Sarum; England, London;
                  c. 1415</head>
               <msContents>
                  <textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>
                  <msItem n="2" xml:id="MS_Hatton_4-item2">
                     <title key="work_14114" type="desc">Secular choir psalter with antiphons and hours</title>
                     <note> Fol. 1 is a blank paper fly-leaf.</note>
                     <note>[item 1 occupies quires I–III]</note>
                     <msItem n="1">
                        <locus from="2r" to="19v">(fols. 2r–19v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc" key="work_10507"> Sarum Office of the Virgin with the
                           Office of the Cross worked in.</title>
                        <note> Includes suffrages after Lauds of the Holy Spirit, the Trinity, the
                           Cross, the angels, John the Baptist, Peter and Paul, John the Evangelist,
                           Thomas Becket (whose name and the second and third lines of the prayer
                           ‘Deus pro cuius ecclesia ...’ are erased on fols. 10v–11r), Stephen,
                           Lawrence, Nicholas, Mary Magdalene, Catherine of Alexandria, Margaret and
                           All Saints; and variants after Vespers. Salve Regina follows the
                           Compline, ending imperfectly. Fifteenth-century corrections and notes on
                           the divergences of the text from the use of Sarum in the margins of the
                           Office of the Virgin and all other texts in the manuscript. </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <note> [item 2 occupies quire IV]</note>
                     <msItem n="2">
                        <locus from="20r" to="25v">(fols. 20r–25v)</locus>
                        <note> Sarum calendar, written in black and red, laid out one month per page
                           (see Scott, 1995, for a comparison of the Hatton calendar with the
                           version printed by Legg, 1916; see also MS. Hatton 45, another London
                           psalter). The calendar is not graded, apart from the use of colour. The
                           vigils are included only for the months June–December for Christmas, the
                           feasts of the apostles, the Virgin Mary and Lawrence (partly erased).
                           ‘Obitus Ric<ex>ard</ex>i Gregori yrmong<ex>er</ex>’ (4 September) is added by the
                           original scribe. The feasts of David and Chad (1 and 2 March),
                           promulgated in 1415, lack flourished capitals and appear to have been
                           added by the original scribe after the manuscript had been flourished
                           (Scott, 1995, pp. 104–5). This presumably happened soon after it was
                           written, and while it was still in the workshop. Guide-letters for the
                           initials are provided, and similar guide-letters written in red against
                           entries in red are visible under flourished capitals elsewhere in the
                           calendar (e.g. ‘Sancti gregorii’, 12 March; ‘Purificatio’, 2
                           February).</note>
                        <note> The feasts of David and Chad and the obit of Richard Gregory were
                           probably added at the same time: both are in a slightly larger script and
                           have capitals, decorated with double vertical strokes, at the beginning
                           of personal names, unlike other names in the calendar. The addition of
                           the feasts and the obit may have been part of a revision undertaken in
                           the workshop, soon after the manuscript was completed. The manuscript has
                           other corrections which appear to have been made in the original
                           workshop. The original red initial in the word Iniquos on fol. 84v, for
                           example, was erased and replaced by a blue initial with red penwork. The
                           added initial is by a different rubricator, possibly the first rubricator
                           of Hatton 4 (see Scott, 1995, p. 100, on the division of work among the
                           three flourishers of Hatton 4).</note>
                        <note> The feast (30 April) and the translation of Erkenwald (14 November),
                           bishop of London, as well as the translation of Nicholas (9 May), are
                           added in a 15th-century hand, presumably in London. Obits, entered in
                           15th-century hands, partially lost when the leaves were trimmed, perhaps
                           of parishioners of a church in London, include: hardy, twice (4 April),
                           Banest<ex>er</ex> (15 April), <unclear>I</unclear>oh<unclear>anne</unclear>m Mekol (17 April), sergan (23
                           April), dallyng (2 May), leuenthorp (27 May), [...]eman (12 August),
                           [...]lesabet (23 August), [...]lesabet scharburh wyfe (23 December). On
                           fol. 20r in the lower margin are Latin verses on prognostication by
                           thunder in a 15th-century hand, ‘Si tonitru<unclear>us</unclear> fuit in mense januarij
                           ventos validos ...’. The same hand added the feast of Antony of Egypt (17
                           January). The feasts of Thomas Becket and the titles ‘pape’ are erased.
                           The calendar includes 16th-century notes recording the births of the
                           children of Edward, 3rd Lord Windsor of Stanwell between 1559 and 1572
                           (printed by Scott, 1995). The months are headed by verses on the
                           ‘Egyptian’ days which correspond to Hennig’s (1955) set III. </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <note> [items 3–8 occupy quires V–XVII]</note>
                     <msItem n="3">
                        <locus from="26r" to="95r">(fols. 26r–95r)</locus>
                        <note> Psalms 1–150 in the biblical order, laid out with each verse starting
                           on a new line, in two columns, without numbers, with rubrics ‘p(salmu)s’.
                           Psalms 25: 1–27: 3 are missing because of the loss of one leaf after fol.
                           36. Punctuated throughout, with punctus used to mark the ends of verses
                           and minor pauses, and punctus elevatus used to mark metrum. Psalms are
                           accompanied by antiphons, versicles, invitatoria, etc., with short
                           rubrics referring to secular use. Subdivisions within psalms are not
                           indicated, apart from psalm 118, subdivided into eleven 16-verse units.
                           Psalms 148–150 are written without a break as a single text. There are
                           textual divisions at psalms 38, 52, 68, 80, 97 and 109 (see
                           ‘Decoration’). Pages containing the beginnings of psalms 1 and 109 have
                           full borders. The text contains corrections in the hand which also
                           corrected the Office of the Virgin. Fragments of parchment bookmarks (or
                           of glue which used to hold them) mark the beginnings of the seven
                           Penitential Psalms: 6 (fol. 27r), 31 (fol. 38v), 37 (fol. 42v), 50 (fol.
                           48v), 101 (fol. 72r), 129 (fol. 88r), 142 (fol. 92r), and the beginning
                           of the litany (fol. 101v). Some psalm initials have been defaced by wet
                           smudging, possibly as a way of making them more noticeable.</note>
                        <note> The presentation of psalms in Hatton 4 has some similarities with MS.
                           Hatton 9, a secular choir psalter made in the second quarter of the 15th
                           century and used in a parish church in West Wycombe, Buckinghamshire, in
                           the third quarter of the 15th century. Hatton 9, like Hatton 4, has
                           parchment bookmarks marking some Penitential Psalms, and psalms 148–150,
                           a sequence for Lauds at all days of the week, written as a single text.
                        </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="4">
                        <locus from="95r" to="99r">(fols. 95r–99r)</locus>
                        <note> Weekly canticles, with rubrics ‘p(salmu)s’, each followed by
                           antiphons: <list>
                              <item> (1) Confitebor tibi domine (Isaiah 12);</item>
                              <item> (2) Ego dixi (Isaiah 38: 10–21);</item>
                              <item> (3) Exultauit cor meum (1 Samuel 2: 1–11);</item>
                              <item> (4) Cantemus domino (Exodus 15: 1–20);</item>
                              <item> (5) Domine audiui (Habakkuk 3);</item>
                              <item> (6) Audite celi (Deuteronomy 32: 1–44).</item>
                           </list>
                        </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="5">
                        <locus from="99r" to="101v">(fols. 99r–101v)</locus>
                        <note> Daily canticles, prayers and creeds, some with rubrics ‘p(salmu)s’: <list>
                              <item> (1) Te deum laudamus (fol. 99r);</item>
                              <item> (2) Benedicite omnia opera (fol. 99v);</item>
                              <item> (3) Benedictus dominus deus (fol. 100r);</item>
                              <item> (4) Magnificat (fol. 100r);</item>
                              <item> (5) Nunc dimittis (fol. 100v);</item>
                              <item> (6) Athanasian Creed (Quicumque uult ...) (fol. 100v), followed
                                 by antiphons.</item>
                           </list>
                        </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="6">
                        <locus from="101v" to="106r">(fols. 101v–106r)</locus>
                        <note> Sarum litanies for each day of the week with lists of saints
                           identical to Sarum litanies published by Procter and Wordsworth (1886).
                           The litanies for feria secunda are followed by petitions, and collects
                           (fols. 103v–104r) with rubrics ‘oratio’: <list>
                              <item>(1) Deus cui proprium est misereri semper et parcere ...</item>
                              <item> (2) Omnipotens sempiterne deus qui facis ...</item>
                              <item> (3) Deus qui caritatis dona per graciam ...</item>
                              <item> (4) Deus a quo sancta desideria recta ...</item>
                              <item> (5) Ineffabilem misericordiam tuam nobis quesumus domine
                                 clementer ostende ut simul nos ...</item>
                              <item> (6) Fidelium deus omnium conditor et redemptor animabus omnium
                                 fidelium defunctorum ...</item>
                              <item> (7) Pietate tua quesumus domine nostrorum solue omnia uincula
                                 ...</item>
                           </list> The phrase ‘dompnum apostolicum’ is erased on fol. 103r. </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="7">
                        <locus from="106v" to="118v">(fols. 106v–118v)</locus>
                        <note> Sarum Office of the Dead with rubrics, 9 lessons at Matins and the
                           full text of psalms. Includes corrections in the hand that corrected the
                           Office of the Virgin and psalter. </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="8">
                        <locus from="118v" to="123v">(fols. 118v–123v)</locus>
                        <note> Sarum Commendation of the Souls with the full text of psalms (see
                           Procter and Wordsworth, 1886). </note>
                     </msItem>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <p><secFol> dei et opera manuum <locus>(Office of the Virgin, fol.
                        3r)</locus></secFol></p>
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="perg">
                        <support> parchment; paper fly-leaves</support>
                        <extent> 124 leaves <dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                              <height quantity="398">c. 398</height>
                              <width>263</width>
                           </dimensions>
                           <note>Hatton 4 is the same height, but about 15 mm narrower than the
                              ‘Ellesmere Chaucer’ (Scott, 1995). The leaves are trimmed both
                              vertically and horizontally, causing the loss of some catchwords and
                              obits in the calendar. According to Scott, Hatton 4 is one of the
                              seven largest psalters to survive from the 15th century (1996, p. 107)
                           </note></extent>


                        <foliation> modern, in pencil; 1–124.</foliation>
                        <collation> (fol. 1) paper fly-leaf conjoint with the upper pastedown |
                           (fols. 2–17) I–II (8) | (fols. 18–19) III two single (?) leaves, the
                           original structure unclear | (fols. 20–25) IV (6) | (fols. 26–33) V (8) |
                           (fols. 34–40) VI (8−1) missing 4 | (fols. 41–120) VII–XVI (8) | (fols.
                           121–123) XVII (4−1) missing 4 (?) | (fol. 124) paper fly-leaf conjoint
                           with the lower pastedown. Catchwords and leaf signatures (which start at
                           ‘a’ in quire V, fol. 26) survive</collation>
                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout columns="2" writtenLines="26">Ruled in purple ink for two columns with single vertical and
                           horizontal bounding lines, extending the full height and width of page;
                           written below the top line; 26 lines per page; prickings survive; written
                           space: <dimensions type="written" unit="mm">
                              <height quantity="270">c. 270</height>
                              <width>170</width>
                           </dimensions></layout>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc>
                     <handNote script="textualisNorthern" execution="formata"> Large formal Gothic
                        book hand; smaller script used for antiphons, etc.; black ink.</handNote>
                  </handDesc>
                  <decoDesc>
                     <summary>Illuminated by three artists, two of whom are probably also
                        responsible for the illumination in San Marino, Huntington Library MS. EL 26
                        C 9 (the ‘Ellesmere Chaucer’ (Scott, 1995)). Hand A is responsible for
                        borders on fols. 2r, 7r, 49v, 56r, 64r; Hand B, whose work does not appear
                        in Ellesmere, is responsible for spray initials on fols. 12v, 14r, 15r, 16r,
                        17r, 18r; and Hand C is responsible for borders on fols. 26r, 43r, 71r, 79r,
                        106v, 118v. The work of Hand B appears only in the Office of the Virgin
                        (quires II–III).</summary>
                     <decoNote type="monogram">Blue KL monograms with red penwork in the
                        calendar.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="decInit">5- to 6-line pink and blue initials in gold frames and
                        on gold, pink and blue backgrounds, decorated with coiled tendrils and
                        leaves, and full or three-quarter borders, made of gold bars, decorated with
                        sprays of foliage and gold discs, at the beginnings of Matins and Lauds in
                        the Office of the Virgin (fols. 2r and 7r), psalms 1 (fol. 26r), 38 (fol.
                        43r), 52 (fol. 49v), 68 (fol. 56r), 80 (fol. 64r), 97 (fol. 71r), 109 (fol.
                        79r) and the Office of the Dead (fol. 106v).</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="border">Major initials with full or three-quarter borders, as
                        above.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="decInit">5- to 6-line pink and blue initials in gold frames on
                        gold, pink and blue backgrounds, decorated with coiled tendrils, sprays of
                        foliage and gold discs, extending into the margins, at the beginnings of the
                        hours in the Office of the Virgin.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="decInit">4-line pink and blue initial in a gold frame and on
                        gold, pink and blue background, decorated with coiled tendrils and leaves,
                        and a three-quarter border made of gold bars, decorated with sprays of
                        leaves and gold discs, at the beginning of the Commendation of the
                        Souls.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="flourInit">2-line blue initials with red penwork at the
                        beginnings of psalms, canticles, litany, prayers and sections of the
                        offices.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="flourInit">1-line alternating red and blue initials, with
                        contrasting purple and blue penwork, at the beginnings of verses and periods
                        and feasts in the calendar.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="lineFill">Red and blue line-endings.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="rubrication"> rubrics in red ink</decoNote>
                  </decoDesc>
                  <bindingDesc>

                     <binding notAfter="1800" notBefore="1700">
                        <p> Sprinkled brown leather over pasteboard, 18th century. Double blind
                           fillet border round the outer edge of both covers. Blind roll border with
                           arabesque designs next to the spine on both covers. Rebacked in the
                           Bodleian with the original spine relaid. Eight raised bands on spine.
                           Gilt lettering on spine ‘HATTON || 108’. Paper label on spine with ‘M.S.
                           || Hatton || 4’. Paper pastedowns and fly-leaves added when the
                           manuscript was rebacked. </p>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="1420" notBefore="1410">15th century,
                        beginning (c. 1415)</origDate>
                     <origPlace>
                        <country key="place_7002445">English</country>, <settlement key="place_7011781">London</settlement>
                     </origPlace>
                  </origin>
                  <provenance>Made for the use in choir in a secular church, as suggested by a large
                     size and the presence of antiphons, versicles, invitatoria, etc. with rubrics
                     referring to secular use. The London origin is suggested by a near contemporary
                     obit of Richard Gregory, a citizen of London, d. 1397 (Scott, 1995), though
                     unlike in MS. Hatton 45 there are no specifically London saints in the calendar
                     or litany. The church may have been St Lawrence Jewry (Lawrence is the only
                     non-biblical saint in the calendar given a vigil) or St Peter’s upon Cornhill
                     in London. Richard Gregory’s will specifies a bequest for interment in the
                     chapel of St Mary at St Peter’s and further bequests for improvements to the
                     church and to the chaplains (see Scott, 1995, p. 103). The rector of St Peter’s
                     upon Cornhill in the first quarter of the 15th century was John Whitby, named
                     as Richard Gregory’s executor on several documents. In a writ, dated 23 October
                     1397 (London, National Archives, C 131/213), he appears as Richard Gregory’s
                     executor with another chaplain, John atte Felde. In another writ, dated 28
                     March 1404 (London, National Archives, C 241/193), he appears as the executor
                     of Richard Gregory and administrator of his goods. In <title>A survey of the cities of
                     London and Westminster and the borough of Southwark</title> John Strype reports that
                     the church of St Peter upon Cornhill had a library and a prominent grammar
                     school (1754–55, vol. 1, p. 464) and that the books in the library were ‘viewed
                     and commended’ by John Leland. Leland mentions the library and, selectively,
                     its books in his <title>Collectanea</title> and <title>Itinerary</title>, but does not include any liturgical
                     books (see Hearne, 1774, iv, p. 48; Toulmin Smith, 1906–10, iv, pp. 54–5;
                     Harris, 2005). </provenance>
                  <provenance>15th-century addition of the feasts of St Erkenwald, patron of London,
                     to the calendar (‘Sancti Erkkynvaldi episcopi’, 30 April, and ‘transelacio
                     sancti Erkkynvaldi episcopi londoniensis’, 14 November) suggests that the
                     psalter continued to be used in the diocese of London. The obits in
                     15th-century hands in the calendar, the addition of the feasts and the presence
                     of corrections and notes comparing the text to the use of Sarum suggest a
                     continued use in a church, rather than private use. The obit ‘leuenthorp’ (27
                     May) is of John Leventhorpe (b. 1360), Receiver General of the Duchy of
                     Lancaster, who had an office in the city of London and died on 27 May 1435 (see
                     Kerr, 1935). His obit also appears on 27 May in the calendar of an early
                     15th-century missal, Cambridge, Trinity College MS. B. 11. 3, with other obits
                     of the Leventhorpe family (James, 1900–04). He is buried in Great Saint Mary’s
                     Church, Sawbridgeworth, Hertfordshire (<title>Monumental inscriptions</title>, 1989, p. 35). </provenance>
                  <provenance>The records of births of the children of <persName role="fmo" key="person_3968">Edward, 3rd Baron Windsor of
                     Stanwell (c. 1532–1574/5)</persName> between 1559 and 1572. </provenance>
                  <provenance><persName role="fmo" key="person_2747">Thomas Windsor, 6th Baron Windsor of Stanwell (d. 1641)</persName>, whose birth
                     is recorded on fol. 22r. </provenance>
                  <provenance><persName role="fmo" key="person_37729288">Christopher, first Baron Hatton (bap. 1605, d. 1670)</persName>, see ODNB.
                     Acquired from Thomas Windsor. </provenance>
                  <provenance>Robert Scott, London bookseller (b. in or before 1632, d. 1709/10),
                     see ODNB: bought as part of the library of Christopher Hatton. </provenance>
                  <acquisition when="1671">Bodleian Library: bought in 1671 from Scott; came to the Library in
                     September 1671 (see Summary catalogue, vol. 2, part 2, pp. 801–2). Former
                     shelfmark: ‘Hatton 108’ (fol. 2r). On fol. 2r ‘Breuiarium Romanum’.
                  </acquisition>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>Elizabeth Solopova, <title>Latin
                              Liturgical Psalters in the Bodleian Library: A Select
                              Catalogue</title> (Oxford, 2013), pp. 226–32. Previously described in
                           the Summary Catalogue. <listBibl>
                              <bibl facs="aaq0218.gif" type="SC">Summary Catalogue, Vol. 2 Part 2,
                                 p. 859</bibl>
                           </listBibl>
                        </source>
                     </recordHist>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <surrogates>
                     <bibl subtype="partial" type="digital-facsimile">
                        <ref target="https://digital.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/objects/d12292a2-3d03-477e-874b-f19bbdfe80a8/">
                           <title>Digital Bodleian</title>
                        </ref>
                        <note>(6 images from 35mm slides)</note>
                     </bibl>
                  </surrogates>
                  <listBibl type="WRAPPER">
                     <listBibl type="PRINT">
                        <head>Select bibliography to 2009:</head>
                        <listBibl>
                           <bibl>Strype, J., <title>A survey of the cities of London and Westminster
                                 and the borough of Southwark: containing the original, antiquity,
                                 increase, present state and government of those cities written at
                                 first in the year 1698 by John Stow; corrected, improved and very
                                 much enlarged, in the year 1720 by John Strype</title>, 6th edn., 2
                              vols. (London: Printed for W. Innys and J. Richardson,
                              1754–55).</bibl>
                           <bibl>Hearne, T., <title>Joannis Lelandi antiquarii De rebus Britannicis
                                 collectanea, 6 vols.</title> (London: Benj. White, 1774).</bibl>
                           <bibl>Procter, F. and Wordsworth, C., <title>Breviarium ad usum insignis
                                 ecclesiae Sarum, 3 vols.</title> (London: CUP; C. J. Clay and Sons,
                              1886).</bibl>
                           <bibl>Sharpe, R. R., <title>Calendar of wills proved and enrolled in the
                                 Court of Husting, London, A. D. 1258–A. D. 1688: preserved among
                                 the archives of the Corporation of the City of London, at the
                                 Guildhall</title>, 2 vols. (London: John C. Francis,
                              1889–90).</bibl>
                           <bibl>Hoskins, E., <title>Horae beatae Mariae virginis; or, Sarum and
                                 York primers with kindred books and primers of the reformed Roman
                                 use</title> (London: Green and Co, 1901).</bibl>
                           <bibl>James, M. R., <title>The western manuscripts in the library of
                                 Trinity College, Cambridge: a descriptive catalogue, 4
                                 vols.</title> (Cambridge: University Press, 1900–04), vol. 1, pp.
                              329–30.</bibl>
                           <bibl>Toulmin Smith, L., <title>The itinerary of John Leland in or about
                                 the years 1535–1543</title> (London: G. Bell, 1906–10).</bibl>
                           <bibl> Sharpe, R. R., <title>Calendar of letter-books preserved among the
                                 archives of the Corporation of the City of London at the Guildhall.
                                 Letter-book A–L, 11 vols.</title> (London, 1899–1912).</bibl>
                           <bibl>Maxwell Lyte, H. C. (ed.), <title>A descriptive catalogue of
                                 ancient deeds in the Public Record Office</title>, 6 vols. (London:
                              1890–1915).</bibl>
                           <bibl>Leach, A. F., <title>The schools of medieval England</title>
                              (London: Methuen, 1915; reprinted London: Routledge, 2007).</bibl>
                           <bibl>Legg, J. W., <title>The Sarum missal edited from three early
                                 manuscripts</title> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1916).</bibl>
                           <bibl>Kerr, P. W., ‘The Leventhorps of Sawbridgeworth’,
                                 <title>Transactions of the East Hertfordshire Archaeological
                                 Society</title> 9, part II (1935), pp. 129–51.</bibl>
                           <bibl>Summary catalogue, vol. 2, part 2, no. 4133.</bibl>
                           <bibl>S. J. P. van Dijk, <title>Latin Liturgical Manuscripts in the
                                 Bodleian Library, Oxford, vol. 2: Office Books</title> (typescript,
                              1957), <citedRange unit="page" from="113" to="113">p. 113</citedRange>
                           </bibl>
                           <bibl><ref target="https://catalog.hathitrust.org/Record/000468709">Pächt
                                 and Alexander</ref> (1966–73), vol. 3, no. 807, pl. LXXIX.</bibl>
                           <bibl>Fitch, M. (ed.), <title>Index to testamentary records in the
                                 Commissary Court of London (London Division): now preserved in the
                                 Guildhall Library</title>, London, 6 vols. (London: British Record
                              Society, 1969–98).</bibl>
                           <bibl><title>Monumental inscriptions: Great St. Mary’s Sawbridgeworth
                                 (Hertfordshire)</title> (Ware: Hertfordshire Family and Population
                              History Society, 1989).</bibl>
                           <bibl>Scott, K. L., ‘An hours and psalter by two Ellesmere illuminators’
                              in M. Stevens and D. Woodward (eds.), <title>The Ellesmere Chaucer:
                                 essays in interpretation</title> (San Marino, CA: Huntington
                              Library, 1995), pp. 87–119.</bibl>
                           <bibl>Scott (1996), vol. 2, pp. 107, 142.</bibl>
                           <bibl>Harris, O., ‘“Motheaten, mouldye, and rotten”: the early custodial
                              history and dissemination of John Leland’s manuscript remains’,
                                 <title>BLR</title> 18 no. 5 (April 2005), pp. 460–501.</bibl>
                           <bibl>The National Archives, Online Catalogue
                              (http://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/catalogue/; accessed 10 June
                              2009).</bibl>
                        </listBibl>



                     </listBibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2024-05">Add extent and leaf dimensions from Summary Catalogue.</change>
         <change when="2024-04-08">Encode full description from Solopova catalogue.</change>
         <change when="2017-07-01">First online publication.</change>
         <change when="2017-05-25">
            <persName>James Cummings</persName> Up-converted the markup using <ref target="https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl">https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl</ref>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>