<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="manuscript_9787">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>MS. Tanner 106</title>
            <title type="collection">MSS. Tanner</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Summary description</resp>
               <persName>Matthew Holford</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </publisher>
            <idno type="msID">MS_Tanner_106</idno>
            <idno type="collection">Tanner</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="MS_Tanner_106" xml:lang="en">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <region type="county">Oxfordshire</region>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <institution>University of Oxford</institution>
                  <repository>Bodleian Library</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">MS. Tanner 106</idno>
                  <idno type="ieArk">ark:29072/x0kh04dp56sb</idno><idno type="crArk">ark:29072/x0jq085k10ks</idno><altIdentifier type="internal">
                     <idno type="SCN">9932</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
               <head>Guardbook of charters, letters and other documents, 1463-1557</head>
               <msContents>
                  <summary>Includes papers of the lawyer <persName key="person_3720">Edward White, of Filby, d. 1528</persName> (F. Blomefield, <title>An Essay Towards A Topographical History of the County of Norfolk</title> 5 (1806), p. 505); a few <persName key="person_10646024">Paston</persName> family papers; some documents from religious houses mostly in Norfolk and Suffolk; and documents from <orgName key="org_140757625">Christ Church Oxford</orgName>.</summary>
                  <textLang mainLang="la" otherLangs="en">Latin and English</textLang>
                  <msItem n="1" xml:id="MS_Tanner_106-item1">
                     <locus from="1">(fol. 1)</locus>
                     <note>Receipt and quitclaim from Henry Wyat, knight, to Edmund Whyte, esquire, for £20 
                        for the purchase (pro perquisitione) of the manor of Parva Thorpe (Little Thorp)
                        Norfolk; Apr. 30, 1529.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="2" xml:id="MS_Tanner_106-item2">
                     <locus from="2">(fol. 2)</locus>
                     <note>Grant by Anne countess of Oxford to Edward Whyte, esquire, of an annuity of 26s. 8d. for the term of her life. Nov. 8, 1526.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="3" xml:id="MS_Tanner_106-item3">
                     <locus from="3">(fol. 3)</locus>
                     <note>Grant by Thomas Feyns, lord Dacre (Dakrys) to Edward Whyte, esquire, of a lifetime annuity of a buck and doe ('a doo') from the manor of Horsford (Horseford), Norfolk; Jun. 3, 1513. </note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="4" xml:id="MS_Tanner_106-item4">
                     <locus from="5">(fol. 5)</locus>
                     <note>Grant by Edmund Stretham, prior of the Crossed Friars by the Tower of London, to James Love of Sudbury, Suffolk, yeoman, of a piece of land called 'Punteslond' in Great Waldingfield (Waldyngfeld Magna); Mar. 16, 1533.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="5" xml:id="MS_Tanner_106-item5">
                     <locus from="6">(fol. 6)</locus>
                     <note>Grant by Philip Calthrope, knight, Thomas Blenerhaysett, knight, John
                        Blenerhaysett, Edward White and Richard Loyde, esquires, to Miles Hobert, esquire, of the manors of Witton [near Blofield] (Wytton), Litte Plumstead (Parva Plumsted) and Brundall (Brundale) [Norfolk] as the jointure of Ellen Hobert wife of Miles. [5] Henry VIII.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="6" xml:id="MS_Tanner_106-item6">
                     <locus from="7">(fol. 7)</locus>
                     <note> Receipt for the rent of a close, given under the hand of Robert
                        <supplied>Walkingtone</supplied>, abbot of Langley, in Norfolk; Feb. 6th 1532. (English)</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="7" xml:id="MS_Tanner_106-item7">
                     <locus from="8">(fol. 8)</locus>
                     <note> Receipt given to Thomas Lucas under the hand of John <supplied>Melford, alias
                        Reeve</supplied>, abbot of Bury St. Edmund’s, for payment of an annuity due to him in
                        right of his church; Dec. 1st 1532.  (English)</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="8" xml:id="MS_Tanner_106-item8">
                     <locus from="9">(fol. 9)</locus>
                     <note> Receipt given under the hand of William Waller of Ipswich, for money paid
                        by John Southwell for the purchase of certain lands in Coddenham [Suffolk]; Oct. 4th
                        1534.  (English)</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="9" xml:id="MS_Tanner_106-item9">
                     <locus from="10">( fol. 10)</locus>
                     <note>Grant by Thomas Thomas Howard, earl of Surrey, to Edward Whyte, for life, of an annuity of 4m. from the manor Winfarthing (Wynferthyng), Norfolk, and of the office of steward of the manor of Framingham Earl (Framyngham comitis); Mar. 10, 1520.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="10" xml:id="MS_Tanner_106-item10">
                     <locus from="11">(fol. 11)</locus>
                     <note>Grant by Christopher Willoughbe, knight, to Edward Whyte, of a lifetime annuity of £3 6s. 8d. from the manor of Parham, Suffolk. Feb. 22, 1527/8.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="11" xml:id="MS_Tanner_106-item11">
                     <locus from="12">(fol. 12)</locus>
                     <note>Grant by Walter Hobart and Anne his wife, to Thomas Wentworth, lord Wentworth, and others, of the manor of Flixton (Flyxton), Suffolk; Jan. 10, 1537.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="12" xml:id="MS_Tanner_106-item12">
                     <locus from="13">(fol. 13)</locus>
                     <note>Grant of confirmation by Thomas Howard, earl of Surrey, and Edmund Jenney, to James Hobart and others, of lands in Norfolk called 'Chapeleyns', 'Coks', and 'Griggis'; Feb. 4, 1510..</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="13" xml:id="MS_Tanner_106-item13">
                     <locus>(fols. 14, 15)</locus>
                     <note> Autographs of the privy council appointed by Henry VIII to exercise the
                        authority of the crown during the minority of Edward VI. (English)</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="14" xml:id="MS_Tanner_106-item14">
                     <locus from="14v">(fol. 14v)</locus>
                     <note> Order from Dr. William Tresham, subdean of Christ Church, Oxford, for the
                        payment of five marks to one T. Byllingsley for two standard candlesticks,
                        &amp;c. ; Dec. 23d 1553. (English)</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="15" xml:id="MS_Tanner_106-item15">
                     <locus from="15v">(fol. 15v)</locus>
                     <note> Dr. William Tresham to sir Colman, parish priest of Dorton,
                        Buckinghamshire; sends one John Drasier to make up the high altar; June 10th
                        1554. (English)</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="16" xml:id="MS_Tanner_106-item16">
                     <locus from="16">(fol. 16)</locus>
                     <note> Dr. William Cooke, dean of the Arches’ in the reign of Edward VI, to the
                        vicar of Harrow-on-the-Hill, for the payment of arrears of procurations. (English)</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="17" xml:id="MS_Tanner_106-item17">
                     <locus from="16v">(fol. 16v)</locus>
                     <note> Dr. Richard Croke, canon of Christ Church, Oxford, on the old Foundation,
                        to Thomas Palmer. (English)</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="18" xml:id="MS_Tanner_106-item18">
                     <locus from="18">(fol. 18)</locus>
                     <note>Letter of attorney by James Hubert and Robert Sowthewell appointing 
                        Robert Fuller and Henry Warner for the manors of Morley Deopham (Depeham), Norfolk; Oct. 28, 1526.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="19" xml:id="MS_Tanner_106-item19">
                     <locus from="19">(fol. 19)</locus>
                     <note>Quitclaim by George Fastolf to 
                        William Paston of the manors of Caister (Caistor), Bedeham,
                        &amp;c. in Norfolk; Feb. 4, 1542. </note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="20" xml:id="MS_Tanner_106-item20">
                     <locus from="20">(fol. 20)</locus>
                     <note> Acknowledgments by sir Richard Wyngfeld of money received from sir Edw.
                        Ichingham for suit of assize for the lordships of Topcroft, Wootton, and
                        Denton; ann. 1516, 1517. (English)</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="21" xml:id="MS_Tanner_106-item21">
                     <locus from="22">(fol. 22)</locus>
                     <note> Letter from John Paslevv, abbot of Whalley, to Thomas Grymedyche. (English)</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="22" xml:id="MS_Tanner_106-item22">
                     <locus from="23">(fol. 23)</locus>
                     <note> Acknowledgment by sir John Jernegan of money received from Robert Crane
                        for lands formerly belonging to the prior of Woodbridge; Jan. 14th 1537. (English)</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="23" xml:id="MS_Tanner_106-item23">
                     <locus from="24">(fol. 24)</locus>
                     <note> Letter from John Baker, prior of Lees, to Mr. Jernyngham, confirming the
                        grant of certain lands out of the manor of Gapton Hall, in Bradwell [Suffolk], to “sir
                        William Jakson, prist;” Oct. 11th 1526. (English)</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="24" xml:id="MS_Tanner_106-item24">
                     <locus from="25">(fol. 25)</locus>
                     <note>Receipt of William Lakenham, prior of St Andrew's, Bromholm (Bromeholm),
                        for 40s. from John Jettoner, farmer of a moiety of the tithes of Carlton Colville (Carleton Colvyll),
                        Suffolk; Jan. 30, 1531. </note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="25" xml:id="MS_Tanner_106-item25">
                     <locus from="26">(fol. 26)</locus>
                     <note>Letter of Thomas Howard, first earl of Surrey, to Symonde White; “written in the
                        Castell of Shirefhoton [Sheriff Hutton], the xith day of Juyn.” . (English)</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="26" xml:id="MS_Tanner_106-item26">
                     <locus from="27">(fol. 27)</locus>
                     <note> Acquittance by sir John Williams, treasurer of the court of
                        augmentations, for money paid by Thomas Woodhowse, of Waxham, for lands and
                        tenements left for the maintenance of obits, lights, lamps, and
                        anniversaries in sundry churches in Norfolk; July 5th 1548. (English)</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="27" xml:id="MS_Tanner_106-item27">
                     <locus from="28">(fol. 28)</locus>
                     <note> Expenses of James Curthropp, canon of Christ Church, Oxford, to London
                        in Midsummer term. (English)</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="28" xml:id="MS_Tanner_106-item28">
                     <locus from="28v">(fol. 28v)</locus>
                     <note> Acquittance by Rob. Ward, [disputant with bishop Ridley,] for money paid
                        him by the treasurer of Christ Church, Oxford, for the “lesson of
                        phylosophy;” July 1st 1557. (English)</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="29" xml:id="MS_Tanner_106-item29">
                     <locus from="29">(fol. 29)</locus>
                     <note>Letter of Dr. William Tresham, subdean of Christ Church, and the canons, to their
                        bailiff and tenants in East Walton, requiring them to pay their rents to Mr.
                        Mildmaye; June 29th 1557. (English)</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="30" xml:id="MS_Tanner_106-item30">
                     <locus from="29v">(fol. 29v)</locus>
                     <note> Acquittance by Roger Marbeck, canon of Christ Church, Oxford, for Mr.
                        Goodryck’s fee; May 18th 1557. (English)</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="31" xml:id="MS_Tanner_106-item31">
                     <locus from="30">(fol. 30)</locus>
                     <note> Henry Syddall’s expenses in certain business of the church in
                        Staffordshire and Cheshire, an. 1553. (English)</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="32" xml:id="MS_Tanner_106-item32">
                     <locus from="30v">(fol. 30v)</locus>
                     <note> Acquittance by sir Edw. North, chancellor of the court of augmentations,
                        for half a years fee received of the dean and chapter of Christ Church,
                        Oxford; June 22d 1554. (English)</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="33" xml:id="MS_Tanner_106-item33">
                     <locus from="30v">(fol.
                        30v)</locus>
                     <note> Acquittance by Arthur Cole for money received of the dean and chapter of
                        Christ Church, Oxford, for the portion of Chalgrove; Sept. 16th 1553. (English)</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="34" xml:id="MS_Tanner_106-item34">
                     <locus from="31">(fol.
                        31)</locus>
                     <note>Letter of Alexander Belsyr, canon of Christ Church, Oxford, to Thomas Palmer. (English)</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="35" xml:id="MS_Tanner_106-item35">
                     <locus from="32">(fol.
                        32)</locus>
                     <note>Letter of Richard Bruerne, canon of Christ Church, Oxford, to the same. (English)</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="36" xml:id="MS_Tanner_106-item36">
                     <locus from="33">(fol. 33)</locus>
                     <note>Letter of John viscount Beaumont to Barthe White; dated “Eppeworth, 21 day of Juyll.”
                        (English)</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="37" xml:id="MS_Tanner_106-item37">
                     <locus>(fols. 33v, 35)</locus>
                     <note> Autographs of Edward VI. and of several eminent men during his reign.
                        (English)</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="38" xml:id="MS_Tanner_106-item38">
                     <locus from="34">(fol. 34)</locus>
                     <note> Memorandum of expenses, made by Richard Wilks, receiver in the family of
                        Dr. Thomas Goodrich, bp. of Ely. (English)</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="39" xml:id="MS_Tanner_106-item39">
                     <locus from="35v">(fol. 35v)</locus>
                     <note> Declaration of Ralph Lampet touching the will of sir John Fastolf as to
                        the manor of Caistor, and other manors in Norfolk; March 19th 1463. (English)</note>
                     <listBibl>
                        <bibl>James Gairdner, <title>The Paston letters, 1422-1509</title> (1904), no. 541</bibl>
                        <bibl>N. Davis et al., <title>Paston Letters and Papers</title>, no. 891</bibl>
                     </listBibl>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="40" xml:id="MS_Tanner_106-item40">
                     <locus from="36">(fol. 36)</locus>
                     <note>Letter of Henry Ratcliffe, earl of Sussex, to his “aunte my ladie Hubberd;”
                        Attleborough, July 19th 1551. (English)</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="41" xml:id="MS_Tanner_106-item41">
                     <locus from="36v">(fol. 36v)</locus>
                     <note> Acquittance by Dr. Thomas White for the procurations of East Garston; Nov.
                        11th 1551. (English)</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="42" xml:id="MS_Tanner_106-item42">
                     <locus from="36v">(fol. 36v)</locus>
                     <note> Acquittance by John Birde, bishop of Chester, for half a year’s pension
                        for Kirkham; Oct. 22d 1551. (English)</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="43" xml:id="MS_Tanner_106-item43">
                     <locus from="37">(fol. 37)</locus>
                     <note>Charter of sale by John Clere, knight, to William Paston, esquire, of part of the manor of Hornynghall and Cleres [in Caister]; Jan. 10th 1556.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="44" xml:id="MS_Tanner_106-item44">
                     <locus from="38">(fol. 38)</locus>
                     <note>Letter of William Potkyn to William Hare, touching the letting of part of the manor of
                        Antyngham. (English)</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="45" xml:id="MS_Tanner_106-item45">
                     <locus from="39">(fol. 39)</locus>
                     <note>Letter of Dr. Richard Nykke, bishop of Norwich, to the same; some things concerning
                        the rectory of Newton Flotman; ruinous state of the parsonage of Hingham. (English)</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="46" xml:id="MS_Tanner_106-item46">
                     <locus from="39v">(fol. 39v)</locus>
                     <note>Letter of John Algood to “Mastyr Appylton,” denying the claim of the prior of
                        Colne to rent for certain lands. (English)</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="47" xml:id="MS_Tanner_106-item47">
                     <locus from="40">(fol. 40)</locus>
                     <note> Acquittance by Seth Hollande to the dean and chapter of Christ Church,
                        Oxford, for two years’ pension due to the bishop of Worcester, out of the
                        parsonages of Twining, Thornbury, Tedbury and Little Compton; May 29th 1557. (English)</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="48" xml:id="MS_Tanner_106-item48">
                     <locus from="41">(fol. 41)</locus>
                     <note>Letter of Sir William Penyngton and Thomas Godsalve to William Potkyn, touching the
                        settlement of certain matters in dispute between his tenants and the vicar
                        of Honing [Norfolk]. (English)</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="49" xml:id="MS_Tanner_106-item49">
                     <locus from="42">(fol. 42)</locus>
                     <note> Acquittance by Richard Thornden, bishop of Dover, vice-collector to
                        cardinal Pole, for money received of sir Hugh Turnbull, treasurer and
                        prebendary of Christ Church, Canterbury, for first-fruits and tenths; Dec.
                        1st 1557. (English)</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="50" xml:id="MS_Tanner_106-item50">
                     <locus from="42v">(fol. 42v)</locus>
                     <note> Acquittance by Dr. Nicholas Harpisfeld for money received of Alexander Belsyr,
                        canon of Christ Church, Oxford, for procurations from the rectories of
                        Ashendon (Ashenden), Dorton, and Lathbury [Bucks]; Feb. 25th 1547 . (English)</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="51" xml:id="MS_Tanner_106-item51">
                     <locus from="43">(fol. 43)</locus>
                     <note> Acquittance by Nicholas Grimold, rhetoric-reader at Christ Church, Oxford,
                        for money paid him by Henry Syddall, sub-dean, for the stipend of his
                        lecture, &amp;c. ; Oct. 3d 1550. (English)</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="52" xml:id="MS_Tanner_106-item52">
                     <locus from="44">(fol. 44)</locus>
                     <note> Acquittance by William Haynes, sub-dean of Christ Church, Oxford, for
                        money received of sir Thomas Holcroft, for the rent of the parsonage of
                        Frodsham [Cheshire]; Dec. 10th 1547. (English)</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="53" xml:id="MS_Tanner_106-item53">
                     <locus from="44v">(fol. 44v)</locus>
                     <note> Acquittance by Dr. Richard Cox, dean of Christ Church, Oxford, for money
                        received of sir Thomas Holcroft, for the rent of the parsonage of Kirkham [Lancashire]; May
                        30th 1547. (English)</note>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="mixed">
                        <support>paper and parchment</support>
                        <extent>44 'leaves'</extent>
                     </supportDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="1557" notBefore="1463">1463–1557</origDate>
                     <origPlace><country key="place_7002445">England</country></origPlace>
                  </origin>

                  <provenance notAfter="1735" notBefore="1674">
                     <persName key="person_11058091" role="fmo">Thomas Tanner, 1674–1735</persName>
                  </provenance>
                  <acquisition resp="#MMM" when="1735">Bequeathed by him to the Bodleian in
                     1735.</acquisition>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>
                           Description adapted (March 2023) from the Quarto Catalogue (A. Hackman,
                              <title>Catalogi codicum manuscriptorum Bibliothecæ Bodleianæ pars
                              quarta codices viri admodum reverendi Thomæ Tanneri, S.T.P., episcopi
                              Asaphensis, complectens</title>, Quarto Catalogues IV, repr. 1966,
                           with corrections, from the ed. of 1860). 
                           <listBibl>
                              <bibl facs="ace0246.gif" type="QUARTO">Quarto Catalogue, cols.
                                 475-6</bibl>
                              <bibl facs="ace0247.gif" type="QUARTO">Quarto Catalogue, cols.
                                 477-8</bibl>
                           </listBibl><listBibl>
                              <bibl facs="aas0099.gif" type="SC">Summary Catalogue, Vol. 3, p.
                                 84</bibl>
                           </listBibl>
                        </source>
                     </recordHist>
                  </adminInfo>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2023-02">Record created.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>