<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="manuscript_7662">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>MS. Laud Lat. 84</title>
            <title type="collection">MSS. Laud Lat. (Latin)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp when="2013">Cataloguer</resp>
               <persName>Elizabeth Solopova</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding</resp>
               <persName>Matthew Holford</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </publisher>
            <idno type="msID">MS_Laud_Lat_84</idno>
            <idno type="collection">Laud_lat</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="MS_Laud_Lat_84" xml:lang="en">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <region type="county">Oxfordshire</region>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <institution>University of Oxford</institution>
                  <repository>Bodleian Library</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">MS. Laud Lat. 84</idno>
                  <idno type="ieArk">ark:29072/x08w32r605g8</idno><idno type="crArk">ark:29072/x0w3763624r6</idno><altIdentifier type="internal">
                     <idno type="SCN">770</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
               <head>Portable psalter; French Flanders, Cambrai (?), late 13th or early 14th
                  century</head>
               <msContents>
                  <msItem class="#liturgica #biblia" xml:id="MS_Laud_Lat_84-item1">
                     <title key="work_14114" type="desc">Psalter </title>
                     <msItem>
                        <note>[item 1 occupies quires I–II]</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="1" xml:id="MS_Laud_Lat_84-item1-1">
                        <locus from="1v" to="13r">(fols. 1v–13r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Calendar</title>
                        <note>Laid out one month per two facing pages, written in black and red,
                           approximately one-quarter full, not graded. Includes Aldegundis (30
                           January), Gertrude of Nivelles (17 March), Valeric of Leuconay (1 April),
                           Servatius, bishop of Tongres (14 May), Godeleva (6 July), Germanus of
                           Auxerre (31 July), Arnulf, bishop of Soissons (16 August), Egidius (1
                           September), Bertin, abbot of St-Omer (5 September), Lambert, bishop of
                           Liège (17 September), Firminus, the first bishop of Amiens (25
                           September), Remigius, bishop of Reims (1 October), Leodegar of Autun (2
                           October), Quentin of Amiens (31 October), Martin of Tours in red (11
                           November) and Eligius, bishop of Tournai in red (1 December). Also
                           includes Benedict (21 March and 11 July), Potentiana (20 May), Oswald (5
                           August), Elizabeth of Hungary (17 November), Catherine in red (25
                           November), Nicholas in red (6 December) and Thomas Becket in red (29
                           December). The months are headed by notes on the length of the solar and
                           lunar month, e.g. ‘Ianuarius habet dies xxxi luna xxx’. Fols. 1r and 13v
                           are blank.</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <note>[items 2–6 occupy quires III–XLVIII]</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="2" xml:id="MS_Laud_Lat_84-item1-2">
                        <locus from="14r" to="18v">(fols. 14r–18v)</locus>
                        <note>Full-page miniatures illustrating the life of Christ, painted on the
                           versos only.</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="3" xml:id="MS_Laud_Lat_84-item1-3">
                        <locus from="19r" to="340v">(fols. 19r–340v)</locus>
                        <note>Psalms 1–150, written with each verse starting on a new line, without
                           titles or numbers. Punctuated throughout, with punctus used to mark the
                           ends of verses and punctus elevatus occasionally used to mark metrum. The
                           psalms are in the biblical order, subdivisions within psalms are not
                           indicated, apart from psalm 118, subdivided into twenty-two 8-verse
                           units. There are textual divisions at psalms 26, 38, 52, 68, 80, 97 and
                           109 (see ‘Decoration’).</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="4" xml:id="MS_Laud_Lat_84-item1-4">
                        <locus from="340v" to="359r">(fols. 340v–359r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Weekly canticles, without titles:</title>
                        <msItem n="1">
                           <note>Confitebor tibi domine (Isaiah 12)</note>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem n="2">
                           <note>Ego dixi (Isaiah 38: 10–21)</note>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem n="3">
                           <note>Exultauit cor meum (1 Samuel 2: 1–11)</note>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem n="4">
                           <note>Cantemus domino (Exodus 15: 1–20)</note>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem n="5">
                           <note>Domine audiui (Habakkuk 3)</note>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem n="6">
                           <note>Audite celi (Deuteronomy 32: 1–44)</note>
                        </msItem>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="5" xml:id="MS_Laud_Lat_84-item1-5">
                        <locus from="359r" to="371r">(fols. 359r–371r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Daily canticles, prayers and creeds, without
                           titles:</title>
                        <msItem n="1">
                           <note>Benedicite omnia opera (fol. 359r)</note>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem n="2">
                           <note>Benedictus dominus deus (fol. 361v)</note>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem n="3">
                           <note>Magnificat (fol. 363r)</note>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem n="4">
                           <note>Nunc dimittis (fol. 364r)</note>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem n="5">
                           <note>Te deum laudamus (fol. 364r)</note>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem n="6">
                           <note>Athanasian Creed (Quicumque uult . . .) (fol. 366v)</note>
                        </msItem>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="6" xml:id="MS_Laud_Lat_84-item1-6">
                        <locus from="371r" to="377v">(fols. 371r–377v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Litany</title>
                        <note>Including seventeen apostles and evangelists, Victor (of
                           Marseilles (?)) and Eustace among the martyrs; Martin (fourth), Remigius,
                           Maximus (bishop of Riez (?)) and Benedict among the confessors.</note>
                        <note> Followed by petitions, and three collects (fols. 376v–377v):</note>
                        <incipit>Exaudi domine supplicum preces et confitentium tibi parce peccatis
                           ut pariter nobis indulgentiam tribuas benignus et pacem </incipit>
                        <incipit>Deus qui nos patrem et matrem honorare precepisti miserere
                           clementer animabus </incipit>
                        <incipit>Fidelium deus omnium conditor et redemptor animabus omnium fidelium
                           defunctorum </incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <p>
                     <secFol>icit uentus a <locus>(psalter, fol. 20r)</locus></secFol>
                  </p>
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="perg">
                        <support>parchment</support>
                        <extent>377 leaves
                           <dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                              <height quantity="132">c. 132</height>
                              <width>88</width>
                           </dimensions>
                           <note>Leaves were trimmed in rebinding, occasionally causing
                              the loss of text and decoration.</note>
                        </extent>
                        <foliation>19th-century (?), very sporadically, and modern, in pencil; 1–377.</foliation>
                        <collation>(fols. 1–5) I (6) the first leaf of the outer bifolium is used as the upper pastedown
                           | (fols. 6–13) II (8) | (fols. 14–17) III (4) | (fols. 18–185) IV–XXIV (8) | (fols.
                           186–195) XXV (10) | (fols. 196–227) XXVI–XXIX (8) | (fols. 228–236) XXX (8+1)
                           fol. 231 containing a miniature is inserted | (fols. 237–260) XXXI–XXXIII (8) | (fols.
                           261–269) XXXIV (8+1) fol. 268 containing a miniature is inserted | (fols. 270–373)
                           XXXV–XLVII (8) | (fols. 374–377) XLVIII (4).
                          <catchwords> Catchwords in ink</catchwords> and <signatures type="quire">quire signatures of Roman numerals in plummet, or traces
                           of them, occasionally survive</signatures>.</collation>
                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout columns="1" writtenLines="14" topLine="below" rulingMedium="leadpoint">Ruled in plummet with single vertical and horizontal bounding lines, extending
                           the full height and width of page; 14 lines per page; written below the top line; written
                           space: <dimensions type="written" unit="mm">
                              <height quantity="67">c. 67</height>
                              <width>44</width>
                           </dimensions> </layout>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc>
                     <handNote script="textualisNorthern" execution="formata">Formal Gothic book hand, black and brown ink.</handNote>
                  </handDesc>
                  <decoDesc>
                     <summary>Illumination is related in style to Los Angeles, J. Paul Getty Museum
                        MS. 83. ML. 99 (MS. Ludwig IX 3, ‘Ruskin Hours’), Chantilly, Musée Condé MS.
                        Lat. 1423 and other manuscripts produced in Cambrai at the end of the 13th
                        to early in the 14th centuries (see A. Bräm, <title>Das Andachtsbuch der Marie de Gavre: Paris, Bibliothèque nationale, Ms. nouv. acq. fr. 16251.
                        Buchmalerei in der Diözese Cambrai im letzten Viertel des 13. Jahrhunderts</title> (Wiesbaden: L. Reichert,
                        1997), ‘Ruskin Hours group’). See
                        also <ref target="https://catalog.hathitrust.org/Record/000468709">Pächt and
                           Alexander</ref> i. 295, pl. XXII.</summary>
                     <decoNote type="decInit">Blue, pink and red KL monograms on gold backgrounds
                        and borders made of gold, blue and pink bars, decorated with coiled
                        tendrils, foliage, animals and birds in the calendar. Man holding a forked
                        staff in the border of the August page (fol. 8v). </decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="miniature">Miniatures with the Labours of the Months, in
                        rectangular frames, with parts of the composition sometimes appearing
                        outside the frame:<list>
                           <item> January: three-faced Janus, feasting</item>
                           <item> February: man warming himself by the fire and cooking in a pot, a
                              heron (?) atop a chimney outside the frame, another in the left
                              margin</item>
                           <item> March: man pruning a tree</item>
                           <item> April: man carrying flowering branches</item>
                           <item> May: man on horseback with a hawk, a dog outside the frame</item>
                           <item> June: man mowing hay with a scythe</item>
                           <item> July: man carrying wood on his back, two trees outside the
                              frame</item>
                           <item> August: man reaping grain</item>
                           <item> September: man cutting grapes, another, outside the frame,
                              carrying them in a basket and eating</item>
                           <item> October: man sowing, a large sack outside the frame</item>
                           <item> November: man knocking down acorns for pigs, a second tree outside
                              the frame</item>
                           <item> December: man slaughtering a pig.</item>
                        </list></decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="miniature">Full-page miniatures illustrating the life of
                        Christ, with the sequence Annunciation– Betrayal forming a prefatory cycle,
                        and scenes of the Passion narrative facing historiated initials at
                        liturgical divisions (see below). The miniatures are on gold backgrounds in
                        frames, decorated with architectural arches and pinnacles, painted on the
                        versos, with the rectos left blank. The last miniature has a pink and blue
                        background and gold frame, decorated with foliage and corner-pieces made of
                        three gold vine leaves. <list>
                           <item> (fol. 14v) Annunciation: the Virgin Mary, holding a book, and
                              angel, holding a scroll with lettering ‘Aue maria gratiatia [sic]
                              plena dominus’.</item>
                           <item> (fol. 15v) Nativity: the Virgin Mary lying on a bed covered with
                              vair (?), Joseph seated by her side, Child in a cradle, heads of the
                              ox and ass (defaced).</item>
                           <item> (fol. 16v) Adoration of the Magi: the Virgin and Child, blessing,
                              three crowned Magi with gifts, one kneeling, another pointing to the
                              star.</item>
                           <item> (fol. 17v) Slaughter of the Innocents: seated Herod, two soldiers,
                              one piercing a baby with a sword (rubbed).</item>
                           <item> (fol. 18v) Betrayal: Judas kissing Christ, soldiers, St Peter with
                              a sword, kneeling Malchus with blood on his head.</item>
                        </list>
                     </decoNote>

                     <decoNote type="histInit">Historiated initials, each 6 or 7 lines high, except
                        the first, occupying two-thirds of a page, often partially rubbed or
                        defaced, accompanied by borders composed of gold, blue and pink bars,
                        decorated with coiled tendrils and foliage, some on gold backgrounds; and
                        full-page miniatures at the liturgical divisions in the psalter. The
                        initials are on gold backgrounds, in gold rectangular frames, decorated with
                        foliage, architectural pinnacles and interlace. The miniatures are in gold
                        rectangular frames, decorated with foliage, architectural arches, pinnacles
                        and foliate corner-pieces. The miniatures are painted on one side of a leaf,
                        leaving the other side blank. <list>
                           <item>fol. 19r Psalm 1 (initial B(eatus)) King David playing harp in the
                              upper part, and David and Goliath in the lower part.</item>
                           <item> fol. 66v (miniature) Christ before Pilate. </item>
                           <item> fol. 67r Psalm 26 (initial D(ominus)) King David seated, pointing
                              to his eyes, blessed by Christ with cruciform halo, standing. </item>
                           <item> fol. 99v (miniature) The Mocking of Christ, his head covered by a
                              cloth.</item>
                           <item> fol. 100r Psalm 38 (initial D(ixi)) King David seated, pointing to
                              his mouth; half-figure of Christ, holding a book and blessing, in
                              clouds above. </item>
                           <item> fol. 129v (miniature) Flagellation.</item>
                           <item> fol. 130r Psalm 52 (initial D(ixit)) The Fool, holding a club and
                              eating bread, spoken to by the Devil. </item>
                           <item> fol. 158v (miniature) Christ carrying the Cross.</item>
                           <item> fol. 159r Psalm 68 (initial S(aluum)) King David praying in waters
                              with fish in the lower part; half-figure of Christ with cruciform
                              halo, holding a book and blessing in the upper part. </item>
                           <item> fol. 196v (miniature) Crucifixion, with Mary and John, sun and
                              moon.</item>
                           <item> fol. 197r Psalm 80 (initial E(xultate)) King David, seated,
                              playing bells (defaced).</item>
                           <item>fol. 230v Psalm 97 (initial C(antate)) Tonsured clerics singing
                              from a book open on a lectern. </item>
                           <item> fol. 231r (miniature) Descent from the Cross (defaced,
                              retouched).</item>
                           <item> fol. 268v (miniature) Two panels depicting (above) Christ’s body
                              embalmed and (below) Resurrection.</item>
                           <item> fol. 269r Psalm 109 (initial D(ixit)) Coronation of the Virgin.
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="border"> Fine borders accompanying historiated initials. <list>
                           <item>fol. 19r, Psalm 1. (full border) Hunter blowing horn and dog
                              chasing a deer; armoured knight piercing a grotesque with a lance;
                              rabbit.</item>
                           <item>fol. 67r, Psalm 26 (full border) Ape; grotesque, playing a musical
                              instrument.</item>
                           <item> fol. 100r Psalm 38 (full border) Bird; grotesques.</item>
                           <item>fol. 130r Psalm 52 (full border) Birds; grotesques.</item>
                           <item>fol. 159r Psalm 68 (full border) Grotesque, butterfly.</item>
                           <item>fol. 197r Psalm 80 (full border) St Margaret emerging from the back
                              of a dragon, a blessing hand of God in clouds above; musician playing
                              vielle; bird; grotesque.</item>
                           <item>fol. 230v Psalm 97 (full border) Half-figure of a tonsured cleric
                              playing organ.</item>
                           <item> fol. 269r Psalm 109 (full border) St Martin and a beggar; knight
                              on horseback holding a lance with pennant, seen from behind;
                              birds.</item>
                        </list></decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="decInit">2-line pink initials on gold backgrounds, decorated
                        with coiled tendrils and foliage, at the beginnings of psalms, canticles and
                        litany. </decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="border">Full borders on pages containing 2- line initials, made
                        of gold, pink and blue bars, decorated with coiled tendrils, foliage,
                        grotesques, human and animal figures and heads (often musicians), birds,
                        fish and butterflies. The borders include lamb with a cross-staff with
                        pennant (fol. 38r), a man on horseback with a sword (fol. 102r), a female
                        saint with a book and palm (fol. 142r), a kneeling woman with an open book
                        (fols. 164r, 323r), a woman spinning (fol. 176v), a nun (?) in a brown habit
                        and black and white veil, playing a musical instrument (fols. 203r, 334r,
                        361v), a woman committing suicide with a dagger (?) (fol. 204v), St Paul,
                        holding a book and a sword (fol. 234v), St Peter, holding a book and a key
                        (fol. 239r), a woman kneeling in prayer (fols. 327r, 335r). Some initials
                        and borders include coats of arms and heraldic decoration (see
                        ‘Provenance’).</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="flourInit">1-line alternating gold and blue initials, decorated
                        with contrasting blue and red penwork at the beginnings of verses and
                        periods.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="lineFill"> Line-endings with foliage, animal figures and heads,
                        birds and grotesques on gold backgrounds.</decoNote>
                  </decoDesc>
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <binding notAfter="1800" notBefore="1300">
                        <p>Sewn on seven tawed (?) medieval (?) thongs, with medieval (?) wood boards covered
                           with worn red velvet, late 18th to early 19th century. The thongs are broken at the
                           joints and the boards are almost detached. Fragments of the Bodleian paper labels
                           on spine. Gilt edges of textblock. Impressions left by the fittings of two clasps on the
                           upper and lower covers.</p>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origPlace>
                        <country key="place_7024097">Flemish</country>, <region>French
                           Flanders</region>, <settlement key="place_7008456">Cambrai</settlement>
                        (?) <!--ORIGINAL: Flemish, French Flanders-->
                     </origPlace>
                     <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="1310" notBefore="1290">13th century,
                        late, or 14th century, early</origDate>
                  </origin>
                  <provenance>Made for the use of the diocese of Cambrai, probably for a lay patron: evidence of
                     the calendar, litany and decoration.</provenance>
                  <provenance>Arms, 1 and 4 or a lion sable, 2 and 3 barry argent and azure a lion gules (fols. 122v
                     and 128r) and or a lion sable (fols. 18v, 19r, 99v, 129v (depicted on shields), 343v).
                     Similar to Chantilly, Musée Condé MS. 1423, made for Isabelle von Luxemburg
                     (1247–1298) (Bräm, 1997).</provenance>
                  <provenance>Defaced inscription, 16th-century (?): ‘Ex libris R[ . . . ?]’ (fol. 377r).</provenance>
                  <provenance><persName role="fmo" key="person_54940373">William Laud (1573–1645)</persName>, see ODNB: ‘Liber Guil: Laud Archiep(iscop)i Cant et Cancellar
                     Vnivers: Oxon. 1636’ (fol. 2r).</provenance>
                  <acquisition when="1636">Bodleian Library: second donation from Laud, 16 June 1636. Former shelfmark:
                     ‘D. 3.’ (upper pastedown).</acquisition>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>Description adapted from Elizabeth Solopova, <title>Latin
                              Liturgical Psalters in the Bodleian Library: A Select
                              Catalogue</title> (Oxford, 2013), pp. 372–8. Previously described in
                           the Quarto Catalogue (H. O. Coxe, <title>Laudian Manuscripts</title>,
                           Quarto Catalogues II, repr. with corrections, 1969, from the original ed.
                           of 1858–1885). <listBibl>
                              <bibl facs="aby0066.gif" type="QUARTO"> Quarto Catalogue, col. 36 </bibl>
                              <bibl facs="aby0067.gif" type="QUARTO"> Quarto Catalogue, col. 37 </bibl>
                              <bibl facs="aby0320.gif" type="QUARTO"> Quarto Catalogue, p. 540
                                 (addenda) </bibl>
                           </listBibl>
                           <listBibl>
                              <bibl facs="aap0054.gif" type="SC">Summary Catalogue, Vol. 2, part 1,
                                 p. 33</bibl>
                           </listBibl>
                        </source>
                     </recordHist>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <surrogates>
                     <bibl type="digital-facsimile" subtype="full">
                        <ref target="https://digital.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/objects/b2fbf3df-74b8-4e9b-bfd8-4e66602470cf/">
                           <title>Digital Bodleian</title></ref> <note>(full digital facsimile)</note>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl subtype="partial" type="digital-facsimile">
                        <ref target="https://digital.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/objects/0d1d156f-b173-4c76-b157-a7315f910f39/">
                           <title>Digital Bodleian</title></ref> <note>(38 images from 35mm slides)</note>
                     </bibl>
                  </surrogates>
                  <listBibl type="WRAPPER">
                     <listBibl type="PRINT">
                        <head>Printed descriptions:</head>
                        <bibl>S. J. P. van Dijk, <title>Latin Liturgical Manuscripts in the Bodleian
                              Library, Oxford, vol. 2: Office Books</title> (typescript, 1957),
                              <citedRange unit="page" from="78" to="78">p. 78</citedRange>
                        </bibl>
                     </listBibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2022-12">Revised to incorporate full description from Solopova catalogue.</change>
         <change when="2017-07-01">First online publication.</change>
         <change when="2017-05-25">
            <persName>James Cummings</persName> Up-converted the markup using <ref target="https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl">https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl</ref>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>