<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="manuscript_7718">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>MS. Liturg. 396</title>
            <title type="collection">MSS. Liturg. (Liturgical)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp when="2013">Cataloguer</resp>
               <persName>Elizabeth Solopova</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp when="2024">Encoding</resp>
               <persName>Matthew Holford</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </publisher>
            <idno type="msID">MS_Liturg_396</idno>
            <idno type="collection">Liturgical</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="MS_Liturg_396" xml:lang="en">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <region type="county">Oxfordshire</region>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <institution>University of Oxford</institution>
                  <repository>Bodleian Library</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">MS. Liturg. 396</idno>
                  <idno type="ieArk">ark:29072/x0fx719m77pq</idno>
                  <idno type="crArk">ark:29072/x0ft848q94cv</idno>
                  <altIdentifier type="internal">
                     <idno type="SCN">30619</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
                  <altIdentifier type="former">
                     <idno>MS. Canon. Liturg. 396</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
               <head>Psalter; Flanders, Bruges (?), 13th century, middle or third quarter; one late
                  13th-century miniature</head>
               <msContents>
                  <msItem class="#liturgica #biblia" n="1" xml:id="MS_Liturg_396-item1">
                     <title key="work_14114" type="desc">Psalter</title>
                     <note>[item 1 occupies quire I]</note>
                     <msItem n="1">
                        <locus from="1r" to="6v">(fols. 1r–6v)</locus>
                        <note> Calendar (published and compared with calendars of other psalters
                           from the Bruges–Ghent area by Carlvant, 1978, pp. 485–508), laid out one
                           month per page, approximately one-third full, not graded, vigils included
                           from June to December. The calendar contains Donatianus (14 October),
                           patron saint of an important parish and collegiate church in Bruges,
                           which in early modern times served as a cathedral of the archdiocese of
                           Bruges, and Boniface (5 June), patron of a church in Bruges. Other feasts
                           may indicate the patron’s connection with Ghent, particularly with the
                           Benedictine monastery of St Bavo: Benedict (21 March) and his translation
                           (11 July), Landoaldus (19 March), Macarius of Ghent (9 May, elevation)
                           and Bavo of Ghent (1 October; ‘bauonis’ is written in a slightly larger
                           script). The monastery preserved the relics of Landoaldus, Macarius and
                           Bavo. The last page of the calendar (December) is in a different, but
                           contemporary, hand, in paler brown ink. Unlike the rest of the calendar,
                           the November and December leaf is not pricked in the lower margin. Its
                           text in red and blue is in the same hand and the decoration is by the
                           same artist as elsewhere in the calendar. The December page may have been
                           copied from a different exemplar: it is fuller than other months and has
                           an octave of Andrew (7 December) (octaves are not included elsewhere).
                           December feasts include Eulalia (10), ‘Martus presbyter’ (15), Lazarus
                           (17), Rufus (18) and Victoria (23), the last rare in contemporary
                           calendars from Bruges and Ghent (see Carlvant, 1978, p. 507). The hand of
                           the December page also added octaves of Stephen, John the Evangelist and
                           the Holy Innocents in January, Bertin on 5 September, and vigils for some
                           feasts. ‘locus bisextus’ is added on 24 February (fol. 1v) in a
                           15th-century hand, followed by an explanation in Netherlandish: ‘locus
                           bissexti bissext es dat men heut tue daghe op de lettre van zente mathis
                           daghe ende bissext gheualt alse men de iare van ons heren ghebornessen
                           mach delen in viren eueneffene’ (‘bissext is that there are two days on
                           the letter of Saint Matthew’s day and bissext falls when the year of our
                           Lord’s birth can be divided equally into four parts’). There is another
                           note by the same hand in March, about the calculation of the date of
                           Easter: ‘Wi selen nemen de niuwe mane nar de nonen van marte ende tellen
                           tote . xiiii . ende derste zondach die comp nar die xiiii dat es
                           pacshdach’ (‘We must take the new moon after the Nones of March and count
                           to the 14th (day) and the first Sunday which comes after the 14th (day)
                           that is Easter day’). The letter ‘d’ marking the ‘Egyptian’ days is also
                           added in darker ink, possibly by the same 15th-century hand. The calendar
                           includes the ‘aparicio . s . marci euangieliste’ [sic] on 25 June, and
                           ‘vigilia’ for the feast of Peter and Paul (29 June) added in a
                           post-medieval, 16th-century (?), probably Italian hand (see
                           ‘Provenance’). </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <note>[item 2 occupies quire II] </note>
                     <msItem n="2">
                        <locus from="7r" to="14v">(fols. 7r–14v)</locus>
                        <note> Miniatures, painted on the versos with the rectos left blank (see
                           ‘Decoration’). </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <note>[items 3–7 occupy quires III–XX]</note>
                     <msItem n="3">
                        <locus from="15r" to="146r">(fols. 15r–146r)</locus>
                        <note> Psalms 1–150, laid out with each verse starting on a new line,
                           without titles, with numbers added in the margins in a late medieval or
                           post-medieval hand. The psalms are in the biblical order; the
                           subdivisions within psalms are not indicated, apart from psalm 118,
                           subdivided into twenty-two 8-verse units. Psalms 17 and 73 follow the
                           preceding psalms without a break or larger initial (fols. 25v and 80r).
                           Punctuated throughout with punctus elevatus used to mark metrum and minor
                           pauses, and punctus used to mark the ends of verses. There are textual
                           divisions at psalms 26, 38, 51, 52, 68, 80, 97, 101 and 109 marked by
                           historiated initials and usually by facing miniatures (see ‘Decoration’).
                           Verses 14–15 of psalm 113B are supplied in the original hand over erasure
                           on fol. 121r. Fol. 15v is occupied by the Beatus-initial and the opening
                           words of psalm 1; fol. 15r is blank. </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="4">
                        <locus from="146r" to="147r">(fols. 146r–147r)</locus>
                        <note> The canticle Benedicite omnia opera, following psalms without a break
                           or title. </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="5">
                        <locus from="147r" to="154v">(fols. 147r–154v)</locus>
                        <note> Weekly canticles, without titles: <list>
                              <item>(1) Confitebor tibi domine (Isaiah 12);</item>
                              <item>(2) Ego dixi (Isaiah 38: 10–21);</item>
                              <item>(3) Exultauit cor meum (1 Samuel 2: 1–11);</item>
                              <item>(4) Cantemus domino (Exodus 15: 1–20);</item>
                              <item>(5) Domine audiui (Habakkuk 3);</item>
                              <item>(6) Audite celi (Deuteronomy 32: 1–44).</item>
                           </list>
                        </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="6">
                        <locus from="154v" to="157v">(fols. 154v–157v)</locus>
                        <note> Daily canticles, prayers and creeds, without titles: <list>
                              <item>(1) Te deum laudamus (fol. 154v);</item>
                              <item>(2) Benedictus dominus deus (fol. 155r);</item>
                              <item>(3) Athanasian Creed (Quicumque uult ...) (fol. 156r).</item>
                           </list>
                        </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="7">
                        <locus from="157v" to="160r">(fols. 157v–160r)</locus>
                        <note> Litany, published and compared with the litanies of other psalters
                           from the Bruges–Ghent area by Carlvant (1978, pp. 509–30), containing
                           saints venerated in Bruges, such as Donatianus and Basil, patron of the
                           chapel of St Basil and the Holy Blood in Bruges, among the confessors,
                           and Boniface among the martyrs. Also includes saints venerated in Ghent,
                           such as Landoaldus and Macarius among the confessors, and Amalberga,
                           Landrada and Pharaildis among the virgins. The relics of Landoaldus,
                           Macarius and Landrada were preserved at the Benedictine Abbey of St Bavo
                           in Ghent (Carlvant, 1978, p. 121). The litany is followed by unusual
                           collects (fols. 159v–160r): <list>
                              <item>(1) Famulorum tuorum quesumus domine delictis ignosce ut qui
                                 tibi placere ...</item>
                              <item>(2) Deus qui apostolis tuis sanctum dedisti spiritum consede
                                 [sic] quesumus plebi tue pie petitionis ...</item>
                              <item> (3) Omnium sanctorum tuorum quesumus domine supplicatione
                                 placatus et ueniam nobis tribue delictorum ...</item>
                              <item>(4) Mentes nostras domine paraclitus qui a te procedit
                                 ...</item>
                              <item>(5) Da nobis quesumus domine omnium sanctorum tuorum semper
                                 ueneratione letari ...</item>
                              <item>(6) Protege domine famulos tuos subsidiis pacis ...</item>
                           </list> Fol. 160v is blank. </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <textLang mainLang="la" otherLangs="dum">Latin with some Middle Dutch in the calendar</textLang>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <p><secFol> Qui non abijt <locus>(psalter, fol. 16r)</locus></secFol></p>
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="perg">
                        <support> parchment</support>
                        <extent> <measure type="leaf" quantity="160">160</measure> leaves <dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                              <height quantity="265">c. 265</height>
                              <width>179</width>
                           </dimensions>
                        </extent>
                        <foliation> modern, in pencil; 1–160.</foliation>
                        <collation> Originally almost entirely in quires of eight leaves with
                           inserted miniatures on single leaves (fols. 14, 34, 47, 60, 73, 88, 103,
                           105, 118), with the other sides left blank: (fols. 1–6) I (8−1) first is
                           the upper pastedown, second is missing | (fols. 7–15) II (8+1) fol. 14
                           inserted | (fols. 16–31) III–IV (8) | (fols. 32–40) V (8+1) fol. 34
                           inserted | (fols. 41–49) VI (8+1) fol. 47 inserted | (fols. 50–57) VII
                           (8) | (fols. 58–66) VIII (8+1) fol. 60 inserted | (fols. 67–75) IX (8+1)
                           fol. 73 inserted | (fols. 76–83) X (8) | (fols. 84–88) XI (4+1) fol. 88
                           inserted | (fols. 89–96) XII (8) | (fols. 97–106) XIII (8+2) fols. 103
                           and 105 inserted | (fols. 107–114) XIV (8) | (fols. 115–123) XV (8+1)
                           fol. 118 inserted | (fols. 124–155) XVI–XIX (8) | (fols. 156–160) XX (6)
                           6 is used as the lower pastedown. Leaf signatures survive sporadically on
                           both rectos and versos in the lower gutter corner, in blue (quires II–X)
                           or red (from quire XIII) ink</collation>




                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout> Ruled in plummet with double vertical and horizontal bounding
                           lines, extending the full height of page; 23 lines per page; prickings
                           visible in the three outer margins on most leaves; written above the top
                           line (see Oliver, 1985, p. 139 n. 27 and compare MS. Douce 49 and MS.
                           Auct. D. 4. 3); written space: variable, c. 178 × 95–105 mm</layout>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc>
                     <handNote script="textualisNorthern" execution="formata"> Formal Gothic book
                        hand, black and brown ink</handNote>
                  </handDesc>
                  <decoDesc>
                     <!--  <decoNote>Fine miniatures, borders, historiated and other initials. The
                        miniature on fol. 14v is by a later hand, 13th century, end. (<ref
                           target="https://catalog.hathitrust.org/Record/000468709">Pächt and
                           Alexander</ref> i. 282, pl. XX)</decoNote>-->


                     <summary>One of the oldest surviving Flemish psalters with a Christological
                        cycle; close in style to several psalters attributed to Bruges (cf. the
                        ‘Eerste Groep’ of Carlvant, 1978), particularly Brussels, Bibliothèque
                        Royale MS. 5074; Saint-Omer, Bibliothèque de l’agglomération MS. 270;
                        Baltimore, Walters Art Museum MS. W. 36; Edinburgh, University Library MS.
                        62; and Oxford, University College MS. 12.</summary>
                     <decoNote type="monogram">Gold KL monograms on blue and pink backgrounds in the
                        calendar; gold, pink and blue bars in the margins terminating with animal
                        heads, usually one in green and one in yellow. </decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="miniature">Irregularly shaped miniatures depicting the Labours
                        of the Months: January: man warming one bare foot by the fire, drinking out
                        of a cup, and holding his shoe in the other hand February: woman with a
                        large candle March: man pruning a tree with an axe April: man carrying
                        flowering branches May: man with a hawk June: man carrying wood on his back
                        July: man mowing hay with a scythe August: man reaping grain September: man
                        sowing October: man cutting grapes from a vine and holding a basket of
                        grapes November: man knocking acorns from a tree for pigs December: man,
                        slaughtering a pig, with one foot on its head.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="miniature">Seven full-page prefatory miniatures forming a
                        Christological cycle that continues with eight further full-page miniatures
                        at liturgical divisions in the psalter, and with nine historiated initials
                        facing the miniatures and forming part of the cycle. The miniatures are
                        painted on the versos, leaving the rectos blank (apart from fol. 88) (see
                        Carlvant, 1985, p. 329, n. 14). The miniatures are on gold backgrounds, in
                        rectangular frames with gold medallions containing male heads at the
                        corners. <list>
                           <item>fol. 7v, Annunciation: Gabriel addressing the Virgin Mary; both
                              holding scrolls with ‘Ave gratia plena’ and ‘Ecce ancilla’,
                              respectively.</item>
                           <item>fol. 8v, Nativity.</item>
                           <item>fol. 9v, Annunciation to two Shepherds.</item>
                           <item>fol. 10v, Presentation in the Temple.</item>
                           <item>fol. 11v, Adoration of the Magi; the middle Magus pointing to the
                              star of Bethlehem.</item>
                           <item>fol. 12v, Christ among the Doctors; behind Christ a man puts his
                              hand on a woman’s shoulder (perhaps Mary and Joseph, but neither is
                              nimbed).</item>
                           <item>fol. 13v, Baptism of Christ.</item>
                           <item>fol. 14v, The Last Judgement in a different Franco-Flemish style,
                              perhaps added later in the 13th century (Pächt and Alexander,
                              1966–73). Christ enthroned in the upper compartment, displaying his
                              wounds, with a star (?) to the right of his head and a flaming sword
                              to the left, flanked by the kneeling Virgin Mary and the Blessed to
                              his right, and by the kneeling St John and the Damned to his left.
                              Souls rising from graves in the smaller lower compartment. Full-length
                              angels sounding the Last Trump in the corners of the frame.</item>
                        </list></decoNote>

                     <decoNote type="histInit">Full-page miniatures and historiated initials at
                        liturgical divisions in the psalter. The initials are typically 11 to 13
                        lines high, with gold backgrounds and in rectangular frames. <list>
                           <item>fol. 15v, Psalm 1 (initial B(eatus)), Full-page Jesse Tree, with
                              sleeping Jesse and a large, full-length figure of an unidentified
                              female saint holding a palm of martyrdom and a book (?), surrounded by
                              male heads; the corners and sides of the frame are decorated with
                              human heads in medallions and semi-circles.</item>
                           <item>fol. 34v, (miniature), The First Temptation: Christ seated on a
                              mount, speaking to the Devil.</item>
                           <item>fol. 35r, Psalm 26 (initial D(ominus)), The Second Temptation: the
                              Devil carrying Christ on his shoulders towards the Temple.</item>
                           <item>fol. 47v, (miniature), The Third Temptation: the Devil offering
                              Christ riches, before a tower (?).</item>
                           <item>fol. 48r, Psalm 38 (initial D(ixi)),Christ’s feet dried by Mary
                              Magdalene with her hair in the house of Simon.</item>
                           <item>fol. 59v, Psalm 51 (initial Q(vid)), The Entry into
                              Jerusalem.</item>
                           <item>fol. 60r, (miniature), Christ addresses the disciples.</item>
                           <item>fol. 61r, Psalm 52 (initial D(ixit)), The Last Supper.</item>
                           <item>fol. 73v, (miniature), Christ washing the disciples’ feet.</item>
                           <item>fol. 74r, Psalm 68 (initial S(aluum)), Christ kneeling in
                              Gethsemane before an angel.</item>
                           <item>fol. 88v, (miniature), The Betrayal; Christ healing Malchus’s
                              ear.</item>
                           <item> fol. 89r, Psalm 80 (initial E(xultate)), Judas receiving a bag of
                              money from the Jews.</item>
                           <item>fol. 102r, Psalm 97 (initial C(antate)), Christ carrying the
                              Cross.</item>
                           <item>fol. 103r, (miniature), Flagellation.</item>
                           <item>fol. 104v, Psalm 101 (initial D(omine)), Crucifixion, with the sun
                              and moon, Mary and John.</item>
                           <item>fol. 105r, (miniature), The Harrowing of Hell.</item>
                           <item>fol. 117v, Psalm 109 (initial D(ixit)), Crucifixion, very similar
                              to that on fol. 104v.</item>
                           <item>fol. 118r, (miniature), Noli me tangere.</item>
                        </list></decoNote>

                     <decoNote type="decInit">4-line gold initials on blue and pink backgrounds with
                        white floral designs, and gold, pink and blue bars in the margins
                        terminating with animal heads, at the beginnings of psalms, canticles and
                        litany; similar 3-line initials to the collects.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="border">Borders: see above.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="decInit">1-line gold initials on blue and pink backgrounds,
                        decorated with white arabesque designs, at the beginnings of verses and
                        periods.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="lineFill">Red and blue penwork line-endings on fol.
                        111v.</decoNote>
                  </decoDesc>
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <binding notAfter="1500" notBefore="1400">
                        <p> Red leather over wood boards, 15th century, Netherlandish. The covers
                           are blindstamped with an all-over pattern of lozenge, circular,
                           triangular, square and rectangular tools. The lozenges and some squares
                           contain fleurs-de-lis; one of the rectangles contains a dragon and
                           another lamb-and-flag. Rebacked at the Bodleian. Sewn on 7 cords, seven
                           raised bands on spine. Gilt lettering on spine: ‘MS. || MISC no. ELL.
                           LITURG. || 396.’. Paper label on spine printed ‘94’. Holes left by the
                           fittings of two clasps on the upper cover. Holes and impressions left by
                           the catches near the foreedge of the lower cover; two holes for pins near
                           the centre of the lower cover. Gilt edges of textblock with a painted
                           pattern of lozenges outlined in black (the two outer rows of lozenges are
                           painted blue and contain a fleur-de-lis in gold, while the centre row of
                           lozenges is painted red and contains a floral shape in a darker colour
                           (see Foot, 1993)). The bottom edge of the textblock has the shelfmark
                           ‘396’, suggesting that the volume was formerly stored fore-edge down. The
                           outer leaves of the first and last quires are used as pastedowns. </p>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origPlace>
                        <country key="place_7024097">Flemish</country>, <settlement
                           key="place_7007867">Bruges (?)</settlement>
                        <!--ORIGINAL: Flemish, Bruges-->
                     </origPlace>
                     <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="1300" notBefore="1240">13th century,
                        middle or third quarter; one late 13th century miniature</origDate>
                  </origin>
                  <provenance>Probably made in Bruges in a workshop which produced other psalters
                     with similar illumination, textual contents and codicological features, and
                     flourished c. 1250–1270 (Carlvant’s ‘Eerste Groep’, 1978, pp. 2–12, 80–8).
                     Psalters are the only known books to come from this workshop. Probably made for
                     a lay patron, perhaps with connections in the Ghent area, since the calendar
                     and litany include saints venerated in Ghent, particularly in the Benedictine
                     monastery of St Bavo (see ‘Text’). </provenance>
                  <provenance>A miniature in a Franco-Flemish style added to the prefatory cycle,
                     probably at the end of the 13th century (fol. 14v). </provenance>
                  <provenance>Notes in Netherlandish added to the calendar in the 15th century;
                     15th-century Netherlandish binding. </provenance>
                  <provenance><country key="place_1000080">Italy</country>, <settlement key="place_7018159">Venice</settlement> (?): a post-medieval addition to the calendar of the
                     feast of the discovery of St Mark’s relics during the construction of his
                     basilica in Venice. The spelling ‘euangieliste’ suggests that the addition was
                     made by an Italian speaker. </provenance>
                  <acquisition>Bodleian Library: ‘Miscell. Liturg, 396’ (upper pastedown, spine and
                     fol. 1r); ‘Misc. Liturg.’ collection was formed in 1860, but went on growing
                     until 1887. The source of this manuscript and of some other ‘Misc. Liturg.’
                     (now MSS. Liturg.) is unknown, but ‘no doubt many ... are unidentifiable
                     Rawlinson MSS.’ (Summary catalogue, vol. 5, p. 844). ‘G. C. 12’, ‘= Selden
                     cupbd. 94’ (upper pastedown). </acquisition>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>Elizabeth Solopova, <title>Latin
                              Liturgical Psalters in the Bodleian Library: A Select
                              Catalogue</title> (Oxford, 2013), pp. 326–34. Previously described in
                           the Summary Catalogue. <listBibl>
                              <bibl facs="aam0891.gif" type="SC">Summary Catalogue, Vol. 5, p.
                                 854</bibl>
                           </listBibl>
                        </source>
                     </recordHist>
                     <availability status="restricted">
                        <p>To ensure its preservation, access to this item is restricted, and
                           readers are asked to work from reproductions and published descriptions
                           as far as possible. If you wish to apply to see the original, please
                           click the request button above. When your request is received, you will
                           be asked to contact the relevant curator outlining the subject of your
                           research, the importance of this item to that research, and the resources
                           you have already consulted.</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <surrogates>
                     <bibl subtype="partial" type="digital-facsimile">
                        <ref
                           target="https://digital.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/objects/7f78b652-2179-45c8-8ea9-9181ee081bbf/">
                           <title>Digital Bodleian</title>
                        </ref>
                        <note>(41 images from 35mm slides)</note>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl type="microfilm">Microfilm available in the open shelf collections in the
                        Weston Library (R. Films 101)</bibl></surrogates>
                  <listBibl type="WRAPPER">
                     <listBibl type="PRINT">
                        <head>Printed descriptions:</head>

                        <bibl>Weale, W., ‘Liturgical manuscripts in the Bodleian Library, Oxford’,
                              <title>The Ecclesiologist</title> 3 (1 September 1888), p.
                           33–4.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Frere, no. 466.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Summary catalogue, vol. 5, no. 30619.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Vitzthum von Eckstaedt, B. G., <title>Die Pariser Miniaturmalerei von
                              der Zeit des hl. Ludwig bis zu Philipp von Valois und ihr Verhältnis
                              zur Malerei in Nordwesteuropa</title> (Leipzig: Verlag von Quelle
                           &amp; Meyer, 1907), p. 13.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Burlington Fine Arts Club, <title>Exhibition of illuminated
                              manuscripts</title> (London: Burlington Fine Arts Club, 1908), p.
                           37.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Lyna, F., <title>De vlaamsche miniatuur van 1200 tot 1530</title>
                           (Brussels; Amsterdam: Standaard-Boekhandel, Van Kampen and Zoon, 1933),
                           p. 27.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Haseloff (1938), p. 67, Tabelle 18.</bibl>
                        <bibl>S. J. P. van Dijk, <title>Latin Liturgical Manuscripts in the Bodleian
                              Library, Oxford, vol. 2: Office Books</title> (typescript, 1957),
                              <citedRange unit="page" from="89" to="89">p. 89</citedRange>
                        </bibl>
                        <bibl>Pächt and Alexander (1966–73), vol. 1, no. 282, pl. XX.</bibl>
                        <bibl><title>Gent, duizend jaar kunst en cultuur: muurschilderkunst,
                              schilderkunst, tekenkunst, graveerkunst, beeldhouwkunst: 19 April–29
                              Juni 1975</title> (Gent: Bijlokemuseum, 1975), no. 567.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Carlvant (1978), pp. 80–8, 276, 473, 480 and passim.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Alexander, J. J. G. and Temple, E., <title>Illuminated manuscripts in
                              Oxford College libraries, the University Archives and the Taylor
                              Institution</title> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1985), no. 804.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Carlvant, K. B. E., ‘Trends in Bruges illumination until 1260, apropos
                           a psalter connected with Oostkerke’, <title>Archives et bibliothèques de
                              Belgique</title> 56 (1985), pp. 321–63, at pp. 348–51.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Oliver, J. H., ‘Medieval alphabet soup: reconstruction of a Mosan
                           psalter-hours in Philadelphia and Oxford and the cult of St Catherine’,
                              <title>Gesta</title> 24/2 (1985), pp. 129–40.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Carlvant, K. B. E., ‘A Brabantine illuminator of the mid-thirteenth
                           century’, <title>Miscellanea Neerlandica</title> 1 (1987), pp. 355–80, at
                           pp. 361–2, 372 n. 26.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Oliver (1988), vol. 1, p. 81; vol. 2, p. 293.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Hamburger, J. F., <title>The Rothschild Canticles: Art and mysticism
                              in Flanders and the Rhineland circa</title> 1300 (New Haven, CT;
                           London: Yale University Press, 1990), p. 267 n. 32.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Foot, M. M., ‘Medieval painted book edges’ in <title>Studies in the
                              history of bookbinding</title> [collected articles] (Aldershot: Scolar
                           Press, 1993), pp. 439–54, at pp. 443–4.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Randall, L. M. C. et al., <title>Medieval and Renaissance manuscripts
                              in the Walters Art Gallery</title>, 3 vols. (Baltimore; London: Johns
                           Hopkins University Press in association with the Walters Art Gallery,
                           1997), vol. 1, France, 875–1420, no. 40, p. 95; vol. 3, Belgium,
                           1250–1530, part 1, no. 214, p. 6; no. 217, p. 18.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Stones, A., ‘The full-page miniatures of the Psalter-Hours New York,
                           PML, MS M. 729. Programme and patron’ in Büttner (2004), pp. 281–307, at
                           pp. 299, 305, 307.</bibl>



                     </listBibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2024-08">Convert full description from Solopova catalogue.</change>
         <change when="2022-04-04">Add binding information from Summary Catalogue.</change>
         <change when="2017-07-01">First online publication.</change>
         <change when="2017-05-25">
            <persName>James Cummings</persName> Up-converted the markup using <ref
               target="https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl"
               >https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl</ref>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
