<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:teitite="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/tite/1.0" xml:id="manuscript_11035">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Exeter College MS. 40</title>
            <title type="collection">Exeter College MSS.</title>
            <respStmt xml:id="AW">
               <resp when="2009">Cataloguer</resp>
               <persName>Andrew Watson</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="TA">
               <resp when="2020">Encoding</resp>
               <persName>Tuija Ainonen</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition/>
            <funder>Conversion of the printed catalogue to TEI funded by the Rector and Fellows of Exeter College.</funder>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </publisher>
            <idno type="msID">Exeter_College_MS_40</idno>
            <idno type="collection">Exeter_College</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="Exeter_College_MS_40" xml:lang="en">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <repository>Exeter College</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">Exeter College MS. 40</idno>
               <idno type="ieArk">ark:29072/e08623hx14rq</idno><idno type="crArk">ark:29072/e08336h131f3</idno></msIdentifier>
               <head>Gregorius I, <title>Homiliae in Ezechielem</title>; England, s. xii<hi rend="superscript">ex</hi>
               </head>
               <msContents>
                  <textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>
                  <msItem n="1" xml:id="Exeter_College_MS_40-1">
                     <locus from="1r" to="96v">(fols. 1<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>–96<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>)</locus>
                     <author key="person_100184667">Gregorius I</author>
                     <title key="work_1869">Homiliae in Ezechielem</title>
                     <rubric>Incipit prologus beati Gregorij pape</rubric>
                     <incipit>Dilectissimo fratri Marimano episcopo. Gregorius seruus seruorum Dei. Omelias que in beatum Ezechielem prophetam </incipit>
                     <explicit>redeatur</explicit>
                     <rubric>Incipit liber primus omeliarum beati Gregorij pape urbis Rome in primam partem Ezechielis prophete que sunt numero duodecim</rubric>
                     <incipit>Dei omnipotentis aspiratione </incipit>
                     <explicit><locus from="52v" to="52v">[fol. 52<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>]</locus> per omnia secula seculorum amen.</explicit>
                     <finalRubric>Explicit liber primus</finalRubric>
                     <rubric>Incipit liber secundus omeliarum Gregorii pape urbis Rome in extremam partem Ezechielis prophete que sunt numero decem</rubric>
                     <incipit>Quoniam multis curis pertinentibus </incipit>
                     <explicit> per omnia secula seculorum. Amen. </explicit>
                     <finalRubric>Explicit omeliarum liber sancti Gregorij pape urbis Rome in extremam partem Ezechielis prophete que sunt numero decem.</finalRubric>
                     <note>Stegmüller, <title>Bibl.</title>, 2643; pr. <title>PL</title> 76. 785–1072. Ed. M. Adriaen, CCSL 142 (1971); <title>GPL</title> 1710. There is occasional loss of small sections of text through the disappearance of patches over which the text had been written. Rough crayon notes in bottom margins relate to the text.</note>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <p>
                     <secFol>aliquando.</secFol>
                  </p>
                  <p>Collation:</p>
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="perg">
                        <support>parchment <term type="disposition"><!--HSOS-->HFFH</term></support>
                        <extent>96 leaves preceded and followed by two 18th-century paper flyleaves. <dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                              <height>345</height>
                              <width>245</width>
                           </dimensions>
                           <dimensions type="column" unit="mm">
                              <height>270</height>
                              <width>70</width>
                           </dimensions>
                        </extent>
                        <collation>1–12<hi rend="superscript">8</hi>. No catchwords; <signatures type="quire">quire numbers, large roman capital figures with pen decorations, in bottom centre of final leaves</signatures>.</collation>
                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout columns="2" writtenLines="40">Two columns, 40 lines. Pricked in inner and outer margins, ruled in crayon. </layout>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc>
                     <handNote>A good English protogothic script, probably by one scribe in spite of a marked difference between the appearances of the first few and the later pages due to increased lateral compression. Insular abbreviations for <hi rend="italic">enim</hi> and <hi rend="italic">est</hi> are used. Punctuated by punctus elevatus, punctus interrogativus, and low point. On a number of pages, probably because of damp, many individual letters or minims have become detached from the surface; most have been lost but on fols. 10<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>, 11<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>, and 12<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> a strange effect results from the adhesion of others, scattered at random over the page.</handNote>
                  </handDesc>
                  <decoDesc>
                     <decoNote type="flourInit">At the beginning of the first homily is a blue and red interlace initial surrounded by muddy brown and green and enclosed in a square, but most other initials are plain blue-and-red 5-line initials filled (probably later) with patterns in the same brown and green except when they are long (e.g. J) and provide no scope for infilling, and are therefore left unadorned except for marginal arabesques. Book 1 has red running book numbers; book 2 black running book numbers dotted red, both being guided by roughly written crayon notes in top margins, such as ‘O<ex>melia</ex> vi. partis prime’, ‘O<ex>melia</ex> v. partis ij.’ There are rubrics in both parts. Alexander and Temple, no. 136.</decoNote>
                  </decoDesc>
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <binding calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="1850" notBefore="1800">
                        <p>Sewn on six bands. Standard Exeter binding: simple and quite elegant, calf over millboards, the calf bearing blind decoration of a floral type, early 19th century. On the spine is a red leather label with a gold title.</p>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="1200" notBefore="1175">s. xii<hi rend="superscript">ex</hi>
                     </origDate>
                     <origPlace><country key="place_7002445">England</country></origPlace>
                  </origin>
                  <provenance>There is no evidence for the book’s pre-Exeter history although it is clearly the product of a monastic scriptorium (in which the standard of script was higher than that of the decoration and of the preparation of the quires). </provenance>
                  <provenance>On fol. 96<hi rend="superscript">v</hi> is ‘lib. Coll. Exon. oxon.’ in a hand of <hi rend="italic">c.</hi> 1600. The book is not recorded in <title>Ecloga</title> as being in the College around 1600 but on fol. 47 a tab for a title has been made as in MSS 28 fol. 273 (272), 37 fol. 109, and 38 fol. 94, the present title, in the same hand as in these books, being ‘Gregorjus in Ezechielem’. See further Watson, <title>Exeter</title>, Introduction, pp. xxii–xxiii. The present volume is <title>CMA</title>, no. 26.</provenance>
                  <provenance>Exeter library identifications are, on the front pastedown, ‘D1–4’ deleted and replaced by (or perhaps replacing), ‘<gap/>–2–9’ (scribbled over),‘173–H–5’, the book stamp and ‘Coxe Cat. no: XL’. On the spine is a round paper label with ‘5’ on it.</provenance>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>
                           <bibl>Andrew G. Watson, <title>A descriptive catalogue of the medieval manuscripts of Exeter College, Oxford</title> (Oxford: Oxford University Press), 2000.</bibl>
                        </source>
                     </recordHist>
                     <availability>
                        <p>For enquiries relating to this manuscript please contact <ref target="https://www.exeter.ox.ac.uk/library-archives-and-special-collections/">Exeter College Library</ref>.</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2020-04-29">First online publication</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>