<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:teitite="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/tite/1.0" xml:id="manuscript_11062">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Exeter College MS. 68</title>
            <title type="collection">Exeter College MSS.</title>
            <respStmt xml:id="AW">
               <resp when="2009">Cataloguer</resp>
               <persName>Andrew Watson</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="TA">
               <resp when="2020">Encoding</resp>
               <persName>Tuija Ainonen</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </publisher>
            <idno type="msID">Exeter_College_MS_68</idno>
            <idno type="collection">Exeter_College</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="Exeter_College_MS_68" xml:lang="en">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <repository>Exeter College</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">Exeter College MS. 68</idno>
               <idno type="ieArk">ark:29072/e0fx719k46r0</idno><idno type="crArk">ark:29072/e0ft848p63f4</idno></msIdentifier>
               <head>Anon., <title>Sermones de tempore et de sanctis</title>; Oxford, England, Fols. 1–197 <hi rend="italic">c.</hi> 1460?, rest 1480 × 1484</head>
               <msContents>
                  <textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>
                  <msItem n="1" xml:id="Exeter_College_MS_68-1">
                     <locus from="1r" to="152r">(fols. 1<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>–152<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>)</locus>
                     <author key="person_8870917">Hugo de S. Caro (attrib.)</author>
                     <title key="work_7412">Seminarium praedicationis (or praedicatorum)</title>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="1r" to="1v">(fol. 1<hi rend="superscript">r–v</hi>)</locus>
                        <rubric>Incipit prologus in seminarium predicacionis.</rubric>
                        <incipit>Ad sugillandum vicia commendandumque virtutes. plerique sacre scripture capitula utiliora in seminarium predicacionis... excerpsi </incipit>
                        <explicit>to ostenditur que sunt illa que suadent presentes sermones. et que sit merces custodiencium verbi dei.</explicit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="1v" to="2r">(fols. 1<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>–2<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>)</locus>
                        <rubric>Sermo inuitatorius ad audiendum verbum dei.</rubric>
                        <incipit>Beati qui audiunt verbum dei et custodiunt illud. Vultis nosse quam beati. primo quidem vox diuina sonans in auribus cor conturbat </incipit>
                        <explicit> Beati ergo qui sic audiunt verbum dei et custodiunt illud.</explicit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="2r" to="2v">(fol. 2<hi rend="superscript">r–v</hi>)</locus>
                        <rubric>Hij sunt tituli capitulorum sermonis in prima dominica aduentus domini.</rubric>
                        <incipit>Primo ostenditur desiderium antiquorum patrum </incipit>
                        <explicit>ad caput illorum et fontis. </explicit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="2v" to="150r">(fols. 2<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>–150<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>)</locus>
                        <rubric>Sermo de dominica prima in aduentum domini.</rubric>
                        <incipit>In die illa erit fons patens domini uel domus dau’ habitantibus Ierusalem. Bernardus. Ardorem desiderij patrum antiquorum</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="150r" to="152r">(fol. 150<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>–152<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>)</locus>
                        <rubric>Sermo de salutacione angelica</rubric>
                        <finalRubric>Hic explicit liber qui cognominatur Seminarium predicacionis super temporale.</finalRubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <note>A collection of sermons of uncertain authorship. Kaeppeli, and Schneyer, ii. 758–85 are unhelpful; Bloomfield, no. 0296, lists as Hugo’s, with a query; Glorieux, <title>Theologie</title>, 2bb, lists as doubtful or spurious, in this probably following E. Mangenot<!-- (see headnote to MSS 51–68 above)-->, <title>Dictionnaire de théologie catholique</title>, vii (Paris, 1921) 221–308. Mangenot points to the lack of medieval evidence to support the attribution, implying that the earliest evidence is that of Trithemius (but not found in his <title>Scriptores</title>) and remarking that the note of attribution in BNF, MS lat. 16515, is in a ‘modern’ hand. No author is named in Salisbury Cathedral MS 21. Nevertheless, although Hugo’s name is not mentioned in the present manuscript, the inclusion of this text in the final volume of Roger Keys’s gift, which is predominandy of works by or attributed to Hugo, suggests that there was a medieval belief in his authorship.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="2" xml:id="Exeter_College_MS_68-2">
                     <locus>(fols. 152<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>–179<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>, 182<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>–235<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>)</locus>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="152v">(fol. 152<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>)</locus>
                        <rubric>Tituli capitulorum sequentis sermonis.</rubric>
                        <incipit>Primo commendatur facilitas conuercionis apostolorum Petri et Andree </incipit>
                        <explicit>optandum est illuc venire.</explicit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="152v">(fol. 152<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>)</locus>
                        <rubric>Sermo in die sancti Andree Apostoli. Secundum Matheum.</rubric>
                        <incipit>Ambulans Iesus iuxta mare Galilee ... Audistis fratres karissimi quia ad vnius uissionis vocem Petrus et Andreas relictis rethibus secuti sunt saluatorem </incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="176r">(fol. 176<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>)</locus>
                        <rubric>Tituli capitulorum sermonis sequentis</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="176v">(fol. 176<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>)</locus>
                        <rubric>Sermo de Sancto Laurencio.</rubric>
                        <incipit>Qui parce seminat parce et metet ... Cum pro certo futurum sit quod omnes astabimus ante tribunal domini nostri </incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="179v">(fol. 179<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>)</locus>
                        <explicit defective="true">Emerunt aromata non reperunt non <note>[<hi rend="italic">followed by catchword</hi>
                              <catchwords>rapuerunt et cetera</catchwords>]</note>
                        </explicit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="182r" to="235v">(fol. 182<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>–235<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>)</locus>
                        <incipit defective="true"> tes venient cum exultacione et cantabunt celeuma diuinum portantes manipulos suos. Quod nobis etc. </incipit>
                        <rubric>Tituli capitulorum sermonis sequentis.</rubric>
                        <incipit>Que est ista que ascendit ... sicut gloriosa domina cuius instat solempnitas ceteris sanctis</incipit>
                        <explicit defective="true">ad peiora attenditur. Hinc Osee propheta </explicit>
                     </msItem>
                     <note>The proper of saints of the same collection of sermons as (1) above. The sermon on St Laurence (10 Aug.) breaks abruptly at the end of fol. 176<hi rend="superscript">v</hi> because of the apparent insertion of (3) and (4) below and the excision of the last leaf of quire 23, resuming only at the end, on fol. 182<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. The excision of a leaf between fols. 227 and 228 leads to no loss of text, but sermon 102, <title>De virginibus</title>, ch. 6, ends abruptly because of the loss of the last leaf of the final quire. The lists of sermons below show that the volume contained at least 110 sermons, but since the book and perhaps also the list end abruptly, the full number cannot be known.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="3" xml:id="Exeter_College_MS_68-3">
                     <locus from="180r" to="181v">(fols. 180<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>–181<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>)</locus>
                     <title key="work_12374">An alphabetical subject index to sermons 1–110 above</title>
                     <incipit>Auditus uerbi primo sermone. Aqua iiº <hi rend="italic">.xxix. xl.viij</hi></incipit>
                     <explicit>elus. <hi rend="italic">ciiiº</hi></explicit>
                     <note>Inserted, with item 4, into the text of 2. References are to sermons by number.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="4" xml:id="Exeter_College_MS_68-4">
                     <locus from="181r" to="181v">(fol. 181<hi rend="superscript">r–v</hi>)</locus>
                     <title key="work_12374">A list of the above sermons</title>
                     <incipit><hi rend="italic">Primus</hi>. Beati qui audiunt </incipit>
                     <explicit defective="true"><hi rend="italic">cx.</hi> Multitudinis credencium. Cum partibus duabus. Multitudinis. Nunc de studio </explicit>
                     <note>The list is in numerical order followed by the incipit and the day on which they should be used, mostly in the form, e.g. ‘In die sancte trinitatis’; ending abruptly because of the loss of the sixth (final) leaf of quire 23. Inserted, with item 3, into the text of 2.</note>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <p>
                     <secFol>est que.</secFol>
                  </p>
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="perg">
                        <support>parchment <term type="disposition"><!--FSOS-->FHHF</term></support>
                        <extent><measure type="leaf" quantity="235">235</measure> leaves preceded and followed by a post-medieval paper flyleaf <dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                              <height>412</height>
                              <width>185</width>
                           </dimensions>
                           <dimensions type="columns" unit="mm">
                              <height>290</height>
                              <width>80</width>
                           </dimensions>
                        </extent>
                        <collation mainStructures="8">1–22<hi rend="superscript">8</hi> 23<hi rend="superscript">6</hi> (wants 6) 24–28<hi rend="superscript">8</hi> 29<hi rend="superscript">8</hi> (wants 7) 30<hi rend="superscript">8</hi> (wants 8). <catchwords>Catchwords are at bottom right-hand corners of leaves and with one exception are plain, the exception being on fol. 213<hi rend="superscript">v</hi> where it is written by a new scribe in an ornamental box.</catchwords> No quire signatures or numbers.</collation>
                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout columns="2" writtenLines="60">Two columns, 60 lines. Ruled in ink.</layout>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc>
                     <handNote>Fols. 1–197 (end of quire) written by <persName key="person_4336" role="scr">Scribe 3 (William Osborne?)</persName>; see MS 51, Script. In this volume he makes no use of high and low decorative ascenders. From there to the end is in several new hands: (1) fols. 198<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>–201<hi rend="superscript">va</hi>/48, (2) fols. 201<hi rend="superscript">va</hi>/48–202<hi rend="superscript">vb</hi>, then in a number of variable and merging hands. Rector’s Accounts, autumn 1480, refer to payments to ‘uni scriptori pro pargameno et labore circa Sermones Hugonis de Vienna xiiii<hi rend="superscript">5</hi> i<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>’ (Boase<hi rend="superscript">2</hi>, xxxvii n. 1): comparison of this sum with the total sum for writing and illuminating paid by John Combe (see History below) suggests that it was the fee of the principal scribe, Osborne.</handNote>
                  </handDesc>
                  <decoDesc>
                     <decoNote type="border">Of the same type as MS 51 but mainly by <persName key="person_4333" role="art">Artist D (Bray)</persName>. On fol. 1<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> is an illuminated border on three sides by Artist D: see headnote to MSS 51–68; q.v. also for a characterization of his work.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="flourInit">Otherwise 3/6-line red-and-blue lombards, flourished red, and 3-line plain blue initials, which seem to be in the same hand throughout; also rubrics, red running numbers of sermons, red marginal authorities, and chapter divisions. The Rector’s Accounts, ut supra, record payment in autumn 1484 to ‘John Bray pro ligacione et illuminatura duorum voluminum operis Hugonis de Vienna, xx<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> pro incathenacione eorundem in libraria’, one of which is certainly this volume and the other probably MS 60. On him see also headnote to MSS 51–68. Alexander and Temple, no. 593.</decoNote>
                  </decoDesc>
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <binding calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="1610" notBefore="1605">
                        <p>Stamped leather bindings over square-edged wooden boards, (presumably) rebound; stamp used was employed in Oxford between 1535 and 1621, here in the second phase state, probably <hi rend="italic">c.</hi> 1605–10. Two straps held by nails. Refurbished in the 19th century (1839?): that volumes were resewn is indicated by the very tight binding, which makes collation difficult, and by the provision of new endbands; edges were stained red; book was reinforced by pasting long strips of canvas round the spine and attached to the boards, and the old spines were replaced. Sewn on five bands. No headbands. For other details see <!--headnote to MSS 51–68-->Watson, <title>Exeter</title>, p. 87.</p>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="1484" notBefore="1460">Fols. 1–197 <hi rend="italic">c.</hi> 1460?, rest 1480 × 1484</origDate>
                     <origPlace><settlement key="place_7011931">Oxford</settlement>, <country key="place_7002445">England</country></origPlace>
                  </origin>
                  <provenance>One of the group of manuscripts, now 51–68, given to the College by <persName key="person_4337" role="fmo dnr">Roger Keys</persName>, whose arms have been excised from the lower margin of fol. 1<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Keys’s <hi rend="italic">ex dono</hi> inscription was probably on a lost preliminary leaf; see MS 53, History. This volume seems, however, to be a kind of appendix to the series: it contains sermons and not biblical commentaries atttributed to Hugo de S. Caro, it is not numbered as the 18th volume, as MSS 51–67 are each numbered 1–17, and the Rector’s Accounts make it clear that writing and illumination were completed in 1480 × 1484 (see Script and Decoration, above) and that M. <persName key="person_4344">John Combe</persName> (d. by April 1499: see <title>BRUO</title>) paid 26s 8d towards this—‘xxvi<hi rend="superscript">s</hi> viii<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> a M. Johanne Combe pro complecione operis Hugonis de Vienna’—and perhaps a second volume referred to (see Decoration, above).</provenance>
                  <provenance>Exeter library identifications are, on the front pastedown, bookplate 3, and on it ‘173.H.8’, deleted and replaced by ‘213.G.7’, and ‘Coxe LXVII’ (pencil). On fol. 1<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> is ‘Liber Coll: Exon’ (s. xvi/xvii?).</provenance>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>
                           <bibl>Andrew G. Watson, <title>A descriptive catalogue of the medieval manuscripts of Exeter College, Oxford</title> (Oxford: Oxford University Press), 2000.</bibl>
                        </source>
                     </recordHist>
                     <availability>
                        <p>For enquiries relating to this manuscript please contact <ref target="https://www.exeter.ox.ac.uk/library-archives-and-special-collections/">Exeter College Library</ref>.</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2020-04-29">First online publication</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>