<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="manuscript_2799">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>MS. Canon. Ital. 85</title>
            <title type="collection">MSS. Canon. Ital. (Canonici Italian)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp when="2022-05">Cataloguer</resp>
               <persName>Matthew Holford</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BCBB">
               <resp when="2020">Cataloguer</resp>
               <persName>B. C. Barker-Benfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </publisher>
            <idno type="msID">MS_Canon_Ital_85</idno>
            <idno type="collection">Canon Ital</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="MS_Canon_Ital_85" xml:lang="en">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <region type="county">Oxfordshire</region>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <institution>University of Oxford</institution>
                  <repository>Bodleian Library</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">MS. Canon. Ital. 85</idno>
                  <idno type="ieArk">ark:29072/x0jw827b53dj</idno><idno type="crArk">ark:29072/x0bc386j77mx</idno><altIdentifier type="internal">
                     <idno type="SCN">20137</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
               <head>Boccaccio, <title>Filocolo</title>; Italy (probably Mantua), c. 1464</head>
               <msContents>
                  <msItem n="1" xml:id="MS_Canon_Ital_85-item1">
                     <locus>(fols. 1r-239v)</locus>
                     <author key="person_64002165">Boccaccio</author>
                     <title key="work_1104">Filocolo</title>
                     <incipit>Mancate gia tanto le forse del valoroso popolo</incipit>
                     <explicit>la cui vita nelle mani della tua donna amore conservi</explicit>
                     <textLang mainLang="it">Italian</textLang>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="perg">
                        <support>parchment</support>
                        <extent>2 (medieval parchment bifolium) + 240 + 2 (medieval parchment bifolium) leaves, with a short 18th-century description of the manuscript in Italian, unfoliated, pasted to fol. 241r. 
                           <dimensions unit="mm" type="leaf">
                              <height>355</height>
                              <width>230</width>
                           </dimensions></extent>
                        <foliation>i-ii, 1-35, 35a-239, 240-1</foliation>
                        <collation mainStructures="10">1(10)-24(10) (de la Mare and Reynolds, 53)</collation>
                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout columns="1" writtenLines="42">1 col, 42 lines; column space <dimensions unit="mm" type="column">
                           <height>239</height>
                           <width>126</width>
                        </dimensions>; ruled in ink (horizontal lines) and drypoint or plummet on versos (verticals), double horizontal bounding lines (de la Mare and Reynolds, 53)</layout>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc hands="1">
                     <handNote script="humanistica">Humanistic script. Written by <persName key="person_59" role="scr">Andrea de Laude</persName> for Lodovico Gonzaga, c. 1464, as is shown by a letter from Andrea to Lodovico in the Gonzaga archive dated 30 Jan. 1464 and referring to the copying of the manuscript (J. J. G. Alexander, 'The scribe of the Boccaccio Filostrato identified', <title>BLR</title> 9 (1973-8), 303-4, with text). De la Mare and Reynolds (p. 53) identified the scribe's hand in Turin, Biblioteca Nazionale Universitaria di Torino, Ms. N. VI. 11 (Dante, <title>Commedia</title>, badly damaged in 1904; see further under Decoration). They also suggested (ibid.) an identification with Andrea Morena da Lodi, who copied <ref target="https://archivesetmanuscrits.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/cc96102">Paris, BnF MS. Italien 81</ref>, but there are several differences between the script of the Oxford and Paris manuscripts. </handNote>
                  </handDesc>
                  <decoDesc>
                     <summary>'Important miniatures, borders, initials' (<ref target="https://catalog.hathitrust.org/Record/000468709">Pächt and Alexander</ref> ii. 393, pl. XXXVII and frontispiece).</summary>
                     <decoNote type="miniature">Half-page miniatures at the beginning of each book illustrating 'episodes described or referred to early in each book' (Alexander 1994):<!-- note: not in Iconclass 19.5.22 -->
                        <list>
                           <item>(fol. 1r) Juno in her chariot drawn by peacocks with Pope, Cardinal and two attendants</item>
                           <item>(fol. 25r) Venus, Mount Cythera, and Cupid tempering his arrows</item>
                           <item>(fol. 67r) Four youths in a walled garden with falcon and dog</item>
                           <item>(fol. 114v) A group of horsemen in a city square</item>
                           <item>(fol. 190v) Filocolo/Florio and Biancafiore parting from the Admiral</item>
                        </list>
                        The artist of the miniatures has also been identified (first in print by Pächt and Alexander in 1970) in <ref target="https://www.bl.uk/catalogues/illuminatedmanuscripts/record.asp?MSID=6586&amp;CollID=8&amp;NStart=3567">British Library Harley MS. 3567</ref> (written for Cardinal Francesco Gonzaga), and (by Fumian in 2014) in Turin, BN, Ms. N. VI. 11, written perhaps also by Andrea de Laude for an unknown patron (see above, Hands). The artist of the Harley manuscript was identified by Meroni in 1966 as <persName role="art" key="person_85976757">Pietro Guindaleri of Cremona (-1506)</persName> whose documented work is Turin, BN, Ms. I. I. 22-23 (Pliny, <title>Natural History</title>), although this identification has not been universally accepted (see the entry in <title>Dizionario biografico dei miniatori italiani: secoli IX-XVI</title>, ed. M. Bollati (Milan, 2004)). The artist of the Turin Dante was tentatively identified by Fumian in 2014, on the basis of documentary evidence, as <persName role="art" key="person_311444578">Jacopo Bellanti da San Pietro di Galatina</persName>. For more detailed descriptions of the miniatures see Alexander 1994 and de la Mare and Reynolds 1991-1992, who suggest that the border and initials (below) may have been the work of different artists.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="border">Strapwork borders on gold ground at the beginning of each book; Alexander 1994 compared the borders of Madrid, Biblioteca Nacional, MS. Vit. 22-5 (Plautus, written for Lodovico Gonzaga III).</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="decInit">Large interlace initials on gold ground at the beginning of each book; 5-line initials in different styles (gold with vine-stem decoration on coloured grounds, or coloured interlace on gold grounds, or coloured with acanthus decoration on gold grounds). De la Mare and Reynolds compared the initials in BL Addit. MS. 14777, <ref target="https://www.bl.uk/catalogues/illuminatedmanuscripts/record.asp?MSID=4352&amp;CollID=8&amp;NStart=3691">BL Harley MS 3691</ref>, and Victoria and Albert Museum L. 366-1956.</decoNote>
                  </decoDesc>
                  <bindingDesc resp="#BCBB">
                     <binding notAfter="1700" notBefore="1600">
                        <p>17th century?, <placeName key="place_1000080">Italian</placeName> or <placeName key="place_1000070">French</placeName>?: pasteboards; red leather with all-over gilt tooling in a diamond-shaped panel with elaborate corner- and centre-pieces, all areas richly infilled with a small fleur-de-lis tool; spine similarly gilt (damaged and re-laid); edges of boards also gilt-tooled with a narrow roll; gilt gauffered edges. Rebacked, 19th or 20th century, Bodleian. <dimensions type="binding" unit="mm">
                              <height max="365" min="264">364–365</height>
                              <width precision="medium" quantity="240">c. 240</width>
                              <depth max="70" min="65" precision="medium">c. 65–70</depth>
                           </dimensions> (book closed) (Barker-Benfield, 2020).</p>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origDate calendar="Gregorian" cert="high" notAfter="1465" notBefore="1463">c. 1464</origDate>
                     <origPlace cert="low">
                        <country key="place_1000080">Italian</country>, <settlement key="place_7005879">Mantua</settlement> or possibly <settlement key="place_7004264">Ferrara</settlement> <!--ORIGINAL: Italian, Mantua or Ferrara (?)--></origPlace>
                  </origin>
                  <provenance>Produced for <persName key="person_32862995" role="pat fmo">Lodovico III Gonzaga of Mantua</persName> (above, Hands); arms of Gonzaga of Mantua integral to the border decoration.</provenance>
                  <provenance>Perhaps dispersed from the Gonzaga library either during its sack in 1630 or in the sale of the library at Venice at 1707 by Ferdinando Carlo Gonzaga (C. H. Clough, ‘The Library of the Gonzaga of Mantua’, <title>Librarium</title> 15, no. 1 (1972), 50-63); there is no evidence of ownership by Bernardo Trevisan or Jacopo Soranzo.</provenance>
                  <provenance>On fol. ii verso is (18th-century?) a device with initials 'S E' and below 'Francesco Squarcione ?', referring to the Italian painter (d. 1468); the connection with the present manuscript is unclear. </provenance>
                  <provenance notAfter="1805" notBefore="1727" resp="#MMM"><persName key="person_2384880" role="fmo">Matteo Luigi Canonici, 1727–1805</persName>, source of acquisition not known.</provenance>
                  <provenance notAfter="1807" resp="#MMM"><persName key="person_446" role="fmo">Giuseppe Canonici , -1807</persName></provenance>
                  <acquisition resp="#MMM" when="1817">Purchased by the Bodleian in 1817.</acquisition>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>Description adapted (May 2022) by Matthew Holford from the following sources, with additional reference to published literature as cited: 
                           <listBibl>
                              <bibl>B. C. Barker-Benfield, <title>Bookbindings of Canonici manuscripts : a survey of early and non-standard bindings, mostly Italian, in the Canonici collection of the Bodleian Library, University of Oxford</title> (Oxford, privately printed, 2020).</bibl>
                              <bibl>Andrew G. Watson, <title>Catalogue of Dated and Datable Manuscripts c. 435-1600 in Oxford Libraries</title> (1984), no. 229</bibl>
                              <bibl>Otto Pächt and J. J. G. Alexander, <title>Illuminated Manuscripts in the Bodleian Library Oxford</title>, II (1970), no. 393</bibl>
                           </listBibl>
                           Previously described in the Quarto Catalogue (A. Mortara, <title>Catalogo dei manoscritti italiani che sotto la denominazione di Codici Canoniciani Italici si conservano nella Biblioteca Bodleiana a Oxford</title>, Quarto Catalogues XI, 1864). 
                           <listBibl>
                              <bibl facs="acp0067.gif" type="QUARTO">Quarto Catalogue, col. 102</bibl>
                              <bibl facs="acp0068.gif" type="QUARTO">Quarto Catalogue, col. 103</bibl>
                              <bibl facs="aaz0432.gif" type="SC">Summary Catalogue, vol. 4, p. 413</bibl>
                           </listBibl>
                        </source>
                     </recordHist>
                     <availability status="restricted">
                        <p>To ensure its preservation, access to this item is restricted, and readers are asked to work from reproductions and published descriptions as far as possible. If you wish to apply to see the original, please click the request button above. When your request is received, you will be asked to contact the relevant curator outlining the subject of your research, the importance of this item to that research, and the resources you have already consulted.</p>
                        
                         <!--  <p>Please not in addition that this item will be on display in the exhibition "Chaucer Here and Now", Bodleian Libraries, Weston Library, 8 December 2023 – 28 April 2024. It will not be orderable between those dates or for a short period before or afterwards.</p>
                        -->
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <surrogates>
                     <bibl type="digital-facsimile" subtype="full">
                        <ref target="https://digital.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/objects/93495971-ec30-431e-8e5f-09ffc3660d73/">
                           <title>Digital Bodleian</title></ref> <note>(full digital facsimile)</note>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl subtype="partial" type="digital-facsimile">
                        <ref target="https://digital.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/objects/858af083-69b0-4c68-a3ea-88378f501d22/">
                           <title>Digital Bodleian</title></ref> <note>(13 images from 35mm slides)</note>
                     </bibl>
                  </surrogates>
                  <listBibl>
                     <head>Selected printed descriptions and studies:</head>
                     <bibl>Fumian, Silvia. ‘Una Nuova Proposta per Il Miniatore Del Filocolo Gonzaga (Oxford, Bodleian Library, MS. Canon. Ital. 85)’, in <title>Il Codice Miniato in Europa: Libri per La Chiesa, per La Città, per La Corte</title>, edited by Giordana Mariani Canova and Alessandra Perriccioli Saggese. Padua: Il Poligrafo casa editrice, 2014.</bibl>
                     <bibl>Alexander, J. J. G., ed. <title>The Painted Page: Italian Renaissance Book Illumination, 1450-1550</title>, Munich: Prestel, 1994, cat. 22 (p. 80).</bibl>
                     <bibl>De la Mare, A. C., and C. Reynolds. ‘Illustrated Boccaccio Manuscripts in Oxford Libraries’. <title>Studi Sul Boccaccio</title> 20 (1992 1991): 45–72.</bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2022-05-18">Description revised for publication on Digital Bodleian.</change>
         <change when="2020-07-21">Binding description added.</change>
         <change when="2018-10-14" xml:id="MMM"><persName>Mitch Fraas</persName> Provenance and acquisition information added using <ref target="https://github.com/littlegustv/oxfordupdates/blob/master/test_case_for_oxford_prov.rb">https://github.com/littlegustv/oxfordupdates/blob/master/test_case_for_oxford_prov.rb</ref> in collaboration with the <ref target="http://mappingmanuscriptmigrations.org/">Mapping Manuscript Migrations</ref> project.</change>
         <change when="2017-07-01">First online publication.</change>
         <change when="2017-05-25"><persName>James Cummings</persName> Up-converted the markup using <ref target="https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl">https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl</ref></change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>