<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="manuscript_2607">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>MS. Canon. Ital. 174</title>
            <title type="collection">MSS. Canon. Ital. (Canonici Italian)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Description</resp>
               <persName>Sarah McNamer</persName>
               <persName>Andrew Dunning</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </publisher>
            <idno type="msID">MS_Canon_Ital_174</idno>
            <idno type="collection">Canon Ital</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="MS_Canon_Ital_174" xml:lang="en">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <region type="county">Oxfordshire</region>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <institution>University of Oxford</institution>
                  <repository>Bodleian Library</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">MS. Canon. Ital. 174</idno>
                  <idno type="ieArk">ark:29072/x0000001078n</idno><idno type="crArk">ark:29072/x0pc289h91x6</idno><altIdentifier type="internal">
                     <idno type="SCN">20226</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents>
                  <textLang mainLang="it">Italian</textLang>
                  <msItem n="1" xml:id="MS_Canon_Ital_174-item1">
                     <locus>(fols. 1r–127r)</locus>
                     <title key="work_3964">Meditazioni della vita di Cristo</title>
                     <rubric>Qui comenza el prologo de le meditatione de la vita del nostro signore miser yhu xpo la cui doctrina e seme de p<supplied>r</supplied>udentia la cui vita e spechio de temperantia e patientia.</rubric>
                     <incipit>Infra le altre gran vertude che se leze de sancta cecilia uergene si e questa zoe che la portaua sempre lo euangelio de cristo iesu ascoxo nel suo pecto e questo de tu intender cusi che ella se hauea scrito algune electe cose piu deuote de la vita de miser iesu cristo e in queste la pensaua di e nocte cum tutto el so cuore e cum tuta la intentione e feruore.</incipit>
                     <explicit>et molte altre cose fece miser iesu le qualle io non scriuo per<locus>(fol. 127r)</locus>che seria tropo longo dire. Ma noi posiamo comprehendere et pensare ch’el fece molte cose le qualle io non scriuo in questo libro. Come se puote vedere nelli evangelii ch’el adopero el nostro signore miser iesu cristo. El qualle sia laudato et ringratiato cum la sua benedecta madre vergene maria in secula seculorum. Amen. Deo gratias.</explicit>
                     <colophon>Priegoue sorelle per caritade che quando legereti in questo libero priegate miser iesu per me che me doni cognoscimento.</colophon>
                     <note>Edited and translated from this manuscript by <ref target="https://doi.org/10.2307/j.ctvpg84z2">Sarah McNamer, <title>Meditations on the Life of Christ: The Short Italian Text</title> (Notre Dame, 2018)</ref>. Scholars dispute whether <title>Meditationes vitae Christi</title> originated as an Italian or Latin text. McNamer argues that the original was the Italian <foreign rend="italic">testo breve</foreign> that this manuscript witnesses and that its author was a woman, an anonymous Poor Clare from Pisa.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="2">
                     <locus>(fols. 127r–137v)</locus>
                     <title type="desc">Letter for the nuns of the Monastero di Sant’Alvise by a priest who served as their confessor</title>
                     <rubric>Seguita vna diuota e utile epistola composta da vno venerabile padre e confessore delle venerande done del monasterio de miser sancto aluuixe nella qualle epistola se trata delli auersarii de lanima çioe di quelli che sono buoni e utile aduersarii.</rubric>
                     <incipit>O choreme per uostra doctrina et conforto in cristo iesu dilectissime figliule. Uno notabel dito evangelico el qualle scriue sancto Mathio e sono parole del nostro signore. Et dice cussi. Esto consentiens aduersario tuo cito dum es in via cum eo ne forte tradat te iudici aduersarius. Iudex tradat te ministro et in carcerem mittaris. Amen dico tibi non exeas inde donec reddes nouissimum quadrantem. Vulgarmente parlando diçe il signore. Sii consentiente al tuo aduersario tosto perfina tanto che tu se in via cum lui açio che per auentura el non te dia ne le man del Iudice.</incipit>
                     <explicit>Aduncha ha <locus>(fol. 137r)</locus> biando notitia de cussi vtili aduersarii come appareno gli sopradeti sforciamose de concordarse o essi secundo el consiglio del Iudice perfeto consigliatore cioe de sopra se contiene nella proposta açio loro non ne metano nelle mani del Iudice iusto et esso vedandone discordi cum li deti aduersarii ne meta ne le mano de i tormentatori demonii e loro ne metano nelle infernale pregione la doue mai vssire non si potra perfina atanto che non se renda infina alultimo quadrante çioe perfina che non si compira de satisfare ala diuinia Iustitia. Et questa satisfacione durera per Infinita secula seculorum. Amen. Deo Gratias.</explicit>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="3">
                     <locus>(fols. 137v–149r)</locus>
                     <author key="person_53562263">Girolamo da Siena</author>
                     <title>Epistola Terza: La Perfetta Monaca</title>
                     <rubric>Incomincia vna diuota e utile epistola di frate ieronimo del lordine di frati romiti di sancto augustino ad vna sua figliola vergene a dio sacrata nella <supplied>qualle</supplied> se dimostra chi e vera monicha.</rubric>
                     <incipit>Frate geronimo alla sua cara figliola serua e sposa di dio. Salute e dono di pace cristiano amore notitia di dio chiareça di veritade pentimento verace confusione e odio di vechia vita pasata e nouamento <locus>(fol. 137r)</locus> di virtu. Dispiacimento del seculo costumi religiosi morte al mondo e vita in cristo iesu dolcissimo salvatore. Amen. Charissima in cristo iesu sono stato gia grande tempo in pensiero di douerti scriuere e a questo aspectaua di auere la mente quieta e pacifica per potermi asotigliare ad scriuerti quello che dio mi facese intendere che ti fuisse piu necessario.</incipit>
                     <explicit>et io che sacrificio non celebro sença la tua memoria sempre cosi il prego che in questa vita el ti riempia di gratia. Et miser iesu cristo figliolo di dio viuo e vero te e me conduca nel sino del suo padre nella cui dextera esso sedendo viue e regna in secula seculorum. Amen. In esso saluatore vaglia e posa l’anima tua e tu serua di dio ora per me peccatore. Deo gratias.</explicit>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="4">
                     <locus>(fols. 149r–154v)</locus>
                     <title type="desc">Letter of spiritual direction concerning ideal qualities that spouses of Christ should strive to embody, qualities similar to those of ideal wives in the secular world.</title>
                     <note>The author is identified here only as a venerable and devout priest, and the text itself is not identified with further precision in the manuscript.</note>
                     <rubric>Incomincia vna diuota e vtele epistola de uno venerabile &amp; diuocto padre la qualle contien in se le conditione che debbeno auere quelle che sono vere spose di miser iesu cristo a similitudine delle spose mondane.</rubric>
                     <incipit>In cristo iesu diletissima figliuola e sorella figliuola dico per ettade sorella per religione. Extimando io voi volere essere tale verso il uestro dilecto sposo qualle gli huomeni del mondo se poteseno tutti uoriano hauere le sue done. Che chome sapeti cerchano quanto li siano possibille hauere done che habino tute queste sotoscripte condictione o piui di quele che posino. Et sel fuse in libertade di cadauna dona mondana di hauerle tute ogniuna se forceria di hauerle per trouare piu marito a suo modo. Et quando trouato lo hauese se forçeria di conseruarsi per eserli grata. La prima cosa he la beleça. La secunda he nobilita. Terço sapie<supplied>n</supplied>tia. Quarto richeçe. Quinto sanita. Sexto amor e fidelta.</incipit>
                     <explicit>et sapiando io voi hauer piui otio che mi apensare di tal cose. Non mi extendero piu oltra. Tanto piu che so per uui medema poreti ben largar queste sie condictione in ogni vestro proposito. Che anchora ho facto piu di quel pensaua quando come[n]çai ascriuere non haue ça tal animo ne so chome mi sia venuto. Se ho in parte satisfacto ri[n]gratio Dio. Se anche mancho chome mi penso pregoue me abiate per escusato. Deo gratias. Amen.</explicit>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="chart">
                        <support>Paper. <watermark>The watermarks, most clearly visible on fols. 48, 63, and 67, are among the features that indicate Venetian provenance. The design, an anchor within a circle, measuring about 45 mm in diameter, corresponds approximately to Briquet nos. 464–472, which are all Venetian.</watermark></support>
                        <extent>154 leaves <dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                              <height>199</height>
                              <width>137</width>
                           </dimensions>
                        </extent>
                        <foliation>Modern foliation.</foliation>
                        <collation>1–15<hi rend="superscript">10</hi>, 16<hi rend="superscript">10</hi> (lacks leaves 5–10, cut away)</collation>
                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout columns="1" writtenLines="24">All texts are written in a single column, with a consistent practice of ruling and writing twenty-four lines per folio throughout the compilation; written area <dimensions type="ruled" unit="mm">
                              <height>141</height>
                              <width>87</width>
                           </dimensions>
                        </layout>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc>
                     <handNote script="textualisSouthern">The script throughout is a clear <foreign rend="italic">littera textualis</foreign> that appears to date to circa 1400 (based on assessments by Albinia de la Mare and Sabina Magrini); it displays certain forms influenced by humanist script, such as the d onciale and the distinctive shape of the letter g, but the duct appears to be gothic. The hand appears uniform throughout. </handNote>
                  </handDesc>
                  <decoDesc>
                     <decoNote type="rubrication">Titles and chapter headings are given in red.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="colInit">Some initials and paraphs in blue or red; in the text of the <title>Meditazioni</title>, there are also splashes of yellow over some capital letters.</decoNote>
                  </decoDesc>
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <binding notAfter="1800" notBefore="1700">
                        <p>The binding of plain white vellum-covered boards is eighteenth-century Italian, with what appear to be seventy-two paper stubs, some of them folded over and uncut, sewn, or pasted into the binding. These stubs appear to have been inserted as a block to fill out the cover and make it possible to use the original boards and spine after a sizable part of the original manuscript was removed.</p>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="1410" notBefore="1400">1400s</origDate>
                     <origPlace>
                        <country key="place_1000080">Italian</country>, likely made in or around <region key="place_7018159">Venice</region>
                     </origPlace> There are many indications that the volume was copied for Venetian nuns. This evidence includes the language of the Meditazioni, which evinces a Tuscan base text with a heavy overlay of Venetian dialect, the paper’s Venetian watermarks, the scribal assumption that the volume’s readers will be familiar with the nuns of the monastery of Sant’Alvise (fol. 127r), and the fact that the volume was later owned by Trevisan and Soranzo, both Venetians whose libraries included many volumes made in Venice. The contents of the epistole as well as the concluding colophon of the <title>Meditazioni</title> addressed to ‘sorelle’ (assuming that this colophon is scribal rather than authorial) appear to indicate that the volume was made for a community of nuns, rather than for one of the many recluses or <foreign rend="italic">pinzochere</foreign> living in Venice at the time or for a group of pious laywomen or widows living in community. </origin>
                  <provenance><persName key="person_39728066" role="fmo">Bernardo Trevisan (1652–1720)</persName>. In his catalogue (fol. 20v): <q>Meditazione della vita di nostro Signor Gesu Christo—ms. 1400. minato in 4º</q>. See J.B. Mitchell, <q>Trevisan and Soranzo: Some Canonici manuscripts from two eighteenth-century Venetian collections</q>, <title>Bodleian Library Record</title>, 8, no. 3 (1969): 125–35. On his death, his manuscripts passed to his brother:</provenance>
                  <provenance><persName key="person_3367151353525352720001" role="fmo">Francesco Trevisan (d. 1732)</persName>, priest; acquired after Francesco’s death by:</provenance>
                  <provenance><persName key="person_308770014" role="fmo">Giacomo Soranzo (1686–1761)</persName>. A number of features indicate that MS. Canon. Ital. 174 came from the Soranzo collection. These include the plain vellum eighteenth-century binding, the distinctive floral carta bassanese paper used for the pastedowns and flyleaves, and the eighteenth-century table of contents, which is written in the hand of Francesco Melchiori, one of Soranzo’s librarians. Melchiori’s table of contents lists a text which is no longer in the manuscript: <q>S. Antonini Archiepiscopi Florentini Interrogationis confessionale, seu theologia Moralis—vide tabulam premissam.</q> From this, it can be deduced that the material excised at a later date included the Summa theologica moralis by St Antoninus of Florence, O.P. (1389–1459). It appears, then, that Soranzo bound two quite different manuscripts together, one Italian and one Latin, and that Canonici separated them once he acquired Soranzo’s collection. The Summa and related texts of Antoninus that were once bound with the current contents of MS. Canon. Ital. 174 are now contained in MS. Canon. Misc. 135, preceded on fols. 1–3v by the ‘tabulam’ mentioned in Melchiori’s note. Acquired after his death by:</provenance>
                  <provenance notAfter="1805" notBefore="1727" resp="#MMM"><persName key="person_2384880" role="fmo">Matteo Luigi Canonici, 1727–1805</persName></provenance>
                  <provenance notAfter="1807" resp="#MMM"><persName key="person_446" role="fmo">Giuseppe Canonici (–1807)</persName></provenance>
                  <acquisition resp="#MMM" when="1817">Purchased by the Bodleian in 1817.</acquisition>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>Description by Sarah McNamer, <q><ref target="https://doi.org/10.2307/j.ctvpg84z2.9">The Manuscript</ref></q>, in <title>Meditations on the Life of Christ: The Short Italian Text</title> (Notre Dame, 2018), pp. cxlix–clvi; adapted by Andrew Dunning (2021). Previously described in the Quarto Catalogue (A. Mortara, <title>Catalogo dei manoscritti italiani che sotto la denominazione di Codici Canoniciani Italici si conservano nella Biblioteca Bodleiana a Oxford</title>, Quarto Catalogues XI, 1864). <listBibl>
                              <bibl facs="acp0106.gif" type="QUARTO">Quarto Catalogue, cols. 179–80</bibl>
                              <bibl facs="aaz0435.gif" type="SC">Summary Catalogue, vol. 4, p. 416</bibl>
                           </listBibl>
                        </source>
                     </recordHist>
                  </adminInfo>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2022-01-05"><persName>Andrew Dunning</persName> Convert description by Sarah McNamer.</change>
         <change when="2018-10-14" xml:id="MMM"><persName>Mitch Fraas</persName> Provenance and acquisition information added using <ref target="https://github.com/littlegustv/oxfordupdates/blob/master/test_case_for_oxford_prov.rb">https://github.com/littlegustv/oxfordupdates/blob/master/test_case_for_oxford_prov.rb</ref> in collaboration with the <ref target="http://mappingmanuscriptmigrations.org/">Mapping Manuscript Migrations</ref> project.</change>
         <change when="2017-07-01">First online publication.</change>
         <change when="2017-05-25"><persName>James Cummings</persName> Up-converted the markup using <ref target="https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl">https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl</ref></change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>