<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xml:id="manuscript_2535" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>MS. Canon. Ital. 100</title>
            <title type="collection">MSS. Canon. Ital. (Canonici Italian)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Description</resp>
               <persName>Vincent Leung</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Revision and encoding</resp>
               <persName>Andrew Dunning</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </publisher>
            <idno type="msID">MS_Canon_Ital_100</idno>
            <idno type="collection">Canon_Ital</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="MS_Canon_Ital_100" xml:lang="en">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <region type="county">Oxfordshire</region>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <institution>University of Oxford</institution>
                  <repository>Bodleian Library</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">MS. Canon. Ital. 100</idno>
                  <idno type="ieArk">ark:29072/x0sf268451wg</idno>
                  <idno type="crArk">ark:29072/x0dz010q43nh</idno>
                  <altIdentifier type="internal">
                     <idno type="SCN">20152</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
               <head>Commentaries on Dante, <title>Divine Comedy</title> by Benvenuto Rambaldi da Imola and others</head>
               <msContents>
                  <textLang mainLang="it" otherLangs="la">Italian and Latin</textLang>
                  <msItem>
                     <locus>(fols 1r–109r)</locus>
                     <title type="desc">Commentary on Dante’s <title>Inferno</title></title>
                     <textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>
                     <rubric><locus>(fol. 1r)</locus> Compendiu<ex>m</ex> Cuiusdam Co<ex>m</ex>mentarij sup<ex>er</ex> dante alhig|rio editi</rubric>
                     <incipit>Nel megio del Cammin de n<ex>ost</ex>ra vita</incipit>
                     <explicit defective="true"><locus>(fol. 109r)</locus> H<hi rend="underline">ora Cen porta lun di duri margini.</hi></explicit>
                     <note>Covers <title>Inferno</title> up to the end of Canto XIV.</note>
                     <note>First identified by Batines (1846, entry at p. 352) and Mortara (1864, entry at pg. 116). Bellomo (2004, entry at p. 148) was the first to posit an authorial attribution to Benvenuto Rambaldi da Imola. Boccini (2011, entry at pp. 915–916) agrees with this attribution. This attribution to Benvenuto seems unfounded on the basis of a close textual comparison with the third redaction of his commentary: cfr. Benvenuto Rambaldi da Imola, <title>Benvenuti de Rambaldis de Imola Comentum super Dantis Aldigherij Comoediam</title>, 5 tomes, ed. by J. P. Lacaita (Florence: G. Barbèra, 1887). The content of the commentary closes corresponds to the Landino vernacular commentary of 1481: cfr. C. Landino, <title>Commento di Cristophoro Landini Fiorentino Sopra la Comedia di Danthe Alighieri Poeta Fiorentino</title> (Florence: Nicholo di Lorenzo della Magna, 1481).</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem>
                     <locus>(fol. 109v)</locus>
                     <note>Blank.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem>
                     <locus>(fols 110r–122r)</locus>
                     <author key="person_69731706">Benvenuto da Imola</author>
                     <title type="desc" key="work_6691">Commentary on Dante’s <title>Inferno</title></title>
                     <textLang mainLang="it">Italian</textLang>
                     <note>Commences from the forty-third verse of <title>Inferno</title> I:</note>
                     <incipit><locus>(fol. 110r)</locus>
                        <hi rend="underline">Lhora del tempo e la dolce stagione</hi></incipit>
                     <note>Partial commentary of <title>Inferno</title> I vv. 43–136 taken from Benvenuto <locus>(fols 110r–112v)</locus>; abbreviated <foreign>proemio</foreign> and commentary on <title>Inferno</title> II taken from Benvenuto <locus>(fols 112v–115r)</locus>; abbreviated <foreign>proemio</foreign> and partial commentary of <title>Inferno</title> III vv. 1–9 taken from Benvenuto <locus>(fols 115r–115v)</locus>; structural announcements of <title>Inferno</title> IV–XXXIV translated and abbreviated from the proemial sections of Benvenuto’s commentary <locus>(fols 116r–122r)</locus>. Boccini does not note these textual lacunae and incorrectly categorises the present section as a commentary on the totality of <title>Inferno</title> starting from Canto I, verse 43.</note>
                     <note>Batines makes no note of the start of this second section. Mortara labels it as the incipit of a Chiose section comprising commentaries on <title>Inferno</title> and <title>Purgatorio</title> (see item 5); moreover, he incorrectly lists the first folio of the section as fol. 109. Bellomo and Boccini make no authorial attribution, and the former does not acknowledge the presence of the section at all.</note>
                     <note>Comparison with the nineteenth cento. Lacaita’s edition reveals that the text of the section is, in effect, a precisely translated abbreviation of Benvenuto’s Latin commentary. Textual comparison with the sole published vernacular translation of Benvenuto’s commentary reveals differing manuscript sources: cfr. <title>Benvenuto Rambaldi da Imola illustrato nella vita e nelle opere, e di lui commento latino sulla <q>Divina Commedia</q> di Dante Allighieri voltato in italiano dall’avvocato Giovanni Tamburini</title>, 3 vols., ed. by G. Tamburini (Imola, 1855–1856), I [see tomes II and III for <title>Purgatorio</title> and <title>Paradiso</title>].</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem>
                     <locus>(fols 122v–125<hi rend="superscript">a</hi>v)</locus>
                     <note>Blank.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem>
                     <locus>(fols 125<hi rend="superscript">b</hi>r–196r)</locus>
                     <author key="person_69731706">Benvenuto da Imola</author>
                     <title type="desc" key="work_6691">Commentary on Dante’s <title>Inferno</title></title>
                     <textLang mainLang="it">Italian</textLang>
                     <note>Commences from the eighth verse of Canto III:</note>
                     <incipit><locus>(fol. 125<hi rend="superscript">b</hi>r)</locus> In・3º・C・Inferni | Per me ssva. Ibi, <hi rend="underline">se no<ex>n</ex> et<ex>er</ex>ne e Io et<ex>er</ex>no duro</hi></incipit>
                     <note>Subsequently skips two tercets to verse sixteen.</note>
                     <note>This work can be considered a continuation of the partial commentary of <title>Inferno</title> III in the preceding section <locus>(fol. 115v)</locus>. The section again adopts the <foreign>proemio</foreign>-commentary structure starting from fol. 189v (Canto XXX). The commentaries to Cantos XXX <locus>(fol. 189v)</locus> and XXXI <locus>(fol. 192v)</locus> are incomplete, the former terminating at verse 129, the latter at verse 139. Subsequently, for the remainder of the section starting from fol. 195v (canto XXXII), the structural announcements taken from Benvenuto’s <foreign>proemi</foreign> replace the commentaries altogether. In this regard, the final two pages of Section 2 <locus>(fols 121v–122r)</locus> are nearly identical to those of the present section <locus>(fols 195v–196r)</locus>. Boccini does not note these textual lacunae and incorrectly categorises the present section as a complete commentary on <title>Inferno</title> Cantos III–XXXIV.</note>
                     <note>Batines makes no note of the start of this third section. Mortara places it within a greater Chiose section comprising commentaries on <title>Inferno</title> and <title>Purgatorio</title> (see item 5). As with Section 2, Bellomo and Boccini make no authorial attribution, and the former does not acknowledge the presence of the section at all.</note>
                     <note>Comparison with Lacaita’s edition reveals that the text of the section is, in effect, a precisely translated abbreviation of Benvenuto’s Latin commentary. The commentaries preceding Canto XXX <locus>(fol. 189v)</locus> are notably more abbreviated and edited than those of the latter part of the section.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem>
                     <locus>(fol. 196v)</locus>
                     <note>Blank, save for a catchword.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem>
                     <locus>(fols 197r–206<hi rend="superscript">a</hi>r)</locus>
                     <title type="desc" key="work_11192">Commentary on Dante’s <title>Inferno</title></title>
                     <textLang mainLang="it">Italian</textLang>
                     <note>Commences from the incipit of <title>Inferno</title> XXXII:</note>
                     <incipit><locus>(fol. 197r)</locus>
                        <hi rend="underline">Se io havesse le rime asspre e chioccie.</hi></incipit>
                     <note>Features complete commentaries of Cantos XXXII–XXXIV. Can be considered a continuation of the above, and in effect the final part of a four-section unit constituting a complete commentary on the <title>Inferno</title>.</note>
                     <note>Batines makes no note of the start of this fourth section. Mortara places it within a greater Chiose section comprising commentaries on <title>Inferno</title> and <title>Purgatorio</title>. Bellomo and Boccini make no authorial attribution, and the former does not acknowledge the presence of the section at all.</note>
                     <note>Whilst the cantos treated within the present section reveal a structural continuity between it and the preceding section, it does not seem to be the same commentary as previously and the model of Benvenuto has been left behind for another. Comparison with Lacaita’s edition and other known commentaries suggests that the commentaries of this section are not sourced from Benvenuto, nor any other known commentators for that matter.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem>
                     <locus>(fols 206<hi rend="superscript">a</hi>v–206<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>v)</locus>
                     <note>Blank.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem>
                     <locus>(fols 207r–326r)</locus>
                     <author key="person_69731706">Benvenuto da Imola</author>
                     <title type="desc" key="work_6691">Commentary on Dante’s <title>Purgatorio</title></title>
                     <textLang mainLang="it">Italian</textLang>
                     <note>Commences from the incipit of <title>Purgatorio</title> I: <q>Capitulu<ex>m</ex> p<ex>ri</ex>mu<ex>m</ex> purgatorij. | <hi rend="underline">Per correr migliore aqua</hi> [...]</q>. Features commentaries on all of the <foreign>cantica</foreign>; mostly complete save for in the following cantos: I (terminates at the end of verse 123); II (terminates at the end of verse 123); XII (terminates at the end of verse 127); XIV (terminates at the end of verse 144); XVIII (terminates at the end of verse 140); XX (terminates at the end of verse 140); XXI (terminates at the end of verse 116); XXIII (terminates at the end of line 117); XXXI (terminates at the end of verse 140); XXXIII (terminates at the end of verse 136). Boccini does not note these textual lacunae and incorrectly categorises the present section as a commentary on the totality of <title>Purgatorio.</title></note>
                     <note>Batines makes no note of the start of this fifth section. Mortara places it within a greater Chiose section comprising commentaries on <title>Inferno</title> and <title>Purgatorio</title>. As with the two preceding sections, Bellomo and Boccini make no authorial attribution, and the former does not acknowledge the presence of the section at all.</note>
                     <note>Comparison with Lacaita’s edition reveals that the text of the section is, in effect, a precisely translated abbreviation of Benvenuto’s Latin commentary (with <foreign>proemi</foreign>).</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem>
                     <locus>(fol. 326v)</locus>
                     <note>Blank.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem>
                     <locus>(fols 327r–493r)</locus>
                     <author key="person_69731706">Benvenuto da Imola</author>
                     <title type="desc" key="work_1003">Commentary on Dante’s <title>Paradiso</title></title>
                     <textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>
                     <note>Commences from the incipit of <title>Paradiso</title> I:</note>
                     <incipit>(fol. 327r) Primu<ex>m</ex>・c<ex>apitulu</ex>m・paradisi. | La gloria de Colui che tutto move</incipit>
                     <note>Features commentaries on all of <title>Paradiso</title>, mostly complete save for in the following cantos: III (terminates at the end of verse 126); V (terminates at the end of verse 129); VI (terminates at the end of verse 138); IX (top half of fol. 374r has been left blank for verses 103–105, save for the first two words of verse 103: <q><hi rend="underline">Non pero.</hi></q> Commentary recommences from verse 106 at the bottom half of the same folio); XV (terminates at the end of verse 144. Additionally there are five leaves from fols 406<hi rend="superscript">a</hi>r–407v [interrupting the continuation of commentary between verses 100–101], mostly blank save for an unintelligible inscription at the top of fol. 406<hi rend="superscript">a</hi>r; XX (terminates at the end of verse 144); XXI (terminates at the end of verse 132); XXII (terminates at the end of verse 153); XXIV (terminates at the end of verse 150); XXVIII (no commentary on verses 28–39; section at the bottom of fol. 467v left blank, save for a catchword for the incipit of verse 40. Verses 40 to the end recommence from the top of the following folio, 468r; XXXI (terminates at the end of verse 139); XXXII (no commentary between verses 44–84 [fols 488<hi rend="superscript">a</hi>r–488<hi rend="superscript">a</hi>v left blank for this section]. The commentary recommences from verse 85 at the top of fol. 488<hi rend="superscript">b</hi>); XXXII (terminates at the end of verse 149). Boccini does not note these textual lacunae and incorrectly categorises the present section as a commentary on the totality of <title>Paradiso</title>.</note>
                     <note>Batines makes no note of the start of this final section. Mortara incorrectly marks the first leaf of this section as fol. 330. Mortara, Bellomo, and Boccini catalogue the section as a Latin commentary on Dante’s <title>Paradiso</title>, the latter two correctly attributing the text as taken from the commentary of Benvenuto Rambaldi da Imola.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem>
                     <locus>(fol. 493v)</locus>
                     <note>Blank.</note>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="chart">
                        <support>paper</support>
                        <extent>
                           <measure>ii + 502 + v leaves</measure>
                           <dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                              <height>210</height>
                              <width>145</width>
                           </dimensions>
                        </extent>
                        <foliation>Modern foliation, i, ii, 1–493, i–v, with omissions emended to fols 125<hi rend="superscript">a</hi>–125<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>, 206<hi rend="superscript">a</hi>–206<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>, 406<hi rend="superscript">a</hi>–406<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>, 488<hi rend="superscript">a</hi>–488<hi rend="superscript">b</hi>.</foliation>
                        <collation>i<hi rend="superscript">2+10</hi> (fols i–ii, 1–10) | ii–ix<hi rend="superscript">12</hi> (fols 11–106) | x–xi5<hi rend="superscript">6+3</hi> (fols 107–125<hi rend="superscript">a</hi>) | xii<hi rend="superscript">8</hi> (fols 125<hi rend="superscript">b</hi>–130) | xiii<hi rend="superscript">12</hi> (fols 131–142) | xiv<hi rend="superscript">10</hi> (fols 143–152) | xv<hi rend="superscript">8</hi> (fols 153–160) | xvi<hi rend="superscript">12</hi> (fols 161–172) | xvii–xviii<hi rend="superscript">10</hi> (fols 173–192) | xix<hi rend="superscript">4</hi> (fols 193–196) | xx<hi rend="superscript">8</hi> (fols 197–204) | xxi<hi rend="superscript">4</hi> (fols 205–206<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>) | xxii–xliv<hi rend="superscript">12</hi> (fols 207–479) | xlv<hi rend="superscript">12+8</hi> (fols 480–493+v). <catchwords>Catchwords throughout.</catchwords></collation>
                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout columns="1" writtenLines="24 37">Unruled paper; single column throughout; space for 24–37 lines varying considerably by section and folio. <dimensions type="ruled" unit="mm">
                              <height min="145" max="170">145–170</height>
                              <width max="115" min="95">95–115</width>
                           </dimensions>
                        </layout>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc>
                     <handNote script="cursiva">One cursive hand with frequently changing orthographic conventions (cf. Boccini). Two sizes of script employed, one for primary text, and a slightly larger one for initial letters.</handNote>
                  </handDesc>
                  <decoDesc>
                     <decoNote type="diagram">A circle symmetrically divided in half by a vertical line, each semicircle containing a small unintelligible word written vertically at their polar end (left margin of fol. 130v).</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="plainInit">Plain raised script majuscule initial letters employed throughout for the first word of the opening verse of each canto.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="other">Quotations from the <title>Comedy</title>, quoted in the vernacular, are underlined.</decoNote>
                  </decoDesc>
                  <additions>
                     <p>Marginalia, unaffected by trimming, appear infrequently throughout the volume; sections 2 and 4 contain no marginalia at all. These can be divided into four functional categories: textual (e.g. fol. 6v), devotional (e.g. fol. 17r, written vertically in the centre of the right margin: <q>J<ex>e</ex>h<ex>su</ex>s Quoniam tu domine</q>), organisational (e.g. fol. 283v features seven of the nine classical poets named within the passage in the left margin beside their respective verses), and illustrative (fol. 130v).</p>
                     <p>There are multiple occasions in which the scribe has set a given space aside for commentary which was ultimately left incomplete (see item 6).</p>
                  </additions>
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <binding notAfter="1799" notBefore="1700">
                        <p>Brown tanned leather, 18th century. Binding cord slightly visible on the exterior of the front and back covers. Two floral paper endleaves (fols i verso–ii recto and back fols. iv recto–v recto).</p>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="1519" notBefore="1500">1500s or 1510s</origDate>
                     <origPlace>
                        <country key="place_1000080">Italy</country>
                     </origPlace>
                     <p>Dating from Bellomo and Boccini; Mortara considered the manuscript to be of the late fifteenth century.</p>
                  </origin>
                  <provenance notAfter="1805" notBefore="1727" resp="#MMM"><persName key="person_2384880" role="fmo">Matteo Luigi Canonici (1727–1805)</persName>.</provenance>
                  <provenance notAfter="1807" resp="#MMM"><persName key="person_446" role="fmo">Giuseppe Canonici (d. 1807)</persName>.</provenance>
                  <acquisition resp="#MMM" when="1817">Purchased by the Bodleian in 1817.</acquisition>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>Description by Vincent Leung (June 2023), edited by Andrew Dunning (July 2024). Previously described in A. Mortara, <title>Catalogo dei manoscritti italiani che sotto la denominazione di Codici Canoniciani Italici si conservano nella Biblioteca Bodleiana a Oxford</title>, Quarto Catalogues XI, 1864. <listBibl>
                              <bibl facs="acp0074.gif" type="QUARTO">Quarto Catalogue, col. 116</bibl>
                              <bibl facs="aaz0432.gif" type="SC">Summary Catalogue, vol. 4, p. 413</bibl>
                           </listBibl>
                        </source>
                     </recordHist>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>C. Landino, <title>Commento di Cristophoro Landini Fiorentino Sopra la Comedia di Danthe Alighieri Poeta Fiorentino</title> (Florence: Nicholo di Lorenzo della Magna, 1481) [first edition print of Cristoforo Landino’s vernacular commentary; the text of this edition, bears high semantic correlation to the texts found in item 1].</bibl>
                     <bibl>C. de Batines, <title>Bibliografia dantesca; ossia, Catalogo delle edizioni, traduzioni, codici manoscritti e comenti della Divina commedia e delle opere minori di Dante: seguito dalla serie de' biografi di lui</title>, 2 vols (Prato, 1846), II, p. 352, no. XII.</bibl>
                     <bibl><title>Benvenuto Rambaldi da Imola illustrato nella vita e nelle opere, e di lui commento latino sulla <q>Divina Commedia</q> di Dante Allighieri voltato in italiano dall’avvocato Giovanni Tamburini</title>, 3 vols., ed. by G. Tamburini (Imola, 1855-1856) [for comparison; first published vernacular translation of Benvenuto’s commentary; its manuscript source—as Bellomo noted, an eighteenth century copy of MS Estense 467 (no. 11)— deviates considerably from the texts of the present MS and the Lacaita integral edition].</bibl>
                     <bibl>A. Mortara, <title>Catalogo dei manoscritti italiani che sotto la denominazione di Canonici Italici si conservano nella Biblioteca Bodleiana a Oxford</title> (Oxford, 1864), p. 116, no. 100.</bibl>
                     <bibl>W. D. Macray, <title>Annals of the Bodleian Library, Oxford, A. D. 1598-A. D. 1867</title> (Oxford, 1868), pp. 223-227 [on provenance].</bibl>
                     <bibl><title>Benvenuti de Rambaldis de Imola Comentum super Dantis Aldigherij Comoediam : nunc primum integre in lucen editum</title>, 5 tomes, ed. by J. P. Lacaita (Florence, 1887) [Latin integral edition of Benvenuto’s commentary and product of the commentary’s third redaction; the principal manuscript sources—noted by Bellomo as MSS Laurenziani 43. 1-3—bear high semantic correlation to the abbreviated texts found in items 2, 3, 5, &amp; 6].</bibl>
                     <bibl>I. Merolle, <title>L’Abate Matteo Luigi Canonici e la sua Biblioteca</title> (Rome &amp; Florence, 1958), especially pp. 53-56 [on provenance].</bibl>
                     <bibl>A. N. L. Munby, <title>Connoisseurs and Medieval Miniatures, 1750-1850</title> (Oxford, 1972), pp. 109-110 [on provenance].</bibl>
                     <bibl>G. H. Bumgardner, <q>An Antecedent of <q>Romeo and Juliet</q></q>, in <title>The Yale University Library Gazette</title>, vol. 49, no. 3, 1975, 268–276 &lt;www.jstor.org/stable/40858557&gt; [accessed 1 February 2020] (p. 268) [on provenance].</bibl>
                     <bibl>S. Bellomo, <q>Benvenuto da Imola</q>, in <title>Dizionario dei Commentatori Danteschi. L’esegesi della Commedia da Iacopo Alighieri a Nidobeato</title> (Florence, 2004), p. 148, no. 22.</bibl>
                     <bibl>F. Boccini, <q>Canoniciani Italiani 100</q>, in <title>Censimento dei Commenti danteschi. 2. I commenti di tradizione a stampa (dal 1477 al 2000) e altri di tradizione manoscritta posteriori al 1480</title>, 3 tomes, ed. by A. Mazzucchi &amp; E. Malato (Rome, 2011) II, pp. 915-916, no. 509.</bibl>
                     <bibl>T. F. Mayer, <title>The Correspondence of Reginald Pole: Volume 1 A Calendar, 1518–1546</title>, 5 vols (Oxford, 2017) I, p. 18 [on provenance].</bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2024-07-24"><persName>Andrew Dunning</persName> revised and encoded description by Vincent Leung.</change>
         <change when="2018-10-14" xml:id="MMM"><persName>Mitch Fraas</persName> Provenance and acquisition information added using <ref target="https://github.com/littlegustv/oxfordupdates/blob/master/test_case_for_oxford_prov.rb">https://github.com/littlegustv/oxfordupdates/blob/master/test_case_for_oxford_prov.rb</ref> in collaboration with the <ref target="http://mappingmanuscriptmigrations.org/">Mapping Manuscript Migrations</ref> project.</change>
         <change when="2017-07-01">First online publication.</change>
         <change when="2017-05-25"><persName>James Cummings</persName> Up-converted the markup using <ref target="https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl">https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl</ref></change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
