<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="manuscript_9906">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Dep. d. 1008</title>
            <title type="collection">Dep. (Deposited manuscripts)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Cataloguer</resp>
               <persName>S. Reynolds</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Abbreviation and encoding</resp>
               <persName>Matthew Holford</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </publisher>
            <idno type="msID">Dep_d_1008</idno>
            <idno type="collection">Dep</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="Dep_d_1008" xml:lang="en">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <region type="county">Oxfordshire</region>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <institution>University of Oxford</institution>
                  <repository>Bodleian Library</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">Dep. d. 1008</idno>
                  <idno type="ieArk">ark:29072/x0x346d496r8</idno>
                  <idno type="crArk">ark:29072/x0x633f1802b</idno>
                  <altIdentifier type="internal">
                     <idno type="SCN">Not in SC (late accession)</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
                  <altIdentifier type="former">
                     <idno type="former">Coughton Court MS. 3</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
               <head>Book of Hours in Latin and English (Use of Sarum); England, s. xv (second half)
                  and s. xvi </head>
               <msContents>
                  <msItem xml:id="Dep_d_1008-item1">
                     <title type="desc">Book of Hours, Use of Sarum, in Latin and English</title>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>fol. v verso</locus>
                        <note>Easter table in English for 1545-1580.</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="1r" to="6v">fols 1r-6v</locus>
                        <note>Calendar: standard Sarum calendar, with all Thomas of Canterbury’s
                           feasts erased (December feast, January Octave, July translation, and
                           Nativity), as are all ‘papa’ designations; does include Cuthburga
                           (Cuthburge virginis) in August (founder and abbess of double monastery at
                           Wimborne, Dorset), who is not in standard Sarum Calendar as printed in
                           <title>The Sarum Missal</title>, ed. J. Wickham Legg, Oxford 1916 </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="1">
                        <locus from="7r" to="14v">fols. 7r-14v</locus>
                        <note>[Fifteen Prayers on the Passion]: Quindecim orationes ad passionem
                           Christi. Domine Ihesu Christi, eterna dulcedo te ... Each prayer finishes
                           with rubric, ‘Pater Noster. Ave Maria’. <!--IDENTIFY, COULD BE THE 15 Oes OF
                           ST BRIDGET (a devotion probably of Brigittine origin and popular in
                           English MSS from the early fifteenth century. CHECK in secondary lit.]-->
                        </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="2">
                        <locus from="15r" to="16r">fols. 15r-16r</locus>
                        <note>[Meditations on the Cross] <!--[is this the Seven Requests to the
                           Saviour?, though there do appear to be only 6; CHECK Leroquais, LH, ii,
                           345,--> with the following incipits: Adoro te domine Ihesu Christe in cruce
                           pendentem et coronam spineam in capite portantem; Adoro te domine Ihesu
                           Christe in cruce vulneratum felle et aceto potatum; Adoro te domine Ihesu
                           Christe in sepulcro positum; Domine Ihesu Christe pastor bone iustos,
                           conserva; Domine ihesu Christe Rogo te propter illam maximam amaritudinem
                           passionis (with R', Adoramus te Christe et benedicimus tibi;
                           Benignissime domine Ihesu Christe respice super me. </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="3">
                        <locus from="16v" to="18r">fols. 16v-18r</locus>
                        <note>[Prayer of St. Bernardino<!-- (Franciscan, died 1446, canonised 1450,
                           refused 3 bishoprics-->]: Oracio sancti Bernardini. O bone Ihesu, o dulcis
                           Ihesu fili Marie virginis ple<supplied>na</supplied> misericordia et
                           veritatem <!--... EDITION? --></note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="4">
                        <locus from="18r" to="18r">fols. 18r</locus>
                        <note>Invocation to St. Appollonia, against toothache: Virgo Christ egregia
                           ... ne morbo vexamur dencium <!--(cf. Sarum Hours in Keble 47, with rubric:
                           pro dentibus)-->. </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="5">
                        <locus from="18v" to="18v">fols. 18v</locus>
                        <note>Prayer: Omnipotens sempiterne deus spes et corona omnibus <!--IS THERE A
                           GENERIC TITLE FOR THE FOLLOWING?? --></note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="6">
                        <locus from="19r" to="20r">fols. 19r-20r</locus>
                        <note>Prayer: These Prayers folowyne ought to be saide er ye departe oute of
                           youre chambre at youre first uprysynge. Auxiliatrix ///lis michi trinitas
                           sancta </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="7">
                        <locus from="20r" to="20r">fols. 20r</locus>
                        <note> Prayer: Wan thou goest first oute of thy hous blesse the sayenge
                           thus, Crux triumphalis domini nostri Ihesu Christi </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="8">
                        <locus from="20r" to="20v"> fol. 20r-v</locus><note> Prayer: Oracio. Deus qui tres magos orientales ...
                        </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="9">
                        <locus from="20v" to="20v">fol. 20v</locus>
                        <note>Prayer: Whan thou entrest to the chirche, saye thus: Domine in
                           multitudine misericordie tue </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="10">
                        <locus from="20v" to="21r">fols. 20v-21r</locus>
                        <note>Prayer: Whan thou takest holy water saye thus, Aqua benedicta sit
                           michi salus [read: salvus] et vita </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="11">
                        <locus from="21r" to="21r">fols. 21r</locus>
                        <note>Prayer: Whanne thou begynnest to praye, thus begynne knelynge,
                           Discendit a me maligni et scrutabor mandatum dei </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="12">
                        <locus from="21v" to="21v">fols. 21v</locus>
                        <note>Prayers: a) Oracio. O Bone Ihesue, tu novisti and b) Oracio. Ascendat
                           ad te domine deus oracio mea </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="13">
                        <locus from="22r" to="22r">fols. 22r</locus>
                        <note>Pater Noster, Ave Maria and Creed. </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="14">
                        <locus from="22v" to="22v">fols. 22v</locus>
                        <note>Prayer: Confiteor in tibi domine Ihesu Christe omnia peccata mea,
                           followed by a standard Sarum Litany </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="15">
                        <locus from="23r" to="23v"> fol. 23r-v</locus>
                        <note> Prayer: Suscipera domine domine deus omnipotens <!--(check against text
                           printed in Downside Review, 42 (1924) p. 184-5--></note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="16">
                        <locus from="24r" to="75r">fols. 24r-75r</locus>
                        <note>Hours of Virgin (Sarum Use): Hore beate Marie virginis. Domine labia
                           ... [fol. 39r, Lauds followed by Suffrages to Holy Spirit, Trinity,
                           Cross, Michael, John the Baptist, Peter and Paul, Andrew, John the
                           Evangelist, Luke, Stephen; on fols 42r-v, James of Compostella added in
                           another hand]; each Hour ends with meditations on the Passion, De
                           sancta cruce and De dolore virginis. </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="17">
                        <locus from="75r" to="77v">fols. 75r-77v</locus>
                        <note>Prayers on the Compassion of Mary: a) Oracio. Domine sancte Ihesu fili
                           dulcis virginis Marie qui pro nobis mortem in cruce tollerasti b) De
                           domina nostra. Salve regina misericordie c) Oracio. Omnipotens sempiterne
                           deus qui gloriose virginis d) De sancta Maria. Gaude virgo mater e)
                           Oracio. Deus qui beatissima virgine Maria in conceptu et partu
                           virginitate <!--(see Sutton and Visser-Fuchs, p. 47)--></note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="18">
                        <locus from="77v" to="79r">fols. 77v-79r</locus>
                        <note>Seven Joys of Mary: Septem gaudiis beate marie virginis. Gaude flore
                           virginale honoresque ... </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="19">
                        <locus from="79v" to="81v">fols. 79v-81v</locus>
                        <note>O intemerata, entitled De sancta Maria oracio (masculine form).
                        </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="20">
                        <locus from="81v" to="84v">fols. 81v-84v</locus>
                        <note>Obsecro te, entitled Ad Virginem Mariam (masculine form). </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="21">
                        <locus from="84v" to="89v">fols. 84v-89v</locus>
                        <note>Prayers with the following incipits: a) A. Stella celi extirpavit b)
                           Oratio. Deus misericordie, deus pietatis c) Alia [oratio]. Ave
                           sanctissimum et preciosissimum corpus d) Alia oratio. In presencia sacro
                           sancti corporis e) Oratio. Domine Ihesu Christe qui hanc sacratissimem
                           carem <!--(SO C-E AT LEAST ON THE BODY OF CHRIST, CHECK to see if a) and b)
                           also, if so, emend heading accordingly)--> f) De sancta trinitate. Sancta
                           trinitas vivus deus miserere nobis g) Deus qui superbis resistis h) Deus
                           qui liberasti Susannam de falso crimine i) Domine Ihesu Christi qui me
                           creasti j) Domine Ihesu Christi qui solus es sapiencia </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="22">
                        <locus from="89v" to="91v">fols. 89v-91v</locus>
                        <note>Prayers <!--?for Epiphany/on the Three Magi-->: In honore trium regnum. a)
                           T[read R]ex Iapsar, rex Melchior b) Deus illuminator omnium gentium c)
                           Oracio. Deus qui tres magos orientales. </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="23">
                        <locus from="92r" to="97r">fols. 92r-97r</locus>
                        <note>four prayers in English: a) O glorious Jesu, o mekest iesu; b) O the
                           most swetest spouse; c) Oracio ad sanctissima Trinitatem. O blessed
                           trinyte; d) O lorde god almyghty, all seynge <!--CHECK IMEV--> </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="24">
                        <locus from="97r" to="100r">fols. 97r-100r</locus>
                        <note>Mediation on the Body of Christ: Oracio ante ymaginem corporis
                           Christi. Conditor celi et terre <!--IS 1OOv BLANK?--> </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="25">
                        <locus from="101r" to="109r">fols. 101r-109r</locus>
                        <note>Seven Penitential Psalms<!--: IS THERE NO RUBRIC HERE? Domine
                           reminiscaris [Tob, 3, 3- this is the antiphon to the PP]: Shd be Domine
                           ne in furore tuo arguas me CHECK --></note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="26">
                        <locus from="109r" to="109v"> fol. 109r-v</locus><note>Fifteen Gradual Psalms (nos. 119-33)<!--. Quindecimi psalmi;
                           give incipits for each. CHECK THIS (see Meerseman, vol 2, p. 33:6--></note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="27">
                        <locus from="109v" to="109v">fols. 109v</locus>
                        <note>Prayer: Memento domine David et omnis mansuetudinis eius <!--(REFLECTION
                           ON THE PSALMS BASED IN BIOGR. READING??)--> </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="28">
                        <locus from="110v" to="113r">fols. 110v-113r</locus>
                        <note><!--further Psalm material NUMBERS PLEASE:--> a) Ecce quam bonum et quam
                           iocundum habitate fratres; b) Ecce nunc benedicite </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="29">
                        <locus from="113r" to="114v">fols. 113r-114v</locus>
                        <note>Prayers, each rubricated Oracio and with the following incipits <!--TRACE-->:
                           a) Deus cui proprium est miserare (sic) semper et parcere, suscipe
                           deprecationem nostram; b) Omnipotens sempiterne deus qui facis mirabilia
                           magna: c) Deus qui caritatis dona per gratiam; d) Deus a quo sancta
                           desideria recta consilia; e) Ineffabilem ?misteriam tuam ?quesumus domine
                           clementer; f) Fidelium deus omnium conditor et redemptor; g) Pietate tua
                           queris domine; h) Per horum omnium sanctorum angelorum </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="30">
                        <locus from="115r" to="116v">fols. 115r-116v</locus>
                        <note>Verses of St. Bernard <!--(Clairvaux, white friar in illumination)-->: Versus
                           sancti Bernardi. Illumina oculos meos ne unquam obdormiam in morte ; 
                           Peto domine Ihesu largire michi in amore tuo (see Leroquais, LH, I, p.
                           xxx and Searle, Fitzwilliam, p. 1)</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="31">
                        <locus from="116v" to="148v">fols. 116v-148v</locus>
                        <note>Office of the Dead, Use of Sarum: Vigilie mortuorum. Placebo. </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="32">
                        <locus from="148v" to="149r">fols. 148v-149r</locus>
                        <note>Prayers, rubricated Oracio and with the following incipits: a) Deus
                           cui proprium est misereri semper et parcare; b) Omnipotens sempiterne
                           deus; c) Deus cuius misericordie non est munerus; d) Inclina domine aurem
                           tuam ad preces nostras; e) Arimibus queris domine omnium fidelium
                           defunctorum </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="33">
                        <locus from="149v" to="163r">fols. 149v-163r</locus>
                        <note> ?Psalm extracts for use between All Souls and Easter: In
                           feriis inter festum animarum et pascha Ps. Extracts beginning: a) Voce
                           mea ad dominum clamavi; b) Retribue servo tuo; c) Legem pone michi domine
                           viam; d) Memor este verbi tui servo tuo; e) Porcio mea domine dixi
                           custodire legem tuam; f) Bonitatem fecisti cum servo tuo; g) Manus tue
                           domine fecerunt me; h) Defecit in salutare tuam anima mea; i) In eternum
                           domine verbum tuum; j) Quomodo dilexi legem tuam; k) Iniquos odio habui;
                           l) Feci iudicium et iustitciam; m) Miribilia testimonia; n) Iustus es
                           domine et rectum; o) Clamavi in toto corde; p) Vide humilitatem meam; q)
                           Principes presenti sunt; r) Appropinquet deprecatio mea in conspectu tuo;
                           s) Domine probasti me; followed by:</note>
                        <msItem n="1">
                           <note> Oracio. Tibi domine commendamus animam famuli tui; </note>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem n="2">
                           <note> Alia oracio. Avete omnes anime fideles quorum </note>
                        </msItem>
                     </msItem>

                     <msItem n="34">
                        <locus>fol. 163v</locus>
                        <note>Meditation in English on an image <!--[Arma Christi, ie instruments of the
                           Passion CHECK] -->no longer present in MS; To them that before this ymage of
                           pyte devoutely say. V. pater noster .V. Ave maria and a Credo pytously
                           beholdynge these armes of christes pass[ioun] </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="35">
                        <locus from="164r" to="173v">fols. 164r-173v</locus>
                        <note>acephalous text, starting ‘matris mee vite proiectus sum ex utero. De
                           ventris matris mee deus meus es tu ne discesseris a me ... with following
                           Psalm incipits starting on fol. 165v (eached marked Ps): a) Dominus regit
                           me et nichil michi deerit in loco pascue; b) Domini est terra et
                           plenitudo eius; c) Ad te domine levavi animam meam; d) Iudica me domine;
                           e) Dominus illuminacio mea <!--CHECK PS NUMBERS, IDENTIFY TEXT; COMMENDATIO
                           ANIMARUM, HOURS OF PASSION/HOLY CROSS Could the interrupted text in this
                           MS be the Commendatio animarum1 printed in the Manuale? (pp. 118-32, lots
                           of Psalm texts etc; check also Sarum Missal, ed. Wickham Legg, pp.
                           428-9--></note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="36">
                        <locus from="173v" to="177r">fols. 173v-177r</locus>
                        <note>Prayers: a) Oracio. Interveniat pro nobis domine Ihesu christe apud
                           tuam clemenciam; b) Oracio. Beati Iohannis apostoli tui et ewangeliste
                           [sic]; c) De sancta Maria. Sancta Maria regina celi et terre mater domini
                           nostri Ihesu Christi in sanctas ???? venerabilis manus; d) Oracio. Ave
                           benigne Ihesu gratia plenus misericordia tecum </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="37">
                        <locus from="177r" to="190r">fols. 177r-190r</locus>
                        <note>Psalter of St. Jerome <!--(compilation of Psalm verses for use of sick)-->;
                           Psalterium beati Iheronimi. Verba mea auribus percipe ... </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="38">
                        <locus from="190r" to="190r"> fol.190r</locus><note> Prayer: Oracio. Omnipotens sempiterne deus clemenciam tuam
                           suppliciter deprecor fol. 190v, blank </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="39">
                        <locus from="191r" to="193v">fols. 191r-193v</locus>
                        <note>Prayers in English and Latin: a) A devoute prayer. O my soverayne
                           lorde Jesu the veray sonne of allmyghty god and of the moost clene and
                           glorious virgyn Mary; b) Deus propicius est iiiio peccatori vel
                           peccatrici. I thanke the also with all my herte ... my moost gracious
                           lorde for the benefites <!--CHECK IMEV;--> c) Oracio. Deus in cuius manu sunt
                           corda regum; d) Oracio. Deus qui nos patrem et matrem honorare precepisti
                        </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="40">
                        <locus from="194r" to="195v">fols. 194r-195v</locus>
                        <note>Prayer of Bede on the Seven Words: Domine qui septem verba in ultimo
                           vite tue <!--(cp. Keble MS 47 (Sarum Hours), has this incipit and rubric,
                           Oracio venerabilis bede presbiteri he vii verbis cristi in cruce
                           pendentis, printed with comparable rubric in Horae Eboracensis, Surtees
                           Soc. cxxxii, 1920, p. 141 COMPARE; see also Leroquais, LH, p. 342; PL 94,
                           cols 561-2; Wilmart, ‘Le grand poème’, pp. 273-4--></note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="41">
                        <locus from="196r" to="201v"> fols. 196r-201v</locus><note> Prayer to the Trinity: Oracio devotissima ad sanctam
                           trinitatem. Adoro te sancta et individua trinitas ... O beata trinitas
                           benedicat te deus simplex et trine omnis spiritus angelicus et humanus;
                           dicens sine intercessione [read: cessatione????] Sanctus, Sanctus,
                           Sanctus, Dominus deus Sabaoth, Pleni sunt celi et terre gloria tua.
                           Osanna in excelsis. Amen. </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <textLang mainLang="la" otherLangs="enm">Latin and Middle English</textLang>

                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="perg">
                        <support>parchment</support>
                        <extent> v (medieval parchment) + 201 + i (medieval) leaves <dimensions
                              unit="mm" type="leaf">
                              <height>190</height>
                              <width>125</width>
                           </dimensions> </extent>
                        <foliation>Foliated inaccurately in modern pencil; folio numbers in this
                           description are one less than that written in the MS.</foliation>
                        <collation>iiii [flyleaves] + i [Easter table] + I(6) [Calendar; stub of
                           singleton for Easter table appears at the end of this quire]; thereafter
                           too tightly bound to collate, with no quire markings or catchwords. One
                           folio, once present between what are now fols 163v and 164r, containing
                           an image on the recto and text on the verso, has been excised. Fol. 1r,
                           the first page of the Calendar, is very worn and was clearly the front
                           cover for some time.</collation>

                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout writtenLines="18 19" rulingMedium="crayon" columns="1">Written space
                              <dimensions unit="mm" type="written">
                              <height>120</height>
                              <width>75</width>
                           </dimensions>; ruled in faded red crayon, 19 lines per page, but fols
                           92r-100r and 191r-201v (Hand 2 stints) have written space 120 x 70mm,
                           thicker lines of ruling in pink ink, 18 lines per page.</layout>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc>
                     <handNote>Hand 1, main text hand, fols 7r-91v and 101r-190r: gothic bookhand
                        with a slightly barbed aspect; second half, s. xv.</handNote>
                     <handNote> Hand 2, main texts on fols 92r-100r and 191r-201v, gothic bookhand
                        but in darker ink and with squarer aspect; possibly slightly later than Hand
                        1</handNote>
                     <handNote> Hand 3, Calendar, fol. 1r-6v, a good quality rounded Gothic bookhand
                        with some barbed seriphs.</handNote>
                     <handNote> Hand 4, writes in margins of fols 84v-85r, s. xv bastard secretary
                        of good quality</handNote>
                     <handNote> Hand 5, s. xvi hand writes Easter table. </handNote>
                  </handDesc>
                  <decoDesc>
                     <decoNote type="miniature">Full page miniatures with full acanthus and berry
                        borders in blue, red, green and brown. <list>
                           <item>fol. 7r, Christ in Judgement</item>
                           <item>fol. 24r (Matins), Annunciation</item>
                           <item> fol. 31v (Lauds), Visitation</item>
                           <item> fol. 47r (Prime) Nativity (incomplete)</item>
                           <item> fols. 52v (Terce), Annunciation to the Shepherds </item>
                           <item> fol. 56v (Sext), Adoration of the Magi</item>
                           <item> fol. 60v (None), Presentation in the Temple</item>
                           <item>fol. 64v (Vespers), Massacre of the Innocents</item>
                           <item> fol. 70v (Compline), Flight into Egypt</item>
                           <item> fol. 101r (Penitential Psalms), Last Judgement</item>
                           <item> fol. 116v (Office of the Dead), Christ raises Lazarus from the
                              dead</item>
                           <item> fol. 177r, (Psalter of St. Jerome), Jerome kneels before
                              Cross</item>
                        </list></decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="miniature">Other miniatures with borders, approx. 8 lines high: <list>
                           <item>fol. 15r (Meditations on the Cross), Three Crosses</item>
                           <item> fol. 16v (Prayer of St. Bernard), Christ Child</item>
                           <item> fol. 19r (Prayers), God the father supports crucified Christ.
                           </item>
                        </list> There follow seven images to accompany the Suffrage to the Holy
                        Cross at the end of each Hour (apart from Matins), taken from the Passion
                        cycle: <list>
                           <item> fol. 45r (Lauds), Arrest of Christ</item>
                           <item> fol. 51r (Prime), Christ before Pilate</item>
                           <item> fol. 55r (Terce), Crown of Thorns</item>
                           <item> fol. 59v (Sext), Christ carries the Cross</item>
                           <item> fol. 63r (None), Crucifixion</item>
                           <item> fol. 69r (Vespers), Deposition</item>
                           <item> fol. 74r (Compline), Entombment.</item>
                        </list><list>
                           <item> fol. 75v (Salve Regina), Christ Child in glory with Madonna</item>
                           <item> fol. 79v (O intemerata), Visitation? or Mary kneeling in prayer
                              with devout layperson</item>
                           <item> fol. 81v (Obsecro te), Pietà</item>
                           <item> fol. 88r (Prayer on the Trinity), Trinity</item>
                           <item> fol. 115r (Verses of St. Bernard), White friar (Bernard) kneeling
                              before Madonna and child.</item>
                        </list></decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="border">Borders: see above.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="decInit">Major initials of 6 lines, fols. 7r, 24r, 31v, 47,
                        52v, 56v, 60v, 64v, 70v, 101r, 116v, 177r. Minor initials of 2
                        lines.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="flourInit">Plain blue initials with red penwork.</decoNote>
                  </decoDesc>
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <binding notAfter="1600" notBefore="1500">
                        <p>16th century.</p>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="1450" notBefore="1400">15th century,
                        first half</origDate>
                     <origPlace>
                        <country key="place_7002445">England</country>
                     </origPlace>
                  </origin>
                  <provenance>Jacobi Sutton armiger, top edge, front inner, rear pastedown, s.xv/xvi
                     hand, liber Jacobi Sutton armigeri. JSutton (JS mingled to form a monogram) in
                     black and red ink, same inscription in faded black ink inside front board.
                     </provenance>
                  <provenance>Throckmorton family: pasted inside front board is the quartered arms with eagle and Sr.
                     <persName role="fmo" key="person_15">Robt. Throckmorton Bart.</persName> with ?Weston shelfmark, J3 No. 10. Recto of flyleaf v
                     has ‘Ex libri[s?] <persName role="fmo" key="person_1125">Dni. Rob. Throckmorton Baronetti.</persName> Biblioth:
                     Weston:’.</provenance>
                  <provenance>Offered for sale, Christie's, 20 Dec. 1972, as part of lots 204,
                     206-211, but withdrawn before the sale.</provenance>
                  <provenance>Sold to the National Trust in 1991.</provenance>
                  <acquisition when="2026">Deposited by the National Trust in 2026.</acquisition>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>Abbreviated from a draft description by Suzanne Reynolds. </source>
                     </recordHist>
                  </adminInfo>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2026-05">Record created.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
