<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="manuscript_469">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>MS. Auct. D. 4. 2</title>
            <title type="collection">MSS. Auct. D. (Auctarium D.)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp when="2013">Cataloguer</resp>
               <persName>Elizabeth Solopova</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp when="2024">Encoding</resp>
               <persName>Matthew Holford</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </publisher>
            <idno type="msID">MS_Auct_D_4_2</idno>
            <idno type="collection">Auct D</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="MS_Auct_D_4_2" xml:lang="en">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <region type="county">Oxfordshire</region>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <institution>University of Oxford</institution>
                  <repository>Bodleian Library</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">MS. Auct. D. 4. 2</idno>
                  <idno type="ieArk">ark:29072/x0zp38wb89kt</idno>
                  <idno type="crArk">ark:29072/x0zk51vg0687</idno>
                  <altIdentifier type="internal">
                     <idno type="SCN">3055</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
               <head>Portable Psalter; Flanders, Bruges–Ghent area; 13th century, second half (perhaps 1276 or soon after)</head>
               <msContents>
                  <msItem class="#liturgica" n="1" xml:id="MS_Auct_D_4_2-item1">
                     <title key="work_14114" type="desc">Portable Psalter</title>

                     <note>[item 1 occupies quire I]</note>
                     <msItem n="1">
                        <locus>(fols. 4r–9v)</locus>
                        <note> Calendar (published and compared to the calendars of other psalters
                           from the Bruges–Ghent area by Carlvant, 1978, pp. 485–508), laid out one
                           month per page, written in red and black, approximately one-quarter full,
                           not graded. Includes saints venerated in Bruges: Walburga (1 May in red
                           and 4 August), Basil, patron of the chapel of St Basil and the Holy Blood
                           in Bruges (14 June) and the translation of Donatianus, patron saint of
                           Bruges (30 August). The feast of Donatianus (14 October) is omitted,
                           possibly as a result of confusion with Donatianus, martyr, entered on 24
                           May as ‘Donatiani archiepiscopi’ (Carlvant, 1978, p. 413). Other saints
                           include Amand (6 February), Egidius (1 September), Lambert, bishop of
                           Liège (17 September), Leodegar of Autun (2 October), Eligius (1 December)
                           and Medard (8 June). The calendar also includes Francis (4 October),
                           Catherine in red (25 November), Martin in red (11 November) and his
                           translation (4 July), Nicholas in red (6 December) and his translation (9
                           May) and Lawrence in red (10 August). There is a 14th-century addition at
                           22 October: ‘Hic Joras (?) [or ‘Ferat’ (?)] de Woseo (?)’. </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <note>[item 2
                        occupies quire II] </note>
                     <msItem n="2">
                        <locus>(fols. 10v–15v)</locus>
                        <note> Full-page miniatures (see ‘Decoration’). Fol. 15v contains a
                           full-page Beatus-initial; fol. 15r is blank. </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <note>[items 3–6 occupy quires
                        III–XXVII] </note>
                     <msItem n="3">
                        <locus>(fols. 16r–183v)</locus>
                        <note> Psalms 1–150 (‘eatus vir’ omitted after historiated initial of psalm
                           1), written with each verse starting on a new line, without titles or
                           numbers. The psalms are in the biblical order; subdivisions within psalms
                           are not indicated, apart from psalm 118, subdivided into twenty-two
                           8-verse units. Punctuated throughout with punctus elevatus used to mark
                           metrum and minor pauses, and punctus used to mark the ends of verses.
                           There are textual divisions at psalms 26, 38, 51, 52, 68, 80, 97, 101 and
                           109 (see ‘Decoration’). </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="4">
                        <locus>(fols. 183v–193v)</locus>
                        <note> Weekly canticles, without titles: <list>
                              <item> (1) Confitebor tibi domine (Isaiah 12);</item>
                              <item> (2) Ego dixi (Isaiah 38: 10–21);</item>
                              <item> (3) Exultauit cor meum (1 Samuel 2: 1–11);</item>
                              <item> (4) Cantemus domino (Exodus 15: 1–20);D (5) Domine audiui
                                 (Habakkuk 3);</item>
                              <item> (6) Audite celi (Deuteronomy 32: 1–44).</item>
                           </list>
                        </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="5">
                        <locus>(fols. 193v–200r)</locus>
                        <note> Daily canticles, prayers and creeds, without titles: <list>
                              <item> (1) Te deum laudamus (fol. 193v);</item>
                              <item> (2) Benedicite omnia opera (fol. 195r);</item>
                              <item> (3) Benedictus dominus deus (fol. 196r);</item>
                              <item> (4) Magnificat (fol. 196v);</item>
                              <item> (5) Nunc dimittis (fol. 197v);</item>
                              <item> (6) Athanasian Creed (Quicumque uult ...) (fol. 197v).</item>
                           </list>
                        </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="6">
                        <locus>(fols. 200r–203r)</locus>
                        <note> Litany, including saints venerated in the Bruges–Ghent and Tournai
                           regions: Martin, Eligius, Bavo, Trudo, Benedict, Remigius, Amand, Vedast,
                           Medard, Audomar, Winnoc, Lambert, Ansbertus and Amatus among the
                           confessors; Julitta (fourth) and Firmina (last) among the virgins. The
                           litany does not contain any of the major Bruges saints. Followed by eight
                           collects; the second (fol. 202v) mentions Innocent, probably Innocent V,
                           who was elected pope in January 1276 and died in June 1276. <list>
                              <item> (1) Omnipotens sempiterne deus dirige actus nostros in
                                 beneplacito tuo ...</item>
                              <item> (2) Deus omnium fidelium pastor et rector famulum tuum
                                 Innocentium quem pastorem ecclesie tue preesse uoluisti propicius
                                 respice ...</item>
                              <item> (3) Deus qui inter apostolicos sacerdotes famulos tuos
                                 ...</item>
                              <item> (4) Fidelium deus omnium conditor et redemptor animabus
                                 famulorum famularumque tuarum remissionem ...</item>
                              <item> (5) Absolue quesumus domine animas famulorum famularumque
                                 tuarum ab omni uinculo delictorum ...</item>
                              <item> (6) Deus qui salutis eterne beate marie uirginitate fecunda
                                 ...</item>
                              <item> (7) Ure igne sancti spiritus renes nostros ...</item>
                              <item> (8) Anime omnium fidelium defunctorum per misericordiam dei
                                 requiescant in pace.</item>
                           </list> Fols. 203–204v are blank. </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc><p><secFol> cum tremore <locus>(psalter, fol. 17r)</locus></secFol></p>
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="perg">
                        <support>parchment</support>
                        <extent>204 leaves
                           <dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                              <height quantity="148">c. 148</height>
                              <width>100</width>
                           </dimensions>
                           <note>(leaves were trimmed in rebinding, occasionally causing
                              the loss of decoration)</note>
                        </extent>
                        <foliation> modern, in pencil; 1–204.</foliation>
                        <collation> (fols. 1–3) I (4) first leaf is a pastedown | (fols. 4–9) II (6) | (fols. 10–15) III (6)
                              | (fols. 16–39) IV–VI (8) | (fols. 40–48) VII (8+1) fol. 40 is a singleton with a miniature
                              | (fols. 49–80) VIII–XI (8) | (fols. 81–89) XII (8+1) fol. 88 is a singleton with a miniature
                              | (fols. 90–97) XIII (8) | (fols. 98–103) XIV (6) no loss of text | (fols. 104–119)
                              XV–XVI (8) | (fols. 120–128) XVII (8+1) fol. 125 is a singleton with a miniature |
                              (fols. 129–136) XVIII (8) | (fols. 137–145) XIX (8+1) fol. 145 is a singleton with a
                              miniature | (fols. 146–201) XX–XXVI (8) | (fols. 202–204) XXVII–XXVIII (2) final
                              leaf of the last quire is the lower pastedown.
                              Inserted singletons containing miniatures have been excised after fols. 56, 72 and
                              107.</collation>
                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc><layout writtenLines="19" columns="1"> Ruled in plummet with double vertical and horizontal bounding lines, extending
                        the full height and width of page; 19 lines per page; written below the top line;
                        written space: <dimensions type="written" unit="mm"><height quantity="95">c. 95</height><width>65</width></dimensions></layout></layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc><handNote script="textualisNorthern" execution="formata">Formal Gothic book hand, black ink; according to Carlvant (1978, p. 371) similar
                     to Bruges, Bisschoppelijk Seminarie MS. 54/100, a breviary made for the use of
                     the Cistercian Abbey of Spermalie, Bruges, c. 1268–1270</handNote></handDesc>
                  <decoDesc>
                     <summary>Illuminated by an artist also responsible for the illumination in two
                        other contemporary psalters from the Bruges area, Dublin, Chester Beatty
                        Library MS. 61 and Darmstadt, Hessische Landes- und Hochschulbibliothek MS.
                        1211 (Carlvant, 1985). </summary>
                     <decoNote type="monogram">Gold KL monograms on blue and pink backgrounds in the
                        calendar.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="miniature"> Miniatures with the Labours of the Months, set in
                        architectural niches, against gold backgrounds: January: man with wings tied
                        to his head, standing next to the fire, drinking from a bowl, holding tap of
                        a barrel February: woman with a twisted candle by an altar March: man
                        pruning a tree with an axe April: man carrying flowering branches May: man
                        on horseback with a hawk June: man carrying a bundle of wood on his back
                        July: man mowing hay with a scythe August: man reaping grain September: man
                        cutting grapes; basket on the ground October: man sowing November: man
                        knocking down acorns for pigs December: man slaughtering a pig.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="miniature"> Five full-page prefatory miniatures forming a
                        Christological cycle that continues with further miniatures at textual
                        divisions in the psalter. The miniatures are in architectural frames, on
                        gold backgrounds, painted on one side of each leaf. <list>
                           <item>fol. 10v Annunciation, with Gabriel, lily-pot and the Virgin
                              holding a book, the dove at her ear.</item>
                           <item>fol. 11v Nativity; the Virgin asleep, holding a book.</item>
                           <item>fol. 12v Adoration of the Magi, the middle Magus pointing to the
                              star.</item>
                           <item>fol. 13v Flagellation.</item>
                           <item>fol. 14v Crucifixion, with Mary and John, the sun and moon.</item>
                        </list></decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="histInit">Four full-page miniatures (of an original seven, or
                        nine (?)) continuing the prefatory cycle, plus a full-page Beatus-initial
                        and nine further historiated initials, each 9 or 10 lines high, at textual
                        divisions. The initials depict saints (several of the same saints occur in
                        London, British Library, Burney MS. 345) on gold backgrounds, with full or
                        three-quarter borders made of gold, pink and blue bars, decorated with
                        grotesques, human heads, birds, coiled tendrils and foliage. The miniatures
                        are painted on single leaves and face historiated initials; those facing the
                        beginnings of psalms 38, 52 and 80 have been cut out, leaving stubs and
                        offsets (Carlvant, 1978). <list>
                           <item>fol. 15v Psalm 1 (initial B(eatus)) King David playing harp in the
                              upper part; David slaying Goliath in the lower part. Lower margin:
                              lovers in a garden; background with a chequered design.</item>
                           <item>fol. 40v (miniature) The Harrowing of Hell.</item>
                           <item>fol. 41r Psalm 26 (initial D(ominus)) Sts Peter with keys and Paul
                              with a sword, seated together.</item>
                           <item>fol. 57r Psalm 38 (initial D(ixi)) St Stephen stoned, dressed as a
                              cleric, with tonsure and maniple (?).</item>
                           <item>fol. 71v Psalm 51 (initial Q(vid)) St Lawrence on a grid, the hand
                              of God above, a small figure with bellows below; border extension with
                              a tonsured head.</item>
                           <item>fol. 72v Psalm 52 (initial D(ixit)) St Bartholomew flayed, the hand
                              of God above.</item>
                           <item>fol. 87v Psalm 68 (initial S(aluum)) St Margaret, holding a cross,
                              emerging from the back of a dragon.</item>
                           <item>fol. 88r (miniature) The Incredulity of St Thomas.</item>
                           <item>fol. 107v Psalm 80 (initial E(xultate)) St Martin on horseback,
                              cutting his cloak with a sword and giving half to a beggar.</item>
                           <item>fol. 124v Psalm 97 (initial C(antate)) John the Baptist beheaded; a
                              wading bird atop the initial.</item>
                           <item>fol. 125r (miniature) Pentecost (the Virgin in the centre, St Peter
                              with keys and a bearded disciple with a book to either side).</item>
                           <item>fol. 128r Psalm 101 (initial D(omine)) St Catherine (?) kneeling in
                              prayer; a man behind her raises sword over her head; another man
                              stands by, holding lance (compare MS. Douce 24 and see Oliver,
                              1985).</item>
                           <item>fol. 144v Psalm 109 (initial D(ixit)) Coronation of the
                              Virgin.</item>
                           <item>fol. 145r (miniature) Christ in Majesty, blessing and holding an
                              orb, surrounded by the symbols of the four evangelists (rectangular
                              non-architectural frame).</item>
                        </list></decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="decInit"> 3-line gold initials on pink and blue backgrounds,
                        decorated with white floral designs at the beginnings of psalms, canticles,
                        litany and prayers. Pages with 3-line initials have three-quarter borders
                        made of gold, pink and blue bars, decorated with white floral
                        designs.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="decInit">1-line gold initials at the beginnings of verses and
                        periods, placed on pink and blue borders in the right margin, decorated with
                        white floral designs.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="lineFill">Gold, and red and blue penwork
                        line-endings.</decoNote>
                  </decoDesc>
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <binding notAfter="1400" notBefore="1375">
                        <p> Wood boards, enclosed in silver, Flemish or French, late 14th century.
                           Silver panels, engraved with the Coronation of the Virgin (upper cover)
                           and Annunciation (lower cover), overlaid with transparent enamel. Both
                           panels are slightly damaged, with losses of enamel exposing the
                           underlying design on the silver. The panels are set in silver-gilt
                           borders with applied foliate scrolls. The border is fragmentary on the
                           lower cover. Four raised studs of silver with engraved flowers in four
                           corners on the upper cover, designed to prevent the cover touching the
                           surface when lying flat. Only two studs are still preserved on the lower
                           cover. The work of the atelier of the ‘Royal Gold Cup’ in the British
                           Museum, London (Pächt and Alexander, 1966–73). </p></binding><binding notAfter="1600" notBefore="1500"><p>Leather spine, 16th
                           century (?), with six raised bands, decorated with gilt floral designs.
                           Panels between the raised bands are framed with double gilt fillet lines.
                           Edges of wood boards, framing the spine, are covered with leather
                           decorated with gilt floral designs. Faded inscription on the second panel
                           from the top, possibly ‘P<supplied>salte</supplied>riv<ex>m</ex>’, with ‘66’ written over it in
                           ink. Printed paper label on spine with ‘D || 4. 2’. Fittings of two
                           clasps, now missing. Gilt gauffered edges of textblock. ‘66’ written in
                           ink on the fore-edge. </p>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="1300" notBefore="1250">13th century,
                        second half (perhaps 1276 or soon after)</origDate>
                     <origPlace cert="low">
                        <country key="place_7024097">Flemish</country>, <settlement key="place_7007867">Bruges</settlement>-<settlement key="place_7007887">Ghent</settlement> area</origPlace>
                  </origin>
                  <provenance>Made in the Bruges–Ghent area, possibly for a Bruges patron (evidence
                     of the calendar and decoration), in a workshop responsible for the production
                     of other luxury psalters (Carlvant, 1985). MS. Auct. D. 4. 2 has many
                     similarities in codicology, illumination and textual contents with other
                     contemporary psalters from the Bruges– Ghent area, such as MS. Douce 38
                     (‘Tweede Groep’, Carlvant, 1978, pp. 140–57). The simplicity of its calendar
                     and textual contents and the lack of agreement between the litany and the
                     calendar suggest that it was made for a lay patron. </provenance>
                  <provenance><persName key="person_3937">Joras de Woseo</persName> (?): 14th-century addition in the
                     calendar on 22 October. </provenance>
                  <provenance><persName role="fmo" key="person_37261411">Sir Robert Cotton (1571–1631)</persName>, see ODNB:
                     inscribed ‘Doctissimo Medico et amico Willio Butler Cantab. Robertus Cotton
                     Coningtoneus LL.MM. D. D. 1614’ (fol. 4r). </provenance>
                  <provenance><persName role="fmo" key="person_167824979">William Butler (1535–1618)</persName>, physician, fellow of
                     Clare College, Cambridge, see ODNB: presented in 1614 by Sir Robert Cotton (see
                     above). </provenance>
                  <provenance><persName key="person_3936" role="fmo">Dame Anne Sadleir (1585–1671/2)</persName>, literary patron,
                     wife of Ralph Sadleir of Standon, Hertfordshire, see ODNB. </provenance>
                  <acquisition when="1648">Bodleian Library: gift from Anne Sadleir, 1648 (‘Julij
                     15. 1648/ Liber Bibliothecæ Bodleyanæ ex dono nobilissimæ D. Annæ Sadler .
                     vxoris Radulphi Sadler de Stonden in Comitatu Harford Armigerj’ on fol. 3v).
                     The shelfmark ‘Auctarium’ was given c. 1789, when books then considered most
                     valuable in the Library were moved to the Auctarium (one of the schools in the
                     Bodleian Library quadrangle) (see Summary catalogue, vol. 1, pp. xiv,
                     xxxix–xl). Former shelfmarks: ‘= Selden cupbd. 111’ (upper pastedown); ‘Arch.
                     B. 66’ (fol. 1r). </acquisition>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>Elizabeth Solopova, <title>Latin Liturgical Psalters in the Bodleian
                              Library: A Select Catalogue</title> (Oxford, 2013), pp. 347–54.
                           Previously described in the Summary Catalogue. <listBibl>
                              <bibl facs="aap0600.gif" type="SC">Summary Catalogue, Vol. 2, part 1,
                                 p. 579</bibl>
                           </listBibl>
                        </source>
                     </recordHist>
                     <availability status="restricted">
                        <p>To ensure its preservation, access to this item is restricted, and
                           readers are asked to work from reproductions and published descriptions
                           as far as possible. If you wish to apply to see the original, please
                           click the request button above. When your request is received, you will
                           be asked to contact the relevant curator outlining the subject of your
                           research, the importance of this item to that research, and the resources
                           you have already consulted.</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <surrogates>
                     <bibl subtype="partial" type="digital-facsimile">
                        <ref target="https://digital.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/objects/b9d0c00a-7d5b-4b03-ae4d-e55623cc845a/">
                           <title>Digital Bodleian</title>
                        </ref>
                        <note>(33 images from 35mm slides)</note>
                     </bibl>
                  <bibl type="microfilm">Microfilm available in the open shelf collections in the Weston Library (R. Films 101)</bibl></surrogates>
                  <listBibl type="WRAPPER">
                     <listBibl type="PRINT">
                        <head>Printed descriptions:</head>
                        <bibl>S. J. P. van Dijk, <title>Latin Liturgical Manuscripts in the Bodleian
                              Library, Oxford, vol. 2: Office Books</title> (typescript, 1957),
                              <citedRange unit="page" from="92" to="92">p. 92</citedRange>
                        </bibl>
                     </listBibl>
                     <listBibl type="Solopova">
                        <head>Select other bibliography to 2009:</head>
                        <bibl>Macray, W. D., <title>Annals of the Bodleian Library, Oxford: with a
                              notice of the earlier library of the University, 2nd edn.</title>
                           (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1890; repr. Bodleian Library, 1984), p.
                           464.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Brassington, W. S., <title>Historic bindings in the Bodleian
                              Library</title> (London, 1891), plate IV.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Frere, no. 433.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Wormald, F., ‘The Fitzwarin Psalter and its allies’, JWCI VI
                              (1943), pp. 71–9, at p. 72; repr. in J. J. G. Alexander, T. J. Brown
                              and J. Gibbs (eds.), <title>Francis Wormald: collected writings</title>
                           (London: H. Miller; New York: OUP, 1984), vol. 2, Studies in English and
                           Continental art of the later Middle Ages, pp. 88–102.</bibl>
                        <bibl>van Dijk (1958), fol. 92.</bibl>
                        <bibl> Randall, L. M. C., <title>Images in the margins of Gothic
                              manuscripts</title> (Berkeley: University of California Press, 1966),
                           p. 40.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Pächt and Alexander (1966–73), vol. 1, no. 285, pls. XX–XXI.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Ragusa, I., ‘An illustrated psalter from Lyre Abbey’, <title>Speculum
                              46</title> (1971), pp. 267–81, at p. 278 n. 40.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Lane, B. G., ‘“Ecce panis angelorum”: the manger as altar in
                              Hugo’s Berlin Nativity’, <title>Art Bulletin 57</title> (1975), pp. 476–86,
                           at p. 480, fig. 10.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Carlvant (1978), pp. 411–13 and passim.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Carlvant, K. B. E., ‘Trends in Bruges illumination until 1260,
                              apropos a psalter connected with Oostkerke’, <title>Archives et bibliothèques
                              de Belgique 56</title> (1985), pp. 321–63, passim.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Oliver, J. H., ‘Medieval alphabet soup: reconstruction of a
                              Mosan psalter-hours in Philadelphia and Oxford and the cult of St
                              Catherine’, <title>Gesta</title> 24/2 (1985), pp. 129–40, at p. 139, n.
                           30.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Oliver (1988), vol. 1, pp. 79 n. 76, 165.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Tite, C. G. C., ‘“Lost or stolen or strayed”: a survey of
                              manuscripts formerly in the Cotton Library’, <title>British Library Journal
                              18</title> (1992), pp. 107–47, at p. 110.</bibl>
                        <bibl>——, <title>The manuscript library of Sir Robert Cotton</title>, Panizzi Lectures 1993
                           (London: British Library, 1994), p. 7 n. 7.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Bräm, A., <title>Das Andachtsbuch der Marie de Gavre: Paris, Bibliothèque
                           nationale, Ms. nouv. acq. fr. 16251. Buchmalerei in der Diözese Cambrai im letzten Viertel des 13.
                           Jahrhunderts</title> (Wiesbaden: L. Reichert, 1997), pp. 31, 65, 161.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Smeyers, M., <title>Flemish miniatures from the 8th to the mid-16th
                              century: the medieval world of parchmen</title>t, transl. by K. Bowen and D.
                              Imhof (Turnhout: Brepols, 1999), pp. 138, 172 n. 57.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Hunt, A., ‘The books, manuscripts and literary patronage of Mrs
                              Anne Sadleir (1585–1670)’ in V. E. Burke and J. Gibson (eds.), <title>Early
                              modern women’s manuscript writing: selected papers from the
                              Trinity/Trent Colloquium</title> (Aldershot: Ashgate, 2004), pp.
                           205–36, at p. 210.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Stones, A., ‘The full-page miniatures of the Psalter-Hours New York,
                           PML, MS. M. 729. Programme and patron’ in Büttner (2004), pp. 281–307, at pp. 299, 305,
                           307.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Bouché, A.-M., ‘The view from the roof: on the chimneys of the Morgan
                           Picture Bible’ in C. Hourihane (ed.), <title>Between the picture and the word: manuscript studies
                           from the Index of Christian Art</title>, Index of Christian Art Occasional Papers
                           8 (Princeton, NJ: Index of Christian Art, Dept. of Art and Archaeology,
                           Princeton University in association with Penn State Press, 2005),
                           pp. 24–50, at p. 34.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Morgan (2009), pp. 64, 70, 72 n. 9.</bibl>
                     </listBibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2024-02">Revised to incorporate full description from Solopova.</change>
         <change when="2022-04-04">Add binding information from Summary Catalogue.</change>
         <change when="2017-07-01">First online publication.</change>
         <change when="2017-05-25">
            <persName>James Cummings</persName> Up-converted the markup using <ref target="https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl">https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl</ref>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>