<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="manuscript_10027">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>MS. Lat. th. e. 59</title>
            <title type="collection">MSS. Lat. th. (Latin theology)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Cataloguer</resp>
               <orgName>Les Enluminures</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp when="2022">Encoding</resp>
               <persName>Matthew Holford</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </publisher>
            <idno type="msID">MS_Lat_th_e_59</idno>
            <idno type="collection">Lat_theol</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="MS_Lat_th_e_51" xml:lang="en">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <region type="county">Oxfordshire</region>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <institution>University of Oxford</institution>
                  <repository>Bodleian Library</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">MS. Lat. th. e. 59</idno>
                  <idno type="ieArk">ark:29072/x03t945r79xq</idno><idno type="crArk">ark:29072/x03r074v96m8</idno><altIdentifier type="internal">
                     <idno type="SCN">Not in SC (late accession)</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
               <head>Michael of Massa, Vita Christi; Germany, 1443</head>
               <msContents>
                  <msItem n="1" xml:id="MS_Lat_th_e_59-item1">
                     <author key="person_19444509"><supplied>Michael of Massa</supplied></author>
                     <title key="work_6749">Vita Christi</title>
                     <rubric>Incipit Vita lhesu Cristi. Prologus</rubric>
                     <incipit type="prologue">Fundamentum aliud nemo potest ponere preter id quod positum est quod est ihesus christus. Prima Chorinth. tercio. <note>[i.e. I Corinthians 3:11]</note> Cum sicut dicit Augustinus deus sit res sluime sufficiens et homo sit res summe deficiens</incipit> 
                     <rubric>De quibusdam incarnationem precedentibus <note>[first chapter]</note></rubric>
                     <rubric>Conclusio libri huius <note>[last chapter]</note></rubric>
                     <incipit>Habes ergo ex predictis vitam domini nostri ihesu christi</incipit>
                     <explicit>aut si corrumpuntur sanes</explicit>
                     <colophon>Deo gratias. Et sic est finis de quo deus est benedictus. Obsecro per christum te qui librum legis istum ut sis scriptoris memor in prece cordis et oris. Scriptus est iste liber per manus Iohannis Inder scholen aleas dictus Boickman. Et finitus Anno domini m<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> cccc<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> xliij in profesto vincula petri</colophon>
                     <note>Followed by several words in red, all but the first erased: "Orate ..." (f. 158v), the erased words were transcribed by 19th-century owners as "Pro meis liberis liberalissime" (ff. ii, 159)</note>
                     <textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="mixed">
                        <support>paper and parchment mixed, the inner and outer bifolia of each quire parchment, the rest paper, with perhaps three or four different watermarks, the only one of which is both clearly visible and distinctive is very close to <watermark>Briquet no. 4639</watermark>, dated 1438.</support>
                        <extent>i (modern paper) + I (medieval parchment) + 159 + i (modern paper) leaves
                           <dimensions unit="mm" type="leaf">
                              <height>210</height>
                              <width>145</width>
                           </dimensions>
                        </extent>
                        <foliation> i-ii, 1-160 in pencil</foliation>
                        <collation>i-xii(12), xiii(16-1), last leaf cancelled without loss of text), <catchwords>catchwords</catchwords> and <signatures type="quire">quire signatures in lower-case roman numerals</signatures> survive in most quires.</collation>
                        <condition>Worm-holes in the first and last leaves, most leaves cockled and stained by damp, the parchment leaves also shrunk smaller than the paper ones, rarely if ever preventing legibility of the text.</condition>
                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout columns="1" writtenLines="25 27">Typically on 25-27 long lines (justification: c. <dimensions unit="mm" type="ruled">
                           <height>145</height>
                           <width>105</width>
                        </dimensions>), frame ruled in plummet.</layout>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc>
                     <handNote script="cursiva">Written in brown ink in a semi-cursive gothic script by <persName role="scr" key="person_3661">Johannes Boikman</persName>.</handNote>
                  </handDesc>
                  <decoDesc><decoNote type="rubrication">Rubrics in red, numerous paraphs, underlinings, and marginal notes and pointing hands in red.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="colInit">Each chapter introduced by a three- or four-line initial in red.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="flourInit">The first initial six lines bigh with reserved foliate designs and penwork ornament.</decoNote></decoDesc>
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <binding notAfter="1925" notBefore="1900">
                        <p>Bound in brown leather and faux leather over pasteboards, probably early 20th century, with gilt spine title "Lebensgeschichte / Jesu Christi / Handschrift / von 1443′′ and with the binder's purple ink stamp on the lower pastedown "G<ex>eor</ex>g. Grob, Köln / Buchbinderei / Rotgerberbach 19".</p>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origDate calendar="Gregorian" when="1443" cert="high">1443</origDate>
                     <origPlace><country key="place_7000084">Germany</country></origPlace>
                  </origin>
                  <provenance>Signed and dated 31 July 1443 by the scribe Johannes Boikman, in an eight-line colophon immediately following the end of the text: "Deo gratias. Et sic est finis de quo deus est benedictus. Obsecro per christum te qui librum legis istum ut sis scriptoris memor in prece cordis et oris. Scriptus est iste liber per manus lohannis Inder scholen aleas dictus Boickman. Et finitus Anno domini m<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> cccc<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> xliij in profesto vincula petri", followed by several words in red, all but the first erased: "Orate ..." (f. 158v), the erased words were transcribed by 19th-century owners as "Pro meis liberis liberalissime" (ff. ii, 159). Boikman refers to himself as "in der scholen" ("in the schools"), which suggests that he was studying at university when he wrote the text; this is most likely to have been Cologne University.</provenance>
                  <provenance>The <orgName role="fmo" key="org_281">Augustinian nunnery of Marienberg, Neuss</orgName>, where it was inscribed in the 15th century, 
                     "Liber regularisaru<ex>m</ex> mo<ex>n</ex>tis ui<ex>r</ex>gine intra nussia<ex>m</ex>" (f. ii). Marienberg was founded in 1462 so this text, written by an Augustinian author, was doubtless acquired as one of their first indispensable books. The monastery was suppressed at the Secularization of 1802 </provenance>
                  <provenance><persName role="fmo" key="person_221015459">Johann Heinrich Küpper (1767-1836)</persName>, last rector of the Neuss grammar school, with a long 
                     inscription immediately beneath the Marienberg inscription, beginning "Gehort itzt Joh. Heinrich Küpper von Neuss" and ending with a transcription of the erased part of the colophon (f. ii'). A note on the back flyleaf, apparently copied from fol. ii' when it was more legible than it is today, refers to Küpper and includes the date 18 November 1826; this is quite possibly the date on which Küpper acquired it. In the years following the Seculariztion Küpper is known to have owned a number of manuscripts from Marienberg: identical Marienberg and Küpper inscriptions occur in the unique manuscript of Geert Grote's treatise Contra turriu Traiectorisem, for example. The present manuscript may have had a similar series of owners as the latter, which went after Heinrich Küpper's death to Sibylla Kamper-Küpper (d. 1851); to Josepha Schram-Kamper; to a series of members of the Schram family of Neuss. (On the Schram family and their manuscripts see Rosmarie Siepe, "Das Archiv Schram und die Familie Schram in Neuß," <title>Mitteilungen der Westdeutschen Gesellschaft für Familienkunde</title>, 27 (1975), pp. 47–51). The manuscript was still in the region of Cologne, perhaps in Neuss, when it received its present binding. Inscribed with former shelfmarks "H 3" (f. ii v) and "H 4" (f. i v, in blue pencil). </provenance>
                  <provenance>Les Enluminures, TM 373.</provenance>
                  <acquisition when="2010">Purchased by the Bodleian, 2010.</acquisition>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>Adapted from the dealer's description by Les Enluminures (<ref target="https://www.textmanuscripts.com/medieval/massa-vita-christi-60653">TM 373</ref>)</source>
                     </recordHist>
                  </adminInfo>
               </additional>
               <msPart type="fragment" xml:id="MS_Lat_th_e_59-endleaf">
                  <msIdentifier>
                     <altIdentifier>
                        <idno>MS. Lat. th. e. 59 - endleaf (fol. ii, former pastedown)</idno>
                     </altIdentifier>
                  </msIdentifier>
                  
                  <msContents>
                     <msItem>
                        <note>Unidentified: about 40 lines of partially legible text in German</note> 
                        <textLang mainLang="de">German</textLang>
                     </msItem>
                  </msContents>
                  <history>
                     <origin>
                        <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notBefore="1300" notAfter="1400">14th century</origDate>
                        <origPlace><country key="place_7000084">Germany</country></origPlace>
                     </origin>
                  </history>
               </msPart>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2022-10-31">Record created.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>