<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="manuscript_7777">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>MS. Lyell 45</title>
            <title type="collection">MSS. Lyell</title>
            <respStmt xml:id="MLH">
               <resp when="2018">Encoding and markup</resp>
               <persName>Matthew Holford</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="LYELL">
               <resp when="1971">Cataloguer</resp>
               <persName>A. de la Mare</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </publisher>
            <idno type="msID">MS_Lyell_45</idno>
            <idno type="collection">Lyell</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc resp="#LYELL" xml:id="MS_Lyell_45" xml:lang="en">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <region type="county">Oxfordshire</region>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <institution>University of Oxford</institution>
                  <repository>Bodleian Library</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">MS. Lyell 45</idno>
               <idno type="ieArk">ark:29072/x0v979v258cw</idno><idno type="crArk">ark:29072/x0v692t57524</idno></msIdentifier>
               <msContents>
                  <msItem class="#liturgica" n="1" xml:id="MS_Lyell_45-item1">
                     <title key="work_13367" type="desc">Missal, Use of Saint-Malo</title>
                     <bibl>Calendar and Temporale</bibl>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="1" to="6">(fols. 1–6)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Calendar</title>
                        <note>With one saint or more for almost every day. Feasts in red include: Vincent (22 Jan.), with octave; <q>Yvonis confessoris</q> (19 May); <q>Aaronis confessoris</q> (22 June); <q>Translacio sancti Martini episcopi</q> (4 July); <q>Translacio sancti Maclovii</q> (11 July); <q>Michaelis in Monte Gargano</q> (29 Sept.); <q>Michaelis in Monte Tumba</q> (16 Oct.); <q>Dedicatio ecclesie Macloviensis</q> (30 Oct.); <q>Maclovii episcopi et confessoris</q> (15 Nov.); Presentation of the Virgin (21 Nov.). Other local saints commemorated include all of those listed by Duine <title>Brev. et missels des eglises et abbayes bretonnes</title>, 1906, p. 79, in his description of the 15th cent. Saint-Malo missal at Rennes, with the exception of <q>Melorii mart.</q> (1 Oct.). <q>Martini abbatis</q> is put on 20 Dec. The inclusion of the feast of the Presentation of the Virgin suggests a date after 1430; see Duine, p. 69.</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="7">(fol. 7)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Temporale</title>
                        <note>From first Sunday in Advent to third Sunday after Pentecost, breaking off imperf. fol. 129v, in middle of the Gospel. The proses are generally the same as those listed by Misset and Weale, from the printed Saint-Malo missal of 1503, in <title>Anal. Liturg.</title> II, 2, Fasc. XII (1894), 391–2, but their nos. 13–14, 16–21, 23, 26–9 are omitted, and in our MS. the prose for the Christmas Mass <q>in aurora</q> (fol. 15) beg.: Sonent regi nato nova: <ref target="http://webserver.erwin-rauner.de/php_ancarm/ancarm_refwerke.php?opus=1003&amp;var=Chev&amp;nr_char=19215">Chevalier 19215</ref>. The prefaces (fol. 116), with square notation on staves of four red lines, and Canon of the Mass (fol. 123) are inserted after the proper for the Saturday after Pentecost, which ends fol. 115va, after which a column and a half are left blank, followed by a catchword, which gives the beginning of the preface for Christmas (not the rubric which actually precedes it). The Canon of the Mass ends (fol. 126ra) with the prayers: Quod ore sumpsimus..., Agimus tibi gratias, etc. Placeat tibi sancta trinitas, followed by the Gloria, with musical cues <q>De festis duplicibus</q>, <q>De beata Maria</q>, <q>De communi</q>. Ends fol. 126vb ; most of the column is left blank.</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="perg">
                        <support>parchment</support>
                        <extent> i + 132 leaves (fol. 13, 37, and 70 are double, fol. 119–20 one leaf, fol. i, 130 flyleaves) <dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                              <height>358</height>
                              <width>260</width>
                           </dimensions>
                           <dimensions type="written" unit="mm">
                              <height>203</height>
                              <width>145</width>
                           </dimensions>
                        </extent>
                        <foliation>Contemporary foliation in red roman numerals, probably by scribe, written in centre of upper margin of recto, does not include the Calendar or the present fol. 116–26.</foliation>
                        <collation>1 original flyleaf, 1⁶, 2⁸-14⁸, 15¹⁰, 16⁸ (2, 3, 6–8 missing), 1 original flyleaf; <catchwords>horizontal catchwords in inner margin, sometimes with decorative surrounds;</catchwords>
                           <secFol>spem habeamus</secFol></collation>
                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout columns="2" writtenLines="33">2 col. of 33 lines, ruled in ink.</layout>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc>
                     <handNote>Two sizes of liturgical text hand. Among the blue pen flourishes of an initial on fo1. 124v is written: <persName key="person_2847" role="scr">Galt(erus?)</persName> scripsit hunc librum <sic>missalle</sic>. In other initials the scribe has similarly written: Gault. (fol. 24v), Galt. (fol. 47, 48, 48v, 61) or simply G. (fol. 6, 10, 41v).</handNote>
                  </handDesc>
                  <musicNotation>
                     <p>Square notation on staves of four red lines.</p>
                  </musicNotation>
                  <decoDesc>
                     <decoNote>
                        <p>On fols. 7r, 122r, large painted initials in blue and pink on gold infilled with foliage, joined to bar borders decorated with acanthus leaves and hairline ink scrolling with painted daisies and other flowers, and small gold leaves and discs, extending into all the margins on fol. 122r, three sides only on fol. 7r. On fol. 123r, a large gold initial with pink and blue background, hairline scrolling, flowers, and gold leaves. Some similar smaller initials; a few others in gold flourished in red and blue; the rest are red or blue flourished in blue or red. (<ref target="https://catalog.hathitrust.org/Record/000468709">Pächt and Alexander</ref> i. 677)</p>
                     </decoNote>
                  </decoDesc>
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <binding when="1470">
                        <p>Binding of c. 1470 with bevelled wooden boards covered with calf, blind stamped with six concentric rectangles of small stamps. Four stamps are used: a crowned <q>M</q>, a fleur-de-lis (both repeated); a dog (?); an ermine in a lozenge. Two straps fastening to studs on lower cover probably added later. The spine (repaired) is crosshatched and also has the ermine stamp.</p>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
                  <accMat>The front pastedown and flyleaf (fol. i) are part of an erased document, made quite illegible by reagent. Some later notes on fol. i, also largely obliterated, are perhaps accounts.</accMat>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="1450" notBefore="1425">15th century, second quarter</origDate>
                     <origPlace>
                        <country key="place_1000070">French</country>, <region key="place_7024267">Brittany</region>
                        <!--ORIGINAL: French, Brittany-->
                     </origPlace>
                  </origin>
                  <provenance notBefore="1425">The MS. was probably written for the <orgName key="org_266852074" role="fmo">Cathedral of Saint-Malo</orgName>, which was dedicated to St. Vincent.</provenance>
                  <provenance>On fol. i verso (flyleaf) is written: Pro <persName key="person_2848" notAfter="1500" notBefore="1400" role="fmo">Magistro Guillelmo Garruargen</persName> (?) (15th cent.). A Dom. Guil1elmus de Garennes from the diocese of Le Mans was a bachelor at the University of Paris in 1455 (Samaran-Van Moé, <title>Auct. Chart. Univ. Paris.</title> v, 1942, col. 654).</provenance>
                  <provenance>Fo1. 1: <persName key="person_2849" role="fmo">Noveril Villegiller</persName> (?) (19th cent.).</provenance>
                  <provenance from="1938" to="1948">Bought by <persName key="person_64157046" role="fmo">Lyell</persName> from Davis and Orioli in May 1938 and said to have been brought direct from Paris.</provenance>
                  <acquisition when="1948">Chosen as one of the hundred manuscripts bequeathed to the library by Lyell in 1948.</acquisition>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>Adapted (2018) from A. de la Mare, <title>Catalogue of the Medieval Manuscripts Bequeathed to the Bodleian Library Oxford by James P. R. Lyell</title> (1971), pp. 124–5 <listBibl>
                              <bibl facs="cah0160.gif" type="LYELL">Catalogue, p. 124</bibl>
                              <bibl facs="cah0161.gif" type="LYELL">Catalogue, p. 125</bibl>
                           </listBibl>
                        </source>
                     </recordHist>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <surrogates>
                     <bibl subtype="partial" type="digital-facsimile">
                        <ref target="https://digital.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/objects/25b4ef2c-652d-452b-a3ed-5355f77f3567/">
                           <title>Digital Bodleian</title>
                        </ref>
                        <note>(1 image of binding from 35mm slides)</note>
                     </bibl>
                  </surrogates>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2017-07-01">First online publication.</change>
         <change when="2017-05-25"><persName>James Cummings</persName> Up-converted the markup using <ref target="https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl">https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl</ref></change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>