<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/msDesc/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/msDesc/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="manuscript_16144">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Lincoln College MS. Lat. 32</title>
            <title type="collection">Lincoln College MSS.</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp when="2026">Cataloguer</resp>
               <persName>James Willoughby</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp when="2026">Encoding</resp>
               <persName>Matthew Holford</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </publisher>
            <idno type="msID">Lincoln_College_MS_Lat_32</idno>
            <idno type="collection">Lincoln_College</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:lang="en" xml:id="Lincoln_College_MS_Lat_32">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <repository>Lincoln College</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">Lincoln College MS. Lat. 32</idno>
               <idno type="ieArk">ark:29072/b4t148ff44dg</idno><idno type="crArk">ark:29072/b4sx61dj613m</idno></msIdentifier>
               <head>Iohannes Boccaccius, <title>De casibus uirorum illustrium</title>, <title>De claris mulieribus</title>; France or Burgundy, s. xv<hi rend="superscript">2/4</hi></head>
               <msContents>
                  <textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>
                  <msItem>
                     <note>Fol. [i] is blank but for the early-modern library marks (see Labels and Marks) and Robert Flemming’s <foreign>ex dono</foreign> inscription on the verso in his own humanistic hand: ‘Collegio lincoln’ Oxon’ ex dono Magistri Roberti Flemmyng decani lincoln’’.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  
                  
                  <msItem n="1">
                     <locus from="1ra" to="115rb">(fols. 1ra–115rb)</locus>
                     <rubric>Incipit liber primus Iohannis Boc<lb/>cacii de <sic>cercaldo</sic> de Casibus virorum <lb/> illustrium  <lb/>  </rubric><incipit type="prol.">Diu stren<lb/>nue miles <lb/> emunctum <lb/> ex ingenio <lb/> meo opus<lb/>culum . in quo <lb/> virorum <lb/> illustrium <lb/> tractantur casus . et ut plurimum in<lb/>felices exitus me penes ociosum fuit <lb/> Non enim satis mecum . . . </incipit><explicit type="prol.">vt <lb/> ipse pro viribus celebre nomen tuum meum<lb/>que aliquali fulgore per ora virum discur<lb/>rens illustret. Vale.</explicit><finalRubric> Explicit prologus <lb/><lb/> </finalRubric><rubric>Incipit liber primus <lb/> </rubric><incipit>Exquirenti michi <lb/> quid ex labore stu<lb/>diorum meorum pos<lb/>sem forsan rei publice vtilita<lb/>tis addere . occur<lb/>rere preter creditum multa maiori tamen <lb/> ornatu in mentem sese ingessere prin<lb/>cipum atque presidencium quorumcunque obsce<lb/>ne libidines </incipit>
                     <explicit> sed <lb/> proteruia pocius fortune cuncta ver<lb/>tentis ¶ Tu autem parue liber longum <lb/> viue felixque insignis militis Maginar<lb/>di meique tenax nominis atque fame <lb/> Amen. <lb/><lb/> </explicit><finalRubric>Explicit liber Nonus et vltimus <lb/> Iohannis Boccacii de cercaldo de Casibus virorum Illustrium.</finalRubric>
                     <author key="person_64002165">Giovanni Boccaccio (1313–1375)</author>
                     <title key="work_1765">De casibus uirorum illustrium</title>
                     <listBibl><bibl>Ed. P. G. Ricci &amp; V. Zaccaria in <title>Tutte le opere di Giovanni Boccaccio</title>, ed. V. Branca (Milan 1964–98), 9. 2–871.</bibl></listBibl>
                     <note>The text ends on l. 21; the rest of the column and fol. 115v is blank.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  
                  
                  
                  <msItem n="2">
                     <locus from="116ra" to="174vb">(fols. 116ra–174vb)</locus>
                     <rubric>Incipit liber Iohannis Boccacii <lb/> de <sic>Cercaldo</sic> de Mulieribus claris <lb/></rubric><incipit type="prol.">Pridie, mu<lb/>lierum egre<lb/>gia, pau<lb/>lulum ab <lb/> inerti vul<lb/>go semo<lb/>tus et a <lb/> ceteris fere <lb/> solutus <lb/> curis in eximiam muliebris <lb/> sexus laudem ac amicorum so<lb/>lacium pocius quam in magnum <lb/> rei publice commodum libellum scripsi <lb/> Verum dum mecum animo versarem . . . </incipit><explicit type="prol.">presentibus cognitam faciet <lb/> et posteritati seruabit eternam. <lb/><lb/> </explicit><incipit type="text">(text) Scripsere iamdudum nonnulli ve<lb/>terum sub compendio de viris <lb/> illustribus libros et nostro euo, laciori <lb/> tamen volumine et accuratiori stilo <lb/> vir insignis et poeta egregius fran<lb/>ciscus petrarcha preceptor noster scribit <lb/> et digne. Nam qui ut <sic>ceteris</sic> anteirent <lb/> claris facinoribus . . . quod scripsero in suam veram <lb/> laudem scripsisse concedat. <lb/> </incipit><rubric>De eua parente prima <lb/> </rubric><incipit>Scripturus igitur quibus fulgoribus <lb/> mulieres claruerint insignes a matre <lb/> omnium sumpsisse exordium non apparebit <lb/> indignum </incipit>
                     <explicit> vt pocius alicuius in bonum vigeat <lb/> opus quam in nullius commodum lace<lb/>ratum dentibus inuidorum depereat <lb/> Amen. <lb/><lb/> </explicit><finalRubric>Iohannis Boccacii de Cercaldo de <lb/> mulieribus claris liber explicit. <lb/> Deo gracias. </finalRubric>
                     <author key="person_64002165">Giovanni Boccaccio (1313–1375)</author>
                     <title key="work_1766">De claris mulieribus</title>
                     <listBibl><bibl>Ed. V. Zaccaria (Milan 1967); ed. V. Zaccaria in <title>Tutte le opere di Giovanni Boccaccio</title>, ed. V. Branca (Milan 1964–98), 10. 18–451. Noticed for the edition with the siglum O<hi rend="superscript">3</hi>, but not collated.</bibl></listBibl>
                     <note>The text ends on l. 14; the rest of the column is blank.</note>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               
               
               <physDesc>
                  <p><secFol>du<ex>m</ex> est detestandis</secFol></p>
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="perg">
                        <support>Parchment is very fine: smooth, thin and pliant with a velvety nap to the flesh-sides, rather more of suede to the hair-side, the surface of both somewhat chalky. There is no difference in colour, which is uniform and creamy white. Arranged like to like, flesh-side outermost. There are very few flaws and the parchment is of consistent thickness. Small holes are written around on fols. 20, 49, 98, 144, 173, with holes stitched on 70, 117; a natural edge at fol. 64. </support>
                        <extent>i (medieval parchment) + 174 + i (early-modern laid paper). Two components (fols. 1–115 and 116–174) produced in the same workshop and by the same scribe and artist. 
                           <dimensions unit="mm" type="leaf">
                              <height>330</height>
                              <width>234</width>
                           </dimensions></extent>
                        <foliation>There is a late medieval foliation which differs in the two parts. The first counts the leaves of each quire in arabic numerals, restarting from 1 with each new quire, with the peculiarity that if a new book begins on the verso at the end of a quire this page is numbered 1. This mark in a grey ink is positioned in the upper right-hand corner. It is the same as that which, at a different time in different ink, centred the number of the quire (1–9) at the head of each page, recto and verso. The second part is foliated in a separate series by the same hand, numbering each leaf, recto and verso, in arabic (1–62), placing the numeral at the head centred between the columns. The continuous foliation (which is followed here) is the one in early twentieth-century Bodleian pencil in the upper right-hand corner, which in part I means it is placed to the left or just above the medieval numeration.</foliation>
                        <collation mainStructures="12">Collation: a<hi rend="superscript">2</hi> (fol. [i], two a stub) 1–3<hi rend="superscript">12</hi> (fols. 1–36) 4<hi rend="superscript">12</hi> (fols. 37–49, with one after twelve) 5<hi rend="superscript">12</hi> (fols. 50–61) 6<hi rend="superscript">14</hi> (fols. 62–74, medieval foliation skips one, no loss of text) 7<hi rend="superscript">12</hi> (fols. 75–86, medieval foliation skips one, no loss of text) 8<hi rend="superscript">12</hi> (fols. 87–98, medieval foliation skips one, no loss of text) 9<hi rend="superscript">16</hi> (fols. 99–115, with one after sixteen) <lb/><lb/> 10<hi rend="superscript">12</hi> (fols. 116–127) 11<hi rend="superscript">12</hi> (fols. 128–140, with ?one after twelve) 12<hi rend="superscript">12</hi> (fols. 141–152) 13–14<hi rend="superscript">8</hi> (fols. 153–168) 15<hi rend="superscript">8</hi> (fols. 169–174, one and eight cancelled). Quires signatures are found at the head of each page (see above). No catchwords.</collation>
                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout columns="2" writtenLines="41" rulingMedium="leadpoint">Both parts are ruled in lead for two columns of 41 lines, with an intercolumnar space of 19 mm. Rules are single: all vertical rules pass to the edges of the page, as does the horizontal at the foot (but not at the head); nor do the horizontals cross the intercolumnar space. No visible prickings. Written below top-line. Written space <dimensions unit="mm" type="written">
                              <height max="229" min="224">224-229</height>
                              <width>150</width>
                        </dimensions><!--, with an intercolumnar space of 17–20 mm.  --></layout>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc hands="1">
                     <handNote script="hybrida"> One scribe, French or Burgundian, writing a stylish hand, clearly professional both by script choice and achievement. The script would be commonly defined as a continental Hybrida, in its deliberate combination of forms from Cursiva and Textualis: <hi rend="italic">a</hi> is single compartment, <hi rend="italic">f</hi> and tall <hi rend="italic">s</hi> descend below the line, and there are no loops on the ascenders (which sometimes have a triangular approach stroke from the left, particularly when in initial position, but more often have none). There is influence here from French Cursiva, albeit the script is upright: the pen is angled and there is a play of chiaroscuro between broad and thin strokes, further elaborated by the addition of hairlines for suspensions, stroking the <hi rend="italic">i</hi> and hanging from the hast of <hi rend="italic">t</hi>. Round <hi rend="italic">s</hi> is used in terminal position, with a third, attenuated shape when it occurs at line-end. The shape of <hi rend="italic">g</hi> is from Cursiva, with a flat tail to the left. There are fusions with <hi rend="italic">d</hi> (which is always loopless) but otherwise these are scaled back. Ink is black and consistent. Punctuation is by <foreign>virgula</foreign> in red ink for a short pause, resembling more a rhetorical pointing than punctuation, and by thickened double <foreign>virgula</foreign> with following majuscule for breaks. Corrections are given in the margins by the scribe with a <foreign>signe-de-renvoie</foreign> over the word in the text; on 22r eye-skip (based on ‘nomen’) was spotted by the scribe and he erased two lines and overwrote them, extending into the margin, then bordered the words with billowing hairlines in red ink; something similar also on 141r. Insertions are interlineated, with a caret mark below the line. There is red-ink rubrication by the scribe and blue ink on 99r (showing that the rubrication was carried out at the same time as the decoration of minor initials in both colours). Majuscules throughout are stroked with red. The same scribe wrote both parts of the manuscript. </handNote>
                  </handDesc>
                  <decoDesc>
                     <decoNote type="decInit">Illuminated initials of intricate delicacy. The major initial (fol. 1r) is a nine-line puzzle initial <hi rend="italic">D</hi> of blue ink and gold leaf; the interior has a marguerite of petals in blind with red floret and sepals with fine line modelling in lilac and pale blue. This is on a blue ground within a lozenge frame and surrounded by acanthus scrolls in blind on a green ground. The initial is flourished with red penwork, and further scrolls in the spandrels on the left, with a border extension of a thin gold line terminating at each end in a blue quatrefoil with gold disk. This bar is flourished down its whole length with lilac penwork, which extends in a spray across the head and foot of the first column. The puzzle initial <hi rend="italic">P</hi> at the start of the second component of the manuscript is of slightly reduced majesty: again, much use of gold leaf but this time with infill of blue penwork and red penwork outside and cusped bar border in red and blue ink with more gold, and with red and blue penwork flourishing. There are no extensions across head or foot. There are similar initials, only a little simplified, of eight or nine lines, for the start of the text proper and for new books: fols. 1v, 13r, 24v, 37r, 49v (excised), 61v, 74v, 86r, 99r. These are found in part 1 only; there is only one decorated initial in part 2. On 1v the gold leaf on the hast of the initial E has been scratched off and the initials ‘EB’ scratched in. </decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="border">Borders: see above.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="colInit">Minor initials throughout are plain lombards of red or blue ink, usually of two lines. </decoNote>
                  </decoDesc>
                  <additions>
                     <p>The manuscript is largely clean of annotations. Marginal headings were supplied here and there by the scribe, presumably copying from his exemplar. He also wrote corrected readings in the margins. There are at least two further correcting hands. One subsequent annotator (of both parts) used two colours, red and black for a variety of marks: a delicate filigree brace, sometimes incorporating a cross, an artistic manicule with fur-cuffed sleeve (15r), and the word ‘nota’ (<foreign>no<hi rend="superscript">a</hi></foreign>) or ‘nota bene’ quite widely. His interest was in pious passages extolling obedience and Christian virtue in the prince. (For example, ‘Meminisse quippe presidentes debent non esse populos seruos sed conseruos’, marked <foreign>nota bene</foreign>, fol. 15r.) At the foot of fol. 82r, lines are drawn in the ruled box at the foot of col. b: a saltire cross intersected by a lozenge; and against this is written ‘abigo demones’. All this in a pale brown ink and hand of the late sixteenth or early seventeenth century. </p>
                  </additions>
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <binding notBefore="1614" notAfter="1631">
                        <p>By <persName key="person_4920" role="bnd">Roger Barnes of Oxford</persName>, an early seventeenth-century blind-stamped binding of tanned calf over pulpboard. The date of binding is after 1614, the date of the printed edition used for the pastedown. To both boards, three-line blind fillets to all edges cross at the corners unmitred, repeated inset at 22 mm to produce a square at each corner and a central panel. At the spine edge the margin is 33 mm and a chevron made of fillets crosses this panel from each raised band. The central panel is formed by two rolls separated by more three-line fillets, the outer roll conforming to Gibson roll XVII, the inner to XXI, both used in combination by Roger Barnes until his death in 1631. The cover is somewhat scuffed, but the condition of the binding is good. Sewn on five double, whittawed bands, raised at the spine. Non-structural endbands of blue and yellow thread. Paired fore-edge ties have been cut away flush to the board. The edges are sprinkled red. On the back board are the marks of the normal early-modern college chain clip, towards the foot of the fore-edge. Pastedowns are waste from two separate printed editions. Most are sheets from Thomas Gibson, <title>Romanæ historiæ anthologia. An English Exposition of the Romane antiquities, wherein many Romane and English offices are paralleld and divers obscure phrases explained . . . for the vse of Abingdon Schoole</title> (Oxford: Joseph Barnes, 1614; 2nd edn 1616). The setting of this copy differs from both the known editions. Showing on the front pastedown, oriented vertically, are a cut-down portion of sigs. ¶ 3<hi rend="superscript">v</hi> and ¶ 2<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> at the spine; on the back pastedown, oriented horizontally, are sigs. ¶ 2<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> and ¶ 3<hi rend="superscript">v</hi> above, with the title-page verso and sig. [¶ 4]<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> below. The larger part of the front pastedown is a bifolium from another edition found in Barnes’ bindings, volume 3 of Matthias Hoë von Hoënegg, <title>Commentariorum in beati apostoli et evangelistae Johannis Apocalypsin liber tertius</title> (Leipzig: Abraham Lamberg, 1611). It is oriented with the foot of the page to the fore-edge; showing are pp. 448 (left) and 441 (right).</p>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origPlace><country key="place_1000070">France</country> or <country key="place_7029372">Burgundy</country></origPlace>
                     <origDate notBefore="1425" notAfter="1450" calendar="Gregorian">s. xv<hi rend="superscript">2/4</hi></origDate>
                  </origin>
                  <provenance>The two parts of the manuscript were made in the same place: they share ruling, parchment, scribe and limner. They were, however, produced separately, for they have individually distinctive foliations, apparently in the same hand of an early owner. Item 2 seems originally to have been bound, or more likely stitched, with the assemblage of works of Cicero in Lat. 38, for it is included in Robert Flemming’s contents list in this latter, marked there with crosses for deletion. It must have been <persName role="fmo" key="person_258392640">Robert Flemming, dean of Lincoln</persName>, who parted item 1 from what is now Lat. 38 and had it bound up with this other text of Boccaccio; both books were given by him to the College. As with Lat. 38, this was one of those manuscripts whose gift belongs to Flemming’s lifetime: the <foreign>ex dono</foreign> inscription is in his own hand (fol. [i]<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>). It was taken into the library and chained at the third desk on the south side of the room, as reported in the 1474 inventory: ‘Item boccasius de viris illustribus et claris mulieribus ex dono eiusdem, 2<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> fo. <hi rend="italic">dum est</hi>’ (A1. 70). On the hast of the initial <hi rend="italic">E</hi> on fol. 1v some of the gold has been scratched off revealing the grey bole, and alongside the (replacement?) initials, ‘EB’ have been scratched in. These are difficult to date and could have been done at any time and probably represent a reader rather than an owner. </provenance>
                  <provenance><hi rend="italic">Labels and marks</hi>: The James number ‘79’ is in black ink at the top of the flyleaf verso, above the <foreign>ex dono</foreign> inscription. The eighteenth-century press-mark is at the top of the recto: ‘E: 47: 12’. The College’s 1703 bookplate is pasted to the middle of the front pastedown; on blank space to the right is pencilled the Bodleian shelf-mark, ‘MS. Linc. Coll. (c) Lat. 32’. The fore-edge paper label is at the head of the fore-edge, the number now rubbed off. Adjacent to it, inked on the fore-edge itself, is the number ‘23’. On the spine, square paper labels: in the top compartment the small label with ‘32’ printed; in the compartment below, the number repeated in boldface, and at the foot, the pale blue label, now torn but bearing the Bodleian shelf-mark.</provenance>
                  <provenance><hi rend="italic">Booklists</hi>: Vetus Registrum, fol. 16r; James, <title>Ecloga</title>, no. 79; <title>CMA</title> 1/2. 1310.</provenance>
               </history>
               
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>Description by James Willoughby, 2026.</source>
                     </recordHist>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <ref target="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/mdp.39015028611856?urlappend=%3Bseq=660"> H. O. Coxe, <title>Catalogus codicum mss. qui in collegiis aulisque Oxoniensibus hodie adservantur</title> (Oxford, 1852)</ref>
                        <citedRange unit="volume">I</citedRange> [individual sections separately paginated], Lincoln College, <citedRange unit="page" from="28" to="28">p. 28</citedRange> (open access at HathiTrust Digital Library). This manuscript is missed by Alexander &amp; Temple.</bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2026-06">New description by James Willoughby</change>
         <change when="2021-06">First online publication.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p><!--body provided for validation and future transcription--></p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>