<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/msDesc/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/msDesc/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="manuscript_16187">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Lincoln College MS. Lat. 92</title>
            <title type="collection">Lincoln College MSS.</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp when="2025">Cataloguer</resp>
               <persName>James Willoughby</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp when="2025">Encoding</resp>
               <persName>Matthew Holford</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </publisher>
            <idno type="msID">Lincoln_College_MS_Lat_92</idno>
            <idno type="collection">Lincoln_College</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:lang="en" xml:id="Lincoln_College_MS_Lat_92">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <repository>Lincoln College</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">Lincoln College MS. Lat. 92</idno>
               <idno type="ieArk">ark:29072/b47w62f764v5</idno><idno type="crArk">ark:29072/b47s75db81j9</idno></msIdentifier>
               <head>Seneca, <title>Tragoediae</title>, Northern Italy (?Bologna), s. xiv <hi rend="superscript">ex</hi>, with binding fragments from a gospel book, England (Lindisfarne), s. viii<hi rend="superscript">in</hi> </head>
               <msContents>
                  <summary>A rare manuscript in which the binding fragments are the most valuable part of the volume, and the volume thereby one of the most precious in the Library. These two leaves at the back belong to an early eighth-century gospel book from Northumbria that originated in the same scriptorium as the Lindisfarne Gospels. Now drastically cut down, the leaves derive from a volume that was once bigger and perhaps even grander than Lindisfarne. It is a priceless witness to the golden age of Anglo-Saxon book art.</summary>
                  <msItem>
                     <locus from="1r" to="162v">(fols. 1r–162v)</locus>
                     <author key="person_90637919">L. Annaeus Seneca</author>
                     <title key="work_4505">Tragoediae</title>
                     <rubric>Hercules furens. <lb/><lb/> Lucii Anei Senece. Incipit Hercules furens. <lb/><lb/> Primus actus Herculis est de querimonia Iunonis in Herculem. <lb/><lb/> </rubric><incipit><damage>excision</damage> OROR TONANTIS HOC ENIM <lb/><lb/> <locus>(1v)</locus> Nomen relictum est semper alienum Iouem </incipit><explicit>fortius ipso genitore tuo <lb/>  fulmina mittes. <lb/><lb/> </explicit><colophon>DEO GRACIAS AMEN M A B <lb/><lb/> Finis adest meto . mercedere posco diete. / Quare nisi nunc dederis . cras minus actus eris. </colophon>
                     <note>Ed. O. Zwierlein, OCT (1986); MacGregor, ‘Handlist’, 1173 (T 426). This witness belongs to the large β-family. The sequence of Tragedies is <title>Hercules Furens</title> (fol. 1r), <title>Thyestes</title> (21r), <title>Thebais</title> (37r), <title>Hippolytus</title> (46r), <title>Oedipus</title> (64r), <title>Troades</title> (79r), <title>Medea</title> (94r), <title>Agamemnon</title> (109r), <title>Octavia</title> (122r), and <title>Hercules Oetaeus</title> (136r), beginning in each case acephalously after the theft of illuminated leaves.</note><note>Fol. 163 is blank but for scribbles.
                     </note>
                     <textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc> <p><secFol> Aperitq<ex>ue</ex> thetis qua.</secFol></p>
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="perg">
                        <support>Parchment is Italian, white and silky on the flesh-side, slightly more velvety nap on the hair, but with little difference in colour. The material is somewhat unyielding and there is cockling at the middle of the fore-edge. Arranged like to like, flesh-side outermost. </support>
                        <extent> i (vellum) + <measure type="leaf">163</measure> + ii (foliated 165–165, conjugate bifolium of Insular parchment (s. viii<hi rend="superscript">in</hi>) 2 formerly pastedown). 
                        <dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                           <height>280</height>
                           <width>200</width>
                        </dimensions></extent>
                        <foliation>Foliated in early twentieth-century Bodleian pencil. </foliation>
                        <collation mainStructures="10">
                           1(2) (fol. i, one is pastedown) 1–2(10) (fols. 1–20) 3(10) (fols. 21–29, 1 robbed) 4(10) (fols. 30–38, 8 robbed) 5(10) (fols. 39–47, 8 robbed) 6(10) (fols. 48–57) 7(10) (fols. 58–66, 7 robbed) 8(10) (fols. 67–76) 9(10) (fols. 77–85, 3 robbed) 10(10) (fols. 86–93, 9, 10 robbed) 11(10) (fols. 94–103) 12(8) (fols. 104–110, 6 robbed) 13(10) (fols. 111–120) 14(10) (fols. 121–129, 2 robbed) 15(10) (fols. 130–138, 7 robbed) 16–17(10) (fols. 139–158) 18(4) (fols. 159–162) 19 (fol. 163, a singleton) 20(2) (fols. 164–165). 
                           <catchwords>Catchwords are initially given unadorned at text size, centred at the foot. From 66v they are given in the same way but ornamented by stylized quatrefoils at the cardinal points. </catchwords>
                        </collation>
                        
                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout columns="1" writtenLines="35 36" rulingMedium="leadpoint">Written space of <dimensions type="written" unit="mm">
                           <height>180</height>
                           <width>95</width>
                        </dimensions> Ruled nearly invisibly in lead for 35 or 36 lines. Single bounding lines pass to the four edges of the page, with a tramline 10 mm apart at the left-hand side to contain the larger initial to each line. The text is written in a single column with wide margins left blank for the addition of notes. </layout>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc hands="1">
                     <handNote script="textualisSouthern">One scribe writing an expert northern Italian Gothic Rotunda. The letters are well formed, entirely consistent and perfectly justified at the left. Tall-<hi rend="italic">s</hi> is found in initial and medial position with round-<hi rend="italic">s</hi> in terminal position and less frequent use at the end of lines of the secondary Italian form of round-<hi rend="italic">s</hi> with attenuated lower curve (becoming more frequent in the later reaches of the manuscript). Although there are small differences in the overall performance, the letters becoming slightly larger and showing increasing effect from the slant-pen angle, it does seem to be the work of one hand throughout, as is affirmed by the ductus in particular of <hi rend="italic">g</hi>, <hi rend="italic">s</hi>, and round-backed <hi rend="italic">d</hi>. Ascenders on the top line are routinely elaborated with cadels. Ink ranges from mid-brown to black. Punctuation by virgule, <foreign rend="italic">punctus elevatus</foreign>, and low point. Running headings were supplied by the rubricator. </handNote>
                     
                  </handDesc>
                  <decoDesc>
                     <decoNote type="histInit">Illuminated pages throughout have been robbed, with consequent loss of text (leaves before 21, 37, 46, 64, 79, 94, 109, 122, 136). The first leaf remains but the initial S has been excised with its border decoration, leaving a window that extends up and down the inner margin; an outlying gold ball remains. Of the more than sixty copies of Seneca’s Tragedies that contain miniatures, the great majority are Italian and were produced at the end of the fourteenth century and start of the fifteenth (MacGregor, ‘Handlist’, 1258–60, with a survey of pictorial treatments which can be applied to this missing initial). </decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="border">Borders, lost: see above.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="flourInit">
                        Remaining decoration is confined to minor initials signifying the start of major new speeches: these are blue or red three-line capitals with some quite extravagant penwork flourishing in the other colour, extending the full height of the written space. These were done by a limner who was not the scribe. Briefer exchanges in the text are signified by simple blue or red capitals in initial position with the speaker’s name abbreviated in red in the adjacent margin, by the main scribe, who also added the rubricated running heads.</decoNote>
                  </decoDesc>
                
                  <additions>
                     <p>Certain of the Tragedies have attracted the annotators, others very little. <title>Hercules Furens</title>, <title>Oedipus</title> and <title>Troades</title> are well served; <title>Hippolytus</title>, <title>Medea</title>, <title>Agamemnon</title>, <title>Octavia</title>, and <title>Hercules Oetaeus</title> have mostly interlinear glosses, while there are only a few annotations in <title>Thebais</title>, and hardly anything at all in <title>Thyestes</title>.</p><p> Corrections <foreign rend="italic">in rasura</foreign> in a blacker ink and less good Italian hand occur throughout. </p><p>In the margin of fol. 82r a different hand supplied, in Italian Rotunda at text size, a forty-one line addition to the text, marked by a <foreign rend="italic">signe-de-renvoi</foreign>. Throughout, there are tiny <foreign rend="italic">id est</foreign> glosses interlineated and, less often, <foreign rend="italic">scholia</foreign> written <foreign rend="italic">en bloc</foreign> in the margins. These are mainly given in a tiny continental <foreign rend="italic">notula</foreign> script, but on fol. 8r the hand is English. There are many <foreign rend="italic">maniculae</foreign> throughout, drawn by at least six different readers: they show an interest in specific tragedies. One, for instance, presenting a very thin, long line for the finger from an otherwise naturalistic hand and sometimes elaborate cuffs, occurs in <title>Medea</title> and <title>Agamemnon</title> (107r, 109r, 111v, 112r, 114r, 116v). Another, a rather stubby hand with natural proportions, starts well but fades away (5r, 7r, v, 12r, 38r, 47v, 48v, 56v). A large, naturalistic hand with shading occurs only once (83r). One reader of <title>Hercules Furens</title> drew an elaborate human-headed serpent, presumably to be understood as a brace operating between the long nose and the tip of the tail (12r, 14r). The two passages so marked relate to the responsibilities of secular power and the preparation for death: ‘et impotentis terga . . . maiore vestra’ and ‘Sera nos illo . . . dedit hora, carpit’ (<title>Her. F.</title> 738–47 and 864–74). These happen to be emphases discernible in Robert Flemming’s notes in other books, although this style of brace is found only here. What appears to be Flemming’s hand appears on fol. 4v, writing ‘Anguel’ next to <foreign rend="italic">angues</foreign> (Her. F. 217), with other <foreign rend="italic">notae</foreign> on snakes and the hydra on this opening in the same distinctive light-brown ink.</p>
                  </additions>
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <binding notAfter="1631" notBefore="1600">
                        <p>By <persName role="bnd" key="person_4920">Roger Barnes of Oxford (d. 1631)</persName>, an early seventeenth-century binding of reverse calf over pulpboard. Decoration on both boards is restricted to a rectilinear pattern of intersecting lines. Three-line blind fillets to the edges crossing unmitred at the corners, repeated inset at 40 mm to produce a square at each corner and a central panel, unembellished. Sewn on six single, whittawed thongs, laced into the board and raised at the spine. Endbands of white thread are non-structural. Paired fore-edge ties of undyed cord are cut away flush to the boards. Fore-edges are sprinkled red. Marks of the usual college chain clip are at the fore-edge of the back board towards the head; nail-holes and verdigris on the lifted pastedown. The condition of the binding is very good with no warping and only a small amount of splitting at the tailcap. Pastedown of Italian vellum at the front, still pasted down, and early Insular parchment at the back, which was lifted in 1896 according to E. N. Bennett (see <title>Labels and marks</title>).</p>
                        <p><title>Labels and marks</title>: There are no medieval marks of ownership. The James number ‘85’ in pale brown ink is at the head of fol. 1v. On the front flyleaf recto in brown ink of s. xvii is ‘ff: 51: 12’. The College bookplate of 1703 is affixed in normal position at the centre of the front pastedown. The Bodleian shelf-mark is written in pencil underneath: ‘MS. Linc. Coll. (d) Lat. 92’. The fore-edge label is rubbed away and illegible. On the spine, square paper labels: at the head, an arabic numeral 25 on the small, printed label, and at the foot the larger, blue-bordered label, nineteenth-century, with ‘92’ in ink. Below that is the printed label with Bodleian shelf-mark, now mostly rubbed away. A brief notice by E. N. Bennett, ‘An eighth-century fragment of the Vulgate’, from <title>The Academy</title>, 30 Nov. 1896 is fixed to the front pastedown.</p>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin><origPlace><country key="place_1000080">Northern Italy</country> (?<settlement cert="low" key="place_7004847">Bologna</settlement>)</origPlace><origDate calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="1400" notBefore="1390">s. xiv <hi rend="superscript">ex</hi>.</origDate></origin>
                  <provenance>The manuscript was produced in northern Italy and appears to have passed between a number of Italian readers before it was acquired by <persName role="fmo" key="person_258392640">Robert Flemming</persName>, who arrived at the university of Padua in 1446 and was in Italy frequently thereafter. </provenance><provenance>There are no medieval inscriptions in the manuscript but it is asserted in the College’s 1474 inventory to have come from Robert Flemming: ‘Item tragedie senece ex dono eiusdem (sc. Roberti Flemmyng’), 2o fo. aperitque’ (A1. 78). It would have been part of Flemming’s large donation of 1465. At that time, it was being shelved on the fourth desk on the south side of the library, among other Latin classics.</provenance><provenance>
                     How this Italian manuscript came to be bound with fragments of an early eighth-century gospel book from Lindisfarne is worth some speculation. Nothing is known of the gospel book’s earlier provenance, but Oxford and not Italy was surely the locale where these leaves were brought into the binding. There are two possibilities: that it was done for Robert Flemming, who was resident in Oxford when he returned from Rome, or done instead at the time of the rebinding by Robert Barnes in the early seventeenth century. In favour of the latter suggestion would be the situation at Durham cathedral priory, which had absorbed books from Lindisfarne into its collection after the exiled community established itself there in 995; the library of Durham College in Oxford was stocked with books from the mother-house. A list of books at this Oxford studium in 1315 refers to a gospel book in two volumes (Durham Cathedral Muniments, Misc. Ch. 7307/4), although this sounds more like the glossed gospels in two volumes that was reported c. 1395 (2.6.Ebor.5). More plausibly, our unglossed copy would have been used as a <foreign rend="italic">textus</foreign> in a liturgical setting, and it would be possible to imagine it in a precious binding on the high altar of the college’s chapel. When Durham College was finally dissolved in 1545, its books were scattered and, as happened to manuscripts from nearby Canterbury College, they found their way into local stationers’ shops to be mined for waste parchment. The supply of parchment leaves in Oxford was so great that it seems to have lasted well into the early seventeenth century, when paper waste began to take over. Against this suggestion it should be pointed out that Barnes’s habitual practice when rebinding the College’s books was to reuse the medieval pastedowns and flyleaves which he found with them. Joining two old, written bifolia to be rear flyleaves would not be his normal practice. The two ancient fragments that are present in Lincoln College bindings—the Lindisfarne specimen and the leaf of a Tours Bible in Lat. 37—happen both to be found in books presented to the College by Robert Flemming. Were these fragments in fact his? They are unusually early specimens of script, not only in relation to the rest of the College’s books but also in relation to Oxford pastedowns in general: Ker, <title>Pastedowns</title>, reports little else of such early date. Flemming had a humanist’s interest in old manuscripts and the reformed script (as is represented by the Tours fragment), and he borrowed and acquired romanesque books, such as Lat. 63, 100 and Oxford, The Queen’s College, MS 202. At least one of these, Lat. 63, was from a northern religious house, which may help to account for his possession of a fragment probably from Durham. </provenance><provenance>
                     
                     <title>Booklists</title>: <title>Vetus Registrum</title>, fol. 16v; James, <title>Ecloga</title>, no. 85; <title>CMA</title> 1/2. 1288.
                  </provenance>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>Description by James Willoughby, 2025.</source>
                     </recordHist>
                     <availability status="restricted">
                        <p>To ensure its availability to future readers, access to this item is restricted, and readers are asked to work from reproductions and published descriptions as far as possible. To apply to see the original, please send a message to <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>, outlining the subject of your research, the importance of this item to that research, and the resources you have already consulted.</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <surrogates>
                     <bibl type="digital-facsimile" subtype="full">
                        <ref target="https://digital.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/objects/ce7070be-9462-4caa-807d-b6d1a2f52116/">
                           <title>Digital Bodleian</title></ref> <note>(full digital facsimile)</note>
                     </bibl>
                  </surrogates>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <ref target="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/mdp.39015028611856?urlappend=%3Bseq=677"> H. O. Coxe, <title>Catalogus codicum mss. qui in collegiis aulisque Oxoniensibus hodie adservantur</title> (Oxford, 1852)</ref>
                        <citedRange unit="volume">I</citedRange> [individual sections separately paginated], Lincoln College, <citedRange unit="page" from="45" to="45">p. 45</citedRange> (open access at HathiTrust Digital Library)</bibl>
                     <bibl>A. P. MacGregor, ‘The manuscripts of Seneca’s Tragedies: a handlist’, <title>Aufstieg und Niedergang der römischen Welt: Geschichte und Kultur Roms im Spiegel der neueren Forschung</title> 32/2 (1985), 1134–1241, at 1173 (T 426)</bibl><bibl><title>CLA</title> 2. 258</bibl><bibl> Gneuss/Lapidge 677</bibl><bibl> T. D. Kendrick &amp; others, <title>Evangeliorum quattuor Codex Lindisfarnensis</title>, 2 vols (Olten and Lausanne 1956–60), 2/1. 89–106 passim (our manuscript cited as O), and pl. 15b</bibl><bibl>A. C. de la Mare &amp; B. C. Barker-Benfield, <title>Manuscripts at Oxford: An Exhibition in Memory of Richard William Hunt (1908–1979)</title>, Bodleian exhibition catalogue (Oxford 1980), 14 and fig. 5; R. Gameson, ‘Northumbrian books in the seventh and eighth centuries’, in <title>The Lindisfarne Gospels: New Perspectives</title>, ed. Gameson (Leiden 2017), 43–83, at 64, 81 and pl. 3.12.</bibl>
                     
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
               <msPart xml:id="Lincoln_College_MS_Lat_92_endleaves">
                  <msIdentifier>
                     <altIdentifier type="partial">
                        <idno type="part">Lincoln College, MS. Lat. 92, endleaves (fols. 164-165)</idno>
                     </altIdentifier>
                  </msIdentifier>
                  <msContents>
                     <textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>
                     <msItem xml:id="Lincoln_College_MS_Lat_92_endleaves-item1">
                        <locus>(fols. 164ra–165vb)</locus>
                        <title type="desc" key="work_12098">Gospel book</title>
                        <incipit defective="true"> ... et hii radices non habent </incipit><explicit defective="true">crede tantum <lb/> et salua erit ...</explicit><note>Two added conjugate leaves, cut down with loss of text, from an Anglo-Saxon gospel book (Lindisfarne, s. viii<hi rend="superscript">in</hi>), preserving Luke 8:13–50 with marginal Eusebian Apparatus. Given the siglum Ex, but not used, by B. Fischer, <title>Die lateinischen Evangelien bis zum 10. Jahrhundert</title>, 4 vols (Freiburg im Breisgau, 1988–91), 3. 16*. It offers a mixed text, ‘neither purely Irish nor purely Italo-Northumbrian’ (T. J. Brown in <title>Evangeliorum quattuor Codex Lindisfarnensis</title>, 2/1. 95).
                        </note>
                     </msItem>
                     
                     
                  </msContents>
                  <physDesc>
                     <objectDesc form="codex">
                        <supportDesc material="perg">
                           <support>Parchment, prepared in the Insular manner</support>
                           <collation>This bifolium came from the centre of a quire. </collation>
                        </supportDesc>
                        <layoutDesc>
                           <layout columns="2" writtenLines="28">E. A. Lowe (<title>CLA</title> 2. 258) calculated the original written space as c. <dimensions type="written" unit="mm">
                              <height>295</height>
                              <width>230</width>
                           </dimensions>, in two columns of 28 lines written <foreign rend="italic">per cola et commata</foreign>, as is typical of Phase II Insular manuscripts. No visible ruling but prickings in both margins.</layout>
                        </layoutDesc>
                     </objectDesc>
                     <handDesc>
                        <handNote script="halfUncial">Written in a broad, expert Insular Half-uncial in a hand that resembles very closely that in which Eadfrith, bishop of Lindisfarne, wrote the Lindisfarne Gospels. As such, the performance belongs firmly to mature Phase II, produced under the influence of the best Italian Uncial exemplars. Uncial forms of <hi rend="italic">d</hi>, <hi rend="italic">n</hi>, <hi rend="italic">r</hi>, <hi rend="italic">s</hi>, are all present, as are monograms of <hi rend="italic">-ur</hi> and <hi rend="italic">-unt</hi> and Uncial <hi rend="italic">a</hi> at line ends. There is one instance of the Insular abbreviation for <foreign rend="italic">autem</foreign>. Typically for Phase II, it is written <foreign rend="italic">per cola et commata</foreign> in two columns. There is one instance of medial point; otherwise unpunctuated. See further the discussion by Julian Brown in Kendrick, <title>Evangeliorum quattuor Codex Lindisfarnensis</title>, 2/1. 89–106 passim. Brown’s discussion of our fragment remains the fullest to date; and although some aspects of his discussion of the Lindisfarne Gospels have been finessed in recent years—in relation to the idea of the Lindisfarne ‘scriptorium’ and redating the manuscript’s production to the early eighth century—the consensus remains that our manuscript is undeniably associated with Lindisfarne (see, for example, Gameson, ‘Northumbrian books’). Certainly, the form of the supplied cross-references to the Eusebian canon tables are typical of Lindisfarne (see Annotations).</handNote>
                     </handDesc>
                     <decoDesc>
                        <decoNote>Typical of Insular writing, there is stippling around initials originally in red ink, now faded. The excellence of the script and the size of the original pages shows that this was once the grandest of books. It is regrettable that these pages do not preserve any further decoration.</decoNote>
                     </decoDesc>
                     <additions>
                        <p>The St Luke gospel leaves are accompanied by a system of marginal cross-references to the Eusebian Canon Tables. These are written in a tiny Insular minuscule, perhaps by the main scribe, against the start of a new verse, on fols. 164r, 165r. These are found in other gospels of the Lindisfarne connection and take the same form: for example (164r), ‘l  lxxxii | ii (in red) | Mt  cxxx | Mr  xxxii’, where the first reference is to the number of the section in this gospel (the ‘l’ presumably for lectio), the red numeral identifies the canon, then two cross-references to the parallel passage in Matthew and then Mark. (See further T. O’Loughlin, ‘The Eusebian Apparatus in the Lindisfarne Gospels: Ailerán’s Kanon euangeliorum as a lens for its appreciation’, in <title>The Lindisfarne Gospels: New Perspectives</title>, ed. R. Gameson (Leiden 2017), 96–111.)</p>
                     </additions>
                  </physDesc>
                  <history>
                     <origin>
                        <origPlace><country key="place_7002445">England</country>, <orgName key="org_207982335">Lindisfarne</orgName></origPlace>
                        <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notBefore="0700" notAfter="0710">s. viii<hi rend="superscript">in</hi></origDate>
                        
                     </origin>
                     <provenance><orgName role="fmo" key="org_144679410" cert="low">Durham, Benedictine priory</orgName> (?) (see above)</provenance>
                     <provenance><orgName role="fmo" key="org_130440205" cert="low">Oxford, Durham College</orgName> (?) (see above)</provenance>
                  </history>
               </msPart>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2025-12">Encode new description by James Willougby.</change>
         <change when="2021-06">First online publication.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p><!--body provided for validation and future transcription--></p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>