<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/msDesc/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/msDesc/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="manuscript_16006">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Lincoln College MS. Lat. 19</title>
            <title type="collection">Lincoln College MSS.</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp when="2026">Cataloguer</resp>
               <persName>James Willoughby</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp when="2026">Encoding</resp>
               <persName>Matthew Holford</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </publisher>
            <idno type="msID">Lincoln_College_MS_Lat_19</idno>
            <idno type="collection">Lincoln_College</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:lang="en" xml:id="Lincoln_College_MS_Lat_19">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <repository>Lincoln College</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">Lincoln College MS. Lat. 19</idno>
               <idno type="ieArk">ark:29072/b4q237hq453j</idno><idno type="crArk">ark:29072/b4pz50gt61sb</idno></msIdentifier>
               <head>Aristoteles, <title>Metaphysicae</title> cum Averroes, <title>Commentarium magnum</title>; France, s. xiii ex.</head>
               <msContents>
                  <textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>
                  <msItem>
                     <note>Fol. [i] is blank except for the early-modern press-mark in the outer top corner and, on the left, 'Liber Metaphysicus' (s. xvi).</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="1">
                     <locus from="1ra" to="140ra">(fols. 1ra–140ra)</locus>
                     <rubric><add>Primus liber Methaph'</add></rubric><incipit type="text">Consideracio quidem <lb/> in ueritate diffi<lb/>cilis est uno modo <lb/> facilis alio . et <lb/> signum eius est quod nullus hominum <lb/> potuit peruenire in ipsam secundum <lb/> quod oportet plene . . . <locus>(1rb)</locus> . . . ualde mani<lb/>festum . similis est dispositioni occulorum ues<lb/>pertilionis apud lucem solis. </incipit><incipit type="commentary">Quia ista scientia perscrutatur simpliciter incepit declerare dis<lb/>positionem uie inducentis ad ipsam secundum difficultatem et fa<lb/>cillitatem</incipit>
                     <explicit type="text">Sed mouet propter aliquid . Dixit <lb/> alium sermonem non sicut uidetur <lb/> medicina enim est aliqua ma<lb/>teria sanitatis et impossibile est ponere <lb/><lb/> continuum bonum et intellectus. </explicit><explicit type="commentary">tunc medicina mo<lb/>ueret utroque scilicet secundum quod est agens motum.</explicit>
                     <msItem>
                        <author key="person_7524651">Aristotle</author>
                        <title key="work_7545">Metaphysica</title>
                        <note>(tr. <persName role="trl" key="person_89415245">Michael Scot</persName>)</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <author key="person_19688718">Averroes</author>
                        <title key="work_847">Commentarium magnum</title>
                        <note>(tr. <persName role="trl" key="person_89415245">Michael Scot</persName>)</note>
                     </msItem>
                     
                     
                     <listBibl><bibl>Pr. <title>Aristotelis omnia quae extant opera</title>, 11 vols (Venice 1573–6), vol. 8</bibl><bibl> <title>AL Codd.</title> 110</bibl><bibl> Thomson, <title>Catalogue Aristotle</title>, 1. 281, no. 259.</bibl></listBibl><note> Aristotle's text (<title>Metaphysica noua</title>, tr. Michael Scot) is presented here at text size with Averroes' commentary following on at gloss size, presented <foreign>en bloc</foreign> after each chapter. In the usual eleven books. A quire has dropped out after fol. 118, taking with it the end of Bk X after 'sicut ueniunt ambo aut unde'. Blank pages are left at the end of a quire where a new book begins on the next quire: at fols. 16 (end of Bk II, entire leaf blank), 94v (end of Bk VII).</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem>
                     <note>Fol. 140r. The rest of the leaf is blank. Fol. 140v. A few lines of plummet notes, very faint.</note>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <p><secFol>generum et esse omnium (gl.).</secFol></p>
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="perg">
                        <support>Parchment. Parchment is very good, well prepared, pliant and of a consistent ivory in colour. There is only a small colour difference between hair- and flesh-sides. Arranged like to like, flesh-side outermost. Holes have been written around on fols. 15, 45, 120; they were stitched on fols. 16, 27, 44, 46, 57, 58, 72, 90, 106, 121; natural edges at 69, 99, 110.</support><extent>i (medieval parchment) + <measure type="leaf" quantity="140">140</measure> folios.
                           <dimensions unit="mm" type="leaf">
                              <height>350</height>
                              <width>230</width>
                           </dimensions>
                           <dimensions unit="mm" type="written">
                              <height min="200" max="205">200–205</height>
                              <width min="120" max="130">120–30</width>
                           </dimensions>
                        </extent>
                        <foliation>Foliation in early twentieth-century Bodleian pencil.  </foliation>
                        <collation mainStructures="12"> 1<hi rend="superscript">12</hi> (fols. 1–12) 2<hi rend="superscript">4</hi> (fols. 13–16, four is blank) 3<hi rend="superscript">12</hi> (fols. 17–28) 4<hi rend="superscript">10</hi> (fols. 29–38) 5<hi rend="superscript">12</hi> (fols. 39–50) 6<hi rend="superscript">10</hi> (fols. 51–60) 7–8<hi rend="superscript">12</hi> (fols. 61–84) 9<hi rend="superscript">10</hi> (fols. 85–94, verso of tenth blank) 10–11<hi rend="superscript">12</hi> (fols. 95–118) [quire missing] 12<hi rend="superscript">12</hi> (fols. 119–130) 13<hi rend="superscript">10</hi> (fols. 131–140). Catchwords appear only in Scribe B's stint, on 28v, 84v, given horizontally next to the gutter. They match the size of script, be it text or gloss. Any other catchwords will have been ploughed away. </collation>
                        
                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout rulingMedium="leadpoint" columns="2" writtenLines="56" topLine="below">Ruled in lead point for 56 gloss lines, the text being written on alternate lines. Two columns with an intercolumnar space of 10 mm. Written below top-line. Outer bounding rules are doubles on both axes and pass to the edges; horizontal rules cross the intercolumnar space but do not extend beyond the outer bounding line. Two further sets of tramlines at the foot are ruled horizontally right across, at 40 mm below the bottom line and another 30 mm below that; similarly, there is a vertical tramline in the outer margin at 30 mm from the ruled edge. Prickings are visible in the inner margin and at the foot where they guide the horizontal and vertical tramlines; doubtless lost to trimming at the head and fore-edge. </layout>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc hands="2">
                     <handNote script="textualisNorthern" execution="formata">A stately book, written by two collaborating scribes, apparently professionals, using formal and consistent <foreign>Littera textualis quadrata media</foreign> of Parisian type, very similar in terms of achievement and discipline. The text script is always a larger bookhand, written on alternate lines, and using the full height with a tightly controlled head- and baseline. The glossing script is always smaller, at the same scale always, and sits between the lines but is still formal, not cursive. Each scribe was responsible for both components of the text. Scribe A with his slight leftwards lean and somewhat wavering minims wrote to the end of Bk II (fol. 15vb; fol. 16 is blank) and from Bk VIII to fol. 118v, where a quire has fallen out, taking the end of Bk X. Scribe B, a firmly based hand, begins a new quire with Bk III (fol. 17ra) and wrote to the end of Bk VII (fol. 94rb; leaving the rest of the leaf blank), and then from the start of Bk XI (fol. 119r) to the end. Ink is dark brown (Scribe A) and black (Scribe B). Abbreviations are conventional and quite restrained, even in the gloss, in line with the stately impression given by the manuscript. Punctuation is by punctus. Deletions by subpuncting.</handNote>
                  </handDesc>
                  <decoDesc>
                     <decoNote type="flourInit">Flourished blue- and red-ink initials throughout, as well as blue and red paraphs. Major initials stand at the front of each book: 1r, 9r, 17r, 31r, 48v, 67r, 71r, 95r, 101v, 111r, 119r. These are three- or four-line puzzle initials (or half the height of the column for the I on 48v), parted in blue and red with penwork flourishing in both colours extended in both directions and with intricate, symmetrical infilling where possible. This flourishing has cascading J-shaped ornaments and is tightly curled in French style, not ranging extensively although there is a step towards spray work in the final, extended curlicule.</decoNote>
                  </decoDesc>
                  <additions>
                     <p>The manuscript is largely clean of annotations. A hand of s. xiv<hi rend="superscript">1</hi> wrote the book number across the openings in a brown ink, taking the form '.li'. || .3<hi rend="superscript">us</hi>.' , giving up in Bk IV (36r), but noting thereafter the start of a new book. Drypoint notes on fols. 13v (erased), 22v, 30v, 46r, 47r, 48r, 50v. There are some tiny interlineated corrections of s. xiii/xiv in Bks VIII and IX.</p>
                  </additions>
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <binding notBefore="1275" notAfter="1500">
                        <p>Original medieval binding of alum-tawed skin over cushion-bevelled wooden boards, with a small overhang. The cover has been repaired in modern times with vellum where the original skin was torn away: at the head and tail of the spine and at the fore-edge where the metal furniture was. Original lacing: sewn on six double alum-tawed thongs, not raised at the spine. Endband is present at the head, lost at the tail, and appears to be structural. Fore-edge is stained red. The marks of six nail holes on the back board show the location of the College's medieval titlepiece, now missing. The space covered by the holes is around 20 × 100 mm. Vestigial evidence for two paired fore-edge clasps or ties, which were anchored in grooves on the upper board and fastened to some arrangement on the lower: this is somewhat indistinct since there is only one nail hole in each position, which could have been for a pin for a tie; but there are also cuts and wear in the cover material where catch-plates would have been, and those would need to be nailed on. Verdigris marks and two nail holes show the College's early-modern chain-clip, which was fixed towards the head of the back board. A similar mark is near the foot of the front board: again, verdigris marks on the inner board from a square-ended staple. The shape is not that of the College's early-modern clip and so may relate to the medieval chaining arrangement. There are also paired rust marks on this board, which may belong to early clasping fixtures. Pastedowns and flyleaves are medieval parchment, original with the binding.</p>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origPlace><country key="place_1000070">France</country></origPlace>
                     <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="1300" notBefore="1290">late thirteenth century</origDate>
                  </origin>
                  <provenance>There are no inscriptions in the book but there are the usual nail holes on the back cover for the College's medieval label, now lost. The manuscript was one of those given by the <persName role="dnr" key="person_34822618">Founder</persName>, according to the 1474 inventory: 'Item textus Methaphisice ex dono fundatoris 2<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> fo. <foreign>generum et esse omnium</foreign>' (A1. 91). At that time it was chained to the fourth desk on the south side of the library.</provenance>
                  <provenance><hi rend="italic">Labels and marks</hi>: No medieval marks of ownership. No James number but instead the 9-shaped mark over the start of the text on fol. 1r, which is found in books not discovered in the <title>Ecloga</title>. However, it is probably the 'Commentarii in Metaphysica Aristotelis' at entry no. 97 since the other candidate, Lat. 14, goes with a work of Augustine (which was the lead item in the Bernard catalogue listing). The eighteenth-century inked press-mark 'ff: 53: 2' in the outer corner of the first flyleaf recto. The College's bookplate of 1703 is pasted to the centre of the front pastedown, with the modern shelf-mark pencilled below: 'MS. Linc. Coll. (c) Lat. 19'. On the spine, two square labels: in the second compartment, the boldface printed numeral '19'; at the tail, the pale blue Bodleian printed label with the modern shelf-mark.</provenance>
                  <provenance><hi rend="italic">Booklists</hi>: Vetus Registrum, fol. 16v; James, <title>Ecloga</title>, no. 97; <title>CMA</title> 1/2. 1315.</provenance>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>Description by James Willoughby, 2026.</source>
                     </recordHist>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <ref target="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/mdp.39015028611856?urlappend=%3Bseq=656"> H. O. Coxe, <title>Catalogus codicum mss. qui in collegiis aulisque Oxoniensibus hodie adservantur</title> (Oxford, 1852)</ref>
                        <citedRange unit="volume">I</citedRange> [individual sections separately paginated], Lincoln College, <citedRange unit="page" from="24" to="25">pp. 24-25</citedRange> (open access at HathiTrust Digital Library)</bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <ref target="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/mdp.39015017028484?urlappend=%3Bseq=48">J. J. G. Alexander and Elżbieta Temple, <title>Illuminated manuscripts in Oxford College libraries, the University Archives, and the Taylor Institution</title> (Oxford, 1985)</ref>, no. <citedRange unit="entry">230</citedRange> (open access at HathiTrust Digital Library)</bibl>
                     <bibl>Thomson/Robinson, 1. 281 (no. 259).</bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2026-06">New description by James Willoughby</change>
         <change when="2021-06">First online publication.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p><!--body provided for validation and future transcription--></p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>