<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/msDesc/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/msDesc/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="manuscript_16183">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Lincoln College MS. Lat. 89</title>
            <title type="collection">Lincoln College MSS.</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp when="2026">Cataloguer</resp>
               <persName>James Willoughby</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp when="2026">Encoding</resp>
               <persName>Matthew Holford</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </publisher>
            <idno type="msID">Lincoln_College_MS_Lat_89</idno>
            <idno type="collection">Lincoln_College</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:lang="en" xml:id="Lincoln_College_MS_Lat_89">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <repository>Lincoln College</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">Lincoln College MS. Lat. 89</idno>
               <idno type="ieArk">ark:29072/b473666398c1</idno><idno type="crArk">ark:29072/b4707957152b</idno></msIdentifier>
               <head>(I) Ricardus Rolle, <title>Melos amoris</title> (II) Polyphonic music. England (Lincs?), (I) s. xv<hi rend="superscript">2/4</hi>, (II) s. xv<hi rend="superscript">2/4–3/4</hi></head>
               <msContents>
                  <summary>The volume gathers two fragments of larger paper books, both roughly coeval and perhaps bearing an intriguing inter-relationship, for some of the extensive notes on the <title>Melos amoris</title> in the first part show an interest in polyphonic music, which is represented in the second part. This is the largest source of English polyphonic kyries from the fifteenth century. Identified names rank among the most celebrated composers of fifteenth-century England: John Dunstable, John Plummer, and Leonel Power.</summary>
               </msContents>
               
               <physDesc>
                  <p><secFol>notandum solum</secFol></p>
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="chart">
                        <support>Paper. 
                           For both parts, leaves are very disordered and can represent only a fraction of the original books. Relationships between leaves are obscured by joints and mending at the spine. Paper and parchment guards and pasting slips at the spine-folds in pt I. 
                           
                           
                           Paper is grey and tattered, consolidated throughout at the edges and rebacked, with considerable portions of loss to part II. Deckle edges are cut square where they have not crumbled; elsewhere, edges are mounted. </support>
                        <extent>i (modern paper) + 31 + i (modern paper, foliated 32); flyleaves conjoint with pastedowns.
                           <dimensions unit="mm" type="leaf">
                              <height>295</height>
                              <width quantity="225">c. 225</width>
                           </dimensions>
                           
                        </extent>
                        <foliation>Foliated in early twentieth-century Bodleian pencil.</foliation>
                        <collation>1(10) (fols. 1–11, with an inserted singleton after the fifth) 2(4) (fols. 12–16, an inserted singleton after the second; another singleton lost after the third) 3(6) (fols. 17–22) 4(3) (fols. 23–25, three singletons) || 7(6) (fols. 26–31, wants sixth; first a misplaced singleton).</collation>
                     </supportDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  
                  <decoDesc>
                     <decoNote type="none">There are no initials or decoration to either part of the manuscript beyond red underlining of chapter incipits in part I; the main scribe also drew the maniculae and left spaces for initials that were never filled.</decoNote>
                  </decoDesc>
                  
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <binding notBefore="1600" notAfter="1625"><p>A tacketed seventeenth-century binding of vellum over millboard. Sewn on four whittawed thongs, not raised. No endbands or any signs of clasps or chains. The binding has been heavily repaired with resewing, patching of the cover on the lower board, recasing, and with lining and consolidation of the friable edges of the textblock. Pastedowns of modern paper, not conjoint with flyleaves.</p></binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <provenance>The inclusion in the margin of fol. 18r of an episode from the Life of St Guthlac would suggest reception, perhaps even origin, in the diocese of Lincoln: his cult by the fifteenth century was restricted mainly to its centre at Crowland. An episode from the Life of Eusebius is found in the marginalia on 20r: as Albin points out (<title>Richard Rolle’s Melody of Love</title>, 52), he was honoured alongside Augustine as the founder of the order of canons regular. An origin for the manuscript within a house of Augustinian canons would therefore be a possibility: hints of pastoral concerns which are often thought of as typically Augustinian may be found in the medical recipes and moral <foreign>exempla</foreign> of the marginalia. When and how the two parts of the manuscript became combined it is difficult to judge. The volume gives the impression of having been assembled to ‘preserve the fragments lest they be lost’, part II valued as a discrete item and not simply added by way of flyleaves. It may be necessary to look for no further connection between them than the word ‘melody’. Indeed, some of the annotations are concerned with song and singing as spiritual practice (1, 2r, 16r, 17v), and one of the <foreign>exempla</foreign> features ‘a certain student well schooled in chant with sweet and melodious voice’ (19r). It would be plausible to think of the two parts travelling together from an early time. ‘Their union may well have been an accident—a happy one to be sure—but this need not mean that subsequent readers would not have found that union significant’ (Albin, <title>Richard Rolle’s Melody of Love</title>, 377).</provenance>
                  <provenance>The time of the manuscript’s arrival at the College is unknown, but it is identifiable in the Bernard catalogue (1697), where the description ‘Tractatus Theologicus (ut videtur) De Unitate, Capitibus 47’ is a good match for an acephalous tract which has a prominent arabic numeral ‘47’ close to the end. It is probably also the ‘Liber chartaceus, imperfectus, de quibusdam notis Theologicis’ reported by Thomas James in his <title>Ecloga</title>. Gerard Langbaine did not construe that entry and so there is no James number in the manuscript such as he entered into other volumes. There is no evidence for any former owner or donor. </provenance>
                  <provenance><hi rend="italic">Labels and marks:</hi> the manuscript lacks the usual earlier marks of College ownership. The number ‘78’ is written in black ink near the top of the front cover. At the head of fol. 1r is ‘Linc. 89 C 22’ in black ink of s. xix/xx. The modern shelfmark in pencil on the front flyleaf recto is ‘MS. Linc. Coll. c. Lat. 89’.</provenance>
                  <provenance><hi rend="italic">Booklists</hi>: James, <title>Ecloga</title>, no. 60; CMA 1/2. 1363.</provenance>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>Description by James Willoughby, 2026.</source>
                     </recordHist>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <ref target="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/mdp.39015028611856?urlappend=%3Bseq=676"> H. O. Coxe, <title>Catalogus codicum mss. qui in collegiis aulisque Oxoniensibus hodie adservantur</title> (Oxford, 1852)</ref>
                        <citedRange unit="volume">I</citedRange> [individual sections separately paginated], Lincoln College, <citedRange unit="page" from="44" to="44">p. 44</citedRange> (open access at HathiTrust Digital Library)</bibl>
                     <bibl> A. Albin, <title>Richard Rolle’s Melody of Love: A Study and Translation with Manuscript and Musical Contexts</title> (Toronto 2018), 52–3 (manuscript), 346–73 (annotations), 374–406 (music)</bibl><bibl>E. J. F. Arnould, <title>The Melos Amoris of Richard Rolle of Hampole</title> (Oxford 1957), lxxiv </bibl><bibl>H. E. Allen, <title>Writings Ascribed to Richard Rolle, Hermit of Hampole and Materials for his Biography</title> (London 1927), 114 </bibl><bibl>A. I. Doyle &amp; R. Hanna, <title>Hope Allen’s Writings Ascribed to Richard Rolle: A Corrected List of Copies</title> (Turnhout 2019), 7–8. </bibl><bibl><title>Census-Catalogue of Manuscript Sources of Polyphonic Music 1400–1550</title>, in the updated online version at https://www.diamm.ac.uk/sources/561</bibl><bibl> A.-M. Seaman &amp; R. Rastall, ‘The music of Oxford, Bodleian Library, MS Lincoln College Latin 89’, <title>Royal Musical Association Research Chronicle</title> 13 (1976) 95–101</bibl><bibl> A.-M. Seaman, ‘The music of Oxford, Bodleian Library, MS Lincoln College Latin 89: a postscript’, <title>Royal Musical Association Research Chronicle</title> 14 (1978) 139–40</bibl><bibl> R. L. Greene, <title>The Early English Carols</title>, 2nd edn (Oxford 1977), 321.</bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
               <msPart xml:id="Lincoln_College_MS_Lat_29part_I">
                  <msIdentifier>
                     <altIdentifier type="partial">
                        <idno type="part">Lincoln College MS. Lat. 29 - I</idno>
                     </altIdentifier>
                  </msIdentifier>
                  <head>Ricardus Rolle, <title>Melos amoris</title>, England (Lincs.?), s. xv 2/4</head>
                  <msContents>
                     <textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>
                     <msItem n="1">
                        <locus>(fols. 1ra–25vb)</locus>
                        <incipit defective="true"> diuina benignitas disposuit quod eciam si voluero <lb/> secularibus me nequeo iungere ne occupacio au<lb/>ditus corporalis in nimia me precipitet perturbacionem</incipit>
                        <explicit defective="true">Siquidem plures sunt <lb/> qui uoluntatem peccandi perfecte non dimitten<lb/>tes multa que in saunctis libris scribuntur <lb/> uera esse non putant et tamen plerique presumentes  </explicit>
                        <author key="person_2465074">Richard Rolle (d. 1349)</author> <title key="work_4292">Melos amoris</title><note>Ed. E. J. F. Arnould, <title>The Melos Amoris of Richard Rolle of Hampole</title> (Oxford 1957), citing our manuscript as O<hi rend="superscript">3</hi>. F. Vandenbroucke, <title>Richard Rolle: Le Chant d’amour</title> (<title>Melos Amoris</title>), 2 vols (Paris 1971); Stegmüller <title>Bibl.</title> 7307,2; Allen, <title>Writings Ascribed to Richard Rolle</title>; Doyle &amp; Hanna, 7–8. This imperfect copy begins halfway through c. 4 and ends in c. 57, with c. 56 intervening between 52 and 53; c. 58 is missing. There are also large gaps in the text between certain leaves, revealing quite substantial losses: (1) 5v breaks off in the latter half of c. 11, ‘eo subtilius incendit’ (edn, p. 33, l. 11), resuming on 6r in the first half of c. 24, ‘Singuli scitote, superbus non sisto’ (p. 70, l. 31); (2) 11v breaks off in the first half of c. 32, ‘pro te circumcisus’ (p. 97, l. 13), resuming on 12r in the latter half of c. 38, ‘consurgunt in contemplacionem’ (p. 118, l. 21); (3) 15v breaks off in the second half of c. 43, ‘petit sic potatus’ (p. 135, l. 25), resuming on 16r in the middle of c. 45, ‘accepisti nobis denoda’ (p. 139, l. 139) (quiring would suggest the loss of a singleton). (4) Three singletons at the back are disordered (misreported by Arnould). Fol. 22v breaks in the second half of c. 52, ‘securus ab hac’ (p. 168, l. 28) and connects to 24r, ‘solicitudine secedat et per sinceram’ (p. 168, l. 28); 24v ends in the second half of c. 53 with ‘aduersus animam et purificans’ (p. 172, l. 31), after which there is a lacuna. Fol. 23r should follow but has been bound before; it starts near the start of c. 55 ‘ut non cadit <supplied>in</supplied> contagiis nec malo’ (p. 176, l. 20) and ends on 23v, near the start of c. 56, ‘exercitatione spiritualis operis’ (p. 180, l. 11), connecting to 25r, ‘omnia immunda et nociua desideria’ (p. 180, l. 11). In spite of these losses, this is one of only ten manuscripts containing substantially the complete text. </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <note>Fol. 26 is a mostly blank leaf which has a similar pattern of deterioration at the right-hand edge to the back leaf of part II, fol. 31, which it apparently followed and is therefore misplaced here. (There is no watermark.) On the recto are several scribbles of the fifteenth century; ‘Fuit homo missus a Deo, cui nomen era<damage><supplied>t Iohannes</supplied></damage>’ (i.e. John 1:6) is presumably from a setting for the Nativity of John the Baptist.</note>
                     </msItem>
                  </msContents>
                  <physDesc>
                     <objectDesc>
                        <supportDesc material="chart">
                           <support>Paper. Watermarks: There are two stocks: (i) bow and arrow centrally on twelve leaves, resembling Piccard IX (Werkzeug &amp; Waffen), X, 2, nos. 1482, 1493 (attested for AD 1386, provenances of Venice and Florence), horizontal chainlines close together; (ii) two crossed keys centrally (fol. 10), closely resembling Piccard VIII (Schlüssel), II, nos. 143–50 and Briquet 3839, 3841 (attested use 1382 × 1410, more widely dispersed).  </support>
                           <collation>One catchword, fol. 7v, written at the gutter just under the end of the text at the same size. </collation>
                        </supportDesc>
                        <layoutDesc>
                           <layout columns="2" writtenLines="48 52">No prickings or ruling apparent. Written in two columns with an intercolumnar space of around 10 mm, with lines varying between 48 and 53 to a page. Written space: <dimensions unit="mm" type="written">
                                 <height max="235" min="232">232-235</height>
                                 <width min="170" max="175">170-175</width>
                           </dimensions></layout>
                        </layoutDesc>
                     </objectDesc>
                     <handDesc>
                        <handNote script="cursivaAntiquior">One scribe writing a documentary Anglicana with no great consistency in size or aspect, varying according to pencut. Ink is pale brown. Punctuation is by <foreign>punctus</foreign>; new <foreign>sententiae</foreign> begin with a majuscule that is sometimes stroked with red. His is also the hand of the many marginal annotations made at other times, revealing it to have been a book copied for his own use. </handNote>
                     </handDesc>
                     <additions>
                        <p>There are many marginal additions of interest, these in the hand of the scribe whose personal book this seems to have been. In spite of published opinions to the contrary (Arnould: ‘there are numerous annotations in the margins, but, as far as they can be deciphered, they offer little interest for the intelligence of the text’; Hope Allen: ‘theological annotations (hardly legible)’), the annotations are neat and clearly written in a smaller version of the main text hand. They have been given full attention and are printed and translated by Albin, <title>Richard Rolle’s Melody of Love</title>, 346–65. They include theological excerpts drawn from Augustine, Jerome, and the Lombard’s Sentences, moral exempla, many of them involving the Virgin Mary, excerpts from the Lives of Sts Guthlac and Eusebius, and medical notes drawn from the <title>Pantegni</title>, <title>Viaticum</title>, and pseudo-Galen, with a particular interest in the humours and flux of blood. Arabic chapter numbers were added in the margin. A manicule is often found, drawn with an outsized, bulbous, jointed forefinger and wide-spreading cuff. Sometimes these are done in the red ink of the underlining and sometimes in the brown ink of the text. It would be sensible to consider these as also the work of the main hand.</p>
                     </additions>
                  </physDesc>
                  <history>
                     <origin>
                        <origPlace><country key="place_7002445">England</country> <region>(Lincs?)</region></origPlace>
                        <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="1450" notBefore="1425">s. xv 2/4</origDate>
                     </origin>
                  </history>
               </msPart>
               <msPart xml:id="Lincoln_College_MS_Lat_29part_II">
                  <msIdentifier>
                     <altIdentifier type="partial">
                        <idno type="part">Lincoln College MS. Lat. 29 - II</idno>
                     </altIdentifier>
                  </msIdentifier>
                  <head>Polyphonic music. England (Lincs?), s. xv 2/4-3/4</head>
                  <msContents>
                     <textLang mainLang="la" otherLangs="enm">Latin and Middle English</textLang>
                     <msItem n="2">
                        <locus>(fols. 27r–31v)</locus>
                        <note>Thirteen separate pieces of liturgical polyphonic music. It is a fragment of what appears to have been a <title key="work_12472">Kyriale</title>. </note><note>The foundational description is that by Rastall &amp; Seaman. ‘The music of Oxford, Bodleian Library, MS Lincoln College Latin 89’, based on A.-M. Seaman, ‘The Music of Lincoln College Ms Lat. 89 at the Bodleian Library, Oxford’, MPhil diss. (University of Leeds 1978). There is also useful discussion, and the contents are printed <foreign>in toto</foreign>, by Albin, <title>Richard Rolle’s Melody of Love</title>, 374–406. The contents (with additional printings) are as follows. (a) (fol. 27r) <persName key="person_12491221" role="aut">John Dunstable (c. 1390–1453)</persName>, <title>Beata mater</title>, a three-part Marian antiphon: ed. M. F. Bukofzer &amp; others, <title>John Dunstable Complete Works</title>, Musica Britannica 8 (London 1970), 110. (b) (27v) <foreign>Gloria</foreign> (anonymous), discantus part only: ed. P. Wright, <title>Fifteenth-Century Liturgical Music, 8: Settings of the Gloria and Credo</title>. Early English Church Music 55 (London 2013), 220–22. (c) (27v) A monophonic carol in English, burden and one verse only: ‘Man assay assay assay / and aske mercy quyle þat þu may / Man hafe mynd how herbefore / for thy mysdede þu was forlore / bot mercy th<supplied>o</supplied>w cry for cryst is bore / assay assay Man assay vt supra’: pr. Greene, <title>Early English Carols</title>, no. 359C. This has been added in a hand of the mid-century to empty staves at the foot of the page. Other versions are known, but the closest, and longer, version is in Oxford, Balliol College, MS 354 (s. xvi), but without musical setting (ibid. no. 359A), and Bodl. Arch. Selden B. 26 (SC 3340) (s. xvmed), with a different musical setting. (d) (28r) A complete three-part <title>Kyrie</title> in score, also found in PRO, E 163/22/1/3. (e) (28v) A three-part <title>Kyrie</title> in score. (f) (29r) Another three-part <title>Kyrie</title> in score. (g) (29v) <persName key="person_30686318" role="aut">John Plummer (c. 1410–c. 1484)</persName>, <title>Descendi in hortum meum ut viderem</title>, a three-part Marian antiphon: ed. B. Trowell, <title>John Plummer: Four Motets</title> (Banbury 1968), 13–15, no. 1, without sight of this manuscript. (h) (30r–31v) Three troped Kyries, ‘Cunctipotens genitor’, ‘Orbis factor’, and ‘Rex virginum amator Deus’. Fol. 30 is only a scrap and most of the content has gone. (i) (31v) <persName key="person_79169248" role="aut">Leonel Power (c. 1375–1445)</persName>, <title>Kyrie Lux et origo lucis</title>, fragmentary, discantus part only. There are also two textless sketches, perhaps exercises in counterpoint..</note>
                     </msItem>
                  </msContents>
                  <physDesc>
                     <objectDesc>
                        <supportDesc material="chart">
                           <support>Paper. Watermarks placed centrally and inverted in fols. 29 and 31, resembling Briquet 11859 and 11868, a triple mount inside a circle with a tall cross on the high central mount, dating 1399 and 1407 respectively; chainlines are vertical and c. 40 mm apart. </support>
                           <collation>Quire signatures from a former arrangement: ‘iij’ at the outer corner at the foot of fol. 28r and ‘ij’ on 29r, showing that these bifolia are in the wrong sequence, if they ever belonged to the same quire. The music is incomplete on 29v and 31r and not related, so these cannot have belonged together (see further Seaman &amp; Rastall, ‘Music of Oxford’, 98). </collation>
                        </supportDesc>
                        <layoutDesc>
                           <layout rulingMedium="leadpoint"> Written space: <dimensions unit="mm" type="written">
                                 <height quantity="240">c. 240</height>
                                 <width>190</width>
                           </dimensions>. Ruled in lead point for ten five-line staves. </layout>
                        </layoutDesc>
                     </objectDesc>
                     <handDesc hands="5">
                        <handNote script="cursivaAntiquior"> The script of the texts is cursive Anglicana, probably five different main hands: Scribe A, 27r; B, 27v, first eight lines; C, 27v, last two lines; D, 28r–29r, 30r–31v; E, 29v; with two further hands behind the musical jottings on fols. 27v and 31v. These are roughly coeval, the kyries and <title>Beata mater</title> comprising the earlier scribal performance, datable to c. 1425–1440 with respect to concordant sources; Scribe C belongs to the third quarter of the century. Ink in shades of brown.</handNote>
                     </handDesc>
                     <musicNotation>
                        <p>Notation is black void, no coloration, no semiminims.</p>
                     </musicNotation>
                     <additions>
                        <p>While not strictly an annotation, <title>Man assay</title> with its two lines of staves has been added in a later hand at the foot of fol. 27v. </p>
                     </additions>
                  </physDesc>
                  <history>
                     <origin>
                        <origPlace><country key="place_7002445">England</country> <region>(Lincs?)</region></origPlace>
                        <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="1475" notBefore="1425">s. xv 2/4-3/4</origDate>
                     </origin>
                  </history>
               </msPart>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2026-06">New description by James Willoughby.</change>
         <change when="2021-06">First online publication.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p><!--body provided for validation and future transcription--></p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>