<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/msDesc/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/msDesc/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="manuscript_16142" type="stub">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Lincoln College MS. Lat. 29</title>
            <title type="collection">Lincoln College MSS.</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp when="2026">Cataloguer</resp>
               <persName>James Willoughby</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp when="2026">Encoding</resp>
               <persName>Matthew Holford</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </publisher>
            <idno type="msID">Lincoln_College_MS_Lat_29</idno>
            <idno type="collection">Lincoln_College</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:lang="en" xml:id="Lincoln_College_MS_Lat_29">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <repository>Lincoln College</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">Lincoln College MS. Lat. 29</idno>
               <idno type="ieArk">ark:29072/b4s7526977x0</idno><idno type="crArk">ark:29072/b4s4655d94m4</idno></msIdentifier>
               <head>Willelmus Tornacensis, <title>Flores Bernardi</title>; England, s. xiv in.</head>
               <msContents>
                  <textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>
                  <msItem n="1">
                     <locus from="1ra" to="1rb">(fol. 1ra–b)</locus>
                     <incipit><add>Capitula primi libri</add> Quid est deus. 1. <lb/><lb/> Quod ubique est deus. 2. </incipit><explicit>De lapsu primi hominis <lb/> a dignitate status sui. 30. <add>31</add> <lb/><lb/> <add>De affinitate anime cum deo</add> <add>32</add> <lb/><lb/> <add>Quomodo cognoscit anima quod a <lb/> deo diligatur</add> <add>33</add> <lb/><lb/> <add>liber 2<hi rend="superscript">us</hi> incipit in folio <choice><sic>precedenti</sic> <corr>sequenti</corr></choice>.</add></explicit>
                     <note>A table of chapter headings and numbers to the first book down to c. 30, concluded half-heartedly by a second hand, leaving the chapter numbers to be added by a third.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="2">
                     <locus from="1v" to="8v">(fols. 1v–8v)</locus>
                     <incipit>Abissus de duplici abisso 7. 49 <lb/><lb/> Abstinencia de abstinencia 5. 29 <lb/><lb/> Actiua de actiua vita et contemplatiua 7. 70 </incipit><explicit> De diuersis modis quibus</explicit>
                     <note>An alphabetical index of contents by keyword, in which reference is to book and chapter in a column ranged at the right-hand side. The index appears to be <foreign>sui generis</foreign>. (It does not follow the index first printed by Johann Koelhoff the Elder at Cologne in 1482 [<title>Bod-inc</title> B-178]). This and the previous table, which ends at the foot of its recto, are on a discrete quire of eight, this one by a new scribe writing a cursive Anglicana of s. xiv<hi rend="superscript">in</hi>.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="3">
                     <locus from="9ra" to="187va">(fols. 9ra–187va)</locus>
                     <rubric type="prol">Par est in uerbis id odiferis opus herbis . Nempe gerit flores bernardi <lb/> nobiliores. incipit prologus sequentis operis.</rubric>
                     <incipit type="prol">Cum non essem alicui exercicio ma<lb/>gno opere occupatus; placuit <lb/> mihi ut opuscula uiri illustrissimi . . .</incipit>
                     <explicit type="prol"><locus>(9vb) . . .</locus> per annotationes ibi <lb/> iuxta se positas de signaui. Flagrat <lb/> bernardus sacer in dictis quasi nardus / Et quibus hic tractus liber est in<lb/>scripta redactus.</explicit>
                     <rubric> Incipit primus <lb/> liber exceptionum collectarum de <lb/> diuersis opusculis beati bern<lb/>ardi clareuallensis abbatis .| De eo quod est Deus. In libro v. de consideracione</rubric>
                     <incipit type="text">Quid est Deus? Qui est? Merito <lb/> quidem. Nil conpetentius eterni<lb/>tati que deus est . Si bonum . Si ma<lb/>gnum . Si beatum.</incipit>
                     <explicit type="text">posse <lb/> falli et fallere cauendum <sic>et</sic> <lb/> hoc et illud quia utrobique per<lb/>iculum.</explicit>
                     <author key="person_268598459">William of Tournai (s. xiii ex.)</author>
                     <title key="work_5103">Flores Bernardi</title>
                     <note>Pr. [Nuremberg not after 1470) (GW 3928), &amp;c.; Stegmüller <title>Bibl.</title> 1731,1; Bloomfield 1155. Books begin at fols. 25va (II), 37ra (III), 50ra (IV), 60rb (V), 85ra (VI), 100vb (VII), 124vb (VIII), 154rb (IX), 169vb (X).</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="4">
                     <locus from="187vb" to="188vb">(fols. 187vb–188vb)</locus>
                     <incipit>Quomodo potest custodiri humilitas <lb/> in sermo . De labore messis 8. <lb/><lb/> De timore 9. </incipit><explicit> De duabus sanguissuge filiabus vt supra 40.</explicit>
                     <note>A curiously partial table of chapter headings, beginning at the top of the column in V 8 and extending to VII 40. The hand is similar to, but distinct from, the second hand of item 1.</note>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <p><secFol>De simplicitate <locus>(tab, fol. 2r)</locus></secFol><secFol> Quid est deus <locus>(text, fol. 10r)</locus></secFol></p>
                  
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="perg">
                        <support>Parchment. Parchment is thin and pliant, slightly cockled. It has a suede-like nap, even on the flesh-side. Arranged like to like, flesh-side outermost. On fol. 41 a large hole was patched with a circular piece of parchment before writing; this patch has now fallen away and is tipped in. A flaw was stitched at fol. 111, the thread now missing. Natural edges at fols. 50, 51, 63, 77, 135, 164. Holes have been written around on fols. 10, 15, 62, 86, 89, 155, 160, and stitched on 139.</support>
                        <extent>i + 191 (flyleaf of early-modern vellum, three rear flyleaves [189–191] of medieval parchment, conjoint with rear pastedown).<dimensions unit="mm" type="leaf"><height>180</height><width>124</width></dimensions><dimensions unit="mm" type="written"><height>126</height><width>85</width></dimensions></extent><foliation>i + 191, counting the inserted front leaf, in early twentieth-century Bodleian pencil.</foliation><collation mainStructures="12">Collation impracticable, but seemingly mostly quires of twelve. No catchwords or quire signatures.</collation>
                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout rulingMedium="leadpoint" columns="2" writtenLines="36">Ruled in faint lead point for two columns of 36 lines with an intercolumnar space of 7 mm. Outer bounding rules are doubles on both axes and run full measure; there is a central line between the single rules separating the columns. A further tramline is ruled right across the top, 6 mm above the text box, for running heads. No visible prickings.</layout>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc hands="2">
                     <handNote script="textualisNorthern">The work of two collaborating scribes, both using <foreign>littera textualis rotunda</foreign> as a small-scale bookhand. The general aspect on the page is dense and black with rather squat forms tight to the line. It suggests university production. Scribe A writes from the beginning to the end of fol. 116v. His ascenders are shortened and finished with a flat-topped, triangular serif; <hi rend="italic">d</hi> is routinely uncial with a notably shortened upper limb, rather like a stalk that hardly breaks the headline. The shape <hi  rend="italic">v</hi> for <hi rend="italic">u</hi> in initial position is routine; <foreign>set</foreign> for <foreign>sed</foreign>.</handNote>
                     <handNote>Scribe B writes from the start of fol. 117r to the end. His letters are firmer; lower bowl of <hi  rend="italic">g</hi> is rounder; serifs are not flat; the upper limb of uncial <hi rend="italic">d</hi> is a natural rounded extension; upright <hi rend="italic">d</hi> is found in initial position when not in fusion. Ink is black for most of the manuscript, a little browner for Scribe B’s portion. Initials at the start of a new sententia are stroked with red by Scribe A, giving up on 92v. Each scribe was responsible for the red-ink rubrication in his own portion. Scribe A punctuates by punctus elevatus, punctus versus, and punctus, also punctus interrogativus. Scribe B uses only the punctus.</handNote>
                  </handDesc>
                  <decoDesc>
                     <decoNote type="flourInit">Penwork decoration throughout by one hand. Only the first initials for the final three books are given special treatment. Book and chapter initials are otherwise modest two-line red or blue lombards with flourishing in the opposing colour extending into the margins; the penwork patterning is quite tight with curlicules rather than sprays. The larger initials stand at the front of Bks VIII, IX, X, fols. 124vb, 154rb, 169vb. The first of these is a plain blue lombard of four lines with red flourishing and extensions of a more elaborate kind; the latter two are five-line puzzle initials, red and blue, with more expansive flourishing in both colours.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="rubrication">Rubrication in red ink was missed between 97v and 117r, and the chapter heading was added later in black (see Annotations).</decoNote>
                  </decoDesc>
                  <additions>
                     <p>The manuscript has almost no verbal annotations or nota marks but does show thorough evidence of reading and indexing. Several annotators may be distinguished. On an added quire at the front, a table of chapter headings was begun (s. xiv<hi rend="superscript">in</hi>), continued by two other hands (s. xiv/xv) and a third gave it a title (s. xiv<hi rend="superscript">in</hi>), before another wrote a more successful index of contents in the remainder of the quire (s. xiv<hi rend="superscript">in</hi>). At the back, another partial table of chapters was written by another hand (s. xv<hi rend="superscript">in</hi>). One man wrote an arabic numeral for the book number as a running head, centred on each recto and verso side. Differences in the ink show it was someone else again who wrote chapter numbers in the margins, in the form “Cm. 31”, and he also supplied chapter headings where the rubrication had been missed; this begins on 97v and continues to 111r; the rubrication picks up again on the verso, but the hand writes no more, as if he had forgotten that chapter numbering had been his original task before he also began supplying headings. Instead, chapter numbers for the rest of the manuscript are given by another hand, roughly coeval, using a grey ink. Only the first two columns are numbered (fol. 9r), an arabic 1 and 2 centred at the top of cols a and b respectively. Most significant of all is the arabic numbering for the lineation, in fives down the central intercolumnar space. This starts at the beginning and gives up at 44v. It represents a scheme designed to assist referencing and indexing that is thought to have originated in mendicant practice in the mid-thirteenth century, and is strongly associated with university manuscripts from Oxford. This sort of arabic line numbering is discussed by R. Hanna, “Graham Pollard and ‘Oxford <foreign>peciae</foreign>’: false starts and discoveries”, <title>The Library</title>, 7th ser. 25 (2024) 289–312, including our manuscript as no. 55 in the listing of examples.</p>
                  </additions>
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <binding notBefore="1375" notAfter="1425"><p>A medieval binding, contemporary with the text-block, of vellum over wooden (?oak) boards, a slight bevel and with a small overhang at head and fore-edge, flush at the tail due to settling over time. The covering is discoloured but in good condition; it has been rebacked and there is some patching, notably at the corners of the back board and all down next to the fore-edge on the front. Sewn on five double whittawed leather thongs, raised at the spine. Endbands seem to be structural and have herringbone sewing around what is probably an alum-tawed leather core. Fore-edge is stained red. On the back board is found evidence for clasping and, apparently, chaining. A hole at the centre relates to a strap-and-pin clasp, the stub of the strap being detectable under the recover. At the fore-edge of the back board are two holes with plugged textile ties cut flush; the housings for the pairs on the front board are detectable under the cover. Two large holes 65 mm apart towards the foot of the back board have verdigris traces and belong probably to a chain staple. The College’s usual early-modern brass clip was secured at the head of the back board. It seems to have been applied over the rear flyleaves. At some stage, someone cut around the clip to release the leaves, perhaps hunting for text. When the clip was finally removed it took the pastedown underneath with it; this scar was then masked with a tongue of parchment extending from the corner patch. Also on the back board are the marks of the medieval title-piece, the fixtures gone but the label itself now pasted to fol. 8v (see <hi rend="italic">Labels and Marks</hi>). The space bounded by the six nail holes, two rows of three, is 77 × 20 mm, dimensions only slightly larger than those of the slip itself. The front pastedown is made from scraps of early-modern paper, one with writing (see above). The rear flyleaves are stout leaves of medieval parchment, conjoint with the pastedown.</p>
                        <p>The front pastedown is, inverted, a scrap of paper from a philosophical tract on universals, in a hand of s. xvi/xvii, beginning ‘Subiectum eius est praedicabile. Est autem praedicabile siue uniuersale quod aptum natum est praedicari de pluribus’, and then a summary of the five predicables. This appears to be drawn from the definition provided by Petrus Hispanus in his <title>Summulae logicales</title>, tract. 2.</p></binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origDate notAfter="1325" notBefore="1300" calendar="Gregorian">s. xiv in.</origDate>
                     <origPlace><country key="place_7002445">England</country>, probably <settlement key="place_7011931">Oxford</settlement></origPlace>
                  </origin>
                  <provenance>The manuscript was probably made in Oxford, and details of its annotation would certainly suggest that it was being read there. It was acquired early in its life by—perhaps it was even commissioned for—<persName role="fmo" key="person_34822618">Bishop Richard Flemming</persName>, and it was given by him to his new college, as is affirmed by the medieval title-piece (see Labels and Marks). It was given its present binding at this time. Its subsequent history in the collection is quiet. It does not appear in the 1474 inventory but may have been held in the electio stock at that time (albeit there is evidence on the back board for chaining at some point in its history). </provenance>
                  <provenance><hi rend="italic">Booklists</hi>: James, <title>Ecloga</title>, no. 24; <title>CMA</title> 1/2. 1374.</provenance>
                  <provenance><hi rend="italic">Labels and marks:</hi> The parchment title-piece from the medieval binding is pasted at the foot of fol. 8v. Measuring 14 × 74 mm, in the usual Textura hand it reads, ‘Flores Bernardi cum tabula | Ex dono fundatoris.’ The James number ‘24’ is in brown ink at the top of the same page. The College bookplate of 1703 is pasted at the top of the recto of the first flyleaf, not the normal position on the inner board. Was this done to avoid obscuring the writing on the manuscript pastedown? In the usual hand, the press-mark ‘E. 45. 10’ is written above the start of the main text on fol. 9r; it was repeated by another hand more accessibly at the front of the book, fol. 1r. The modern shelf-mark is at the foot of that same leaf: ‘MS. Linc. Coll. (e) Lat. 29’. On the spine, two square paper labels: at the head, a boldface ‘29’ in print; at the tail, the pale blue Bodleian label with ‘MS. Linc. Coll. E Lat. 29’, in print.</provenance>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>Description by James Willoughby, 2026.</source>
                     </recordHist>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <ref target="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/mdp.39015028611856?urlappend=%3Bseq=659"> H. O. Coxe, <title>Catalogus codicum mss. qui in collegiis aulisque Oxoniensibus hodie adservantur</title> (Oxford, 1852)</ref>
                        <citedRange unit="volume">I</citedRange> [individual sections separately paginated], Lincoln College, <citedRange unit="page" from="27" to="28">pp. 27-28</citedRange> (open access at HathiTrust Digital Library)</bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2026-06">Description by James Willoughby.</change>
         <change when="2021-06">First online publication.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p><!--body provided for validation and future transcription--></p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>