<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xml:id="manuscript_1574" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>MS. Bodl. 554</title>
            <title type="collection">MSS. Bodl. (Bodley)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Description</resp>
               <persName>Elizabeth Solopova</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Revision</resp>
               <persName>Andrew Dunning</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </publisher>
            <idno type="msID">MS_Bodl_554</idno>
            <idno type="collection">Bodl</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="MS_Bodl_554" xml:lang="en">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <region type="county">Oxfordshire</region>
                  <settlement key="place_7011931">Oxford</settlement>
                  <institution>University of Oxford</institution>
                  <repository>Bodleian Library</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">MS. Bodl. 554</idno>
                  <idno type="ieArk">ark:29072/x0nc580m58nd</idno>
                  <idno type="crArk">ark:29072/x0n870zq75bf</idno>
                  <altIdentifier type="internal">
                     <idno type="SCN">2326</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents>
                  <textLang mainLang="enm" otherLangs="la">Middle English with Latin</textLang>
                  <msItem>
                     <note>Fol. i is a parchment flyleaf, mostly blank.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="1">
                     <locus from="1r" to="81r">(fols. 1r–81r)</locus>
                     <title key="work_14082" type="desc">Psalms 1–150 in the Later Version of the Wycliffite Bible</title>
                     <note>In the biblical order, written as prose, with English titles in red and numbers as part of titles. Latin incipits are written in red in the margins or on lines containing the titles up to fol. 21v, and immediately preceding the English opening words of each psalm afterwards. Psalms 1–43, therefore, have English initials, whereas psalms 44–150 have initials of their Latin incipits. Some incipits have errors (e.g., <q>D<ex>omi</ex>ne est t<ex>er</ex>ra</q> for <q>Domini est terra</q>, fol. 10v). There are textual divisions at psalms 26, 38, 52, 68, 80, 97 and 109 (see Decoration). Subdivisions within psalms are not indicated, apart from psalm 118, subdivided into twenty-two 8-verse units. The seven Penitential Psalms are marked with Roman numerals in the margins in a medieval hand. Punctuated throughout with <foreign rend="italic">punctus</foreign> used to mark the ends of verses and minor pauses, and <foreign rend="italic">punctus elevatus</foreign> used to mark <foreign rend="italic">metrum</foreign>. Extensive glosses in English in the margins throughout, including glosses on the titles, glosses explaining difficult readings and giving spiritual, moral and literal interpretation of psalms. Some glosses comment on the differences between the Latin and Hebrew texts. The glosses (apart from the title glosses which appear in the margins at the beginning of psalms) are linked to their lemmata by special signs, placed at the beginning of the gloss and above the word on which it comments (red circles with a stroke and similar). Most glosses derive from Nicholas of Lyra’s <foreign rend="italic">Postilles</foreign>, but some from Augustine’s <title>Enarrationes in Psalmos</title>, Jerome and Cassiodorus, often cited through Lyra, as well as from the <q>comun glos</q> or <title>Glossa Ordinaria</title> (Kuczynski (1994), p. 24; Dove, M., <title>The first English Bible: the text and context of the Wycliffite versions</title> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2007), p. 161 n. 144). The sources of most glosses are stated at their end (e.g., <q>lire here</q>, <q>austin here</q> in red ink). MS. Bodl. 554 preserves the Wycliffite psalter glosses better than any other manuscript (Dove, M., <title>The first English Bible: the text and context of the Wycliffite versions</title> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2007), p. 161). Most the Later Version of the Wycliffite Bible manuscripts include title glosses (that serve as prologues of psalms) as far as psalm 72, and a few include such glosses afterwards; MS. Bodl. 554 includes such glosses for all psalms (Dove, M., <title>The first English Bible: the text and context of the Wycliffite versions</title> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2007), p. 156).</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="2">
                     <locus from="81r" to="81v">(fol. 81r–v)</locus>
                     <title type="desc">Prayer of Manasseh</title>
                     <rubric>Here bigynneþ þe preier of manasses kyng of iuda</rubric>
                     <incipit>Lord god almyȝti of oure fadris abraham ysaac &amp; iacob &amp; of her iust seed</incipit>
                     <note>Glosses in the margins.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="3">
                     <locus from="81v" to="86r">(fol. 81v–86r)</locus>
                     <title type="desc">Weekly canticles</title>
                     <note>With references to their Old Testament sources in the margins in the hand of the original rubricator. Each is preceded by a Latin incipit, some with errors (i.e., <q>domino</q> for <q>domini</q>, <q>ira</q> for <q>iratus</q> in <foreign rend="italic">Confitebor</foreign>). Glosses in the margins of <foreign rend="italic">Confitebor</foreign> and <foreign rend="italic">Ego dixi,</foreign> fols. 81v–82r, derived entirely from Lyra (Dove, M., <title>The first English Bible: the text and context of the Wycliffite versions</title> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2007), p. 161 n. 144).</note>
                     <msItem>
                        <incipit>Confitebor tibi domino quoniam ira</incipit>
                        <incipit>Lord i shal knouleche to þe…</incipit>
                        <bibl>(Isaiah 12)</bibl>
                        <rubric>ysaie 12</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <incipit>Ego dixi</incipit>
                        <incipit>I seide in þe myddil of my daies</incipit>
                        <bibl>(Isaiah 38:10–21)</bibl>
                        <rubric>ysaie 38</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <incipit>Exultauit cor meum in domino</incipit>
                        <incipit>Myn herte fulli ioiede</incipit>
                        <bibl>(1 Samuel 2:1–11)</bibl>
                        <rubric>pº Regum pº</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <incipit>Cantemus domino</incipit>
                        <incipit>Synge we to þe lord</incipit>
                        <bibl>(Exodus 15:1–20)</bibl>
                        <rubric>exodi 15</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <incipit>Domine audiui</incipit>
                        <incipit>Lord I herde þyn heryng</incipit>
                        <bibl>(Habacuc 3)</bibl>
                        <rubric>abacuk 3</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <incipit>Audite celi que loquar</incipit>
                        <incipit>Ȝe heuenes here</incipit>
                        <bibl>(Deuteronomy 32:1–44)</bibl>
                        <rubric>deutronomii 32</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="4">
                     <locus from="86r" to="87v">(fols. 86r–87v)</locus>
                     <title type="desc">Daily canticles with references to their sources</title>
                     <msItem>
                        <incipit>Benedicite omnia opera domini domino</incipit>
                        <incipit>Alle werkis of þe lord</incipit>
                        <rubric>Danyel 3</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="2">
                        <incipit>Benedictus dominus deus israel</incipit>
                        <incipit>Blessid be þe lord</incipit>
                        <rubric>luce pº</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <incipit>Magnificat anima mea</incipit>
                        <incipit>Mi soule magnefieþ</incipit>
                        <rubric>luce pº</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <incipit>Nunc dimittis</incipit>
                        <incipit>Lord now þou leeuest þi seruaunt</incipit>
                        <rubric>luce 2</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <note>Followed by a rubric <q><supplied>t</supplied>e deum laudamus</q> in red, apparently in the hand of the original rubricator, but the initial is not filled in and the rest of the page is blank.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="5">
                     <locus from="88r">(fol. 88r)</locus>
                     <author key="person_24637109">John Beleth</author>
                     <title key="work_2623">Summa de ecclesiasticis officiis</title>
                     <note>Extract added in the third quarter of the 15th century in a mixed Anglicana/ Secretary hand. The extract is partly a copy and partly a summary of chapters 122, 123 and 128 (Douteil (1976), cols. 128–130), telling stories about the introduction of <foreign rend="italic">letania maior</foreign> by Gregory the Great during an epidemic in Rome, and of the institution of <foreign rend="italic">letania minor</foreign> by St Mamertus, Bishop of Vienne, during the earthquakes and other disasters at the end of the fifth century (published by Solopova (2012)).</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="6">
                     <locus from="88v" to="89r">(fol. 88v–89r)</locus>
                     <author key="person_2465074">Richard Rolle</author>
                     <title key="work_4287">Form of Living</title>
                     <note>An extract, added probably in a different 15th-century hand, from chapter 6, consisting of a list of the sins of thought, word, deed and omission (published by Kuczynski (1994)).</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem>
                     <locus>(lower pastedown)</locus>
                     <msItem>
                        <note>Casually written 1-line inscription in a late 15th-century hand, possibly <q>Thes ben þe p<ex>ro</ex>fessollyng en Joh<ex>a</ex>n belet</q> or <q>Thes ben [th]e prosesses oweng cu Iohan Beket</q>; more erased text above the inscription. Possibly in the hand which added the price at the bottom of the pastedown (see Provenance).</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <note>Medical recipe <q>To provok vryne</q>, in English, in a hand of the first half of the 16th century.</note>
                     </msItem>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="perg">
                        <support>parchment</support>
                        <extent><measure type="leaf" quantity="90">90</measure> leaves, <foreign rend="italic">c.</foreign><dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                              <height>231</height>
                              <width>165</width>
                           </dimensions>; the leaves were trimmed in rebinding, occasionally causing the loss of text in the margins</extent>
                        <foliation>modern in ink; i + 1–89</foliation>
                        <collation><locus from="i" to="i">(fol. i)</locus> parchment flyleaf | <locus from="1" to="88">(fols. 1–88)</locus> I–XI (8) | <locus from="89" to="89">(fol. 89)</locus> parchment flyleaf conjoint with the lower pastedown. <catchwords>Catchwords survive.</catchwords>
                           <signatures>Leaf signatures run consecutively a–l.</signatures>
                           <secFol><q>hast ȝoue</q></secFol>
                        </collation>
                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout columns="1" writtenLines="31">ruled in ink for a single column with single vertical and horizontal bounding lines extending the full height and width of page, and a further set of bounding lines for the gloss; 31 line per page; written space <foreign rend="italic">c.</foreign><dimensions type="ruled" unit="mm">
                              <height>114</height>
                              <width>92</width>
                           </dimensions></layout>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc>
                     <handNote script="textualisNorthern">textura (psalms) and Anglicana (glosses), black ink</handNote>
                  </handDesc>
                  <decoDesc>
                     <decoNote type="flourInit">3- to 4-line blue initials with red penwork at liturgical divisions at psalms 26 <locus from="12r" to="12r">(fol. 12r)</locus>, 38 <locus from="19r" to="19r">(fol. 19r)</locus>, 52 <locus from="26v" to="26v">(fol. 26v)</locus>, 68 <locus from="34v" to="34v">(fol. 34v)</locus>, 80 <locus from="44r" to="44r">(fol. 44r)</locus>, 97 <locus from="52v" to="52v">(fol. 52v)</locus> and 109 <locus from="62r" to="62r">(fol. 62r)</locus>.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="flourInit">2-line similar initials at the beginnings of psalms and canticles.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="colInit">1-line plain red or occasionally blue initials at the beginnings of verses.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="rubrication">Rubrics in red ink.</decoNote>
                  </decoDesc>
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <binding notAfter="1500" notBefore="1400">
                        <p>Fifteenth-century binding, worn red leather over boards, fittings of two clasps, now lost, on both covers. Sewn on five cords. ‘554’ written on spine in black ink. Parchment pastedowns. A chain-staple mark on the lower edge of the upper board (Watson’s position 4) (Hanna (2010)).</p>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origPlace>
                        <country key="place_7002445">England</country>
                     </origPlace>
                     <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="1419" notBefore="1400">15th century, early</origDate>
                     <p>Probably unfinished (see Text). Less professionally produced than many WB manuscripts (errors in Latin; the gloss is written without ruling; red ink spills on fols. 12v, 74r–v, 77r, 78v, etc.; wrong gloss entered and crossed out on fol. 30v).</p>
                     <p>Dialect survey: <list>
                           <item>ony(10), ech(10), fier(10), ȝoue(10), lijf(10), lijk(10), myche(10), siȝ(6)/siȝe(1) (sg.), sien(7)/siȝen(1) (pl.), silf(10), thouȝ(2), þorou(5)</item>
                           <item>-iþ(9)/-eþ(1) (pres.ind.3sg.), -en(10) (pres.ind.pl.), -ynge(9)/-yng(1) (pres. part.), she(1) (3sg.fem.pronoun, nom.), þei(9)/thei(1) (3pl.pronoun, nom.), hem(10) (3pl.pronoun, oblique), her(10) (3pl.pronoun, possessive)</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                  </origin>
                  <provenance>Fifteenth-century clerical (?) owners interested in liturgy (Latin extract from Beleth) and penitential practice (English extract from Rolle).</provenance>
                  <provenance>On the lower pastedown: <q>p<ex>re</ex>c<ex>ium</ex> x s</q>, presumably ‘price 10 shillings’, 15th century. Inscription, possibly in the same hand, perhaps containing the name ‘John Beket’.</provenance>
                  <provenance>Sixteenth-century owner who added a medical recipe.</provenance>
                  <provenance>‘A. P. 7. 13’ on the upper pastedown.</provenance>
                  <acquisition when="1607">Bodleian Library: probably a gift in 1607 of <persName key="person_2956" role="dnr">Sir Richard Wolseley</persName> described as <q>Liber continens expositionem vel glossam in Psalmos Anglice. 4º. MS</q> (Madan, F. and Craster, H. H. E., <title>Summary catalogue of western manuscripts in the Bodleian Library at Oxford</title>, vol. 2, part I <title>(collections received before 1660 and miscellaneous MSS acquired during the first half of the 17th century), nos. 1–3490</title> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1922)). Earlier shelfmarks: ‘Th. P 914’, ‘NE E. 6. 7’.</acquisition>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>Elizabeth Solopova, <title><ref target="https://jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1gn6cmr">Manuscripts of the Wycliffite Bible in the Bodleian and Oxford College Libraries</ref></title>, Exeter Medieval Texts and Studies (Liverpool: Liverpool University Press, 2016), no. 6. Previously described: <listBibl>
                              <bibl facs="aap0332.gif" type="SC">Summary Catalogue, vol. 2, part 1, p. 311</bibl>
                           </listBibl>
                        </source>
                     </recordHist>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl type="WRAPPER">
                     <listBibl type="PRINT">
                        <bibl>Forshall, J. and Madden, F. (eds), <title>The Holy Bible … in the earliest English versions made from the Latin Vulgate by John Wycliffe and his followers</title>, 4 vols (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1850), vol. 1, p. xlviii.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Madan, F. and Craster, H. H. E., <title>Summary catalogue of western manuscripts in the Bodleian Library at Oxford</title>, vol. 2, part I <title>(collections received before 1660 and miscellaneous MSS acquired during the first half of the 17th century), nos. 1–3490</title> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1922), no. 2326.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Deanesly, M., <title>The Lollard Bible and other medieval biblical versions</title> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1920), p. 381.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Hargreaves, H., ‘The Latin text of Purvey’s psalter’, <title>Medium Aevum</title> 24 (1955), pp. 73–90 at pp. 88, 90.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Douteil, H. (ed.), <title>Iohannis Beleth Summa de ecclesiasticis officiis</title>, 2 vols, <title>Corpus Christianorum. Continuatio Mediaevalis</title>; 41–41a (Turnholti: Brepols, 1976).</bibl>
                        <bibl>Ogilvie-Thomson, S. J., <title>Index of Middle English prose</title>, 18 vols (Cambridge, 1984– ), Handlist VIII (1991), pp. 74, 75, 94.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Kuczynski, M. P., ‘A fragment of Richard Rolle’s <title>Form of Living</title> in MS. Bodley 554’, <title>Bodleian Library Record</title> 15 (1994), pp. 20–32.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Kuczynski, M. P., <title>Prophetic song: the psalms as moral discourse in late Medieval England</title> (Philadelphia: University of Pennsylvania Press, 1995), pp. 21, 71–4 (pl. 3), 173, 180, 214, 255 n. 16.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Kuczynski, M. P., ‘Rolle among the reformers: orthodoxy and heterodoxy in Wycliffite copies of Richard Rolle’s English Pslater’, in Pollard, W. F. and Boenig, R. (eds), <title>Mysticism and spirituality in medieval England</title> (Woodbridge: D. S. Brewer, 1997), pp. 191–5 and <foreign rend="italic">passim</foreign>.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Hanna, R., <title>Index of Middle English prose</title>, 18 vols (Cambridge, 1984– ), Handlist XII, p. 5.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Kuczynski, M. P., ‘An “electric stream”: the religious contents’ in Fein, S. (ed.), <title>Studies in the Harley manuscript: the scribes, contents, and social contexts of British Library MS. Harley 2253</title> (Kalamazoo, Mich.: Medieval Institute Publications, Western Michigan University, 2000), pp. 123–61 at pp. 148–9.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Dove, M., <title>The first English Bible: the text and context of the Wycliffite versions</title> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2007), pp. 156, 161, 170, 183, 210, 216, 217, 218, 219, 229, 298–9; siglum B-554.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Hanna, R., <title>The English manuscripts of Richard Rolle: a descriptive catalogue</title> (Exeter: University of Exeter, 2010), pp. 139–40.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Solopova, E., ‘A previously unidentified extract about the litany in a Wycliffite psalter (Oxford, Bodleian Library, MS. Bodl. 554)’, <title>Bodleian Library Record</title> 24 (2011), pp. 217–23.</bibl>
                     </listBibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2023-03-24">Add Solopova description.</change>
         <change when="2022-04-04">Add binding information from Summary Catalogue.</change>
         <change when="2017-07-01">First online publication.</change>
         <change when="2017-05-25">
            <persName>James Cummings</persName> Up-converted the markup using <ref target="https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl">https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl</ref>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
