<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/msDesc/consolidated-tei-schema/refs/heads/master/msdesc-mmol.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:msdesc="http://www.example.org/ns/msdesc" xml:id="manuscript_1423">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>MS. Bodl. 392</title>
            <title type="collection">MSS. Bodl. (Bodley)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Summary description</resp>
               <persName>Elizabeth Solopova</persName>
               <persName>Matthew Holford</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </publisher>
            <idno type="msID">MS_Bodl_392</idno>
            <idno type="collection">Bodl</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="MS_Bodl_392" xml:lang="en">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <region type="county">Oxfordshire</region>
                  <settlement key="place_7011931">Oxford</settlement>
                  <institution>University of Oxford</institution>
                  <repository>Bodleian Library</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">MS. Bodl. 392</idno>
                  <idno type="ieArk">ark:29072/x0n870zq7592</idno><idno type="crArk">ark:29072/x0n583xt9206</idno><altIdentifier type="internal">
                     <idno type="SCN">2223</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents>
                  <msItem class="#sermones" n="1" xml:id="MS_Bodl_392-item1">
                     <title key="work_14583" type="desc">Sermons</title>
                     <textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="perg">
                        <support>parchment</support>
                     </supportDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <decoDesc>
                     <decoNote>Ornamental capitals.</decoNote>
                  </decoDesc>
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <summary><p>English, Salisbury 11th century, second half, inboard binding, date and place of binding as manuscript, with a ‘Romanesque’ structure (cf. Szirmai, pp. 140-142); the sewing supports laced through oblong tunnels in the spine edge of the oak boards. Covered with alum-tawed skin and probably originally with spine tabs, held closed with a single left-to-right long pin strap. </p>
                        <p>This binding, with MS. Bodl. 444, Part 1 and MS. Rawl. C. 723, form a group of related Salisbury bindings with exaggerated canted spine-edge corners to their bookblocks. This canted spine-edge trim is much greater than usually found on bindings with a ‘Romanesque’ structure and is much greater than required to accommodate the endbands; although none of the three bindings are now complete they form an identifiable group.</p> 
                        
                        <p>The binding was altered in 1602 either for Sir Walter Cope, or at Oxford following his donation to the Bodleian. The projecting tabs above the endbands and the single left-to-right long pin strap and pin were removed, and the bookblock edges were coloured yellow/green. The volume was recovered with alum-tawed sheepskin and fore-edge ties were added.  An additional blank leaf was added as a new left pastedown (fol. i), and the earlier free endleaf (fol. 63) was put down as the right pastedown. For similar work to other Cope manuscripts donated to the Bodleian see Watson, ‘The Manuscript Collection of Sir Walter Cope (d. 1614)’, BLR 12:4 (1987), pp. 262-297, at pp. 270-271, this binding (B15) at p. 294. The binding was rebacked for the Bodleian in the late 19th or early 20th century and both layers of earlier spine coverings are now lost. Although the binding has been altered and then rebacked it remains the first binding of the manuscript.</p>
                        
                        <p>There are brown stains of unknown cause to fols. 14v-15r; similar unexplained brown stains are also found in other Bodleian manuscripts with a Salisbury provenance: MS. Arch. Selden B. 26, MSS. Bodl. 407, 444, 516, and at least nine manuscripts still at Salisbury (information from Anne Dutton, Cathedral Librarian).</p>
                        <dimensions type="binding" unit="mm">
                           <height>276</height>
                           <width>183</width>
                           <depth>41</depth>
                           
                        </dimensions>
                        <p>The bookbinding is described in the order of binding using the controlled vocabulary of the Language of Bindings Thesaurus (LoB).</p><p>Bookbinding description by Andrew Honey (March 2026).</p>
                     </summary>
                     <binding notBefore="1050" notAfter="1100" type="inboard" subtype="firstBinding" structure="romanesque">
                        <head>First binding, <origPlace>Salisbury</origPlace>, 11th century, second half</head>
                        <!--<history><origin><origPlace><country>England</country>, <settlement>Salisbury</settlement></origPlace><origDate notAfter="1100" notBefore="1050">11th century, second half</origDate></origin></history>
                        --><msdesc:endleaves type="separate" support="perg" subtype="firstUse">Left: Separate endleaves. An unfoliated parchment pastedown before fol. i, now partly covered by the turn-ins of the 1602 covering.</msdesc:endleaves>
                        <msdesc:endleaves type="separate" support="perg" subtype="firstUse">Right: Separate endleaves. A blank parchment bifolium consisting of fol. 63, a free endleaf, and an unfoliated pastedown after fol. 63. The pastedown is partly covered by the turn-ins of the later covering. The bifolium is now split entirely at the joint. 
                           
                        </msdesc:endleaves>
                        <msdesc:sewing sewing="supported" supports="2">Sewn all-along with undyed plain thread at four sewing stations on two raised sewing supports. Sewing stations (measured in mm from the head-edge at fols. 42v-43r): 50 (kettle), 93 (support 1), 179 (support 2), 222 (kettle), 270 (tail). There are no earlier sewing stations.</msdesc:sewing>
                        <msdesc:boards material="wood" squares="false" reused="false">Wooden oak boards the size of the bookblock, 8-12 mm thick (including two layers of covering material), wood identified from grain pattern where exposed. Both boards are wedge shaped, the spine edge is noticeably thicker than the fore-edge. Square edge profile and exaggerated canted spine-edge corners to the boards (11-13 mm high). The two sewing supports were laced through tunnels in the spine-edge of the boards into channels in a short lacing path and are secured with wooden pegs. </msdesc:boards>
                        <msdesc:edges decoration="none">The edges of the bookblock have been cut, though the trim was minimal and some leaves retain the uneven natural cut edges of the parchment at their tail edges, particularly quires 3-4 (fols. 15-30). The edges were not decorated. The bookblock has exaggerated canted spine-edge corners (11-13 mm high), much greater than required to accommodate the endbands. </msdesc:edges>
                        <msdesc:spine profile="flat">The binding has a flat spine shape. The altered binding retains the spine tabs of alum-tawed skin (hairside facing spine) to the outer spine panels only extending to the kettlestitches, the projecting tabs above the endbands have been cut off.  </msdesc:spine>
                        <msdesc:endbands subtype="structural" type="primary">Sewn endbands worked through the spine tabs and sewn on a single core of alum-tawed skin with plain undyed thread (wound-packed-on-core). The endband cores laced into the boards at the base of the exaggerated canted spine-edge corners with a short lacing path. The projecting parts above the endbands of the spine tabs have been cut off and are lost. Both endband cores are now split at both joints.</msdesc:endbands>
                        <msdesc:covering status="lost">The turn-ins visible beneath the pastedowns show that the first binding was covered with a full cover of alum tawed skin, turned in on all edges with wide irregular turn-ins.</msdesc:covering>
                        <decoNote type="unknown">No evidence.</decoNote>
                        <msdesc:fastenings type="strap" direction="ltr" status="lost" quantity="1">The first binding was held closed with a single left-to-right long pin strap, all now lost. There are rust stains to the centre of the fore-edge of fols. 1-4 from the strap anchor, and the rusting end of a side pin can be seen at the inner face of the right board, approximately a quarter of the way across from the fore-edge, with matching stains on fols. 61-63. </msdesc:fastenings>
                        <msdesc:furniture status="unknown">No evidence.</msdesc:furniture>
                        <msdesc:tacketing status="none">None.</msdesc:tacketing>
                        <msdesc:alterations xmlns="http://www.example.org/ns/msdesc">No repairs prior to the alteration of 1602.</msdesc:alterations>
                        <msdesc:bookmarks status="none">None.</msdesc:bookmarks>
                        <msdesc:curtains status="none">None.</msdesc:curtains>
                        <msdesc:chaining status="none">None.</msdesc:chaining>
                        <msdesc:labels status="unknown">No evidence.</msdesc:labels>
                     </binding>
                     <binding when="1602" type="inboard" subtype="alteration">
                        <head>Alteration, England, 1602</head>
                        <!--<history><origin><origPlace><country>England</country></origPlace><origDate when="1602">1602</origDate></origin></history>-->
                        <msdesc:endleaves type="separate" support="perg" subtype="firstUse">
                           Left: Separate endleaves. Fol. i a pastedown (now lifted) added as part of the alteration and put down after recovering. The now lifted pastedown was guarded to fol. 1 with a paper strip during the later reback.</msdesc:endleaves>
                        <msdesc:endleaves type="separate" support="perg" subtype="reused">
                              Right: Separate endleaves, the alteration retains and reuses the first endleaves. Fol. 63 the first free endleaf was put down as a pastedown (now lifted) after recovering. The bifolium is now split entirely at the joint. </msdesc:endleaves>
                        <msdesc:edges decoration="coloured">The edges of the bookblock were not trimmed for the alteration, but the edges were decorated, coloured yellow/green.</msdesc:edges>
                        <msdesc:covering material="skinTawed" colour="natural">The alteration added a full cover of alum-tawed skin used hairside out (from follicle pattern possibly sheep) over the first covering, now a warm cream colour. Turned in on all edges with lapped mitre corners.</msdesc:covering>
                        <decoNote type="none">None.</decoNote>
                        <msdesc:fastenings status="lost" type="tie" quantity="2">Now none. There are slits and later patches to the recovering from two fore-edge ties (now lost), added as part of the alteration.</msdesc:fastenings>
                        <msdesc:furniture status="none">None.</msdesc:furniture>
                        <msdesc:alterations xmlns="http://www.example.org/ns/msdesc">The altered binding was repaired for the Bodleian in the late 19th or early 20th century. The pastedowns were lifted and three leaves were repaired (fols. 1, 16 &amp; 40), with the left pastedown 
                           guarded to fol. 1 with a paper strip. Any remaining spine covering was removed and the sewing supports were cut to the width of the spine. The boards are reattached with new tanned leather slips and the binding was rebacked with light brown tanned leather, heavily moulded over the spine and sewing supports. The covering on both boards were patched with tawed skin where the ties had been removed.</msdesc:alterations>
                        <msdesc:chaining notBefore="1602" status="lost"> There are pairs of holes from two now removed Bodleian chain shackles or staples, towards the head and the tail of the fore-edge of the left board, with matching holes to fol. i, the added pastedown. There is a Bodleian instruction ‘to be chaisned (sic) againe’ to fol. i verso.</msdesc:chaining>
                        <msdesc:labels xmlns="http://www.example.org/ns/msdesc">None.</msdesc:labels>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="1100" notBefore="1050">11th century, second half</origDate>
                  </origin>
                  <provenance type="MLGB3_provenance_evidence" source="http://mlgb3.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/mlgb/book/4962">
                     <orgName role="fmo" key="org_144217511">Salisbury, Wiltshire, Cathedral church of St Mary the Virgin; see removed from Sherborne in 1078</orgName>: 'Iste liber est Sancte Marie Sar. qui eum furatus fuerit vel celauer[it] vel titulum istum deleuerit anatema sit' on front pastedown (s. xii). (<ref target="http://mlgb3.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/mlgb/book/4962">MLGB3</ref>: evidence from an ex-libris inscription or note of gift to an institution). </provenance>
                  <provenance type="MLGB3_laterOwners" source="http://mlgb3.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/mlgb/book/4962">Cope, 1602. (<ref target="http://mlgb3.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/mlgb/book/4962">MLGB3</ref>)</provenance>
                  <provenance type="MLGB3_generalNotes" source="http://mlgb3.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/mlgb/book/4962">Medieval binding.     Marginal marking 'D. M.' in same hand (s. xii) as in other MSS. from Salisbury: the same scribe s. xii wrote the letters 'D.M.' as a 'nota bene' sign in the margins of Aberdeen UL 216, Bodl. 392, 444 (fols. 1–27), 756, 765, 768, 835; Fell 1, 4; Rawl. C.723; Salisbury Cath. 10, 24, 25, 37, 67, 78, 88, 106, 128, 129, 135, 140, 154, 159, 165. (<ref target="http://mlgb3.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/mlgb/book/4962">MLGB3</ref>)
                                             </provenance>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>
                           <ref target="https://medieval.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/about">Summary description</ref> abbreviated from the Summary Catalogue (1922). <listBibl>
                              <bibl facs="aap0287.gif" type="SC">Summary Catalogue, vol. 2, part 1, p. 266</bibl>
                           </listBibl>
                        </source>
                     </recordHist>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl type="WRAPPER">
                     <listBibl type="INTERNET">
                        <head>Online resources:</head>
                        <bibl>
                           <ref target="https://clasp.ell.ox.ac.uk/db-latest/apmo/entry/574">
                              <title>Electronic Gneuss-Lapidge</title> (entry 574)</ref>
                        </bibl>
                        <bibl>
                           <ref target="http://mlgb3.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/mlgb/book/4962">
                              <title>MLGB3: Medieval Libraries of Great Britain</title>
                           </ref>
                        </bibl>
                     </listBibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2022-04-04">Add binding information from Summary Catalogue.</change>
         <change when="2021-12-14">Add provenance information from MLGB3.</change>
         <change when="2017-07-01">First online publication.</change>
         <change when="2017-05-25">
            <persName>James Cummings</persName> Up-converted the markup using <ref target="https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl">https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl</ref>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>