<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="manuscript_1327">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>MS. Bodl. 277</title>
            <title type="collection">MSS. Bodl. (Bodley)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Description</resp>
               <persName>Elizabeth Solopova</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Revision</resp>
               <persName>Andrew Dunning</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </publisher>
            <idno type="msID">MS_Bodl_277</idno>
            <idno type="collection">Bodl</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="MS_Bodl_277" xml:lang="en">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <region type="county">Oxfordshire</region>
                  <settlement key="place_7011931">Oxford</settlement>
                  <institution>University of Oxford</institution>
                  <repository>Bodleian Library</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">MS. Bodl. 277</idno>
                  <idno type="ieArk">ark:29072/x002870x133z</idno><idno type="crArk">ark:29072/x000000129sn</idno><altIdentifier type="internal">
                     <idno type="SCN">2124</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents>
                  <textLang mainLang="enm" otherLangs="la">Middle English with Latin</textLang>
                  <msItem>
                     <note>Blank paper flyleaf at the beginning.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem class="#biblia">
                     <locus from="1r" to="375v">(fols. 1r–375v)</locus>
                     <title key="work_10451" type="desc">Old and New Testaments in the Later Version of the Wycliffite Bible</title>
                     <note>An apparently unique further revision preceded by chapter 1 of the General Prologue.</note>
                     <note>Includes 3 Ezra, found otherwise only in the Earlier Version of the Wycliffite Bible MSS, in a lightly revised form. Prologues to Isaiah and Baruch and to the books of the New Testament. In addition to the Later Version of the Wycliffite Bible Prologue to Romans, the Earlier Version of the Wycliffite Bible prologue is included, possibly as an afterthought (see Collation).</note>
                     <note>Chapter numbers as red Roman numerals with blue paraphs in Old Testament and as alternating red and blue Roman numerals in New Testament. Running titles in red with blue paraphs on both rectos and versos in Old Testament, and in alternating red and blue capitals written across the opening in New Testament. Added material within the text is underlined in black throughout. Omissions added in the margins, often decorated with red penwork; some are in a cursive script with Secretary influence (e.g., fol. 87r–v). Occasionally an addition, originally written in the margin, is erased and entered within the text over an erasure in a contemporary hand (e.g., fol. 93v). There are two glosses in red in the margins in the hand of the original rubricator: <q>Pater noster</q> at Matthew 15 <locus from="303v" to="303v">(fol. 303v)</locus> and <q>Note þis decree</q> at 1 Ezra 7:25–26 <locus from="137r" to="137r">(fol. 137r)</locus>, marking a passage on the observance of the law of God and the law of the king. Other marginal glosses by the original scribe, linked by sigla to the text. Very few glosses in New Testament. Added (?) note <q>of ymages</q>, fol. 200r, Wisdom 15. Parchment tabs at the beginning of books throughout, apart from some short prophetic books and New Testament epistles. The tabs have short titles of books (e.g., <q>Iudicum</q>) or the opening letters of such titles written on the recto in the hand responsible for most Carthusian additions (see below).</note>
                     <note>Fifteenth-century additions similar to those found in Latin bibles owned by the Carthusians (Doyle (1998); Hudson, A., ‘The Carthusians and a Wycliffite Bible’, in Kras, P. et al. (eds), <title>Ecclesia, cultura, potestas: studia z dziejów kultury i społeczenstwa</title> (Krakow: Societas Vistulana, 2006), pp. 731–42). Lections during the week for the year are marked in the margins throughout; their opening words are also often marked within the text. Such notation is absent in psalms and much of the four gospels, presumably because other copies of these texts with instructions existed (Hudson, A., ‘The Carthusians and a Wycliffite Bible’, in Kras, P. et al. (eds), <title>Ecclesia, cultura, potestas: studia z dziejów kultury i społeczenstwa</title> (Krakow: Societas Vistulana, 2006), pp. 731–42, p. 737). The markings include marginal letters in red P, S and T (<q>Prima</q>, <q>Secunda</q> and <q>Tertia lectio</q>); the first of these is often followed by an indication of day (e.g., <q>Feria ii, Feria iij, Sabbato</q>) and season (e.g., <q>Dominica in sexagesima</q>, fol. 17v; <q>On passyon Sunday</q>, fol. 229r).</note>
                     <note>A different set of readings is marked <q>In Refectorio</q>, followed by the number of leaves to be read. Occasionally these are accompanied by further comments in plummet indicating that these longer passages to be read <foreign rend="italic">in refectorio</foreign> were compared with the text in another book, presumably a Latin bible (de Hamel, C., <title>The book: a history of the Bible</title> (London: Phaidon, 2001), pp. 184–5; Hudson, A., ‘The Carthusians and a Wycliffite Bible’, in Kras, P. et al. (eds), <title>Ecclesia, cultura, potestas: studia z dziejów kultury i społeczenstwa</title> (Krakow: Societas Vistulana, 2006), pp. 731–42, p. 738; Dove, M., <title>The first English Bible: the text and context of the Wycliffite versions</title> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2007), p. 65): <list>
                           <item><q>In Refectorio iiij ff in alio libro xiiij et d<ex>imidium</ex></q>
                              <locus from="1v" to="1v">(fol. 1v)</locus></item>
                           <item><q>In Refectorio iij ff in alio libro x ff et di<ex>midium</ex></q>
                              <locus from="18r" to="18r">(fol. 18r)</locus></item>
                           <item><q>In Refectorio iiij fol in alio libro xiij ff</q>
                              <locus from="31r" to="31r">(fol. 31r)</locus></item>
                           <item><q>In Refectorio xix ffoliis et di<ex>midium</ex></q>
                              <locus from="116r" to="116r">(fol. 116r)</locus></item>
                           <item><q>In Refectorio xij folia</q>
                              <locus from="135v" to="135v">(fol. 135v)</locus></item>
                           <item><q>In refectorio iij fol of þis boke</q> (right margin)</item>
                           <item><q>and <note>[or <q>et</q>]</note> ix fol of þe latyn B…</q> (lower margin; the rest is cut off; fol. 159r)</item>
                           <item><q>In Refectorio v ff</q>
                              <locus from="229v" to="229v">(fol. 229v)</locus></item>
                           <item><q>In Refectorio iiij fol et di<ex>midium</ex></q>
                              <locus from="239v" to="239v">(fol. 239v)</locus></item>
                           <item><q>In Refectorio vi et di<ex>midium</ex> fol</q>
                              <locus from="265v" to="265v">(fol. 265v)</locus></item>
                           <item><q>In Refectorio</q>
                              <locus>(fols. 332r and 332v)</locus></item>
                           <item><q>Dominica in Refectorio ii folia</q>
                              <locus from="371r" to="371r">(fol. 371r)</locus>.</item>
                        </list>
                     </note>
                     <note>The notes suggest that the Latin book was much smaller than MS. Bodl. 277, presumably a portable ‘Parisian’ bible: four leaves in MS. Bodl. 277 correspond once to 14½ leaves in ‘another book’ and to 13 leaves on the second occasion. Several notes suggest that the text was indeed compared to a Bible, e.g., a note about omitted names of towns in Joshua 15:33 <locus from="66v" to="66v">(fol. 66v)</locus>; <q>þe prologe wantyth</q> at the beginning of Jeremiah <locus from="229r" to="229r">(fol. 229r)</locus> and <q>prologus car</q>’ at the beginning of Ezekiel <locus from="249v" to="249v">(fol. 249v)</locus>. Other notes include <q>Cantatur in Choro</q> at the beginning of the psalter <locus from="167r" to="167r">(fol. 167r)</locus>; <q>turne to þe boke Ieremie &amp; leve &amp; <sic>leve</sic> þe boke of kynges for þat is next after ebre vse</q> at the beginning of 1 Kings (fol. 78v; see Hudson, A., ‘The Carthusians and a Wycliffite Bible’, in Kras, P. et al. (eds), <title>Ecclesia, cultura, potestas: studia z dziejów kultury i społeczenstwa</title> (Krakow: Societas Vistulana, 2006), pp. 731–42, p. 737); <q>id est canonicum</q> added to a rubric introducing Canonical epistles <locus from="365v" to="365v">(fol. 365v)</locus>, and <q>Odyr wyse callyd Epistole Canonicales</q>
                        <locus from="366r" to="366r">(fol. 366r)</locus>.</note>
                     <note>Marginal divisions A–H, found in other Carthusian bibles combined with <q>primo</q>, <q>secundo</q> and <q>tertio</q>, appear in many parts of the text (Saenger (2005), p. 92 n. 71). Unlike the indexing letters they run across chapters and again suggest that the text was compared with a Latin bible. They often (though not always) start at the beginnings of books, and if a prologue is present, A is used to mark the prologue, whereas B corresponds to the beginning of the first chapter in a book (e.g., Canonical epistles, fol. 365v). If a prologue is not included, A is missing and B appears at the beginning of the first chapter (e.g., Genesis, Joshua, I Kings, Tobit, Judith, Esther, Job). At the beginning of Ezechiel <locus from="249v" to="249v">(fol. 249v)</locus> a note about a missing prologue is accompanied by A, whereas B corresponds to the beginning of the first chapter. In books that do not have a prologue A tends to appear at the start of the book (e.g., Exodus, Leviticus, Deuteronomy, Judges, 2 Kings, 3 Kings). Occasionally the subdivisions are accompanied by comments which suggest comparison to another manuscript, such as <q>capitulum vij</q>
                        <locus from="194v" to="194v">(fol. 194v)</locus> at subdivision ‘G’ marking <q>What nede is it to a man…</q> which appears at the beginning of Ecclesiastes 7 in the Earlier Version of the Wycliffite Bible, but belongs to the end of chapter 6 in the Later Version of the Wycliffite Bible. On fol. 294v the subdivision ‘E’ is accompanied by a note <q>ii col<ex>umna</ex></q>; on fol. 195v ‘G’ is accompanied by <q>vi</q> and on fol. 198r another ‘G’ is marked <q>c<ex>apitulum</ex> viij</q>.</note>
                     <note>[quires I–XXV]</note>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="1r">(fol. 1r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Chapter 1 of the General Prologue</title>
                        <rubric>Prolog</rubric>
                        <incipit>Fyue &amp; twenty bookis</incipit>
                        <finalRubric>Heere endiþ prolog on þe book of Genesis</finalRubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="1v">(fol. 1v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Genesis</title>
                        <rubric>Here biginniþ þe book of Genesis</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="17v">(fol. 17v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Exodus</title>
                        <rubric>Heere endiþ Genesis and bigynniþ Exodus</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="30v">(fol. 30v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Leviticus</title>
                        <rubric>Heere endiþ Exodus and biginniþ leuyticus</rubric>
                        <finalRubric>Heere endiþ leuyticus</finalRubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="39r">(fol. 39r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Numbers</title>
                        <rubric>Here bigynniþ þe book of Numery</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="51r">(fol. 51r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Deuteronomy</title>
                        <rubric>Heere endiþ Numery and bigynniþ Deutronomye</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="62r">(fol. 62r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Joshua</title>
                        <rubric>Heere endiþ þe book of Deutronomie and bigynniþ þe book of Iosie</rubric>
                        <finalRubric>Heere endiþ þe book of Iosue</finalRubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="69v">(fol. 69v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Judges</title>
                        <rubric>Here bigynniþ þe book of Iudicum</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="77r">(fol. 77r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Ruth</title>
                        <rubric>Heere endiþ þe book of Iudicum and bigynneþ þe book of Ruth</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="78v">(fol. 78v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">1 Kings</title>
                        <rubric>Heere endiþ þe book of Ruth and bigynniþ þe firste book of kyngis</rubric>
                        <finalRubric>Heere endiþ þe firste book of kyngis</finalRubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="89r">(fol. 89r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">2 Kings</title>
                        <rubric>Heere bigynniþ þe ii book of kyngis</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="97r">(fol. 97r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">3 Kings</title>
                        <rubric><sic>Hee</sic> endiþ þe secounde book of kyngis and bigynneþ þe þridde</rubric>
                        <note>Imperfect at the end because of the loss of a leaf after fol. 106, ends at 22:11.</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="107r">(fol. 107r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">4 Kings</title>
                        <note>Begins imperfectly at 2:16.</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="116r">(fol. 116r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">1 Chronicles</title>
                        <rubric>Heere endiþ þe fourþe book of kyngis and bigynniþ þe firste book of Paralipomynon þat is of wordis of daies</rubric>
                        <finalRubric>Heere endiþ þe firste book of Paralipomynon</finalRubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="124v">(fol. 124v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">2 Chronicles</title>
                        <rubric>Heere biginniþ þe secounde book of Paralipomynon</rubric>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="135r">(fol. 135r)</locus>
                           <title>Prayer of Manasseh</title>
                           <note>without a rubric.</note>
                        </msItem>
                        <finalRubric>Heere endiþ þe seconde book of Paralipomynon</finalRubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="135v">(fol. 135v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">1 Ezra</title>
                        <rubric>Heere biginniþ þe firste book of Esdre</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="138r">(fol. 138r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">2 Ezra</title>
                        <rubric>Heere eendiþ þe firste book of Esdre and þe secounde biginniþ</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="142v">(fol. 142v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">3 Ezra</title>
                        <rubric>Heere endiþ þe secounde book of Esdre and heere biginnyþ þe þridde book of Esdre</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="147v">(fol. 147v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Tobit</title>
                        <rubric>Heere endiþ þe þridde book of Esdre and bigynniþ Thobie</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="150v">(fol. 150v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Judith</title>
                        <rubric>Here endiþ Thobie and bigynniþ Iudith</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="154v">(fol. 154v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Esther</title>
                        <rubric>Heere endiþ þe book of Iudith and bigynniþ Ester</rubric>
                        <note>Usual notes on the differences between the Hebrew and Latin texts in red in chapters X–XV.</note>
                        <finalRubric>Heere endiþ hester</finalRubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="159r">(fol. 159r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Job</title>
                        <rubric>Heere bignniþ Iob</rubric>
                        <note><q>Iob was a very man in kynde…</q> at the end of the second column on fol. 158v in red, by the original rubricator, with a rubric <q>a glose</q>.</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="167r">(fol. 167r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Psalms</title>
                        <rubric>Heere endiþ Iob And bigynniþ þe Sauter</rubric>
                        <finalRubric>Heere endiþ þe sauter of Dauid þe prophete</finalRubric>
                        <note>Laid out as prose, with alternating red and blue capitals at the beginning of verses. Psalm numbers in the margins as red Roman numerals, and occasionally also as Arabic numerals (e.g., fol. 184r). Most psalms have titles in English, underlined in red. Latin incipits in the margins. Glosses in the original hand in the margins, starting at psalm 92, commenting on the interpretation of psalms, particularly those that have ‘no title in Hebrew or Jerome’. Textual divisions marked with larger initials and borders at psalms 26, 38, 52, 68, 97, 109.</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="186v">(fol. 186v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Proverbs</title>
                        <rubric>Heere bigynniþ þe book of prouerbis</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="193r">(fol. 193r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Ecclesiastes</title>
                        <rubric>Heere endiþ þe book of prouerbis and bigynniþ Ecclesiastes</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="195v">(fol. 195v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Song of Songs</title>
                        <rubric>Heere endiþ Ecclesiastes and bigynniþ Song of songis</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="196v">(fol. 196v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Wisdom</title>
                        <rubric>Heere endiþ þe book of songis and biginniþ þe book of wisdom</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="201v">(fol. 201v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Ecclesiasticus</title>
                        <rubric>Heere endiþ þe book of wisdom and bigynniþ þe book of Ecclesiasticus</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="214r">(fol. 214r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Prologue to Isaiah</title>
                        <rubric>Heere endeþ Ecclesiasticus and biginniþ a prologe on ysaie &amp; oopere prophetis</rubric>
                        <incipit>As seynt Ierom seiþ</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="214v">(fol. 214v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Isaiah</title>
                        <rubric>Heere eendiþ þe prologe and biginniþ ysaie þe prophete</rubric>
                        <note>Rubric <q>þe scripture of Ezechie kyng of Iuda</q> at chapter 38 that starts with a small gold initial.</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="229r">(fol. 229r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Jeremiah</title>
                        <rubric>Heere endiþ ysaie and biginniþ Ieremye</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="246r">(fol. 246r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Lamentations of Jeremiah</title>
                        <rubric>Heere biginnen þe lamentacions of Ieremye</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="247r">(fol. 247r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Prayer of Jeremiah</title>
                        <rubric>Heere enden þe lamentacions and here biginniþ þe preier of Ieremye þe prophet</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="247v">(fol. 247v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Prologue to Baruch</title>
                        <rubric>Heere biginniþ þe prolog of Baruk</rubric>
                        <incipit>Þis book whiche is titlid</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="247v">(fol. 247v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Baruch</title>
                        <rubric>Heere endiþ þe prologe and biginniþ Baruk</rubric>
                        <note>Chapter 6 with a gold initial and rubric <q>Heere biginniþ þe saumple…</q>.</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="249v">(fol. 249v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Ezekiel</title>
                        <rubric>Heere endiþ Baruk and biginniþ Ezechiel</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="265v">(fol. 265v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Daniel</title>
                        <rubric>Heere endiþ Ezechiel and here biginniþ Daniel</rubric>
                        <note>Notes in red on the passages not found in Hebrew in chapters 3, 12.</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="272r">(fol. 272r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Hosea</title>
                        <rubric>Heere endiþ Daniel and biginniþ Osee</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="274r">(fol. 274r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Joel</title>
                        <rubric>Heere endiþ Osee and biginniþ Ioel</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="275r">(fol. 275r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Amos</title>
                        <rubric>Heere endiþ Ioel and biginniþ Amos</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="276v">(fol. 276v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Obadiah</title>
                        <rubric>Heere endiþ amos and biginniþ Abdias</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="277r">(fol. 277r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Jonah</title>
                        <rubric>Heere endiþ Abdias and biginniþ Ionas</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="277v">(fol. 277v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Micah</title>
                        <rubric>Heere endiþ Ionas and biginniþ Micheas</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="278v">(fol. 278v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Nahum</title>
                        <rubric>Heere endiþ Michee and biginniþ Naum</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="279r">(fol. 279r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Habakkuk</title>
                        <rubric>Heere endiþ Naum and biginniþ Abacuk</rubric>
                        <note>Chapter 3 with a rubric <q>þe preier of abakuc…</q>.</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="280r">(fol. 280r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Zephaniah</title>
                        <rubric>Heere endiþ abakuc and biginniþ Sophonie</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="280v">(fol. 280v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Haggai</title>
                        <rubric>Heere endiþ Sophonye and biginniþ Aggey</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="281r">(fol. 281r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Zechariah</title>
                        <rubric>Heere endiþ Aggey and biginniþ Zacharie</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="283v">(fol. 283v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Malachi</title>
                        <rubric>Heere endiþ Zacharie and biginniþ Malachie</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="284v">(fol. 284v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">1 Maccabees</title>
                        <rubric>Heere endiþ Malachie and biginniþ þe firste book of Machabeis</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="294r">(fol. 294r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">2 Maccabees</title>
                        <rubric>Heere endiþ þe firste book of Machabeis and biginniþ þe seconde</rubric>
                        <finalRubric>Heere endiþ þe secounde book of Machabeis þe whiche is þe ende of þe olde testament</finalRubric>
                        <note>Most of the last leaf is blank.</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <note>[quires XXVI–XXXI]</note>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="302r">(fol. 302r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Prologue to Matthew</title>
                        <rubric>Heere bigynniþ þe prologe of ierom on þe gospel of Matheu</rubric>
                        <incipit>Matheu þat was of Iudee</incipit>
                        <finalRubric>Heere endiþ þe prologe</finalRubric>
                        <note>19 lines of the first column, containing the prologue, are left blank and are framed with a square border. The box may have contained pasted decoration, possibly including an indication of ownership; the edges of the box are smudged and rough as if the decoration was ‘lifted off’ (see Hudson, A., ‘The Carthusians and a Wycliffite Bible’, in Kras, P. et al. (eds), <title>Ecclesia, cultura, potestas: studia z dziejów kultury i społeczenstwa</title> (Krakow: Societas Vistulana, 2006), pp. 731–42, p. 732).</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="302r">(fol. 302r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Matthew</title>
                        <rubric>Here bigynniþ þe gospel of Matheu</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="311v">(fol. 311v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Prologue to Mark</title>
                        <rubric>Heere endiþ þe gospel of Matheu and biginniþ þe prologe on þe gospel of Mark</rubric>
                        <incipit>Mark þe gospeller was þe chosen seruaunt</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="311v">(fol. 311v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Mark</title>
                        <rubric>Heere endiþ þe prologe &amp; bigynniþ þe gospel of Mark</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="317v">(fol. 317v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Prologue to Luke</title>
                        <rubric>Heere endiþ þe gospel of Mark and biginniþ þe prologe on Luyk</rubric>
                        <incipit>Luye was a man of sirie</incipit>
                        <finalRubric>Heere endiþ þe prologe</finalRubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="318r">(fol. 318r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Luke</title>
                        <rubric>Here biginniþ þe gospel of luyk</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="327v">(fol. 327v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Prologue to John</title>
                        <rubric>Heere endiþ þe gospel of Luyk and biginniþ þe prologe of Ierom on þe gospel of Ioon</rubric>
                        <incipit>This is ioon euangelist</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="327v">(fol. 327v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">John</title>
                        <rubric>Heere endiþ þe prologe and heere biginniþ þe gospel of Ioon</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="334v">(fol. 334v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">The earlier version of the Wycliffite Bible’s Prologue to Romans</title>
                        <rubric>Heere endiþ þe gospel of Ioon and biginniþ þe firste prologe on þe pistle to Romayns</rubric>
                        <incipit>First us bihoueþ vndirstonde</incipit>
                        <finalRubric>Heere endiþ þe firste prolog on þe pistil to Romayns</finalRubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="335r">(fol. 335r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">The later version of the Wycliffite Bible’s Prologue to Romans</title>
                        <rubric>Heere biginniþ þe ii. prologe on þe pistle to Romains</rubric>
                        <incipit>Romayns ben in þe cuntrey</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="335r">(fol. 335r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Romans</title>
                        <rubric>Heere endiþ þe prologe and here biginniþ þe pistle</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="338v">(fol. 338v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Prologue to 1 Corinthians</title>
                        <rubric>Here endiþ þe pistle to Romayns And bigynneþ þe prolog on þe firste pistle to Corinthies</rubric>
                        <incipit>Corynthis ben</incipit>
                        <finalRubric>þis seiþ Ierom in his prolog on þe firste pistle to corynthies</finalRubric>
                        <note>(written in black, underlined in red).</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="338v">(fol. 338v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">1 Corinthians.</title>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="342r">(fol. 342r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Prologue to 2 Corinthians</title>
                        <rubric>Heere endiþ þe firste pistle to Corinthies and biginiþ þe prologe on þe ii pistle to Corinth</rubric>
                        <incipit>Aftir penaunce</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="342r">(fol. 342r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">2 Corinthians</title>
                        <rubric>Heere endiþ þe prologe &amp; biginiþ þe pistle</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="344v">(fol. 344v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Prologue to Galatians</title>
                        <rubric>Heere endiþ þe secounde pistle to Corynthies and biginiþ þe prologe on þe pistle to Galathies</rubric>
                        <incipit>Galathies ben grekis</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="355r">(fol. 355r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Galatians</title>
                        <rubric>Heere endiþ þe prologe &amp; biginniþ þe pistle</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="346r">(fol. 346r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Prologue to Ephesians</title>
                        <rubric>Heere endiþ þe pistle to Galathies &amp; biginniþ þe prologe on þe epistle to Ephesians</rubric>
                        <incipit>Ephecians ben of asye</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="346r">(fol. 346r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Ephesians</title>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="347r">(fol. 347r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Prologue to Philippians</title>
                        <rubric>Heere endiþ þe pistle to Effesians and bigynniþ þe prologe on þe pistle to Philippencis</rubric>
                        <incipit>Filipencis ben of macedonye</incipit>
                        <finalRubric>Here endiþ þe prologe</finalRubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="347r">(fol. 347r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Philippians</title>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="348r">(fol. 348r)</locus>
                        <title>Prologue to Colossians</title>
                        <rubric>Heere endeþ þe pistle to Philipencis and biginiþ þe prologe on þe pistle to Colocencis</rubric>
                        <incipit>Colocencis ben also laodicencis</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="348r">(fol. 348r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Colossians</title>
                        <rubric>Here biginniþ þe pistle</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="349r">(fol. 349r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Prologue to 1 Thessalonians</title>
                        <rubric>Heere endiþ þe pistle to Colocencis and biginniþ þe prologe on þe i pistle to Thess’</rubric>
                        <incipit>Tessalonycensis ben macedonies</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="349r">(fol. 349r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">1 Thessalonians</title>
                        <rubric>Here biginniþ þe pistle</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="349v">(fol. 349v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Prologue to 2 Thessalonians</title>
                        <rubric>Heere endiþ þe firste pistle to Tessalonicencis and biginniþ þe prologe on þe ii pistle to Thessalonycencis</rubric>
                        <incipit>Þe postle writeþ</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="349v">(fol. 349v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">2 Thessalonians</title>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="350r">(fol. 350r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Prologue to 1 Timothy</title>
                        <rubric>Heere endiþ þe ii epistle to thessalonicensis and biginniþ þe prologe of þe i epistle to Thymothe</rubric>
                        <incipit>He enformiþ and techiþ </incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="350r">(fol. 350r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">1 Timothy</title>
                        <rubric>Heere biginniþ þe pistle</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="351r">(fol. 351r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Prologue to 2 Timothy</title>
                        <rubric>Heere endiþ þen i pistle to Thymothe &amp; biginniþ þe prologe on þe ii</rubric>
                        <incipit>He writiþ also</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="351r">(fol. 351r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">2 Timothy</title>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="351v">(fol. 351v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Prologue to Titus</title>
                        <rubric>Heere endiþ þe ii pistle to Thymothe and biginniþ þe prologe of þe pistle to Tite</rubric>
                        <incipit>He warniþ tyte</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="351v">(fol. 351v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Titus</title>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="352r">(fol. 352r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Prologue to Philemon</title>
                        <rubric>Heere endiþ þe pistle to tyte &amp; biginniþ þe prologe on þe pistle to Philemon</rubric>
                        <incipit>He makeþ familiar</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="352r">(fol. 352r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Philemon</title>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="352v">(fol. 352v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Prologue to Hebrews</title>
                        <rubric>Heere endiþ the pistle to Philemon and biginniþ þe prologe on þe pistle to Ebrewis</rubric>
                        <incipit>First it is to sey</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="352v">(fol. 352v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Hebrews</title>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="355v">(fol. 355v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Prologue to Acts</title>
                        <rubric>Heere endiþ þe pistle to Ebrewis and biginniþ þe prologe on þe dedis of apostlis</rubric>
                        <incipit>Luyk of antioche</incipit>
                        <finalRubric>Heere endiþ þe prologe</finalRubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="355v">(fol. 355v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Acts</title>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="365v">(fol. 365v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">The Catholic epistles. Prologue to James</title>
                        <rubric>Heere enden þe dedis of apostlis and heere biginniþ a prologe on þe pistlis of cristen feiþ þat ben seuene in ordre</rubric>
                        <incipit>Þe ordre of þe seuene epistlis</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="365v">(fol. 365v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">James</title>
                        <rubric>Heere endiþ þe prologe and bigynniþ þe epistle</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="366v">(fol. 366v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">1 Peter</title>
                        <rubric>Heere endiþ þe epistle of iames and bigynniþ þe firste epistle of Petir</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="367v">(fol. 367v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">2 Peter</title>
                        <rubric>Heere biginniþ þe ii of petre</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="368r">(fol. 368r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">1 John</title>
                        <rubric>Heere endiþ þe ii epistle of petre &amp; bigynniþ þe i epistle of Ion</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="369r">(fol. 369r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">2 John</title>
                        <rubric>Heere endiþ þe i epistle of Ioon and biginniþ þe ii</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="369v">(fol. 369v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">3 John</title>
                        <rubric>Heere endeþ þe ii epistle of Ioon and biginniþ þe iii</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="369v">(fol. 369v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Jude</title>
                        <rubric>Heere endiþ þe þridde epistle of Ioon and biginniþ þe epistle of Iudas</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="370r">(fol. 370r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Prologue to the Apocalypse</title>
                        <rubric>Heere endiþ þe epistle of iudas and heere bigynniþ a prologe of þe apocalips þat is þe reuelacioun of seint Ioon</rubric>
                        <incipit>Alle men þat wolen </incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="370r">(fol. 370r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Apocalypse</title>
                        <rubric>Heer endiþ þe prologe and bigynniþ þe apocalips</rubric>
                        <finalRubric>Heere endiþ þe apocalips þat Ioon wroot in þe Ile of Pathmos þe whiche is þe ende of þe newe testament</finalRubric>
                     </msItem>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem>
                     <note>Fols. 375v–377v are mostly blank; a woodcut is pasted to fol. 376v.</note>
                     <note>A note about the countries where the four gospels were written in a contemporary hand on fol. 377r: <q>Matthew in iudee. Mark in ytalie. luyk in aca<supplied>ye</supplied> Ioon in asy<supplied>ae</supplied></q>.</note>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="perg">
                        <support>parchment, paper flyleaves</support>
                        <extent>377 leaves, <foreign rend="italic">c.</foreign><dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                              <height>415</height>
                              <width>260</width>
                           </dimensions></extent>
                        <foliation>modern in pencil, 1–377</foliation>
                        <collation>unnumbered paper flyleaf | <locus from="1" to="96">(fols. 1–96)</locus> I–VIII (12) | <locus from="97" to="107">(fols. 97–107)</locus> IX (12–1) missing 11 | 108–287) X–XXIV (12) | <locus from="288" to="301">(fols. 288–301)</locus> XXV (14) | <locus from="302" to="361">(fols. 302–361)</locus> XXVI–XXX (12) | <locus from="362" to="369">(fols. 362–369)</locus> XXXI (8) | <locus from="370" to="375">(fols. 370–375)</locus> (6) | <locus from="376" to="377">(fols. 376–377)</locus> parchment and paper flyleaves. A leaf, corresponding in width to a single column is added in the middle of quire XXVII, after fol. 326, to finish the prologue to Romans. <catchwords>Catchwords survive; leaf signatures occasionally survive.</catchwords>
                           <secFol><q>&amp; settide hym</q>
                              <locus from="2r" to="2r">(fol. 2r)</locus></secFol>
                        </collation>
                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout columns="2" writtenLines="64">Ruled in plummet for two columns with double vertical and horizontal bounding lines extending the full height and width of page; a further set of bounding lines comprising double lines in the lower and outer margins and single lines in the upper margin; 64 lines per page; written space: <foreign rend="italic">c.</foreign><dimensions type="ruled" unit="mm">
                              <height>290</height>
                              <width>180</width>
                           </dimensions>. Fol. 1r, containing chapter 1 of the General Prologue, has further 8 lines of text in the lower margin in both columns in order to start Genesis at the head of fol. 1v</layout>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc>
                     <handNote script="textualisNorthern">textura, black ink</handNote>
                  </handDesc>
                  <decoDesc>
                     <decoNote type="border">Full borders made of gold, pink and blue bars, decorated with foliage, flowers, gold disks, human figures and grotesques, at the beginning of Genesis, 1 Kings, 1 Chronicles, 1 Ezra, Psalms, Proverbs, Isaiah, gospels, Romans and the Apocalypse (particularly sumptuous at Genesis, Psalms, Mathew, Romans and the Apocalypse).</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="decInit">4- to 9-line gold initials and three-quarters borders made of gold, pink and blue bars, decorated with foliage, flowers and gold disks, at the beginning of the chapter from the General Prologue and most books. Some books do not have borders, and start with initials decorated with sprays of foliage extending into margins (e.g., minor prophets and some epistles).</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="decInit">3- to 7-line initials, gold or on gold background, at the beginnings of prologues.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="flourInit">3-line blue initials with red penwork at the beginnings of chapters.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="border">As in other Wycliffite bibles the borders are painted avoiding the text in the margins, including corrections, psalm numbers and glosses, suggesting that such text was added before the manuscript was passed to the illuminator. Pächt and Alexander (1973) suggest with a query that the decoration could be of London origin.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="woodcut">Large woodcut of Henry VI, damaged, pasted in on fol. 376v. (<ref target="https://catalog.hathitrust.org/Record/000468709">Pächt and Alexander</ref> iii. 880, pl. LXXXIV)</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="rubrication">Rubrics in red ink.</decoNote>
                  </decoDesc>
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <binding notAfter="1900" notBefore="1800">
                        <p>Brown leather over boards. Blind fillet-line border and rectangular blind roll floral decoration with floral corner-pieces on both covers. Raised bands on spine. Gold lettering ‘BIBLE <lb/> WICKLIFFE’ and a fragment of a paper label with handwritten ‘Bodl 277’ on spine. Marbled paper pastedowns, turn-ins with circular stamps containing ‘IHS’ monogram. Fragments of a large woodcut (Hodnett, no. 2514) pasted to fol. 376v, depicting a group of English martyrs kneeling before a king (Henry VI); includes an antelope, his badge (animal with two horns and tusks) and the coat of arms of England (three lions passant quartered with three fleurs de lis). Fol. 377 was a pastedown of an earlier binding and contains on the verso staining from a red (leather?) binding. The red is similar to that of parchment tabs which mark the beginning of most books (see Hudson, A., ‘The Carthusians and a Wycliffite Bible’, in Kras, P. et al. (eds), <title>Ecclesia, cultura, potestas: studia z dziejów kultury i społeczenstwa</title> (Krakow: Societas Vistulana, 2006), pp. 731–42, p. 734). Since the tabs have book titles in a hand responsible for most Carthusian additions, both the red leather binding and the tabs must date from the time when the manuscript was in the possession of the London charterhouse.</p>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origPlace>
                        <country key="place_7002445">England</country>, <settlement key="place_7011781">London (?)</settlement>
                     </origPlace>
                     <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="1425" notBefore="1415">1415 × 1425 (?)</origDate>
                     <p>Old Testament and New Testament are codicologically separate and there are differences in their execution. Decoration of London origin (Pächt and Alexander (1973)).</p>
                     <p>Dialect survey: <list>
                           <item>ony(10), ech(8)/eche(2), fijr(5)/fire(4)/fuir(1), ȝoue(7)/ȝouen(2)/ȝiuen(1), lijf(10), lijk(10), myche(10), sawȝe(2)/siȝ(3)/siȝe(1)/sayȝ(1) (sg.), saien(4)/ siȝen(2)/sauȝen(1) (pl.), self(5)/silf(5), sich(2)/siche(8), þouȝ(8), þorouȝ(10)</item>
                           <item>-iþ(8)/-eþ(2) (pres.ind.3sg.), -en(10) (pres.ind.pl.), -ynge(10) (pres.part.), sche(10) (3sg.fem.pronoun, nom.), þei(10) (3pl.pronoun, nom.), hem(10) (3pl.pronoun, oblique), her(10) (3pl.pronoun, possessive)</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                  </origin>
                  <provenance>May have originally contained a coat of arms or another indication of ownership on fol. 302r (see Text).</provenance>
                  <provenance><persName key="person_96926832" role="fmo">King Henry VI</persName>: two inscriptions in different, probably early 16th-century hands on fol. 375r, one crossed out, the second reading <q>Hic liber erat quondam henrici sexti qui postea donabatur domui Cartusiensium quæ Londino contigua est</q>. Hudson (2006, p. 736) argues against a possibility that the book belonged to Henry V, but not against a suggestion that this may be the English bible known to have been owned by Henry IV (Summerson (1997); Meale (1989)).</provenance>
                  <provenance><orgName key="org_313181544" role="fmo">Charterhouse, London</orgName>: 15th-century Carthusian additions; text compared with a portable Latin bible.</provenance>
                  <provenance><persName key="person_39246400" role="fmo">Sir George More</persName> (1553–1632), see <title>Oxford Dictionary of National Biography</title>.</provenance>
                  <acquisition when="1604">Bodleian Library: presented by <persName key="person_39246400" role="dnr">More</persName> in 1604. Earlier shelfmarks: ‘Th. B. 24. 9’, ‘NE. C. 7. 1 (2124)’ (upper pastedown).</acquisition>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>Elizabeth Solopova, <title><ref target="https://jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1gn6cmr">Manuscripts of the Wycliffite Bible in the Bodleian and Oxford College Libraries</ref></title>, Exeter Medieval Texts and Studies (Liverpool: Liverpool University Press, 2016), no. 3. Previously described: <listBibl>
                              <bibl>Otto Pächt and J. J. G. Alexander, <title><ref target="https://catalog.hathitrust.org/Record/000468709">Illuminated Manuscripts in the Bodleian Library, Oxford</ref></title>, III (1973), no. 880 [decoration, origin, date]</bibl>
                              <bibl facs="aap0244.gif" type="SC">Summary Catalogue, vol. 2, part 1, p. 223</bibl>
                           </listBibl>
                        </source>
                     </recordHist>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <surrogates>
                     <bibl subtype="partial" type="digital-facsimile">
                        <ref target="https://digital.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/objects/bfbb83b1-9ee3-49a7-a434-ef0f602d2350/">
                           <title>Digital Bodleian</title>
                        </ref>
                        <note>(14 images from 35mm slides)</note>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl subtype="partial" type="digital-facsimile">
                        <ref target="https://digital.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/objects/81772d5f-704e-4d4c-a692-25f1c8799da0/">
                           <title>Digital Bodleian</title>
                        </ref>
                        <note>(1 image of woodcut)</note>
                     </bibl>
                  </surrogates>
                  <listBibl type="WRAPPER">
                     <listBibl type="PRINT">
                        <bibl>Bod-Inc XYL-24 [<ref target="https://www.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/__data/assets/pdf_file/0010/48871/bod-inc_Blockbooks.pdf">pdf</ref>] (woodcut: description by Nigel Palmer and Andrew Honey)</bibl>
                        <bibl>Forshall, J. and Madden, F. (eds), <title>The Holy Bible … in the earliest English versions made from the Latin Vulgate by John Wycliffe and his followers</title>, 4 vols (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1850), vol. 1, p. xlvii; collated throughout; base text for revised 3 Ezra for which this is the only known text; sigla <title>a</title> – prologue to Romans; γ – General Prologue.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Deanesly, M., <title>The Lollard Bible and other medieval biblical versions</title> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1920), pp. 252, 261, 382.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Madan, F. and Craster, H. H. E., <title>Summary catalogue of western manuscripts in the Bodleian Library at Oxford</title>, vol. 2, part I <title>(collections received before 1660 and miscellaneous MSS acquired during the first half of the 17th century), nos. 1–3490</title> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1922), no. 2124.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Thompson, E. M., <title>The Carthusian order in England</title> (London and New York: Society for Promoting Christian Knowledge/Macmillan, 1930), p. 324.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Hodnett, E., <title>English Woodcuts, 1480–1535</title>, 1st edn 1935 (Oxford: University Press, 1973).</bibl>
                        <bibl>Dodgson, C., <title>English woodcuts of the fifteenth century</title> (Strasbourg: J. H. E. Heitz, 1936), pp. 35–6.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Fristedt, S. L., <title>The Wycliffe Bible</title>, 3 vols (Stockholm: Almquvist &amp; Wiksells, 1953–73), vol. 1, pp. 17, 29 and <foreign rend="italic">passim</foreign>.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Lindberg, C. (ed.), <title>The earlier version of the Wycliffite Bible,</title> 8 vols (Stockholm: Almqvist &amp; Wiksell, 1959–97), vol. 8 (1997), p. 43, siglum ‘I’.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Pächt, O. and Alexander, J. J. G., <title>Illuminated manuscripts in the Bodleian Library, Oxford</title>, 3 vols (Oxford, 1966–73), vol. 3 (1973), no. 880.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Spenser, B., ‘King Henry of Windsor and the London pilgrim’, in Bird. J., Chapman, H. and Clark, J. (eds), <title>Collectanea Londiniensia: studies in London archaeology and history presented to Ralph Merrifield</title> (London: London and Middlesex Archaeological Society, 1978), pp. 235–64 at p. 242.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Alexander J. J. G., ‘Painting and manuscript illumination for royal patrons in the later Middle Ages’, in Scattergood, V. J. and Sherborne, J. W. (eds), <title>English court culture in the later Middle Ages</title> (London: Duckworth, 1983), pp. 141–62 at p. 151.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Catto, J., Gradon P. and Hudson, A. (eds), <title>Wyclif and his followers: an exhibition to mark the 600th anniversary of the death of John Wyclif, December 1984 to April 1985</title> (Oxford: Bodleian Library, 1984), pp. 47–8.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Hudson, A., ‘Lollard book production’, in Griffiths, J. and Pearsall, D. A. (eds), <title>Book production and publishing in Britain 1375–1475</title> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1989), pp. 125–42, pp. 125–42 at p. 131.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Lindberg, C. (ed.), <title>The Middle English Bible, The Book of Judges</title> (Oslo: Norwegian University Press, 1989), siglum I and pp. 65, 70.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Meale, C. M., ‘Patrons, buyers and owners: book production and social status’ in Griffiths, J. and Pearsall, D. (eds), <title>Book production and publishing in Britain 1375–1475</title> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1989), pp. 201–38 at p. 223 n. 14.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Scott, K. L., <title>Later Gothic manuscripts, 1390–1490</title>, Survey of manuscripts illuminated in the British Isles (HMMSBI 6), 2 vols (London: Harvey Miller, 1996), vol. 1, p. 70 n. 13.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Summerson, H., ‘An English Bible and other books belonging to Henry IV’, <title>Bulletin of the John Rylands Library</title> 79 (1997), pp. 109–15.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Doyle, A. I., ‘English Carthusian books not yet linked with a charterhouse’, in Barnard, T., Ó Cróinín, D. and Simms, K. (eds), <title>A miracle of learning: studies in manuscripts and Irish learning; essays in honour of William O’Sullivan</title> (Aldershot: Ashgate, 1998), pp. 122–36 at p. 132 n. 32.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Scott, K. L. (gen. ed.), <title>An index of images in English manuscripts from the time of Chaucer to Henry VIII, c.1380–c.1509: the Bodleian Library, Oxford</title>, 3 vols (Turnhout: Harvey Miller Publishers, 2000–02), vol. 1, p. 58, no. 183. de Hamel, C., <title>The book: a history of the Bible</title> (London: Phaidon, 2001), pp. 183–4, figs. 130–1.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Hanna, R., <title>A descriptive catalogue of the western medieval manuscripts of St John’s College, Oxford</title> (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2002), p. 9.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Craig, L. A., ‘Royalty, virtue, and adversity: the cult of king Henry VI’, <title>Albion</title> 35.2 (2003), pp. 187–209.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Hanna, R., ‘English biblical texts before Lollardy and their fate’, in Somerset, F., Havens, J. C. and Pitard, D. G. (eds), <title>Lollards and their influence in late medieval England</title> (Woodbridge: Boydell, 2003), pp 141–53 at p. 153 and n. 38.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Marks, R., ‘Images of Henry VI’, in Stratford, J. (ed.), <title>The Lancastrian court: proceedings of the 2001 Harlaxton Symposium</title> (Donington: Shaun Tyas, 2003), pp. 111–24 at p. 117.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Hanna, R., <title>London literature, 1300–1380</title> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2005), p. 312.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Saenger, P., ‘The British Isles and the origin of the modern mode of biblical citation’, <title>Syntagma</title> 1 (2005), pp. 77–123.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Hudson, A., ‘The Carthusians and a Wycliffite Bible’, in Kras, P. et al. (eds), <title>Ecclesia, cultura, potestas: studia z dziejów kultury i społeczenstwa</title> (Krakow: Societas Vistulana, 2006), pp. 731–42.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Brantley, J., <title>Reading in the wilderness: private devotion and public performance in late medieval England</title> (Chicago and London: University of Chicago Press, 2007), p. 353 n. 190.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Dove, M., <title>The first English Bible: the text and context of the Wycliffite versions</title> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2007), pp. 253–5 and <foreign rend="italic">passim</foreign>.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Cole, A., <title>Literature and heresy in the age of Chaucer</title> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2008), p. 222 n. 24.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Luxford, J. M., ‘Precept and practice: the decoration of English Carthusian books’, in Luxford, J. M. (ed.), <title>Studies in Carthusian monasticism in the late Middle Ages</title> (Turnhout: Brepols, 2008), pp. 225–67 at pp. 232, 264–5.</bibl>
                     </listBibl>
                     <listBibl type="INTERNET">
                        <head>Online resources:</head>
                        <bibl>
                           <ref target="http://mlgb3.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/mlgb/book/3781">
                              <title>MLGB3: Medieval Libraries of Great Britain</title>
                           </ref>
                        </bibl>
                     </listBibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2023-03-23">Add Solopova description.</change>
         <change when="2020-06-16">Description revised to include all information in SC.</change>
         <change when="2017-07-01">First online publication.</change>
         <change when="2017-05-25"><persName>James Cummings</persName> Up-converted the markup using <ref target="https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl">https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl</ref></change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>