<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="manuscript_1241">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>MS. Bodl. 183</title>
            <title type="collection">MSS. Bodl. (Bodley)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Description</resp>
               <persName>Elizabeth Solopova</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Revision</resp>
               <persName>Andrew Dunning</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </publisher>
            <idno type="msID">MS_Bodl_183</idno>
            <idno type="collection">Bodl</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="MS_Bodl_183" xml:lang="en">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <region type="county">Oxfordshire</region>
                  <settlement key="place_7011931">Oxford</settlement>
                  <institution>University of Oxford</institution>
                  <repository>Bodleian Library</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">MS. Bodl. 183</idno>
                  <idno type="ieArk">ark:29072/x0cz30pt109m</idno><idno type="crArk">ark:29072/x0cv43nx270w</idno><altIdentifier type="internal">
                     <idno type="SCN">2084</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents>
                  <textLang mainLang="enm" otherLangs="la">Middle English with Latin</textLang>
                  <msItem>
                     <note>Fols. i–v are blank paper and parchment flyleaves.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="1">
                     <locus>(fols. vi recto-xv verso)</locus>
                     <note>[item 1 occupies quire II]</note>
                     <title type="desc">Table of lections of Type I</title>
                     <rubric>Here bigynneþ a rule þat telliþ in whiche placis of þis book ȝe schulen fynde þe lessouns pistlis &amp; gospels þat ben rad in þe chirche aftir þe vse of Salisbury markid wiþ lettris of þe abc þe bigynnyngis &amp; þe eendyngis with twei strikis first is sett þe sonedaies &amp; ferials &amp; after þe sanctorum comoun &amp; propre writen a clause of þe bigynnyng þerof &amp; a clause of þe eending also</rubric>
                     <note>Includes the temporal, commemorations and the sanctoral, both the proper and common according to the rubric, but only the proper is present. The entries consist of the name of a liturgical occasion in red, abbreviated reference to a book and chapter of the Bible, an indexing letter in red, the opening words of a reading, <q>ende</q> in red, the closing words of a reading and double strokes. Larger initials with penwork at Christmas, Easter, Pentecost, Trinity and Candlemas. The table was apparently produced from an exemplar that had a full set of Old Testament and New Testament readings, but Old Testament readings were removed from the temporal, and only those from books included in MS. Bodl. 183 were retained in the commemorations and the sanctoral. <q>Osee</q>, erroneously entered at Friday, 17th week after Trinity <locus>(fol. x recto)</locus>, suggests that the exemplar had not only New Testament but also Old Testament readings (see Solopova, E., ‘Manuscript Evidence for the Patronage, Ownership and Use of the Wycliffite Bible’, in Poleg, E. and Light, L. (eds), <title>Form and Function in the Late Medieval Bible</title> (Leiden: Brill, 2013), pp. 333–49, pp. 338–40). Includes all feasts characteristic of the Later Version of the Wycliffite Bible apart from Giles (1 September) (Forshall, J. and Madden, F. (eds), <title>The Holy Bible … in the earliest English versions made from the Latin Vulgate by John Wycliffe and his followers</title>, 4 vols (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1850), vol. 4, pp. 683, 690–6). Commemorations are in the following order: the Virgin Mary, Trinity, Holy Ghost, Cross, angels, <q>ffor briþeren &amp; sistren &amp; salus populi</q>, peace, clear weather, reyn, <q>In time of batels</q>, <q>A man for him silf</q>, <q>ffor pestilence of bestis</q>, pilgrims, weddings, sinners, sick, <q>Pistils for dede</q>, <q>Gospels for dede</q>.</note>
                     <finalRubric>Thus eendiþ þe kalender of lessouns pistlis &amp; gospels</finalRubric>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem class="#biblia" n="2">
                     <locus>(fols. 1r–284r)</locus>
                     <title key="work_10451" type="desc">New Testament and part of Old Testament, three biographies and sapiential books, in the Later Version of the Wycliffite Bible</title>
                     <note>Old Testament books, except Tobit, have prologues in the Earlier Version of the Wycliffite Bible (slightly revised) (Dove, M., <title>The first English Bible: the text and context of the Wycliffite versions</title> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2007), p. 298). Chapter numbers in red as words in English or as Roman numerals, usually in the form <q>þe i cº</q>, preceding each chapter. Running titles on both rectos and versos consisting of an abbreviated title of a biblical book in red preceded by a blue paraph and a chapter number on pages containing the beginnings of chapters. Indexing letters and double strokes in the margins inside the bounding lines framing each page. The indexing letters are entered at the beginnings of lections only rather than consistently; the beginnings and ends of lections are also highlighted with yellow wash. Added material within the text is underlined in red in the Old Testament only. Contains corrections throughout presumably made in the original workshop. On fols. 82v, 173v, 192v and 212v the artist, who added the border, worked around corrections and glosses in the margins. Notes <q>fro þis</q> and <q>hidirto</q> in a medieval hand in the margins, marking passages in the Song of Song <locus>(fols. 237v–239r)</locus> and Ecclesiastes <locus>(fol. 260v)</locus>, apparently added in the original workshop (the sign used to indicate the start and end of passages is also used to link glosses to the text on fol. 212v).</note>
                     <note>[New Testament occupies quires III–XXIII]</note>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fol. 1r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Prologue to Matthew</title>
                        <rubric>Here bigynneþ þe prolog of matheu</rubric>
                        <incipit>Matheu þat was of iude</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fol. 1r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Matthew</title>
                        <rubric>Ierom on hise two prologis on Matheu seiþ þis plainly þe firste cº</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fol. 23v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Prologue to Mark</title>
                        <incipit>Mark þe gospeller was þe chosen seruaunt</incipit>
                        <rubric>Here eendiþ þe gospel on matheu &amp; bigynneþ þe prolog on Mark</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fol. 24r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Mark</title>
                        <rubric>þis seiþ Ierom in his prolog on mark And here bigynneþ þe i cº</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fol. 39r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Prologue to Luke</title>
                        <rubric>Here eendiþ þe gospel of Mark &amp; Here bigynneþ þe prolog on Luyk</rubric>
                        <incipit>Luk was a man of sirie</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fol. 39r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Luke</title>
                        <rubric>Ierom in his prolog on luk seiþ plainli þis sentence þe firste cº</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fol. 64r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Prologue to John</title>
                        <rubric>Here eendiþ þe gospel of luk &amp; bigynneþ þe prolog on Ioon</rubric>
                        <incipit>This is Joon euangelist</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fol. 64v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">John</title>
                        <rubric>Ierom in his prolog on Iohn seiþ al þis sentence And here bigynneþ þe gospel of Ioon þis þe firste chapitre</rubric>
                        <finalRubric>Here endiþ þe gospel of Ioon</finalRubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fol. 82v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Prologue to Romans</title>
                        <rubric>Here bigynneþ þe prolog to fore þe pistil to romayns</rubric>
                        <incipit>Romayns ben in þe cuntre</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fol. 82v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Romans</title>
                        <rubric>Ierom seiþ þis in his prolog to Romayns þe firste chapitre</rubric>
                        <note>Chapters 11–16 are imperfect because the lower part of fols. 89–92 is cut off.</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fol. 92v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Prologue to 1 Corinthians</title>
                        <rubric>Here eendiþ þe pistil of romayns &amp; bigynneþ þe prolog to þe firste Corenthies</rubric>
                        <incipit>Corynthies ben</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fol. 92v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">1 Corinthians</title>
                        <rubric>… in his prolog on þe firste pistil to Corinthies the firste chapitre</rubric>
                        <note>The beginning of the rubric and parts of the text of the prologue and chapters 1–3 are missing because the lower part of fols. 92–93 is cut off.</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fol. 102r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Prologue to 2 Corinthians</title>
                        <rubric>Here eendiþ þe firste pistil to Corinthies &amp; here bigynneþ þe prolog on þe secunde <sic>piste</sic> to Corinthies</rubric>
                        <incipit>Afftir penaunce</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fol. 102v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">2 Corinthians</title>
                        <rubric>Ierom in his prolog on þis epistil seiþ þis þe firste chapitre</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fol. 108v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Prologue to Galatians</title>
                        <rubric>Here eendiþ þe secunde pistil to Corinthies &amp; biginneþ þe prolog to Galathies</rubric>
                        <incipit>Galathies ben grekis</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fol. 108v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Galatians</title>
                        <rubric>Ierom in his prolog to galathies writiþ þus þe firste cº</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fol. 111v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Prologue to Ephesians</title>
                        <rubric>Here eendiþ þe pistil to galaþies &amp; biginneþ þe prolog on þe pistil to effeses</rubric>
                        <incipit>Effesians ben of asie</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fol. 111v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Ephesians</title>
                        <rubric>Ierom in his prolog on þis pistil seiþ þis þe i cº</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fol. 115r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Prologue to Philippians</title>
                        <rubric>Here eendiþ þe pistil to effecies &amp; bigynneþ þe prolog to þe pistlil of filipencis</rubric>
                        <incipit>Filipencis ben of macedonye</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fol. 115r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Philippians</title>
                        <rubric>Ierom in his prolog on þis pistil seiþ al þis The firste chapitre</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fol. 117v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Prologue to Colossians</title>
                        <rubric>Here eendiþ þe pistil to filipensis &amp; bigynneþ þe prolog on þe pistil to colosences</rubric>
                        <incipit>Colosencis ben also laodisencis</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fol. 117v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Colossians</title>
                        <rubric>Ierom in his prolog on þis pistil seiþ þis þe firste cº</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fol. 119v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Prologue to 1 Thessalonians</title>
                        <rubric>Here eendiþ þe pistil to Colocensis &amp; bigynneþ þe prolog on þe firste pistil to Tessalonycensis</rubric>
                        <incipit>Tessalonicensis ben Macedonies</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fol. 119v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">1 Thessalonians</title>
                        <rubric>Ierom in his prolog on þis pistil seiþ þis And here bigynneþ þe firste cº</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fol. 122r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Prologue to 2 Thessalonians</title>
                        <rubric>Here endiþ þe firste pistil to tessalonisencis and bigynneþ þe prolog to þe secunde pistil to tessalonysencis</rubric>
                        <incipit>The apostil wrytiþ</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fol. 122r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">2 Thessalonians</title>
                        <rubric>Ierom in his prolog on þis pistil seiþ þis þe i cº</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fol. 123r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Prologue to 1 Timothy</title>
                        <rubric>Here eendiþ þe secunde pistil to tessalonysencis &amp; bigynneþ þe prolog on þe firste pistil to tymoþe</rubric>
                        <incipit>He enfoormeþ and techiþ</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fol. 123r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">1 Timothy</title>
                        <rubric>Ierom in his prolog on þis pistil seiþ þis The firste chapitre</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fol. 126r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Prologue to 2 Timothy</title>
                        <rubric>Here eendiþ þe firste pistil to Tymoþe &amp; bigynneþ þe prolog on þe secunde pistil to Timoþe</rubric>
                        <incipit>He writith also</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fol. 126r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">2 Timothy</title>
                        <rubric>Ierom in his prolog on þis pistil seiþ þis þe firste cº</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fol. 128r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Prologue to Titus</title>
                        <rubric>Here eendiþ þe secunde pistil to tymoþe &amp; bigynneþ þe prolog on þe pistil to Tite</rubric>
                        <incipit>He warneþ tite</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fol. 128r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Titus</title>
                        <rubric>Ierom in his prolog on þis pistil seiþ þis Here bigynneþ þe firste chapitre</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fol. 129r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Prologue to Philemon</title>
                        <rubric>Here eendiþ þe pistil to tyte &amp; here bygynneþ the prolog on þe pistil to ffilemon</rubric>
                        <incipit>He makiþ famyliar</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fol. 129r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Philemon</title>
                        <rubric>Ierom in his prolog on þis pistil seiþ þis þe firste chapitre</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fol. 129v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Prologue to Hebrews</title>
                        <rubric>Here eendiþ the pistil to filemon &amp; bigynneþ þe prolog on þe pistil to Ebrews</rubric>
                        <incipit>First it is to seie</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fol. 130r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Hebrews</title>
                        <rubric>Ierom in his prolog on þis pistil seiþ þis Here bigynneþ þe firste chapitre</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fol. 137r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Prologue to Acts</title>
                        <rubric>Here eendiþ þe pistil to Ebrews And bigynneþ þe prolog on þe dedis of apostlis</rubric>
                        <incipit>Luk of antioche</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fol. 137v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Acts</title>
                        <rubric>Ierom in his prolog seiþ þis þe firste chapitre</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fol. 162r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">The Catholic epistles. Prologue to James</title>
                        <rubric>Here eendiþ þe deedis of apostlis And here bigynneþ þe prolog on þe pistlis of cristen feiþ þat ben seuene in ordre</rubric>
                        <incipit>The ordre of þe seuene epistlis</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fol. 162r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">James</title>
                        <rubric>Ierom in his prolog on þis pistil seiþ al þis Here bigynneþ þe pistil of Iames þe firste chapitre</rubric>
                        <note>The text of chapters 4–5 is slightly imperfect because the lower part of fol. 164 is cut off.</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fol. 164v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">1 Peter</title>
                        <rubric>Here eendiþ þe pistil of Iames And here bigynneþ þe firste pistil of petir þe firste cº</rubric>
                        <note>Slightly imperfect because the lower part of fols. 164–166 is cut off.</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fol. 167r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">2 Peter</title>
                        <rubric>Here endiþ þe firste pistil of petir &amp; here bigynneþ þe secunde þe i cº</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fol. 169r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">1 John</title>
                        <rubric>Here eendiþ þe secunde epistil of petir &amp; here bigynneþ þe firste pistil of Ioon þe firste cº</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fol. 171r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">2 John</title>
                        <rubric>Here eendiþ þe firste pistil of Ioon &amp; <sic>bigyngynneþ</sic> þe secunde þe firste cº</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fol. 171v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">3 John</title>
                        <rubric>Here eendiþ þe secunde pistil of Ioon &amp; here bigynne þe þridde þe firste chapitre</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fol. 172r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Jude</title>
                        <rubric>Here eendiþ þe iii pistil of Ioon &amp; here bigynneþ þe pistil of iudas þe i cº</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fol. 172v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Prologue to Apocalypse</title>
                        <rubric>Here eendiþ þe pistil of Iudas &amp; here bigynneþ a prolog on apocalips</rubric>
                        <incipit>Alle men þat wole</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fol. 173v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Apocalypse</title>
                        <rubric>Here endiþ þe prolog on þe apocalips þe firste chapitre</rubric>
                        <finalRubric>Here eendiþ þe apocalips of Ioon</finalRubric>
                        <note>Fol. 184 is ruled but blank.</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <note>[Old Testament occupies quires XXIV–XXXVI]</note>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fol. 185r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Tobit</title>
                        <rubric>Here bigynneþ tobie þe firste cº</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fol. 192r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Prologue to Judith</title>
                        <rubric>Here eendiþ tobie And here bigynneþ þe prolog on iudith</rubric>
                        <incipit>Anentis þe ebrews</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fol. 192v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Judith</title>
                        <rubric>Here eendiþ þe prolog of iudith &amp; bigynneþ þe book of hir þe firste cº</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fol. 201v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Prologue to Esther</title>
                        <rubric>Here endiþ þe book of iudith Here bigynneþ þe prolog on þe book of hester</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fol. 202r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Esther</title>
                        <rubric>Here eendiþ þe prolog of hester &amp; bigynneþ <sic>&amp;</sic> i cº</rubric>
                        <note>Usual notes on the differences between the Hebrew and Latin texts in red in chapters X–XV.</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fol. 212r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Prologue to Proverbs</title>
                        <rubric>Here endiþ þe book of hester Here bigynneth þe prolog on þe parablis of salamon</rubric>
                        <incipit>Ierom sendiþ greetinge to Cromacie</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fol. 212v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Proverbs</title>
                        <rubric>Here eendiþ þe prolog &amp; bigynneþ þe firste cº</rubric>
                        <note>Glosses in the original hand on fols. 212v–213r.</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fol. 230v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Prologue to Ecclesiastes</title>
                        <rubric>Here eendiþ þe parablis &amp; bigynneþ þe prolog on ecclesiates</rubric>
                        <incipit>Þis almoost þe fifþe</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fol. 231r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Ecclesiastes</title>
                        <rubric>Here eendiþ þe prolog &amp; bigynneþ þe firste chapitre</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fol. 236v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Song of Songs</title>
                        <rubric>Her eendiþ ecclesiates &amp; biginneþ song of songis þe i cº</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fol. 239v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Prologue to Wisdom</title>
                        <rubric>Here eendiþ cantica canticorum &amp; biginneþ þe prolog on sapiens</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fol. 239v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Wisdom</title>
                        <rubric>Here eendiþ þe prolog &amp; bigynneþ sapiens i chapº</rubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fol. 252r)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Ecclesiasticus</title>
                        <rubric>Here eendiþ þe book of wisdom &amp; here biginneþ þe book of ecclesiastici &amp; biginneþ þe firste cº</rubric>
                        <finalRubric>Here endiþ ecclesiasticus</finalRubric>
                        <note>Fol. 284v is ruled but blank.</note>
                     </msItem>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="3">
                     <locus>(fols. 285r–286v)</locus>
                     <note>Fol. 285r–v is blank.</note>
                     <note>Fol. 286r contains an added list of contents of the manuscript in Latin, in a late 15th-century hand, including the table of lections, New Testament (omitting Philemon) and Old Testament books. At the beginning: <q>In isto libro continentur omnia subscripta</q>.</note>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="perg">
                        <support>parchment, paper flyleaves; the lower part of leaves cut off in quires XII <locus>(fols. 89–96)</locus> and XX <locus>(fols. 161–168)</locus>, and damaged in quires XIV–XV <locus>(fols. 105–120)</locus></support>
                        <extent>302 leaves, <foreign rend="italic">c.</foreign><dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                              <height>292</height>
                              <width>194</width>
                           </dimensions>, originally possibly identical to Fairfax 11; leaves were trimmed in rebinding, occasionally causing the loss of decoration in the margins</extent>
                        <foliation>modern in pencil (flyleaves and the table of lections) and ink (the rest): i–xv + 1–287</foliation>
                        <collation><locus>(fol. i)</locus> paper flyleaf conjoint with the upper pastedown | <locus>(fols. ii–v)</locus> I (4) | <locus>(fols. vi–xv)</locus> II (10) | <locus>(fols. 1–280)</locus> I–XXXV (8) | <locus>(fols. 281–284)</locus> XXXVI (4) | <locus>(fols. 285–286)</locus> XXXVII (2) | <locus>(fol. 287)</locus> paper flyleaf conjoint with the lower pastedown. <signatures>Quire I (table of lections) has a signature ‘a’; quires containing New Testament <locus>(fols. 1–184)</locus> have signatures ‘a–z’; and quires containing Old Testament <locus>(fols. 185–284)</locus> have signatures ‘a–n’.</signatures> The last empty page of New Testament has an offset of decoration not found on the page it currently faces (the first page of Tobit). <catchwords>Catchwords survive (see Decoration); the one on fol. 216 is cut off.</catchwords>
                           <secFol><q>Gospel Matheu</q>
                              <locus>(fol. vii recto, table of lections)</locus>; <q>when crist schulde</q>
                              <locus>(fol. 2r, gospel)</locus></secFol></collation>
                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout columns="2" writtenLines="31 35">Ruled in ink for two columns with single vertical and double horizontal bounding lines extending the full height and width of page, and a further set of double bounding lines in all margins; prickings survive; 31–5 lines per page; written space: <foreign rend="italic">c.</foreign><dimensions type="ruled" unit="mm">
                              <height>125</height>
                              <width>185</width>
                           </dimensions>; nearly identical to MS Fairfax 11</layout>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc>
                     <handNote script="textualisNorthern">textura, the same hand as in MS. Fairfax 11; black ink</handNote>
                  </handDesc>
                  <decoDesc>
                     <summary>Possibly decorated by the same artist as MS. Fairfax 11 (de Hamel, C., <title>The book: a history of the Bible</title> (London: Phaidon, 2001), p. 178).</summary>
                     <decoNote type="decInit">5- to 8-line initials on gold background and full or three-quarters borders made of pink, blue and gold bars decorated with floral designs, interlace and gold disks at the beginnings of books.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="decInit">3-line gold initials on pink and blue background at the beginnings of prologues.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="colInit">2- to 3-line red or blue initials with contrasting blue or red penwork at the beginnings of chapters.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="marginal">Catchwords are decorated with drawings of animals, grotesques and human heads in black and red ink and yellow wash, including Christ’s head <locus>(fols. 8v, 48v)</locus>, crowned head <locus>(fol. 256v)</locus> and a head in a triple tiara <locus>(fol. 272v)</locus>. Running titles are also occasionally decorated with similar designs.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="rubrication">Rubrics in red; blue paraphs.</decoNote>
                  </decoDesc>
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <binding notAfter="1700" notBefore="1600">
                        <p>Brown leather over thick pasteboard, 17th century. Blind fillet-line border with floral corner-pieces round the outer edge of both covers; floral blind-roll rectangular figure with floral corner-pieces at the centre and blind-roll strips with the same designs next to the spine on both covers. Re-backed in the Bodleian with the original spine relaid. Five raised bands framed by blind fillet lines on spine. Floral decoration on the edges of covers. ‘183’ written in white paint on spine. Laid paper pastedowns and flyleaves. Fols. ii–iii and 286 have fragments of glue and red pigment and were pastedowns of an earlier binding.</p>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origPlace>
                        <country key="place_7002445">England</country>
                     </origPlace>
                     <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="1425" notBefore="1400">15th century, first quarter</origDate>
                     <p>Written by the same scribe as MS. Fairfax 11, and possibly illuminated by the same artist; MS. Bodl. 665 may be also the work of this scribe (de Hamel, C., <title>The book: a history of the Bible</title> (London: Phaidon, 2001)) though this is questioned by Peikola, M., ‘The Wycliffite Bible and “Central Midland Standard”: assessing the manuscript evidence’, <title>Nordic Journal of English Studies</title> 2 (2003), pp. 29–51. Consists of three codicologically separate parts: the table of lections, New Testament and a selection of Old Testament books. The parts were put together by a team that may have had access to several exemplars (New Testament and Old Testament may have been copied from different exemplars; Old Testament books have the Earlier Version of the Wycliffite Bible prologues). The table of lections, though described as being for the use of Sarum, was modified to reflect the selection of Old Testament texts in this manuscript. The sanctoral contains Old Testament readings only from Ecclesiastes, Wisdom, Proverbs, the Song of Song and Ecclesiasticus. The readings that are omitted (Malachi for Candlemas; Isaiah for Annunciation; Jeremiah and Isaiah for the eve, day and octave of John the Baptist; Ezekiel for Matthew and Luke) are all from books that are not included in MS. Bodl. 183. Commemorations omit most Old Testament readings, apart from the ones from Ecclesiastes and Esther, both included in MS. Bodl. 183. The table of lections, as is consistent with its standard form (Forshall, J. and Madden, F. (eds), <title>The Holy Bible … in the earliest English versions made from the Latin Vulgate by John Wycliffe and his followers</title>, 4 vols (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1850), vol. 4, pp. 683–96), does not contain any readings from Tobit or Judith, but both books are included in MS. Bodl. 183.</p>
                     <p>There may have been originally another text or texts at the beginning of the Old Testament section, as suggested by an offset of decoration on fol. 184v (see Collation). The parts were in their present order in the late 15th century as witnessed by the list of contents on fol. 286r.</p>
                     <p>Dialect survey: <list>
                           <item>ony(10), ech(10), fier(10), ȝouen(10), lijf(10), lijk(10), myche(10), say(6)/ sai(3) (sg.), saien(5)/siȝen(1) (pl.), silf(10), siche(6)/sich(2)/suche(2), þouȝ(8), þoru(9)/þoruȝ(1)</item>
                           <item>-iþ(9)/-eþ(1) (pres.ind.3sg.), -en(10) (pres.ind.pl.), -ynge(5)/-inge(5) (pres. part.), sche(10) (3sg.fem.pronoun, nom.), þei(10) (3pl.pronoun, nom.), hem(10) (3pl.pronoun, oblique), her(10) (3pl.pronoun, possessive)</item>
                        </list></p>
                  </origin>
                  <provenance>Late 15th-century clerical (?) owner who listed the contents in Latin.</provenance>
                  <provenance><persName key="person_91800083" role="fmo">Robert Barker</persName> (<foreign rend="italic">c.</foreign>1568–1646), king’s printer, see <title>Oxford Dictionary of National Biography</title> entry ‘Authorized Version of the Bible, translators of the’.</provenance>
                  <acquisition when="1604">Bodleian Library: presented by Robert Barker in 1604. Earlier shelfmarks: ‘Th E 5 5’, ‘NE. C. 4.1.’ <locus>(fol. v recto)</locus>.</acquisition>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>Elizabeth Solopova, <title><ref target="https://jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1gn6cmr">Manuscripts of the Wycliffite Bible in the Bodleian and Oxford College Libraries</ref></title>, Exeter Medieval Texts and Studies (Liverpool: Liverpool University Press, 2016), no. 2. Previously described: <listBibl>
                              <bibl>Otto Pächt and J. J. G. Alexander, <title><ref target="https://catalog.hathitrust.org/Record/000468709">Illuminated Manuscripts in the Bodleian Library, Oxford</ref></title>, III (1973), no. 806 [decoration, origin, date]</bibl>
                              <bibl>Summary Catalogue (1922) [contents, physical description, provenance and acquisition]</bibl>
                           </listBibl>
                           <listBibl>
                              <bibl facs="aap0224.gif" type="SC">Summary Catalogue, vol. 2, part 1, p. 203</bibl>
                           </listBibl>
                        </source>
                     </recordHist>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <surrogates><bibl subtype="partial" type="digital-facsimile"><ref target="https://digital.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/objects/ffd0eea3-7f87-4e83-a3f4-612d64e83084/"><title>Digital Bodleian</title></ref>
                        <note>(6 images from 35mm slides)</note></bibl></surrogates>
                  <listBibl type="WRAPPER">
                     <listBibl type="PRINT">
                        <bibl>Madan, F. and Craster, H. H. E., <title>Summary catalogue of western manuscripts in the Bodleian Library at Oxford</title>, vol. 2, part I <title>(collections received before 1660 and miscellaneous MSS acquired during the first half of the 17th century), nos. 1–3490</title> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1922), no. 2084.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Forshall, J. and Madden, F. (eds), <title>The Holy Bible … in the earliest English versions made from the Latin Vulgate by John Wycliffe and his followers</title>, 4 vols (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1850), vol. 1, pp. xxxv, xlvii, sigla <title>a</title> – Tobit to Ecclesiasticus; <title>L</title> – prologues from Tobit to Wisdom.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Fristedt, S. L., <title>The Wycliffe Bible</title>, 3 vols (Stockholm: Almquvist &amp; Wiksells, 1953–73), vol. 1, p. 15.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Ker, N. R., Piper, A. J., Watson, A. G. and Cunningham, I. C., <title>Medieval manuscripts in British libraries</title>, 5 vols (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1969–2002), vol. 4, p. 752.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Hudson, A., ‘Lollard book production’, in Griffiths, J. and Pearsall, D. A. (eds), <title>Book production and publishing in Britain 1375–1475</title> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1989), pp. 125–42, pp. 44, 140 n. 29.</bibl>
                        <bibl><title>The Bodleian Library and its treasures: September 17–October 14, 1990, Tokyo, Fuji Art Museum</title> (Tokyo: Fuji Art Museum, 1990), no. 23.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Scott, K. L., <title>Later Gothic manuscripts, 1390–1490</title>, Survey of manuscripts illuminated in the British Isles (HMMSBI 6), 2 vols (London: Harvey Miller, 1996), vol. 1, p. 78 n. 57; vol. 2, p. 79.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Lindberg, C. (ed.), <title>King Henry’s Bible, MS. Bodley 277: the revised version of the Wyclif Bible</title>, 4 vols (Stockholm: Almqvist &amp; Wiksell, 1999–2004), vol. 3, p. 5.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Scott, K. L. (gen. ed.), <title>An index of images in English manuscripts from the time of Chaucer to Henry VIII, c.1380–c.1509: the Bodleian Library, Oxford</title>, 3 vols (Turnhout: Harvey Miller Publishers, 2000–02), vol. 1, p. 54, no. 160.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Peikola, M., ‘The Wycliffite Bible and “Central Midland Standard”: assessing the manuscript evidence’, <title>Nordic Journal of English Studies</title> 2 (2003), pp. 29–51, pp. 39–40.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Dove, M., <title>The first English Bible: the text and context of the Wycliffite versions</title> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2007), pp. 59, 94, 96, 98, 100, 141, 156, 202, 203, 298.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Scott, K. L., ‘The remains of a missal: Chetham’s Library MS. 6713’, in Smith, K. A. and Krinsky, C. H. (eds), <title>Tributes to Lucy Freeman Sandler: studies in manuscript illumination</title> (London: Harvey Miller, 2007), p. 301 n. 14.</bibl>
                     </listBibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2023-03-23">Add Solopova description.</change>
         <change when="2020-05-07">Description revised to incorporate all information in SC.</change>
         <change when="2017-07-01">First online publication.</change>
         <change when="2017-05-25"><persName>James Cummings</persName> Up-converted the markup using <ref target="https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl">https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl</ref></change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>