<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/msDesc/consolidated-tei-schema/refs/heads/master/msdesc-mmol.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/msDesc/consolidated-tei-schema/refs/heads/master/msdesc-mmol.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="manuscript_1743">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>MS. Bodl. 756</title>
            <title type="collection">MSS. Bodl. (Bodley)</title>
           
            <respStmt xml:id="SC">
               <resp when="1922">Cataloguer</resp>
               <persName>Falconer Madan</persName>
               <persName>H. H. E. Craster</persName>
            </respStmt>
            
            <respStmt xml:id="SJB">
               <resp when="2022">Encoding</resp>
               <persName>Stewart Brookes</persName>
            </respStmt>
           
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </publisher>
            <idno type="msID">MS_Bodl_756</idno>
            <idno type="collection">Bodl</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="MS_Bodl_756" xml:lang="en">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <region type="county">Oxfordshire</region>
                  <settlement key="place_7011931">Oxford</settlement>
                  <institution>University of Oxford</institution>
                  <repository>Bodleian Library</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">MS. Bodl. 756</idno>
                  <idno type="ieArk">ark:29072/x0s4655g24g9</idno><idno type="crArk">ark:29072/x0s1784k415f</idno><altIdentifier type="internal">
                     <idno type="SCN">2526</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents>
                  
                  <msItem n="1" xml:id="MS_Bodl_756-item1"><locus from="1r" to="145v" type="inferred"/>
                     <author key="person_281829495">Ambrosiaster</author>
                     <title key="work_487">Commentaries on the Epistles of St Paul</title>
                     <note>Each with prologue and with a separate rubric</note>
                    
                     <msItem>
                       <locus from="1" to="42r" type="inferredEnd">(fol. 1)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Romans</title>
                     </msItem>
                     
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="42v" to="73r" type="inferredEnd">(fol. 42v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">1 Corinthians</title>
                     </msItem>
                     
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="73v" to="89" type="inferredEnd">(fol. 73v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">2 Corinthians</title>
                     </msItem>
                     
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="90" to="101r" type="inferredEnd">(fol. 90)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Galatians</title>
                     </msItem>
                     
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="101v" to="110r" type="inferredEnd">(fol. 101v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Ephesians</title>
                     </msItem>
                     
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="110v" to="116r" type="inferredEnd">(fol. 110v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Philippians</title>
                     </msItem>
                     
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="116v" to="119" type="inferredEnd">(fol. 116v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">1 Thessalonians</title>
                     </msItem>
                     
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="120" to="121" type="inferredEnd">(fol. 120)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">2 Thessalonians</title>
                     </msItem>
                           
                     <msItem>
                         <locus from="122" to="128r" type="inferredEnd">(fol. 122)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Colossians</title>
                     </msItem>
                        
                      <msItem>
                         <locus from="128v" to="130r" type="inferredEnd">(fol. 128v)</locus>
                         <title type="desc">Titus</title>
                      </msItem>        
                        
                      <msItem>
                         <locus from="130v" to="137" type="inferredEnd">(fol. 130v)</locus>
                         <title type="desc">1 Timothy</title>
                      </msItem>        
                        
                      <msItem>
                         <locus from="138" to="141" type="inferredEnd">(fol. 138)</locus>
                         <title type="desc">2 Timothy</title>
                      </msItem>
                        
                      <msItem>
                         <locus from="142" to="145" type="inferredEnd">(fol. 142)</locus>
                         <title type="desc">Philemon</title>
                       </msItem> 
                        
                        
                     <textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>
                    
                  </msItem>
                     
               </msContents>
               
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="perg">
                        <support>parchment</support>
                        
                        <extent>
                           <seg type="leaf"><measure type="laterEndleaf" quantity="2">ii</measure> + <measure type="leaf" quantity="145">145</measure></seg> leaves
                           <dimensions unit="in" type="binding">
                              <height>11.875</height>
                              <width>8.375</width>
                           </dimensions>
                        </extent>
                     </supportDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc>
                     <handNote script="uncial" scope="minor">The lemmata are often in Uncials</handNote>
                  </handDesc>
                  <additions>Teresa Webber, <title>
                        <ref target="https://www.zotero.org/groups/434020/bodleian_library_western_medieval_manuscripts_bibliography/tags/MS.%20Bodl.%20698/items/6XUT395I/item-list">Scribes and Scholars at Salisbury Cathedral c. 1075-c. 1125</ref>
                     </title> (1992), p. 20, notes the experimental (and spasmodic) use of catchwords in this manuscript, 'unusual in England at this time'. Comparable examples from Salisbury are <ref target="https://medieval.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/catalog/manuscript_1423">MS. Bodl. 392</ref> and Salisbury Cathedral, MSS 9, 12, 33, 169, 221, and 222</additions>
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <summary><p>Now an English, Salisbury, 15th century inboard rebinding with a ‘Gothic’ structure (cf. Szirmai, pp. 173-174); the sewing supports laced over the outer spine edge of the oak boards, reusing the boards of an earlier binding. Covered with alum-tawed skin and with compound endbands worked in blue and white thread through the covering. This is the second binding of the manuscript, it was repaired and rebound for and probably at Salisbury. There are blank parchment patches to the spine-folds of a number of quires, either covering the entire fold or as smaller patches at head or tail: repairs to outer bifolia of quires 1-4, 12, 16-17; and repairs to inner bifolia of quires 2 and 14 (fols. 9/16, 105/108). A second set of quire numbers were added during this repair and rebinding in the tail margin of the first leaf of quire 1-18 in the form ‘+’, ‘1’-‘17’. The binding has the remains of a left-to-right fore-edge clasp that closed onto a flat slotted catchplate, matching the catchplate added in the 15th century to MS. Bodl. 835. Each board, at the centre of the tail edge, has a recess and two vertical holes with matching holes and green staining to the cover from two now removed copper-alloy chain staples. The chain staple position matches those found on the left boards of MSS. Bodl. 516 and 835, both manuscripts with Salisbury provenance. The manuscript and binding were repaired for the Bodleian in the late 19th or early 20th century, with extensive repairs to quires 15-18.</p>
                        <p>First binding: English, Salisbury, later 11th or early 12th century, inboard binding, date and location of binding as manuscript, with a ‘Romanesque’ structure (cf. Szirmai, pp. 140-142); the two sewing supports laced through oblong tunnels in the spine edge of wooden boards. A binding with canted spine-edge corners and endbands, but without a fastening. The boards used for the 15th century rebinding are a pair of recycled and turned boards, with the earlier support lacing now at the fore-edge of the boards, most probably reused from the first binding of this manuscript. The positions of the earlier sewing stations within the manuscript match the positions of the earlier sewing support lacing of the turned boards. The technique of the earlier board attachment, where each support slip is separated within the exterior lacing channel and each half is secured individually with wooden pegs at staggered holes is not recorded by Szirmai for bindings with a ‘Romanesque’ structure. The lacing technique is also found on MS. Bodl. 835, a manuscript copied and bound at Salisbury in the late 11th or early 12th-century as an inboard binding with a ‘Romanesque’ structure.
                        </p>
                        <dimensions type="binding" unit="mm">
                           <height>302</height>
                           <width>215</width>
                           <depth>63</depth>
                        </dimensions>   <p>The bookbinding is described in the order of binding using the controlled vocabulary of the Language of Bindings Thesaurus (LoB). Digital pulsed X-ray photographs of the wooden boards were taken in February 2025 at the Ashmolean Museum, Oxford for this binding entry.
                        </p> <p>Bookbinding description by Andrew Honey (July 2026).</p>
                     </summary>
                     <binding notAfter="1110" notBefore="1090">
                        <head>First binding, Salisbury, later 11th or early 12th century</head>
                        <endleaves xmlns="http://www.example.org/ns/msdesc" status="unknown">Left: No evidence
                           Right: No evidence.
                        </endleaves>
                        <sewing xmlns="http://www.example.org/ns/msdesc" status="lost" supports="2" sewing="supported">Now lost, the manuscript was sewn on two supports and there are sewing stations that match the positions of earlier support lacing channels on the turned and reused boards (see boards). Sewing stations (measured in mm from the head-edge at fols. 36v-37r): 90 (support 1), 211 (support 2).</sewing>
                        <boards xmlns="http://www.example.org/ns/msdesc" status="extant" material="wood" squares="unknown">The 15th century rebinding uses a pair of recycled and turned boards, with the earlier support lacing now at the fore-edge of the boards, most probably reused from the first binding of this manuscript. Wooden oak boards, 11-12 mm thick (including later covering material), wood identified from grain pattern exposed on inner faces of boards. X-rays of the boards, and pegs visible on the inner face of each board, show that the lacing paths match the sewing stations of the first sewing of the manuscript (see sewing). Although the original spine edges of the boards have been altered by 15th century peripheral cushions, the X-rays confirm that the two earlier sewing supports were laced through oblong tunnels in the spine edge of the boards into channels in a short lacing path, with each support slip separated within the lacing channel on the outer face of the board, and each half secured individually with wooden pegs at staggered holes. This form of attachment is not recorded by Szirmai for bindings with a ‘Romanesque’ structure, though it was also used for MS. Bodl. 835, a manuscript copied and bound in Salisbury in the late 11th or early 12th-century as an inboard binding with a ‘Romanesque’ structure.</boards>
                        <edges xmlns="http://www.example.org/ns/msdesc" decoration="none">The edges of the bookblock were trimmed for the 15th century rebinding, though the trim was modest and traces of canted spine-edge corners for the first binding can be seen in some quires. </edges>
                        <spine xmlns="http://www.example.org/ns/msdesc" status="unknown">No evidence.</spine>
                        <endbands xmlns="http://www.example.org/ns/msdesc" status="lost" subtype="structural">Now replaced. The X-rays show that the first binding had endbands with cores laced into the boards at the canted spine-edge corners, in a short lacing path.</endbands><!-- subtype is wierd here -->
                        <covering xmlns="http://www.example.org/ns/msdesc" status="unknown">No evidence.</covering>
                        <decoNote type="unknown">No evidence.</decoNote>
                        <fastenings xmlns="http://www.example.org/ns/msdesc" status="none">None. There are no marks from fastenings shown on the X-rays of the boards and no stains to the first or last text leaves (fols. 1 and 142).</fastenings>
                        <furniture xmlns="http://www.example.org/ns/msdesc" status="unknown">No evidence.</furniture>
                        <alterations xmlns="http://www.example.org/ns/msdesc" status="unknown">No evidence.</alterations>
                        <bookmarks xmlns="http://www.example.org/ns/msdesc" status="unknown">No evidence.</bookmarks>
                        <curtains xmlns="http://www.example.org/ns/msdesc" status="none">None.</curtains>
                        <chaining xmlns="http://www.example.org/ns/msdesc" status="none">None.</chaining>
                        <labels xmlns="http://www.example.org/ns/msdesc" status="unknown">No evidence.</labels>
                     </binding>
                     <binding notBefore="1400" notAfter="1500">
                        <head>Rebinding, Salisbury, 15th century</head>
                        <endleaves xmlns="http://www.example.org/ns/msdesc" status="partiallyExtant" type="separate" support="perg" subtype="firstUse">Left: Separate endleaves added for the rebinding, originally an endleaf unit of two bifolia of thick blank parchment. Now, the unfoliated partial torn remains of a lifted pastedown, before and stuck to fol. I and conjoint with fol. ii, a free endleaf. Fol. i, a free endleaf conjoint with a now excised free endleaf whose stub is between fols. i and ii.
                           </endleaves>
                        <endleaves xmlns="http://www.example.org/ns/msdesc" subtype="firstUse" support="perg" type="separate" status="partiallyExtant">Right: Separate endleaves added for the rebinding, originally an endleaf unit of two bifolia of thick blank parchment. Now fol. 143, a free endleaf conjoint with fol. 145, a now lifted pastedown. Fol. 144, a free endleaf conjoint with a now excised free endleaf whose stub is between fols. 143 and 144.
                        </endleaves>
                        <sewing xmlns="http://www.example.org/ns/msdesc" supports="5" status="extant" sewing="supported">Sewn all-along as linked supported or herringbone sewing with undyed plain thread at seven sewing stations on five raised alum-tawed intertwisted split thong sewing supports (8- 11 mm wide). Sewing stations (measured in mm from the head-edge at fols. 36v-37r): 24 (kettle), 44 (support 1), 97 (support 2), 147 (support 3), 197 (support 4), 245 (support 5), 269 (kettle), 294 (tail).</sewing>
                        <boards xmlns="http://www.example.org/ns/msdesc" reused="true" status="extant" material="wood" squares="true">The 15th century rebinding uses a pair of recycled and turned boards, most probably reused from the first binding of this manuscript. Wooden oak boards with modest squares, 11-12 mm thick (including covering material), wood identified from grain pattern exposed on inner faces of boards. Peripheral cushions to the boards. The five sewing supports are laced to the boards with parallel two-hole lacing and secured with wooden pegs at the exit holes. The channels to the inner face of the boards are staggered with supports 2 and 4 wider than 1, 3 and 5 (Szirmai, fig. 9.33C, p. 223).</boards>
                        <edges xmlns="http://www.example.org/ns/msdesc" decoration="none">The edges of the bookblock are trimmed undecorated. </edges>
                        <spine xmlns="http://www.example.org/ns/msdesc" profile="rounded" status="extant">The rebinding has a slight round spine shape, no spine linings.</spine>
                        <endbands xmlns="http://www.example.org/ns/msdesc" type="compound" subtype="structural" status="extant">Compound chevron endbands, consisting of primary sewing on a single core of alum-tawed skin with plain undyed thread, the endband cores laced into the boards. Secondary chevron sewing in blue and undyed plain thread after the book was covered, now worn, worked through the covering material at head and tail of spine.</endbands>
                        <covering xmlns="http://www.example.org/ns/msdesc" extent="full" status="extant" material="skinTawed">Full cover, now worn, of alum-tawed skin used hairside out (from follicle pattern probably sheep). The cover is moulded over the spine and sewing supports with tying-up marks at the centre and at either side of the sewing supports, turned in on all edges with lapped mitre corners. The covering was not turned in at the spine and is trimmed to the height of the endbands, with the secondary endbands worked through the covering material at head and tail of the spine.</covering>
                        <decoNote type="unknown">None.</decoNote>
                        <fastenings xmlns="http://www.example.org/ns/msdesc" type="clasp" direction="ltr" quantity="1" status="partiallyExtant">The rebinding has a single left-to-right fore-edge clasp, though the clasp and strap beyond the edge of the board are now lost. The fastening consisted of a short clasp strap of alum-tawed skin (13 mm wide, 2 mm thick) attached to the left board under a slit in the covering with two copper-alloy nails. The x-ray confirms that the clasp closed onto a triangular-shaped flat slotted catchplate attached to the left board under a slit in the covering with a copper-alloy nail. The catchplate is identical to that on MS. Bodl. 835, another manuscript with a Salisbury provenance, and similar to Szirmai fig. 9.53c-e (found on three English bindings of the 14th-15th centuries) and Howsam A.6.1 and A.6.3 (four archaeological examples excavated at Battle and Fountains abbeys; Howsam, Charlotte L. ‘Book Fastenings and Furnishings: An Archaeology of Late Medieval Books’. Phd, University of Sheffield, 2016, pp. 36, 423-4, 442).
                           
                        </fastenings>
                        <furniture xmlns="http://www.example.org/ns/msdesc" status="none">None.</furniture>
                        <alterations xmlns="http://www.example.org/ns/msdesc" notAfter="1910" notBefore="1890" >The manuscript was repaired for the Bodleian in the late 19th or early 20th century, with extensive repairs to the leaves of quires 15-18 (fols. 111-142) and with other smaller paper patches throughout. The sewing was cut to remove quires 15-18 and most of their leaves are laminated with a facing of transparent paper on both sides over infills of wove paper. The repaired leaves were trimmed and the quires were resewn all-along at supports 1, 3 and 5 with new thread. Losses to the covering were patched with alum-tawed and tanned skin.</alterations>
                        <bookmarks xmlns="http://www.example.org/ns/msdesc" status="none">None.</bookmarks>
                        <curtains xmlns="http://www.example.org/ns/msdesc" status="none">None.</curtains>
                        <chaining xmlns="http://www.example.org/ns/msdesc">There are stains, holes and recesses from now removed copper-alloy chain staples at the centre of the tail edge of each board; two holes in a vertical line, with a vertical recess on the inner face of the board (60-63 x 15 mm), and with green stains to the covering. There are rust marks to the tail edge of the bookblock from an iron chain, see also MSS. Bodl. 516 and 835 for the same chain staple position on the left board, and MS. Rawl. C. 723 for the same rust marks, all manuscripts with Salisbury provenance.</chaining>
                        <labels xmlns="http://www.example.org/ns/msdesc">‘I’ in brown ink to left cover where covered by chain staple. </labels>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               
               </physDesc>
               
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="1100" notBefore="1000">11th century</origDate>
                  </origin>
                  <provenance type="MLGB3_provenance_evidence" source="http://mlgb3.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/mlgb/book/4967">
                     <orgName role="fmo" key="org_144217511">Salisbury, Wiltshire, Cathedral church of St Mary the Virgin</orgName>: (<ref target="http://mlgb3.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/mlgb/book/4967/">MLGB3</ref>);  
                     <ref target="http://mlgb3.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/mlgb/?search_term=removed+from+Sherborne&amp;field_to_search=medieval_library&amp;page_size=All&amp;order_by=provenance_location_shelfmark&amp;output_style=treeview">
                        see medieval manuscripts removed from Sherborne in 1078(?)</ref>
                  </provenance>
                  
                     <provenance>A Salisbury scribe (s. xii) wrote the letters 'D.M.' as a 'nota bene' sign in the margins of Aberdeen UL 216, 
                     
                     <ref target="https://medieval.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/catalog/manuscript_1423">MS. Bodl. 392</ref>, 
                     <ref target="https://medieval.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/catalog/manuscript_1477">MS. Bodl. 444</ref> (fols. 1-27), 
                     MS. Bodl. 756,  
                     <ref target="https://medieval.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/catalog/manuscript_1751">MS. Bodl. 765</ref>, 
                     <ref target="https://medieval.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/catalog/manuscript_1753">MS. Bodl. 768</ref>, 
                     <ref target="https://medieval.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/catalog/manuscript_1825">MS. Bodl. 835</ref>, 
                     <ref target="https://medieval.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/catalog/manuscript_4871">MS. Fell 1</ref>, 
                     <ref target="https://medieval.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/catalog/manuscript_4871">MS. Fell 4</ref>, 
                     <ref target="https://medieval.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/catalog/manuscript_8331">MS. Rawl. C. 723</ref>,  
                     Salisbury Cathedral, MSS. 10, 24, 25, 37, 67, 78, 88, 106, 128, 129, 135, 140, 154, 159, 165 
                     (<ref target="http://mlgb3.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/mlgb/book/4967">MLGB3</ref>); see Webber, <title>
                        <ref target="https://www.zotero.org/groups/434020/bodleian_library_western_medieval_manuscripts_bibliography/tags/MS.%20Bodl.%20698/items/6XUT395I/item-list">Scribes and Scholars at Salisbury Cathedral c. 1075-c. 1125</ref>
                     </title> (1992), pp. 132-139</provenance>
                  
                  <provenance>
                     <p>'B' at head of fol. 1r (<ref target="http://mlgb3.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/mlgb/book/4967">MLGB3</ref>)</p>
                  </provenance>
                  
                  <provenance>
                     <p>'2. Liber Bibliothecae Saresburiensis' (s. xvii): No. 2 in a set of 7 numbered manuscripts from Salisbury (no. 1 has not been identified). 
                        The other 6 manuscripts are:
                        
                        No. 3: <ref target="https://medieval.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/catalog/manuscript_1690">MS. Bodl. 698</ref>, 
                        No. 4: <ref target="https://medieval.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/catalog/manuscript_1751">MS. Bodl. 765</ref>, 
                        No. 5: <ref target="https://medieval.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/catalog/manuscript_1753">MS. Bodl. 768</ref>,
                        No. 6: <ref target="https://medieval.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/catalog/manuscript_1541">MS. Bodl. 516</ref>, 
                        No. 7: <ref target="https://medieval.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/catalog/manuscript_1825">MS. Bodl. 835</ref>
                     </p>
                  </provenance>
       
                  <acquisition>Salisbury Cathedral library was raided in the English Civil War, and this manuscript was probably given (as part of the set of 7 manuscripts) 
                     to the Bodleian during or soon after the war, but it is not found in Bodleian lists until about 1655</acquisition>
                
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>
                           Description adapted (December 2022) by Stewart J. Brookes from the Summary Catalogue (1922), with additional reference to published literature as cited
                        <listBibl>
                              <bibl facs="aap0431.gif" type="SC">Summary Catalogue, vol. 2, part 1, p. 410</bibl>
                           </listBibl>
                        </source>
                     </recordHist>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <surrogates>
                     <bibl subtype="partial" type="digital-facsimile">
                        <ref target="https://digital.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/objects/bd28af01-338b-451a-96d4-521de487955c/">
                           <title>Digital Bodleian</title>
                        </ref>
                        <note>(1 image from 35mm slides)</note>
                     </bibl>
                  </surrogates>
                  <listBibl type="WRAPPER">
                     <listBibl type="INTERNET">
                        <head>Online resources:</head>
                        <bibl>
                           <ref target="https://clasp.ell.ox.ac.uk/db-latest/apmo/entry/594">
                              <title>Electronic Gneuss-Lapidge</title> (entry 594)</ref>
                        </bibl>
                        <bibl>
                           <ref target="http://mlgb3.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/mlgb/book/4967">
                              <title>MLGB3: Medieval Libraries of Great Britain</title>
                           </ref>
                        </bibl>
                     </listBibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2022-12-12">Description revised to incorporate all the information in the Summary Catalogue (1922)</change>
         <change when="2022-04-04">Add binding information from Summary Catalogue.</change>
         <change when="2021-12-14">Add provenance information from MLGB3.</change>
         <change when="2017-07-01">First online publication.</change>
         <change when="2017-05-25">
            <persName>James Cummings</persName> Up-converted the markup using <ref target="https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl">https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl</ref>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>