<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xml:id="manuscript_10618" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Jesus College MS. 94</title>
            <title type="collection">Jesus College MSS.</title>
            <respStmt xml:id="AD">
               <resp when="2026-02">Description</resp>
               <persName>Andrew Dunning</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </publisher>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">This summary description is released under a CC0 licence.</licence>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/share-your-work/public-domain/pdm/">The text of H. O. Coxe, <title>Catalogus codicum mss. qui in collegiis aulisque Oxoniensibus hodie adservantur</title>, is free of known copyright restrictions.</licence>
            </availability>
            <idno type="msID">Jesus_College_MS_94</idno>
            <idno type="collection">Jesus_College_MSS</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="Jesus_College_MS_94" xml:lang="en">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <repository>Jesus College</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">Jesus College MS. 94</idno>
                  <idno type="ieArk">ark:29072/j8mp48sb45nj</idno>
                  <idno type="crArk">ark:29072/j8mk61rf62bs</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <head>Alexander Neckam, Commentaries on the Psalter and Proverbs</head>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="perg">
                        <support>parchment</support>
                        <extent>i + 128 leaves</extent>
                        <foliation>Foliated in modern pencil in top-right corner, first on the opening pages of quires and later continuously.</foliation>
                        <collation>
                           <formula>i, 1<hi rend="superscript">8</hi>, 2–4<hi rend="superscript">10</hi> (·iiii·), 5<hi rend="superscript">10</hi> (·ix·), 6<hi rend="superscript">8</hi> (x) || 7<hi rend="superscript">8</hi>, 8<hi rend="superscript">8</hi>, 9<hi rend="superscript">8-1</hi> (8th cancelled) || 10–14<hi rend="superscript">8</hi>, 15<hi rend="superscript">6</hi>, 16<hi rend="superscript">4</hi> (4 pastedown)</formula>
                        </collation>
                     </supportDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <binding contemporary="true">
                        <p>Contemporary wooden boards covered in whittawed leather, finish mostly worn away; upper two thirds recovered. Packed straight sewing attached to four white thongs, 10 mm wide, now broken at the join to the left board. Label written on left board, <q>Alexander Nekam in psal</q> (17th century, same hand as pressmark on back). Parchment label affixed to right board, covered with horn and attached with brass nails: <q>Alexander Neckam super psalterium. Tractatus super parabolas salamonis. Mulierem fortem quis inveniet:</q> (15th century). This positioning implies that the book was kept on a desk in a library room with the left board facing down.</p>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <provenance notAfter="1540"><orgName key="org_211447911">Cirencester, Augustinian Abbey of St Mary the Virgin</orgName>. The volume consists of three manuscripts annotated by Alexander Neckam in various states of completion; it may have been assembled at his death in 1217, possibly by <persName ref="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q60800793" role="scr">Walter of Mileto</persName>, who annotated it. In 1246 × 1260, <persName ref="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q123182967" role="scr">Geoffrey Brito</persName>, a canon of Cirencester and Alexander’s nephew, annotated these copies of <title>Tractatus super prouerbia Salomonis</title> and <title>Tractatus super <q>Mulierem fortem</q></title> while preparing his miscellany <title>Sol meldunensis</title>, but used a revised copy of <title xml:lang="la">Glose super psalterium</title>, MS. Bodl. 284 (Dunning, ‘Geoffrey Brito’s <title>Sol meldunensis</title>’, 358–60), probably due to the fragmentary state of this work in MS. 94. Inscribed, <q>Liber sancte Marie Cyrencestris in quo continentur glose super psalterium quas composuit magister Alexander. Item tractatus super principium parabolarum et finem. Item tractatus super Mulierem fortem</q> (14th century, fol. 1r). Leland observed this manuscript at Cirencester in 1536 × 1540 (Webber and Watson, no. A9.*1).</provenance>
                  <provenance notAfter="1555" notBefore="1539"><persName key="person_65071134" role="fmo">Sir John Prise (1502?–1555)</persName>. Prise was one of the royal commissioners at the dissolution of the monasteries and acquired many books from Cirencester (Fulton, 63–6).</provenance>
                  <provenance notAfter="1602" notBefore="1555"><name key="person_4805" role="fmo">Gregory Prise (1535–1600)</name>. The book appears in the list of his 1602 donation (register for 1621/2, Oxford, Jesus College, RE.1; printed in Ker, 13).</provenance>
                  <acquisition when="1602"><orgName key="org_122611272">Oxford, Jesus College</orgName>. Pressmarks: <q>16</q> (back, 17th century, same hand as note on left board); <q>1 Arch 4_2</q> (slip added to back, 17th century, and written on fol. i verso); <q>MS. Jesus Coll. Ox. B. 94</q> (printed blue slip added to back, early 20th century); <q>2064 = 45</q> (<q>45</q> in same hand as <q>Alexander Neckam</q>, above, <q>2064 =</q> added, 17th century?); <q>45 (16)</q> (top-right corner of fol. 1r, 17th century?); <q>43</q> (top of fol. 1r, 17th century?).</acquisition>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>
                           <p>Description by Andrew Dunning (February 2026). Previously described:</p>
                           <listBibl>
                              <bibl facs="jes0094.png">H. O. Coxe, <title>Catalogus codicum mss. qui in collegiis aulisque Oxoniensibus hodie adservantur</title> (1852)</bibl>
                           </listBibl>
                        </source>
                     </recordHist>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>Dunning, Andrew N. J., ‘<ref target="https://hdl.handle.net/1807/72968">Alexander Neckam’s Manuscripts and the Augustinian Canons of Oxford and Cirencester</ref>’, PhD diss., University of Toronto, 2016.</bibl>
                     <bibl>Dunning, Andrew N. J., ‘<ref target="https://doi.org/10.3828/blr.2018.31.1-2.188">The Ascott Park Gateway’s Link to Alexander Neckam (1157–1217), an Early Oxford Lecturer</ref>’, <title>Bodleian Library Record</title>, 31/1–2 (2018), 188–91.</bibl>
                     <bibl>Dunning, Andrew N. J., ‘<ref target="https://ora.ox.ac.uk/objects/uuid:19507830-e60a-4bc6-ac57-df23d1d9c845">Friendship and Publishing in Geoffrey Brito’s <title>Sol meldunensis</title>: A Collaborative Gift Book from Cirencester Abbey for Geoffrey, Abbot of Malmesbury, 1246–60</ref>’, <title>Transactions of the Cambridge Bibliographical Society</title>, 17/3–4 (2022–3), 340–75.</bibl>
                     <bibl>Dunning, Andrew N. J., ‘<ref target="https://doi.org/10.1093/odnb/9780198614128.013.111226">Mileto [Melida, Melide], Walter of (fl. c.1170–c.1220), Scribe and Augustinian Canon</ref>’, in <title>Oxford Dictionary of National Biography</title> (Oxford, 2018).</bibl>
                     <bibl>Fulton, Helen, ‘<ref target="https://doi.org/10.16922/whr.31.1.3">Sir John Prise and His Books: Manuscript Culture in the March of Wales</ref>’, <title>Welsh History Review</title>, 31/1 (2022), 55–78.</bibl>
                     <bibl>Hunt, R. W., <title>The Schools and the Cloister: The Life and Writings of Alexander Nequam (1157–1217)</title>, ed. Margaret T. Gibson (Oxford, 1984).</bibl>
                     <bibl>Ker, Neil R., ‘<ref target="https://doi.org/10.1093/library/s5-x.1.1">Sir John Prise</ref>’, <title>The Library</title>, 5th ser., 10/1 (1955), 1–24.</bibl>
                     <bibl>Stegmüller, Friedrich, <title>Repertorium biblicum medii aevi</title>, 11 vols (Madrid, 1950).</bibl>
                     <bibl>Webber, M. Teresa J., and Andrew G. Watson, eds, <title>The Libraries of the Augustinian Canons</title>, Corpus of British Medieval Library Catalogues, 6 (London, 1998).</bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
               <msPart n="1" xml:id="Jesus_College_MS_94-part1">
                  <msIdentifier>
                     <altIdentifier type="partial">
                        <idno type="part">Jesus College MS. 94, fols 1–56</idno>
                     </altIdentifier>
                  </msIdentifier>
                  <msContents>
                     <textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fols 1r–56v)</locus>
                        <author key="person_71420958">Alexander Neckam</author>
                        <title key="work_5484" xml:lang="la">Glose super psalterium</title>
                        <rubric xml:lang="la">Glose magistri Alexander abbatis cyrencestrie. super psalterium. <note>(addition, 13th century)</note></rubric>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus>(fol. 1r–v)</locus>
                           <bibl>Proem</bibl>
                           <incipit xml:lang="la"><locus>(fol. 1r)</locus> De orto deliciarum paradisi</incipit>
                           <explicit xml:lang="la"><locus>(fol. 1v)</locus> nulla discordia. nec postulatio. qualis sit inuia.</explicit>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus>(fols 1v–38v)</locus>
                           <bibl>Psalms 1 to 37</bibl>
                           <incipit><hi rend="underline">Beatus uir qui non abiit. etc.</hi> Licet psalmus iste exponatur a quibusdam de ioseph ab arimathia.</incipit>
                           <explicit defective="true"><locus>(fol. 38v)</locus> cum de operibus misericordie disceptaturus dices. esuriui etc. <note>(with catchword: <q>sitium etc.</q>)</note></explicit>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus>(fols 39r–56v)</locus>
                           <bibl>Psalms 92 to 119</bibl>
                           <incipit><locus>(fol. 39r)</locus><hi rend="underline">Bonum est. etc.</hi>
                              <subst><del>Eforas</del>
                              <add place="above">Neemias</add></subst> precepit filiis israel ut quolibet</incipit>
                           <explicit defective="true"><locus>(fol. 56v)</locus> domine uiuifica me iuxta uerbum tuum</explicit>
                        </msItem>
                        <filiation>First recension of Alexander’s commentary on the Psalms, with the author’s revisions.</filiation>
                        <listBibl>
                           <bibl>Gilbert Dahan, ‘En marge du <title>Proslogion</title> de Saint Anselme: l’exégèse patristique et médiévale du Psaume’, <title>Archives d’histoire doctrinale et littéraire du Moyen Âge</title> 13 (1990), 11–29 (ed. of Ps. 13:1 at 26–7).</bibl>
                           <bibl>Stegmüller, <title>Repertorium biblicum</title>, no. 1163.</bibl>
                        </listBibl>
                     </msItem>
                  </msContents>
                  <physDesc>
                     <objectDesc form="codex">
                        <supportDesc material="perg">
                           <support>parchment</support>
                           <extent>56 leaves <dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                                 <height max="343" min="330">330–43</height>
                                 <width max="285" min="272">272–85</width>
                              </dimensions>
                           </extent>
                           <collation>
                              <signatures>Contemporary ink Roman numeral at the end of each quire, centred at the bottom of the page. Sequence skips from ·iiii· to ·ix· between quires 4 and 5.</signatures>
                              <catchwords>Contemporary catchwords to the right of signatures.</catchwords>
                              <secFol>ut ei offeramus</secFol>
                           </collation>
                        </supportDesc>
                        <layoutDesc>
                           <layout columns="2" ruledLines="46 58"><dimensions type="written" unit="mm">
                                 <height max="268" min="248">248–68</height>
                                 <width max="200" min="195">195–200</width>
                              </dimensions> Margins of layout are fairly consistent, but some quires have much tighter line spacing than others, ranging from 4.5–6 mm. Ruled in leadpoint, with pricking for bounds of the writing area around the entire page. </layout>
                        </layoutDesc>
                     </objectDesc>
                     <handDesc>
                        <handNote script="protogothic">Written in protogothic script, probably by one scribe, though with varying levels of execution.</handNote>
                     </handDesc>
                     <decoDesc>
                        <decoNote type="unfilled">Space left for a four-line initial on fol. 1r, and for two- to three-line initials at the opening of each psalm.</decoNote>
                     </decoDesc>
                     <additions>Extensively revised, with a hand identified as that of <persName key="person_71420958" role="scr">Alexander Neckam</persName> by Hunt and Gullick making corrections and additions, mostly in ink; others written in leadpoint, are recopied by the original scribe into the margin or integrated with the text. Some additions are also made by Alexander’s clerk, Walter of Melito.</additions>
                  </physDesc>
                  <history>
                     <origin>
                        <origPlace><orgName key="org_136179651">Oxford, Augustinian priory of St Frideswide</orgName></origPlace>
                        <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notBefore="1193">1193 × 1204</origDate>
                        <p>Hunt and Gullick demonstrate that fols 1–56 include Alexander’s autograph revisions. It was presumably written after the death of Saladin in March 1193, since the text interprets Psalm 78:3 as referring to the conflict at Antioch. This section is lacking in MS. 94, found in MS. Bodl. 284, fol. 192r, which integrates Alexander’s revisions: hence it is theoretically possible that he composed the original recension before 1193. The work predates Alexander’s <title>De naturis rerum</title>, written before the fall of Rouen in 1204, which refers to <title xml:lang="la">Glose super psalterium</title> (Hunt, 26–7).</p>
                        <p>Hunt (94–103) characterizes <title xml:lang="la">Glose super psalterium</title> as scholastic, apparently meant to be delivered as lectures, in contrast to Alexander’s later meditative commentaries. Alexander he says that he <q>was reading publicly in theology</q> at Oxford (<q><sic>puplice</sic> legerem in theologia</q>, <title>Super cantica</title>, 1.4, Oxford, Magdalen College, MS 149, fol. 5r). He writes as a regular canon: he probably took up orders before 1195, when he appears as a papal judge-delegate, defending the Augustinian house of Llanthony Priory. He was presumably based at St Frideswide’s Priory, where he gave a sermon responding to a fire of 1190. He became a canon of Cirencester Abbey before 8 May 1203 (Dunning, <q>St Frideswide’s Priory</q>, 277–85).</p>
                     </origin>
                  </history>
                  <additional>
                     <listBibl>
                        <bibl>Gullick, Michael, ‘A Twelfth-Century Manuscript of the Letters of Thomas Becket’, <title>English Manuscript Studies, 1100–1700</title>, 2 (1990), 1–31.</bibl>
                     </listBibl>
                  </additional>
               </msPart>
               <msPart n="2" xml:id="Jesus_College_MS_94-part2">
                  <msIdentifier>
                     <altIdentifier type="partial">
                        <idno type="part">Jesus College MS. 94, fols 57–78</idno>
                     </altIdentifier>
                  </msIdentifier>
                  <msContents>
                     <textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fols 57r–74r)</locus>
                        <author key="person_71420958">Alexander Neckam</author>
                        <title xml:lang="la">Tractatus super prouerbia Salomonis</title>
                        <rubric xml:lang="la">Incipit tractatus magistri alexander abbatis cyrenc’ super parabolas salomonis.</rubric>
                        <msItem>
                           <bibl>proem</bibl>
                           <rubric xml:lang="la"><locus>(fol. 57r)</locus> ¶ Proemyum.</rubric>
                           <incipit xml:lang="la">Meditatio humana nunc in ipsum hominem reflectitur. nunc in ceteras transit creaturas⹎ nunc in auctorem rerum dirigitur.</incipit>
                           <explicit xml:lang="la"><locus>(fol. 59v)</locus> Set quid? Apicula cum aculeo destitui ceperit⹎ mellificare desinit.</explicit>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <bibl>book 1</bibl>
                           <rubric xml:lang="la"><locus>(fol. 59v)</locus> Incipit liber primus. Capitulum .i.</rubric>
                           <incipit xml:lang="la">Parabole salomonis filii dauid regis israel. ad sciendam sapientiam et disciplinam. et ad intelligenda uerba prudentie et suscipiendam eruditionem doctrine. iustitiam et iuditium et equitatem. ut detur paruulis astucia⹎ adolescenti scientia. <note>[Prov. 1:1]</note> Vereor ne dum liber parabolarum˷ nostris se concedit manibus⹎ inuidia faciem infecta liuore˷ intonet ore cinico dicens. O dedecus⹎ o indignatio.</incipit>
                           <explicit xml:lang="la"><locus>(fol. 74r)</locus> Ne audias a domino cum phariseis. Ipsi non introistis⹎ et eos qui introibant prohibuistis.</explicit>
                           <note>Commentary breaks off at Prov. 3:27.</note>
                        </msItem>
                        <filiation>Sole surviving manuscript of this work; numerous excerpts in <title>Sol meldunensis</title> (Cambridge, University Library, MS Gg.6.42) and a brief passage in Oxford, Bodleian Library, MS Hatton 102, fol. 200v. Other copies recorded at the Dominicans, Lincoln (FD5.1) and the Carmelites, Hulne (F15.1).</filiation>
                        <listBibl>
                           <bibl>Stegmüller, <title>Repertorium biblicum</title>, no. 1164.</bibl>
                        </listBibl>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fols 74v–77v)</locus>
                        <title type="desc">Sermons</title>
                        <note>The rubrics of both sermons incorrectly attribute the text to Alexander Neckam; the rubricator appears to have introduced this error, as the guides leave the texts anonymous.</note>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus>(fols 74v–75v)</locus>
                           <author key="person_40175167">Peter Comestor</author>
                           <title key="work_3496">Sermones</title>
                           <bibl>no. 35</bibl>
                           <rubric xml:lang="la"><locus>(fol. 74v, foot, in the text hand)</locus> Sermo magistri Alexandri abbatis Cyrencestr’. Feria Vª Dominice quinquagesime.</rubric>
                           <rubric xml:lang="la"><note>(guide for rubricator)</note> Feria Vª Dominice quinquagesime</rubric>
                           <incipit xml:lang="la">Dispone domui tue quia morieris <add place="above">tu</add> et non viues. <note>[Isaiah 38:1]</note> Famuliaris fuit hec ammonitio et semel</incipit>
                           <explicit xml:lang="la"><locus>(fol. 75v)</locus> et de utraque postmodum transferamur ad mensam patris. heredes facti dei⹎ coheredes autem cristi⹎ qui est benedictus in secula seculorum. Amen.</explicit>
                           <listBibl>
                              <bibl>Schneyer, <title>Repertorium</title>, 4.638 (no. 35); 1.275 (no. 59).</bibl>
                              <bibl>PL 198, 1764</bibl>
                           </listBibl>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus>(fols 75v–77v)</locus>
                           <rubric xml:lang="la"><locus>(fol. 75v, foot)</locus> Sermo magistri Alexandri abbatis Cyrencestr’ In natiuitate beate Marie Virginis.</rubric>
                           <rubric xml:lang="la"><note>guide for rubricator, leadpoint</note> Sermo <add place="above">in</add> natiuitate beate marie.</rubric>
                           <incipit xml:lang="la"><supplied reason="omitted">S</supplied>icut spina rosam genuit iudea Mariam. Fratres licet prout testatur Augustinus magister egregius.</incipit>
                           <explicit xml:lang="la"><locus>(fol. 77v)</locus> ut ea mediante⹎ percipiatis eternam gloriam. Quam nobis et vobis precare dignetur ihesus cristus. qui est benedictus in secula. Amen.</explicit>
                           <filiation>Also found in London, British Library, Harley MS 325, where it is without attribution.</filiation>
                           <listBibl>
                              <bibl>Schneyer, <title>Repertorium</title>, 1.275, no. 60.</bibl>
                           </listBibl>
                        </msItem>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fol. 78r-v)</locus>
                        <note>blank</note>
                     </msItem>
                  </msContents>
                  <physDesc>
                     <objectDesc form="codex">
                        <supportDesc material="perg">
                           <support>parchment</support>
                           <extent>22 leaves. <locus>Fols 57-72 (quire 7/8)</locus>: <dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                                 <height max="381" min="374">374–81</height>
                                 <width max="270" min="266">266–70</width>
                              </dimensions>
                              <locus>Fols 73–76 (quire 9)</locus>: <dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                                 <height max="370" min="364">364–70</height>
                                 <width max="248" min="242">242–8</width>
                              </dimensions>
                           </extent>
                           <collation>
                              <catchwords>Catchword at bottom right of 64v; at the base of 72v, a note reading ‘Requi<supplied reason="omitted">re?</supplied> in libro Et bene’ (corresponding to the following quire).</catchwords>
                              <secFol>qui triumphorum suorum</secFol>
                           </collation>
                        </supportDesc>
                        <layoutDesc>
                           <layout columns="2" ruledLines="48 49"><dimensions type="written" unit="mm">
                                 <height max="284" min="270">270–84</height>
                                 <width max="177" min="174">174–7</width>
                              </dimensions><locus>Fols 57r–72v (quires 7/8)</locus> ruled in leadpoint, with pricking for frame. Extra rules in inner and outer margins to align running headers. Double series of pricking for individual lines in quire 7, single series in quire 8. Line spacing 5.5–7 mm. Fol. 64 is set lower on the page, with a larger top margin (37 mm against 23–25 mm elsewhere).</layout>
                           <layout columns="2" ruledLines="43 47"><dimensions type="written" unit="mm">
                                 <height max="263" min="260">260–3</height>
                                 <width max="166" min="163">163–6</width>
                              </dimensions><locus>Fols 73r–77v (quire 9)</locus> ruled in leadpoint, with pricking for frame and one series of pricking for individual lines; line spacing 5–6.5 mm. No extra rules in margins.</layout>
                        </layoutDesc>
                     </objectDesc>
                     <handDesc>
                        <summary>Protogothic, early 13th century. Written in many stints with different scribes, with shifts often corresponding to transitions in the text, suggesting that it was copied concurrently with composition.</summary>
                        <handNote script="protogothic"><locus>Fols 57r–61v</locus>, two scribes or one scribe writing in multiple stages (note the extra stroke added to capital T and Q). One of these may be <persName ref="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q60800793" role="scr">Walter of Mileto</persName>. Returns at fols 62v–63v.</handNote>
                        <handNote script="protogothic"><locus>Fols 61v–62r</locus>, a larger, heavier hand introduced, alternating with one that is smaller and square.</handNote>
                        <handNote script="protogothic"><locus>Fols 63v–64v</locus>, a light, somewhat elongated hand, with an extra stroke added to rounded capitals (e.g. E, C, T), probably <persName ref="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q60800793" role="scr">Walter of Mileto</persName>.</handNote>
                        <handNote script="protogothic"><locus>Fols 65r–67v</locus> (i.e. starting with quire 8), a larger, heavier, more formal hand; from fols 68r–69v, this shifts to a slightly heavier script with bold capitals opening each sentence.</handNote>
                        <handNote script="protogothic">Further shifts in hand at fols 70r; 70v; 71r; 71r–v; 71v–72v; 72v; 73r; 73r; 73r–v; 73v; 73v–74r; 74r; 74v–77v.</handNote>
                     </handDesc>
                     <decoDesc>
                        <decoNote type="decInit">Fol. 57r, a four-line Arabesque initial with penwork, red and blue; opening of book 1 marked by a red four-line initial with penwork; two- and three-line initials, red, blue, or green with penwork, mark smaller section divisions.</decoNote>
                        <decoNote type="colInit">Openings of paragraphs marked with enlarged red capitals, alternating on occasion with blue or green.</decoNote>
                        <decoNote type="border">Penwork added to frame additions on fols 57v–58r.</decoNote>
                     </decoDesc>
                     <additions>
                        <p>Corrections by <persName key="person_71420958" role="scr">Alexander Neckam</persName> and <persName ref="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q60800793" role="scr">Walter of Mileto</persName> (cf. Psalms commentary).</p>
                        <p>Fol. 57r, cursive marginal notes, 15th century.</p>
                     </additions>
                  </physDesc>
                  <history>
                     <origin>
                        <origPlace><orgName key="org_211447911">Cirencester, Augustinian Abbey of St Mary the Virgin</orgName></origPlace>
                        <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="1217" notBefore="1199">1199 × 1217</origDate>
                        <p>The variability of the manuscript’s layout and hands, together with the extensive revisions, imply that it was copied while Alexander was still composing the text. The work refers to the death of King Richard I in 1199 (see fol. 58r).</p>
                     </origin>
                  </history>
                  <additional>
                     <listBibl>
                        <bibl>Schneyer, Johannes Baptist, <title>Repertorium der lateinischen Sermones des Mittelalters für die Zeit von 1150–1350</title>, 11 vols, Beiträge zur Geschichte der Philosophie und Theologie des Mittelalters, Texte und Untersuchungen, 43 (Münster, 1969).</bibl>
                     </listBibl>
                  </additional>
               </msPart>
               <msPart n="3" xml:id="Jesus_College_MS_94-part3">
                  <msIdentifier>
                     <altIdentifier type="partial">
                        <idno type="part">Jesus College MS. 94, fols 79–125</idno>
                     </altIdentifier>
                  </msIdentifier>
                  <msContents>
                     <textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fols 79r–125r)</locus>
                        <author key="person_71420958">Alexander Neckam</author>
                        <title key="work_404" xml:lang="la">Tractatus super <q>Mulierem fortem</q></title>
                        <note>Commentary on Prov. 31:10–31.</note>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus>(fols 79r–98v)</locus>
                           <bibl>book 1</bibl>
                           <note>(on Mary Magdalene)</note>
                           <incipit xml:lang="la"><locus>(fol. 79r)</locus>
                              <q>Mulierem fortem quis inueniet? Procul et de ultimis finibus pretium eius.</q> Splendor radii solaris in iaspide⸝ serenitati aeris exposito⹎ uirescere. in carbunculo⹎ rutilare. in cristallo⹎ scintillare uidetur.</incipit>
                           <explicit xml:lang="la"><locus>(fol. 98v)</locus> que in beata uirgine edificauit sibi domum decoris⹎ septem gratis columnis munitam.</explicit>
                           <listBibl>
                              <bibl>Mahoney, Denis Gerard, ‘<title><ref target="https://proquest.com/docview/302621665">A Critical Edition of Alexander Nequam’s <title>Tractatus super Mulierem fortem</title>, Section One</ref></title>’, PhD diss., University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign, 1971.</bibl>
                           </listBibl>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus>(fols 98v–114v)</locus>
                           <bibl>book 2</bibl>
                           <note>(on the Virgin Mary)</note>
                           <rubric xml:lang="la"><locus>(fol. 98v)</locus> De gloriosa uirgine.</rubric>
                           <incipit>Mulierem fortem quis inueniet? Exurge osalterium et cithara⹎ in laudes <del>in laudes</del> gloriose uirginis.</incipit>
                           <explicit xml:lang="la"><locus>(fol. 114v)</locus> Remunerabor egregie⹎ si pro me apud serenissimum iudicem digneris intercedere.</explicit>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus>(fols 114v–124v)</locus>
                           <bibl>book 3</bibl>
                           <note>(on the Church)</note>
                           <rubric xml:lang="la"><locus>(fol. 114v)</locus> Laus sacro sancte ecclesie.</rubric>
                           <incipit xml:lang="la">Mulierem fortem quis inueniet? <hi rend="bold">P</hi>reconiis gloriose dei genitricis⹎ laudes sacro sancte matris ecclesie decreuimus adicere.</incipit>
                           <explicit xml:lang="la"><locus>(fol. 124v)</locus> Et ecce iam opus consummauimus⹎ in laudem domini nostri ihesu cristi. cui honor˷ uirtus et gloria⹎ per infinita seculorum secula. <hi rend="smallcaps">Amen.</hi></explicit>
                        </msItem>
                        <filiation>The only other known manuscript of this work, Oxford, Bodleian Library, MS Bodl. 528, from Reading, was copied from Jesus College MS 94 before it was corrected.</filiation>
                        <listBibl>
                           <bibl>Stegmüller, <title>Repertorium biblicum</title>, no. 1166.</bibl>
                        </listBibl>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fol. 125r)</locus>
                        <author key="person_71420958">Alexander Neckam</author>
                        <title type="desc">Prose apostrophe to the book</title>
                        <quote xml:lang="la">Fortasse tuo liber superstes eris alexandro. Prius enim me uermes comedent⹎ quam te tinea corrosura sit. Vermibus debetur corpus meum. te⹎ demolientur tinee. Tu speculum es animi mei. tu meditacionum mearum interpres⹎ propositi nostri certissimus es iudex. affectuum mentis mee fidelis es nuncius⹎ tu dulce solacium meroris. tu testis consciencie uerax. Tibi tanquam fideli depositario⹎ cordis archana commendaui. Restituis fideliter michi ea que fidei tue commisi. in te⹎ me ipsum lego. Venies uenies⸝ in manus alicuius pii lectoris⹎ qui pro me preces effundere dignabitur. Tunc quidem tuo libelle domino proderis⹎ tunc tuo alexandro gratissimam recompensabis uicissitudinem. Vincet⸝ nec inuideo laborem meum⹎ pii lectoris deuotio. qui te nunc gremio repositurus˷ nunc pectori suo admoturus. non numquam capiti tanquam dulce ceruical suppositurus˷ quandoque te letis manibus leniter contrectaturus⹎ pro me affectuose dominum exorabit ihesum cristum⹎ qui cum patre et spiritu sancto uiuit et regnat deus per infinita seculorum secula⹎ Amen.</quote>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fols 125v–128r)</locus>
                        <note>blank</note>
                     </msItem>
                  </msContents>
                  <physDesc>
                     <objectDesc form="codex">
                        <supportDesc material="perg">
                           <support>parchment</support>
                           <extent>50 leaves <dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                                 <height max="392" min="383">383–92</height>
                                 <width max="297" min="275">275–97</width>
                              </dimensions>
                           </extent>
                           <collation>
                              <catchwords>Catchwords in ink centred at the base of the last page of each quire.</catchwords>
                              <signatures>In quire 12 (fols 95–102), letters are placed in the inner margin of most pages to indicate their order.</signatures>
                              <secFol/>
                           </collation>
                        </supportDesc>
                        <layoutDesc>
                           <layout columns="2" ruledLines="42 52"><dimensions type="written" unit="mm">
                                 <height max="310" min="280">280–310</height>
                                 <width max="208" min="175">175–208</width>
                              </dimensions> Ruled in leadpoint. Pricking for frame throughout on all edges of page; pricking for individual lines in quire 10 only, in inner and outer margins. Line spacing 5–7 mm. Extra rules in inner and outer margins to align running headers. Beginning at fol. 86v, an extra rule is added 9–12 mm from the top of the page for a running heading, filled in by the rubricator only from fol. 99v (with book 2) until fol. 122r.</layout>
                        </layoutDesc>
                     </objectDesc>
                     <handDesc>
                        <handNote script="protogothic">Written in several protogothic hands, first quarter of the 13th century, many the same as those found in <title>Super parabolas</title>. Shifts in hand found at fols 79r–85r; 85r; 85r–v; 85v; 86v; 85v–91r; 91r–92r; 92v–95r; 96r; 96r–100v; 100v–103r; 103v–106r; 106r–107v; 107v–108r; 108r–108v; 108v–110v; 110v; 111r–112v; 112v–113v; 113v–114r; 114r-v; 114v–115r; 115r–118v; 118v; 118v–119r; 119r; 119r–v; 119v–123r; 123r–v; 123v; 123v–124v; 124v–124v; 124v–125r.</handNote>
                     </handDesc>
                     <decoDesc>
                        <decoNote type="decInit">Opening six-line arabesque initial in red and blue with penwork.</decoNote>
                        <decoNote type="colInit">Subsequent paragraphs and sections begin with an enlarged capital, alternating between red, blue, and green (occasionally with paraph marks).</decoNote>
                        <decoNote type="border">Penwork in red and blue added to frame longer marginal additions.</decoNote>
                     </decoDesc>
                     <additions>
                        <p>Corrections in leadpoint by <persName key="person_71420958" role="scr">Alexander Neckam</persName>, <persName ref="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q60800793" role="scr">Walter of Mileto</persName>, and another corrector, later entered formally by the original scribes in ink.</p>
                     </additions>
                  </physDesc>
                  <history>
                     <origin>
                        <origPlace><orgName key="org_211447911">Cirencester, Augustinian Abbey of St Mary the Virgin</orgName></origPlace>
                        <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="1217" notBefore="1204">1204 × 1217</origDate>
                        <p>The variability of the manuscript’s layout and hands, together with the extensive revisions, imply that it was copied while Alexander was still composing the text. The work postdates his <title>De naturis rerum</title> (written before 1204).</p>
                     </origin>
                  </history>
               </msPart>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2026-02-25"><persName>Andrew Dunning</persName> New description.</change>
         <change when="2019-01-23">Record created.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
