<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="manuscript_8339">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>MS. Rawl. C. 752</title>
            <title type="collection">MSS. Rawl. C (Rawlinson C)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Description</resp>
               <persName>Elizabeth Solopova</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Revision</resp>
               <persName>Andrew Dunning</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </publisher>
            <idno type="msID">MS_Rawl_C_752</idno>
            <idno type="collection">Rawl C</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="MS_Rawl_C_752" xml:lang="en">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <region type="county">Oxfordshire</region>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <institution>University of Oxford</institution>
                  <repository>Bodleian Library</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">MS. Rawl. C. 752</idno>
                  <idno type="ieArk">ark:29072/x0xk81jj61pq</idno>
                  <idno type="crArk">ark:29072/x02j62s59732</idno>
                  <altIdentifier type="internal">
                     <idno type="SCN">12595</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents>
                  <textLang mainLang="enm" otherLangs="la">Middle English with Latin</textLang>
                  <msItem class="#biblia" n="1" xml:id="MS_Rawl_C_752-item1">
                     <title key="work_13437" type="desc">New Testament, later Wycliffite version</title>
                     <note>(part: Gospels, Jude, Apocalypse)</note>
                     <bibl type="bible">
                        <title>Bible, New Testament</title>
                     </bibl>
                     <textLang mainLang="enm">Middle English</textLang>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="1">
                     <locus>(fols. 1r–119v)</locus>
                     <note>[items 1–2 occupy quires I–XVI]</note>
                     <title key="work_12092" type="desc">Four gospels in the Later Version of the Wycliffite Bible with usual prologues</title>
                     <note>Usual rubrics in red. Running titles on both rectos and versos consisting of abbreviated titles of biblical books and chapter numbers on fols. 1v–3v; elsewhere the chapter numbers are added to running titles in a post-medieval hand. Chapter numbers in red as Roman numerals. Red and blue paraphs within the text, often at the beginnings of lections. Indexing letters in the margins entered at the beginnings of lections rather than consistently; double strokes at the ends of lections. Corrections in a contemporary hand. Gloss within the text is written in red on fol. 28r. Ends halfway through the second column on fol. 119v with a rubric <q>Here eendiþ þe gospel of Ioon</q>.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="2">
                     <locus>(fols. 119v–120r)</locus>
                     <note>The gospels are immediately followed by two added devotional pieces transcribed below, probably in the same contemporary hand. A space is left at the beginning for a 2-line initial, not filled in, though there is a small ‘d’ in red as an instruction to the rubricator.</note>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fol. 119v)</locus>
                        <quote>[D]ere cristen soulis. I praie ȝou wiþ al mekenesse &amp; charite. lifteþ up þe iȝen of ȝoure vndirstondynge and openeþ þe eris of ȝour soulis: þat ȝe may lerne and vndirstonde þe charge &amp; couenaunt þat ȝe maden wiþ god. in takynge of ȝoure cristendom / ffor alle cristen peple. ben bounden to knowe &amp; kepe þis charge &amp; couenaunt: but speciali prestis / wherfore bi goddis mercy: I schal schewe ȝou þe sacrament of <sic>baptym</sic> schortly declared</quote>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fol. 120r)</locus>
                        <quote>and at þe laste he suffride þe moost shameful deeþ. þat synners cowden ymagene to hym / O þis was a greet loue / for gretter loue may no man haue: þan to suffre bodili deeþ for his frendis / wherfore crist seide in his passioun to hise disciplis / wiþ desire I haue desired: to ete þis soupere wiþ ȝou / and aftir þis he seide I þirste / þat is þe sauacioun and helþe of alle chosen soulis / þe whiche soulis houynge aboue þe bodi. in þe our of her departyng: shullen be resseyued wiþ þe aungels of god. and be born in to heuene. þere to be fedde wiþ breed of liyf. þat is iesu crist hym silf / as he seiþ in þe gospel</quote>
                     </msItem>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem>
                     <note>Most of fol. 120r–v is blank.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="3">
                     <locus>(fols. 121r–139r)</locus>
                     <note>[items 3–4 occupy quires XVII–XVIII]</note>
                     <title key="work_11705" type="desc">Apocalypse without a prologue, followed by Jude, both in the Later Version of the Wycliffite Bible</title>
                     <note>Written by a different scribe and with a penwork border in a different style than the borders in the gospels. Running titles on both rectos and versos in black ink preceded by blue paraphs. Chapter numbers as red Roman numerals.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="4">
                     <locus>(fol. 139v)</locus>
                     <title type="desc">Extracts from epistles: 2 Peter 2:21–22 and James 5:1–6 in the Later Version of the Wycliffite Bible</title>
                     <rubric>Iamys v. 5.</rubric>
                     <note>Badly faded.</note>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="perg">
                        <support>thin parchment, paper flyleaves</support>
                        <extent>143 leaves, <foreign rend="italic">c.</foreign><dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                              <height>145</height>
                              <width>95</width>
                           </dimensions>; leaves were trimmed in rebinding occasionally causing the loss of decoration in the margins</extent>
                        <foliation>two unnumbered paper leaves at the beginning and end; modern in pencil, 1–29 + 29(a) + 30–139</foliation>
                        <collation>paper flyleaves | <locus>(fols. 1–118)</locus> I–XV (8) | <locus>(fols. 119–120)</locus> XVI (2) | <locus>(fols. 121–132)</locus> XVII (12) | <locus>(fols. 133–139)</locus> XVIII (8–1(?)) missing 8 (?) <catchwords>Catchwords survive.</catchwords>
                        </collation>
                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout columns="2" writtenLines="33">ruled in plummet for two columns with single vertical and horizontal bounding lines extending the full height and width of page; 33 lines per page; written space: <foreign rend="italic">c.</foreign><dimensions type="ruled" unit="mm">
                              <height>105</height>
                              <width>68</width>
                           </dimensions></layout>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc>
                     <handNote script="textualisNorthern">textura; gospels and the Apocalypse are probably copied by different scribes; another change of scribe on fol. 139r</handNote>
                  </handDesc>
                  <decoDesc>
                     <decoNote type="decInit">5- to 6-line initials in pigment and gold, and 1-sided borders, decorated with foliage and gold disks at the beginnings of gospels.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="flourInit">2- to 3-line blue initials with red penwork at the beginnings of prologues and chapters.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="flourInit">Floral or occasionally zoomorphic <locus>(fol. 17r)</locus> designs in penwork, some with red and yellow wash, decorating catchwords, running titles, indexing letters, etc.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="flourInit">4-line red and blue ‘puzzle’ initial and a penwork border at the beginning of the Apocalypse.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote>Decoration in the gospels is in a different style than elsewhere in the manuscript.</decoNote>
                  </decoDesc>
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <binding notAfter="1800" notBefore="1700">
                        <p>Black leather over pasteboard, 18th century. Rebacked with the original spine relaid. Rectangular gilt roll floral decoration with floral corner-pieces on both covers. Double gilt fillet-line border around the outer edge of the covers. Four raised bands on spine. Gilt decoration on the panels between the bands. Red leather label on spine with gilt lettering ‘EUANGELISTS’. Marbled paper pastedowns and flyleaves; further laid paper flyleaves.</p>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origPlace>
                        <country key="place_7002445">England</country>
                     </origPlace>
                     <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="1429" notBefore="1410">15th century, end of the first quarter (?)</origDate>
                     <p>Dialect survey (gospels): <list>
                           <item>ony(10), eche(9)/ech(1), fier(7)/fire(2)/fir(1), ȝouun(10), lijf(10), like(9)/lic(1), myche(8)/mych(2), siȝ(7)/syȝe(1) (sg.), saien(3)/sayen(1)/siȝen(1)/sien(1) (pl.), silf(10), suche(7)/siche(1), þouȝ(6), þoruȝ(9)</item>
                           <item>-iþ(9)/-eþ(1) (pres.ind.3sg.), -en(6)/-n(4) (pres.ind.pl.), -ynge(4)/-inge(6) (pres.part.), sche(10) (3sg.fem.pronoun, nom.), þei(10) (3pl.pronoun, nom.), hem(10) (3pl.pronoun, oblique), her(10) (3pl.pronoun, possessive)</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                  </origin>
                  <provenance><q>Constat iste liber domino <persName role="fmo">Rogero Waltun</persName> clerico et presbetero anno domini mº qgisim … et Regis Henrici octavi</q>
                     <locus>(fol. 139v)</locus>.</provenance>
                  <provenance><q><persName role="fmo">Ric Stauntonj</persName> liber 1603</q>
                     <locus>(fol. 139v)</locus>.</provenance>
                  <provenance>Bookplate of <persName role="fmo" key="person_4813">Robert Nash (1691/2–1752)</persName>, fellow of Wadham College, Oxford, and, from 1731, Chancellor of the Diocese of Norwich on the upper pastedown (see Blomefield (1806)).</provenance>
                  <provenance><persName key="person_47563478" role="fmo">Richard Rawlinson</persName> (1690–1755); see <title>Oxford Dictionary of National Biography</title>: bookplate on the first flyleaf.</provenance>
                  <acquisition when="1756">Bodleian Library: bequeathed by Rawlinson and accessioned in 1756.</acquisition>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>Elizabeth Solopova, <title>
                              <ref target="https://jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1gn6cmr">Manuscripts of the Wycliffite Bible in the Bodleian and Oxford College Libraries</ref>
                           </title>, Exeter Medieval Texts and Studies (Liverpool: Liverpool University Press, 2016), no. 43. Previously described: <listBibl>
                              <bibl facs="aei0201.gif" type="QUARTO">Quarto Catalogue, col. 389</bibl>
                              <bibl facs="aas0235.gif" type="SC">Summary Catalogue, vol. 3, p. 220</bibl>
                           </listBibl>
                        </source>
                     </recordHist>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <surrogates>
                     <bibl subtype="partial" type="digital-facsimile">
                        <ref target="https://digital.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/objects/94873e33-67a8-4d4b-b424-50db37357c58/">
                           <title>Digital Bodleian</title>
                        </ref>
                        <note>(2 images from 35mm slides)</note>
                     </bibl>
                  </surrogates>
                  <listBibl type="WRAPPER">
                     <listBibl type="PRINT">
                        <bibl>Blomefield, F., ‘The city of Norwich, chapter 40: Deans, Vicars-General, or Chancellors, Archdeacons, Commissaries, Officials, and Prebends’, in <title>An essay towards a topographical history of the county of Norfolk</title>, vol. 3, <title>The History of the city and county of Norwich</title>, part I (London, 1806), pp. 617–71 (<ref target="http://www.british-history.ac.uk/topographical-hist-norfolk/vol3/pp617">http://www.british-history.ac.uk/topographical-hist-norfolk/vol3/pp617-</ref>671) [accessed 27 July 2015].</bibl>
                        <bibl>Forshall, J. and Madden, F. (eds), <title>The Holy Bible … in the earliest English versions made from the Latin Vulgate by John Wycliffe and his followers</title>, 4 vols (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1850), vol. 1, p. xlix.</bibl>
                        <bibl>William D. Macray, <title>Catalogi codicum manuscriptorum Bibliothecæ Bodleianæ partis quintæ fasciculus secundus, viri munificentissimi Ricardi Rawlinson, J.C.D., codicum classem tertiam, in qua libri theologici atque miscellanei, complectens; accedit in uniuscujusque classis codicum contenta index locupletissimus</title> (Oxford, 1878), col. 389.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Scott, K. L. (gen. ed.), <title>An index of images in English manuscripts from the time of Chaucer to Henry VIII, c.1380–c.1509: the Bodleian Library, Oxford</title>, 3 vols (Turnhout: Harvey Miller Publishers, 2000–02), vol. 3, p. 56, no. 918.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Dove, M., <title>The first English Bible: the text and context of the Wycliffite versions</title> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2007), p. 299.</bibl>
                     </listBibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2023-03-24">Add Solopova description.</change>
         <change when="2019-10-31" xml:id="MMM"><persName>Toby Burrows/Mapping Manuscript Migrations</persName>Provenance and acquisition information added using <ref target="https://github.com/mapping-manuscript-migrations/oxford-tei-updates/blob/master/update_oxford_prov.rb">https://github.com/mapping-manuscript-migrations/oxford-tei-updates/blob/master/update_oxford_prov.rb</ref> in collaboration with the <ref target="http://mappingmanuscriptmigrations.org/">Mapping Manuscript Migrations</ref> project.</change>
         <change when="2017-07-01">First online publication.</change>
         <change when="2017-05-25"><persName>James Cummings</persName> Up-converted the markup using <ref target="https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl">https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl</ref></change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
