<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="manuscript_8138">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>MS. Rawl. C. 259</title>
            <title type="collection">MSS. Rawl. C (Rawlinson C)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Description</resp>
               <persName>Elizabeth Solopova</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Revision</resp>
               <persName>Andrew Dunning</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </publisher>
            <idno type="msID">MS_Rawl_C_259</idno>
            <idno type="collection">Rawl C</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="MS_Rawl_C_259" xml:lang="en">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <region type="county">Oxfordshire</region>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <institution>University of Oxford</institution>
                  <repository>Bodleian Library</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">MS. Rawl. C. 259</idno>
                  <idno type="ieArk">ark:29072/x01c18dg84g9</idno>
                  <idno type="crArk">ark:29072/x0cc08hg11pz</idno>
                  <altIdentifier type="internal">
                     <idno type="SCN">15418</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents>
                  <textLang mainLang="enm" otherLangs="la">Middle English with Latin</textLang>
                  <msItem>
                     <note>Fol. i–v are paper and parchment flyleaves.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="1">
                     <locus>(fols. 1r–6v)</locus>
                     <note>[item 1 occupies quire I]</note>
                     <title key="work_10687" type="desc">Calendar in Latin</title>
                     <note>Written in black and red, not graded, less than one-quarter full. Includes Dunstan (19 May), Alban (22 June), Leonard (6 November) and Martin (11 November), all in red, and Alphege with a red capital (19 April). Also includes Benedict Biscop (12 January), Brigid of Kildare (1 February), Edward the Martyr (18 March), Benedict of Nursia (21 March), Pancras (12 May), Botulph (17 June), the translation of Swithin (15 July) and Edmund the Martyr (20 November), all in black. Does not include David, Chad or other saints whose feasts were promulgated after 1415 under Archbishop Chichele (Pfaff, R. W., <title>The liturgy in medieval England: a history</title> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2009), pp. 438–41). The translation of Thomas Becket (7 July) is erased, but not his feast (29 December). Includes the following entries in the original hand in the lower margins: <q>Anno domini m.ccc.lxi in festo sancti mauri abbatis erat ventus validus</q>
                        <locus>(fol. 1r)</locus>, and <q>Anno domini mcccxlviii in festo sancti michaelis incipiebat prima pestilencia lond.</q>
                        <locus>(fol. 5r)</locus>. The entries commemorate ‘Grote Mandrenke’ storm on 16 January 1362 and the arrival of the Black Death in London in 1348. Fifteenth-century additions, including the translation of Edward the Confessor (13 October); <q>ffro þe tyme þat adam hadde synned in to þat tyme þat crist dyed &amp; ros .v. þousand ȝer .ij. cc. &amp; xxx</q>
                        <locus>(fol. 1r)</locus>; notes on blood letting <locus>(fol. 1v)</locus>. Days are numbered throughout in an early modern hand.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="2">
                     <locus>(fols. 7r–204v)</locus>
                     <note>[item 2 occupies quires II–XXV]</note>
                     <title key="work_13437" type="desc">New Testament in the Later Version of the Wycliffite Bible with usual prologues</title>
                     <note>Two prologues to Romans, <q>First vs bihoueþ vndirstonde…</q> and <q>Romayns ben in þe cuntrey…</q> (Dove, M., <title>The first English Bible: the text and context of the Wycliffite versions</title> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2007), p. 206). the Earlier Version of the Wycliffite Bible prologue to Philemon, <q>He makiþ homeli lettris to filemon…</q> (Dove, M., <title>The first English Bible: the text and context of the Wycliffite versions</title> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2007), p. 208). Rubrics in red or black, most with usual wording, e.g., <q>Here bigynneþ þe prolog on matheu</q>; <q>Ierom in his twei prologis on matheu seiþ pleynli þus. Here bigynneþ þe book of matheu</q>
                        <locus>(fol. 7r)</locus>.</note>
                     <note>Matthew ends on fol. 25v, where the end of the second column is left blank, and Mark starts on a new leaf <locus>(fol. 26r)</locus>. John, the prologue to Romans, and Philippians start on new pages as well. Running titles on both rectos and versos, consisting of abbreviated titles of biblical books; chapter numbers are added to some running titles in a medieval hand. Chapter numbers in red, most as Roman numerals. Red or blue paraphs at the start of sections within the text. Many corrections over erasures within the text and in the margins in contemporary and later hands; some text crossed out in red. No marginal glosses with very few exceptions; added material within the text is underlined in red. Indexing letters in the margins, entered at the beginning of lections rather than consistently; double strokes at the ends of lections; letters and strokes in red may be original, but many letters in black were probably added in the 15th century. Numerous added pointing hands and <q>nota</q> in the margins.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="3">
                     <locus>(fols. 205r–240v)</locus>
                     <title type="desc">Old Testament lectionary of Type II</title>
                     <rubric>Here bygynnen þe lessouns &amp; pistlis of þe oolde lawe þat ben rad in þe chirche bi al þe ȝeer</rubric>
                     <note>Includes the temporal, followed by the proper (containing Silvester, Martin and Lawrence as the only non-biblical saints), common and commemorations. Each reading is preceded by a rubric, stating the liturgical occasion, the title of the biblical book and the chapter number. The readings begin with statements that introduce them at Mass (e.g., <q>The lord god seiþ þese þingis</q>, fol. 205r) underlined in red. Indexing letters in the margins in the original hand at the start of most readings and double strokes at the ends of readings. The readings used for more than one occasion are not repeated and instead rubrics contain references to liturgical occasions earlier in the lectionary. The reading for the first Mass on Christmas morning is preceded by a lengthy rubric explaining that it is performed by two voices; the part of one of the voices is underlined in red in the text that follows <locus>(fols. 207v–208r)</locus>. Running titles in red above each column, preceded by blue paraphs, consisting of an abbreviated title of a biblical book and a chapter number. On the final page much of the second column is left blank and the table of lections starts on a new page.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="4">
                     <locus>(fols. 241r–251r)</locus>
                     <note>[item 4 occupies quires XXXII–XXXIII]</note>
                     <title type="desc">Table of lections of Type I</title>
                     <rubric>Here bigynneþ a rule þat telliþ in whiche chapitres of þe bible ȝe mai fynde þe lessouns pistlis &amp; gospels þat ben rad in þe chirche after þe vse of Salisberie markid wiþ lettris of þe a b c at þe bigynnynge of þe chapitris toward þe myddil or ende aftir þe ordre as þe lettris stonden in þe a b c ffirst ben set sondaies and ferials to gidere and aftir þe sanctorum comyn and propre to gidere of al þe ȝer ffirst writen a clause of þe bigynnynge þerof and a clause of þe endynge þerof also</rubric>
                     <note>Includes the temporal, commemorations and the sanctoral (no common, in spite of the rubric). Commemorations are in the following order: Our Lady, Trinity, Holy Ghost, cross, angels, <q>ffor briþ’ and s’ &amp; salus populi</q>, peace, clear weather, rain, <q>in tyme of batels</q>, <q>a man for himsilf</q>, for pestilence of beasts, pilgrims, weddings, sick and dead. Includes all feasts characteristic of the Later Version of the Wycliffite Bible, apart from Giles (1 September) (Forshall, J. and Madden, F. (eds), <title>The Holy Bible … in the earliest English versions made from the Latin Vulgate by John Wycliffe and his followers</title>, 4 vols (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1850), vol. 4, pp. 683, 690–6). The entries consist of the name of the liturgical occasion in red, abbreviated title and chapter of the biblical book, an indexing letter in red, the opening words of a reading, <q>ende</q> in red and the closing words of a reading. More than a half of the last page is left blank.</note>
                     <note>Fols. 251v–252v, originally ruled for a table of lections, but blank, contain: (1) a list of New Testament books (Romans–Apocalypse) added in a 15th-century hand <locus>(fols. 251v–252r)</locus>; (2) a rubric <q>The tokenys of þe doom</q>, followed by references to chapters in the gospels in the same hand; and (3) two short notes in a 16th-century hand with references to historical events in the 1550s. More historical notes in the same hand on paper fly-leaves 255v–256r.</note>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="perg">
                        <support>parchment, paper flyleaves</support>
                        <extent>263 leaves, <foreign rend="italic">c.</foreign><dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                              <height>189</height>
                              <width>122</width>
                           </dimensions></extent>
                        <foliation>modern in pencil, i–v + 1–256 + two unnumbered flyleaves; early modern (?) pagination in the calendar in ink in Greek letters, alpha – mu; late 15th-century (?) foliation, 1–234, in ink on fols. 7–241</foliation>
                        <collation><locus>(fols. i–v)</locus> paper flyleaves | <locus>(fols. 1–6)</locus> I (6) | <locus>(fols. 7–198)</locus> II– XXIV (8) | <locus>(fols. 199–204)</locus> XXV (8–2) 7 and 8 excised | <locus>(fols. 205–236)</locus> XXVI–XXIX (8) | <locus>(fols. 237–234)</locus> XXX (4) | <locus>(fols. 235–240)</locus> XXXI (4) | <locus>(fols. 241–248)</locus> XXXII (8) | <locus>(fols. 249–252)</locus> XXXIII (4) | <locus>(fols. 253–256 + two unnumbered leaves)</locus> parchment and paper flyleaves. <catchwords>Catchwords survive;</catchwords>
                           <signatures>quire signatures partially survive in New Testament running consecutively a–z, followed by three non-numerical characters <locus>(fols. 7–204)</locus>.</signatures>
                           <secFol><q>fro þe eest…</q> (New Testament, fol. 8r)</secFol>
                        </collation>
                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout columns="2" writtenLines="38">ruled for two columns, with single vertical and horizontal bounding lines extending the full height and width of page; 38 lines per page in New Testament; 39 lines per page in Old Testament lectionary; prickings occasionally survive; written space: <foreign rend="italic">c.</foreign><dimensions type="ruled" unit="mm">
                              <height>117</height>
                              <width>75</width>
                           </dimensions></layout>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc>
                     <handNote script="textualisNorthern">textura, black and brown ink; the scribe of Old Testament lectionary is different from the scribe of New Testament</handNote>
                  </handDesc>
                  <decoDesc>
                     <decoNote type="flourInit">3- to 5-line red and blue ‘puzzle’ initials with red and purple penwork at the beginnings of books; 3- to 4-line similar initials at the beginnings of prologues; 2- to 3-line blue initials with red penwork at the beginnings of chapters. Penwork in Old Testament lectionary is in a different style than that in the calendar and New Testament.</decoNote>
                  </decoDesc>
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <binding notAfter="1900" notBefore="1800">
                        <p>Light brown leather over pasteboard, 19th century. Blind fillet-line border round the outer edge of both covers. Five raised bands on spine framed by blind fillet lines. Gilt lettering on spine: ‘WICKLIFFE’S <lb/> NEW <lb/> TESTAMENT’ and ‘RAWL. <lb/> MS. <lb/> C. 259’. Blind roll floral designs on the edges of covers and turn-ins. 19th-century paper pastedowns and flyleaves. Flyleaves made of laid paper with Hearne’s inscriptions, dating from a 17th- or early 18th-century binding. Parchment flyleaves made from a 12th-century Latin manuscript containing fragments of St Augustine’s <title>Confessions</title>. These flyleaves may have served as pastedowns of a medieval binding sewn on four stations (offprints on the flyleaf at the beginning).</p>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origPlace>
                        <country key="place_7002445">England</country>, <settlement key="place_7011781">London (?)</settlement>
                     </origPlace>
                     <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="1425" notBefore="1400">15th century, first quarter</origDate>
                     <p>Perhaps made for a patron in London: references in the original hand in the calendar to the arrival of the Black Death in London and to the ‘Grote Mandrenke’ storm of 1362 that devastated southern and eastern England. The calendar includes Benedict Biscop. The calendar, New Testament, Old Testament lectionary and the table of lections are all codicologically separate; Old Testament lectionary and the table of lections may have been produced separately and bound with New Testament and the calendar.</p>
                     <p>Dialect survey: <list>
                           <item>ony(10), ech(9)/eche(1), fier(10), ȝouun(10), lijf(10), lijk(10), myche(9)/ miche(1), siȝ(3)/seiȝ(1)/siȝe(1)/saye(2)/saiȝ(1) (sg.), sayn(4)/sien(1)/seyn(1) (pl.), silf(10), sich(1)/siche(8)/suche(1), þouȝ(7), þorou(10)</item>
                           <item>-iþ(7)/eþ(3) (pres.ind.3sg.), -en(10) (pres.ind.pl.), -ynge(9)/-inge(1) (pres. part.), sche(10) (3sg.fem.pronoun, nom.), þei(10) (3pl.pronoun, nom.), hem(10) (3pl.pronoun, oblique), her(10) (3pl.pronoun, possessive)</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                  </origin>
                  <provenance>Translation of Thomas Becket is erased, presumably at Reformation.</provenance>
                  <provenance><persName role="fmo" key="person_4814">Edward Etterick</persName> of Totteridge, Hertfordshire (Foster, J., <title>Alumni Oxonienses: the members of the University of Oxford, 1500–1714</title>, 4 vols (London: Joseph Foster; Oxford: Parker and Co., 1891–92), p. 467), fellow of New College, matriculated 1714.</provenance>
                  <provenance><persName key="person_29543710" role="fmo">Thomas Hearne</persName>, bap. 1678, d. 1735; see <title>Oxford Dictionary of National Biography</title>: <q>Suum cuiq. Tho. Hearne, Oct. 9. 1719. I have made mention of this MS. in my Preface to Camden’s Eliz. (Oxon. 1717, p. 123.) It then belong’d to Edw. Etterick, Esq., Fellow of New College. I purchas’d it since his death</q> on fol. iv recto in his hand; see Hearne, Thomas (ed.), <title>Annales rerum Anglicarum et Hibernicarum, regnante Elizabetha, ad annum M.D.LXXXIX</title> (Oxford: 1717). On fol. v recto in Hearne’s hand: <q>The New Testament, in old English, commonly called Wicliff’s Translation, with the Calendar prefix’d</q>. On fol. v verso in Hearne’s hand: <q>Scriptus hic liber circa AD 1370, nam quae notantur paginis a &amp; k videntur tum recentia</q> and beneath in the hand of Thomas Baker (1656–1740; see <title>Oxford Dictionary of National Biography</title>) <q>Scriptum fuisse hunc librum exploratum haveo AD. 1345</q> and lower <q>Sed Amicus noster egregie fallitur, aut edo fallor</q>.</provenance>
                  <provenance><persName key="person_47563478" role="fmo">Richard Rawlinson</persName> (1690–1755); see <title>Oxford Dictionary of National Biography</title>.</provenance>
                  <acquisition when="1756">Bodleian Library: bequeathed by Rawlinson and accessioned in 1756.</acquisition>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>Elizabeth Solopova, <title>
                              <ref target="https://jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1gn6cmr">Manuscripts of the Wycliffite Bible in the Bodleian and Oxford College Libraries</ref>
                           </title>, Exeter Medieval Texts and Studies (Liverpool: Liverpool University Press, 2016), no. 42. Previously described: <listBibl>
                              <bibl facs="aei0063.gif" type="QUARTO">Quarto Catalogue, col. 113</bibl>
                              <bibl facs="aas0441.gif" type="SC">Summary Catalogue, vol. 3, p. 426</bibl>
                           </listBibl>
                        </source>
                     </recordHist>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl type="WRAPPER">
                     <listBibl type="PRINT">
                        <bibl>Forshall, J. and Madden, F. (eds), <title>The Holy Bible … in the earliest English versions made from the Latin Vulgate by John Wycliffe and his followers</title>, 4 vols (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1850), vol. 1, pp. xlix.</bibl>
                        <bibl>William D. Macray, <title>Catalogi codicum manuscriptorum Bibliothecæ Bodleianæ partis quintæ fasciculus secundus, viri munificentissimi Ricardi Rawlinson, J.C.D., codicum classem tertiam, in qua libri theologici atque miscellanei, complectens; accedit in uniuscujusque classis codicum contenta index locupletissimus</title> (Oxford, 1878), col. 113.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Hudson, A., ‘Lollard book production’, in Griffiths, J. and Pearsall, D. A. (eds), <title>Book production and publishing in Britain 1375–1475</title> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1989), pp. 125–42, p. 140.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Lindberg, C. (ed.), <title>The earlier version of the Wycliffite Bible,</title> 8 vols (Stockholm: Almqvist &amp; Wiksell, 1959–97), vol. 8 (1997), p. 274.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Scott, K. L. (gen. ed.), <title>An index of images in English manuscripts from the time of Chaucer to Henry VIII, c.1380–c.1509: the Bodleian Library, Oxford</title>, 3 vols (Turnhout: Harvey Miller Publishers, 2000–02), vol. 3, p. 49, no. 863. de Hamel, C., <title>The book: a history of the Bible</title> (London: Phaidon, 2001), p. 187. Dove, M., <title>The first English Bible: the text and context of the Wycliffite versions</title> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2007), pp. 269, 301.</bibl>
                     </listBibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2023-03-24">Add Solopova description.</change>
         <change when="2019-10-31" xml:id="MMM">
            <persName>Toby Burrows/Mapping Manuscript Migrations</persName>Provenance and acquisition information added using <ref target="https://github.com/mapping-manuscript-migrations/oxford-tei-updates/blob/master/update_oxford_prov.rb">https://github.com/mapping-manuscript-migrations/oxford-tei-updates/blob/master/update_oxford_prov.rb</ref> in collaboration with the <ref target="http://mappingmanuscriptmigrations.org/">Mapping Manuscript Migrations</ref> project.</change>
         <change when="2017-07-01">First online publication.</change>
         <change when="2017-05-25">
            <persName>James Cummings</persName> Up-converted the markup using <ref target="https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl">https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl</ref>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
