<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="manuscript_4352">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>MS. Digby 23</title>
            <title type="collection">MSS. Digby</title>
            <!-- <respStmt xml:id="Q1">
               <resp when="1888">Cataloguer</resp>
               <persName>W. D. Macray</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="PA">
               <resp when="1973">Cataloguer</resp>
               <persName>Otto Pächt</persName>
               <persName>J. J. G. Alexander</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="Q2">
               <resp when="1999">Cataloguer</resp>
               <persName>A. G. Watson</persName>
            </respStmt>-->
            <respStmt xml:id="MLH">
               <resp when="2020">Encoding</resp>
               <resp when="2020">Cataloguer</resp>
               <persName>Matthew Holford</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </publisher>
            <idno type="msID">MS_Digby_23</idno>
            <idno type="collection">Digby</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="MS_Digby_23" xml:lang="en">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <region type="county">Oxfordshire</region>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <institution>University of Oxford</institution>
                  <repository>Bodleian Library</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">MS. Digby 23</idno>
                  <idno type="ieArk">ark:29072/x0s4655g025k</idno><idno type="crArk">ark:29072/x0n870zq75p7</idno><altIdentifier type="internal">
                     <idno type="SCN">1624</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents>
                  <summary>This composite manuscript is famous for its second part, which contains the earliest copy of the <title>Chanson de Roland</title>. Written in the Anglo-Norman dialect of French, this copy was probably produced in England in the second quarter of the twelfth century, but its medieval provenance remains tantalisingly opaque. The first part of the manuscript, containing a Latin translation of Plato's <title>Timaeus</title>, was owned by Oseney Abbey from the thirteenth century: that the abbey also owned the <hi rend="italic">chanson de geste</hi> is possible but unproven.</summary>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <p n="composite">Composite: two manuscripts, separately foliated : fols. 1–55 || fols. 1–76</p>
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <binding notAfter="1634" notBefore="1602">
                        <p>Standard binding of the Digby collection, between 1632 and 1634: light brown leather, stamped on each cover in gilt with the large armorial stamp of Sir Kenelm Digby, with his arms in a laurel leaf within a pointed oval frame which carries the legend ‘INSIGNIA KENELMI DIGBY EQVITIS AURATI’; two clasps.</p>
                        <condition>Rebacked.</condition>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <!-- bottom of f. 28r incomplete coat of arms  -->
                  <provenance>Both parts of the manuscript were demonstrably together in <persName key="person_25374986" role="fmo">Thomas Allen</persName>'s library (octavo section, no. 48: <q>Timaeus Platonis Lat: cum Romances Gallicis metro</q>). Whether they were together previously is uncertain. Possible evidence in favour of an earlier association is provided by matching rust stains and holes on part 1, fol. 1 and part 2, fol. 76 which may suggest a shared earlier binding. Samaran and Parkes believed that the word 'Chalcidiu[s]' in thirteenth-century script could be read on part 2, fol. 72r, which would suggest that the two parts had been together since the thirteenth century.</provenance>
                  <provenance>Against this must be set other arguments: the title on part 1, fol. 2r (thirteenth century, second half according to Ker) refers only to the <title>Timaeus</title>; and the added text at the end of part 1, fol. 55v, mid-14th century, would seem to suggest that this page was then the end of a volume. Worm-damage at the beginning of part 2 indicates that it was separately bound at some stage.</provenance>
                  <provenance><persName key="person_49357645" role="fmo">Kenelm Digby</persName>: his signature and motto, fol. 2r, ‘Vindica te tibi / Ken: Digby’.</provenance>
                  <provenance>Presented by him to the Bodleian in 1634.</provenance>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>Description by Matthew Holford (March 2020, with thanks to Bruce Barker-Benfield for his comments). Previously described in the Quarto Catalogue (W. D. Macray, <title>Bodleian Library Quarto Catalogues IX: Digby Manuscripts</title>, repr. with addenda by R. W. Hunt and A. G. Watson, 1999). <listBibl>
                              <bibl facs="abw0019.gif" type="QUARTO">Quarto Catalogue, cols. 19–20</bibl>
                              <bibl facs="abw0192.gif" type="QUARTO">Quarto Catalogue (addenda), p. 15</bibl>
                              <bibl facs="abw0193.gif" type="QUARTO">Quarto Catalogue (addenda), p. 16</bibl>
                              <bibl facs="aap0091.gif" type="SC">Summary Catalogue, vol. 2, part 1, p. 70</bibl>
                           </listBibl>
                        </source>
                     </recordHist>
                     <availability status="restricted">
                        <p>To ensure its preservation, access to this item is restricted, and readers are asked to work from reproductions and published descriptions as far as possible. If you wish to apply to see the original, please click the request button above. When your request is received, you will be asked to contact the relevant curator outlining the subject of your research, the importance of this item to that research, and the resources you have already consulted.</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <surrogates>
                     <bibl subtype="full" type="digital-facsimile"><ref target="https://digital.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/objects/378bf1f5-a728-4b9e-aa4d-3fd20f59ef13/"><title>Digital Bodleian</title>
                           <note>(full digital facsimile of part 1)</note></ref>
                     </bibl><bibl subtype="full" type="digital-facsimile"><ref target="https://digital.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/objects/79097275-ef1d-4107-85d3-e8402120f365/"><title>Digital Bodleian</title>
                           <note>(full digital facsimile of part 2)</note></ref></bibl>
                  </surrogates>
                  <listBibl type="WRAPPER">
                     <listBibl type="PRINT">
                        <head>Printed descriptions, editions and facsimiles:</head>
                        <bibl><title>La Chanson de Roland</title>, gen. ed. Joseph. J. Duggan, I (2005)</bibl>
                        <bibl>Otto Pächt and J. J. G. Alexander, <title><ref target="https://catalog.hathitrust.org/Record/000468709">Illuminated Manuscripts in the Bodleian Library, Oxford</ref></title>, I (1966), no. 475 [part 1]</bibl>
                        <bibl><title>La chanson de Roland : reproduction phototypique du manuscrit Digby 23 de la Bodleian Library d'Oxford</title>, ed. A. de Laborde and C. Samaran (1933)</bibl>
                        <bibl><title>Photographische Wiedergabe der HS. Digby 23</title>, ed. Edmund Stengel (Heilbronn, 1878)</bibl>
                     </listBibl>
                     <listBibl type="INTERNET">
                        <head>Online resources:</head>
                        <!--Existing bibliography in place: check sorting of entries-->
                        <bibl><ref target="http://jonas.irht.cnrs.fr/manuscrit/40193"><title>JONAS: Répertoire des textes et des manuscrits médiévaux d'oc et d'oïl</title></ref></bibl>
                        <bibl><ref target="http://mlgb3.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/mlgb/book/4196"><title>MLGB3: Medieval Libraries of Great Britain</title></ref></bibl>
                     </listBibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
               <msPart xml:id="MS_Digby_23-part1">
                  <msIdentifier>
                     <altIdentifier type="partial">
                        <idno type="part">MS. Digby 23 – Part 1</idno>
                     </altIdentifier>
                  </msIdentifier>
                  <msContents>
                     <textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="1v" to="2r">(fols. 1v–2r)</locus>
                        <incipit>Vehementer opinamur beatam uirginem dei genitricem Mariam corpore resuscitatam et glorificatam</incipit>
                        <explicit>aut sepultam reddant aut nobiscum resuscitatam pie credant</explicit>
                        <title type="desc">Arguments for the Assumption of the Virgin</title>
                        <note>Added in anglicana script in the second half of the thirteenth century.</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="2r">(fol. 2r)</locus>
                        <note>Ex libris of Osney abbey and pressmarks (see Provenance), with title 'Thymeus platonis', 13th century, second half (the pressmarks later; for dates see MLGB3).</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="2v">(fol. 2v)</locus>
                        <incipit>Nulla res potest simul esse eadem festinata et examinata</incipit>
                        <note>13th century. Followed by the note <q>quere in 2º registri</q> (15th century)</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <!-- fol. 2v, notes -->
                     <msItem n="1" xml:id="MS_Digby_23-part1-item1">
                        <locus from="3r">(fol. 3r)</locus>
                        <rubric>Incipit Thimeus Platonis</rubric>
                        <author key="person_108159964">Plato</author>
                        <title key="work_3700">Timaeus</title>
                        <note>In the Latin version of <persName key="person_266558598" role="trl">Calcidius</persName>; most recently edited in <title>On Plato's Timaeus</title>, ed. J. Magee (2016).</note>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="3r" to="4r">(fols. 3r–4r)</locus>
                           <incipit>Isocrates in exortacionibus suis</incipit>
                           <note>Prefatory letter of Calcidius to Ossius, with interlinear and marginal glosses.</note>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="4v" to="51r">(fols. 4v–51r)</locus>
                           <incipit>Socrates. Vnus. iiº. iii<hi rend="superscript">es</hi>. quartum enumero uestro Thimęę requiro</incipit>
                           <rubric><locus from="30v" to="30v">(fol. 30v)</locus> Explicit liber primus incipit secundus</rubric>
                           <explicit>ex leui admonitione perspicuo. Explicit.</explicit>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <note>Three layers of gloss:</note>
                           <msItem n="i">
                              <note>Marginal and interlinear gloss contemporary with the original production of the book.</note>
                              <incipit><locus from="3r" to="3r">(fol. 3r)</locus> In quodam libro in quo exortabatur homines ad uirtutem</incipit>
                              <incipit><locus from="3r" to="3r">(fol. 3r)</locus> Calcidius ut aiunt archidiaconus cordubiensis osio pape romano uel ut quidam uolunt cordubensi episcopo</incipit>
                              <incipit><locus from="4v" to="4v">(fol. 4v)</locus> Vtitur dialogo et ponit senarium numerum ut operis designet perfectionem</incipit>
                           </msItem>
                           <msItem n="ii">
                              <note>Marginal and interlinear glosses in several thirteenth-century hands.</note>
                           </msItem>
                           <msItem n="iii">
                              <note>Less frequent marginal and interlinear glosses in anglicana script (14th century, first half); also responsible for adding an incomplete (?) series of chapter numbers reflecting a division into three books of respectively 9, 15 and 17 chapters (book 1 in the original organization being divided into two books, the second starting at 'Est igitur (27d, fol. 18v)). For this division of the text see <bibl>P. E. Dutton, 'Material remains of the study of the <title>Timaeus</title> in the later middle ages', in <title>L'enseignement de la philosophie au XIIIe siècle: autour du "Guide de l'étudiant" du ms. Ripoll 109 ; actes du colloque international</title> (1997), pp. 224–5</bibl>.</note>
                           </msItem>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="51v" to="55v">(fols. 51v–55v)</locus>
                           <note>The final quire is filled up with diagrams and notes, from or related to Calcidius’ <title>Commentary on the Timaeus</title>, Macrobius, and Martianus Capella.</note>
                           <msItem>
                              <locus from="51v">(fol. 51v)</locus>
                              <note>Diagram of the harmony of spheres with accompanying text on squaring the circle.</note>
                              <incipit>Si uis reperire quadraturam in circulo </incipit>
                           </msItem>
                           <msItem>
                              <locus from="52r">(fol. 52r)</locus>
                              <note>Diagrams including planetary orbits, the zodiac, lunar eclipse</note>
                           </msItem>
                           <msItem>
                              <locus from="52v">(fol. 52v)</locus>
                              <note>Geographical diagrams including a Macrobian map of the world with its oceans, and another zonal map; and phases of the moon</note>
                           </msItem>
                           <msItem>
                              <locus from="53r">(fol. 53r)</locus>
                              <note>Diagrams of the elements</note>
                              <rubric>Colligatio elementorum secundum platonicos numeros</rubric>
                              <rubric>Colligatio elementorum secundum solidos numeros</rubric>
                           </msItem>
                           <msItem>
                              <locus from="53v">(fol. 53v)</locus>
                              <note>Diagram of musical intervals</note>
                           </msItem>
                           <msItem>
                              <locus from="54r">(fol. 54r)</locus>
                              <note>Cosmographical diagram of the five elemental layers; and Calcidius’ lambda diagrams, combined.</note>
                           </msItem>
                           <msItem>
                              <locus from="54v">(fol. 54v)</locus>
                              <note>Diagrams of the elements and seasons</note>
                           </msItem>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="55r" to="55v">(fol. 55r–v)</locus>
                           <note>Short contemporary additions: </note>
                           <msItem n="a">
                              <locus from="55r">(fol. 55r)</locus>
                              <incipit>Quibus ita diuisis consequenter implebat interualla duplicis et triplicis quantitatis <note>[Tim. I.35c-36a]</note>. sesqualteris. et sesquitertiis. et binis medietatibus. medietas alia est arismetica. alia geometrica. alia armonica. Arismetica est que consideratur in sola identitate differentiarum. </incipit>
                           </msItem>
                           <msItem n="b">
                              <locus from="55v">(fol. 55v)</locus>
                              <incipit><hi rend="italic">Sumpsit unam</hi> Uisis uiribus anime, considerandum est qui sint motus eius</incipit>
                           </msItem>
                           <msItem n="c">
                              <locus from="55v">(fol. 55v)</locus>
                              <incipit>Discipline due sunt species. Astronomia. Astrologia. Astronomia est que consideratur secundum rei veritatem</incipit>
                           </msItem>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem n="d">
                           <locus from="55v">(fol. 55v)</locus>
                           <incipit>Mitte mihi per Johannem fratrem tuum dimidium centum de partie Gold</incipit>
                           <note>Request for gold and colours (presumably materials for painting or illuminating) added in anglicana script, mid-14th century</note>
                        </msItem>
                     </msItem>
                  </msContents>
                  <physDesc>
                     <p><secFol><locus from="4" to="4">(fol. 4)</locus> tionis. calida</secFol></p>
                     <objectDesc form="codex">
                        <supportDesc material="perg">
                           <support>parchment</support>
                           <extent>ii + 1 + 54 folios <dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                                 <height>175</height>
                                 <width>120</width>
                              </dimensions></extent>
                           <collation>medieval flyleaf (fol. 1), 1(10) (fols. 2–11), 2(8), 3(10), 4(8)-5(8), 6(10); <signatures>medieval numbering i-vi at the ends of quires (fols. 11v, 19v, etc.), modern numbering 2–8 at the beginning of quires (fols. 1, 2, 12, etc.), implying a quire (added by Allen?) lost at the beginning <!-- the number Allen's? cf. Digby 35 --></signatures></collation>
                        </supportDesc>
                        <layoutDesc>
                           <layout columns="1" writtenLines="15">The main text in 1 col. of 15 lines, written space <dimensions type="written" unit="mm">
                                 <height>120</height>
                                 <width>60</width>
                              </dimensions>. Ruled in leadpoint, pricked in the outer margins only.</layout>
                        </layoutDesc>
                     </objectDesc>
                     <decoDesc>
                        <summary>Good initials, diagrams. (<ref target="https://catalog.hathitrust.org/Record/000468709">Pächt and Alexander</ref> i. 475)</summary>
                        <decoNote type="decInit">(fol. 1) decorated initial I</decoNote>
                        <decoNote type="diagram">Diagrams.</decoNote>
                        <decoNote type="drawing">Marginal sketches and drawings including incomplete heraldry, fol. 28r.</decoNote>
                     </decoDesc>
                  </physDesc>
                  <history>
                     <origin resp="#PA">
                        <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="1160" notBefore="1140">12th century, middle</origDate>
                        <origPlace>
                           <country key="place_1000070">French</country> (?) </origPlace>
                     </origin>
                     <provenance>J. L. Waszink (Plato latinus, vol. IV) thought this manuscript 'clearly English' but the script and decoration suggest a French origin.</provenance>
                     <provenance>'Liber ecclesie sancte Marie de Oseneya ex legato magistri Henrici de Langeleya', fol. 2r (thirteenth century, second half). Usually identified as <persName key="person_2802" role="dnr">mr. Henry of Langley (fl. 1246–1263)</persName>; see <bibl>A. B. Emden, ‘Additions and corrections to <title>A biographical register of the University of Oxford to A.D. 1500</title> supplemental list no. 1’, <title>The Bodleian Library Record</title>, vol. VI no. 6 (Sept. 1961), pp. 668–688, at p. 677, and I. Short in <title>Romania</title> 94 (1973), 231 n. 1</bibl>.</provenance>
                     <provenance><orgName key="org_155836576" role="fmo">Osney Abbey</orgName>: pressmarks <q>114</q>, <q>168</q>, fol. 2r.</provenance>
                  </history>
               </msPart>
               <msPart xml:id="MS_Digby_23-part2">
                  <msIdentifier>
                     <altIdentifier type="partial">
                        <idno type="part">MS. Digby 23 – Part 2</idno>
                     </altIdentifier>
                  </msIdentifier>
                  <msContents>
                     <msItem class="#romances" n="1" xml:id="MS_Digby_23-part2-item1">
                        <locus from="1r" to="72r">(fols. 1r–72r)</locus>
                        <title key="work_10865">Chanson de Roland</title>
                        <note>R. J. Dean &amp; M. Boulton, <title>Anglo-Norman literature: a guide to texts and manuscripts</title> (London, 1999), no. 76</note>
                        <note>Ed. I. Short in <title>La Chanson de Roland</title>, gen. ed. Joseph. J. Duggan, I (2005), with a full discussion of the scribe's language. The text was corrected or revised in the late twelfth or the thirteenth century (Short, pp. 103–4).</note>
                        <textLang mainLang="xno">Anglo-Norman</textLang>
                        <msItem>
                           <locus from="72r">(fol. 72r)</locus>
                           <note>Six lines of badly faded text following the explicit were transcribed as follows by C. Samaran under ultra-violet light for the facsimile edition of 1932 (<title>La chanson de Roland: reproduction phototypique</title>) and dated by him to the 13th century; the readings were confirmed by R. W. Hunt in 1975 (see M. B. Parkes, <title>Scribes, Scripts and Readers</title> (1991), p. 76): <q>Ci fait la geste [que Turoldus declinet] <lb/> . odo ................. <lb/> .............. <lb/>C. . . (ligne sinueuse) <lb/>C os (?) [ ...]. C.]o rd[uben]s[is. ....] Chalcidiu[s] <lb/> .....</q></note>
                        </msItem>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="73r">(fol. 73r)</locus>
                        <note>Ten lines of Middle English, written in leadpoint, c. 1400 (?) (not noted in <title>Index of Middle English Prose</title> or the <title>Index of Middle English Verse</title>). The following transcription was given by Samaran (<bibl><title>La chanson de Roland: reproduction phototypique</title> (1932), p. 32</bibl>): <q><gap quantity="3" unit="char"/> men among <gap quantity="3" unit="char"/> he dos to wi<gap quantity="11" unit="char"/>
                              <lb/> grene and gray <gap quantity="3" unit="char"/> as sinful me w<gap quantity="8" unit="char"/>
                              <lb/> mykil wrong <gap quantity="4" unit="char"/> mani <gap quantity="6" unit="char"/> at was <gap quantity="4" unit="char"/>
                              <lb/> at maked his song of so <gap quantity="14" unit="char"/>
                              <lb/> all his ban <gap quantity="6" unit="char"/> say reant oym. W<gap quantity="6" unit="char"/>
                              <lb/> him <gap quantity="4" unit="char"/> niht <gap quantity="4" unit="char"/> long for g<gap quantity="6" unit="char"/> Was <gap quantity="4" unit="char"/>
                              <lb/>
                              <unclear>allaye</unclear> to hurten we <gap quantity="20" unit="char"/>
                              <lb/> long <gap quantity="17" unit="char"/> was <gap quantity="24" unit="char"/><lb/>
                              <gap quantity="14" unit="char"/> n<gap quantity="5" unit="char"/>es ful a songe <gap quantity="11" unit="char"/>
                              <lb/> wryte <gap quantity="7" unit="char"/> s<gap quantity="33" unit="char"/></q></note>
                        <textLang mainLang="enm">Middle English</textLang>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="73v">(fol. 73v)</locus>
                        <note>Pen trials at the foot of the page.</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="74r" to="75v">(fols. 74r–75v)</locus>
                        <note>Blank.</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="76r">(fol. 76r)</locus>
                        <note>Three lines from <persName key="person_83985148" role="aut">Juvenal</persName>, <title key="work_2896">Satires</title> (viii.269–71) added at the foot of the page (former pastedown) by an early hand, 12th or 13th century.</note>
                        <textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>
                        <!-- date? French script? -->
                     </msItem>
                  </msContents>
                  <physDesc>
                     <p><secFol><locus from="2" to="2">(fol. 2)</locus> Asez est</secFol></p>
                     <objectDesc form="codex">
                        <supportDesc material="perg">
                           <support>parchment</support>
                           <extent>
                              <dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                                 <height max="175" min="170">c. 170–5</height>
                                 <width max="125" min="120">120–5</width>
                              </dimensions>
                           </extent>
                           <collation>1(8)-9(8) (fols. 1–72), followed by four endleaves, of which fols. 73 and 76 are a medieval bifolium and fols. 74–5 a later parchment bifolium. Fol. 76 was the back pastedown of a previous binding, showing the marks of leather turn-ins, and two large holes (echoed at fol. 73) probably from the pins of two strap-and-pin fastenings.</collation>
                        </supportDesc>
                        <layoutDesc>
                           <layout columns="1" writtenLines="27 30">Ruled in drypoint. 1 col., 27–30 lines. Written space <dimensions type="written" unit="mm">
                                 <height max="145" min="130">c. 130–45</height>
                                 <width max="90" min="75">75–90</width>
                              </dimensions> Pricked in the outer margins only.</layout>
                        </layoutDesc>
                     </objectDesc>
                     <decoDesc>
                        <decoNote type="colInit">Initials in red (once, fol. 39r, in green) at the beginning of each laisse with occasional sparse decoration.</decoNote>
                     </decoDesc>
                  </physDesc>
                  <history>
                     <origin>
                        <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="1160" notBefore="1125" resp="#Q2">12th century, second quarter (?)</origDate>
                        <origPlace>
                           <country key="place_7002445">England</country>
                        </origPlace>
                     </origin>
                     <provenance>For assessments of the date see Short, pp. 19–20, with reference to earlier literature.</provenance>
                     <provenance>Possibly bound with part 1 since the thirteenth century (see above).</provenance>
                  </history>
               </msPart>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2017-05-25"><persName>James Cummings</persName> Up-converted the markup using <ref target="https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl">https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl</ref></change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>