<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="manuscript_8545">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>MS. Rawl. G. 185</title>
            <title type="collection">MSS. Rawl. G. (Rawlinson G)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp when="2013">Cataloguer</resp>
               <persName>Elizabeth Solopova</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp when="2024">Encoding</resp>
               <persName>Matthew Holford</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </publisher>
            <idno type="msID">MS_Rawl_G_185</idno>
            <idno type="collection">Rawl_G</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="MS_Rawl_G_185" xml:lang="en">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <region type="county">Oxfordshire</region>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <institution>University of Oxford</institution>
                  <repository>Bodleian Library</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">MS. Rawl. G. 185</idno>
                  <idno type="ieArk">ark:29072/x0d217qp94x2</idno>
                  <idno type="crArk">ark:29072/x0cz30pt11mc</idno>
                  <altIdentifier type="internal">
                     <idno type="SCN">14902</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
               <head>Choir Psalter with Antiphons, Use of the Augustinian Canons of Christ Church
                  Cathedral, Dublin; England, 14th century, third quarter (before 1368)</head>
               <msContents>
                  <msItem class="#liturgica #biblia #historica" n="1" xml:id="MS_Rawl_G_185-item1">
                     <title key="work_14114" type="desc">Psalter</title>
                     <note>Choir Psalter with antiphons, Use of the Augustinian Canons of Christ Church Cathedral, Dublin.</note>

                     <msItem n="1">
                        <locus>(fols. ii verso–iii recto, 142v, 144r)</locus>
                        <note> Notes concerning the affairs of the Priory of Christ Church
                           Cathedral, Dublin, ranging from 1368 to 1416 (described and partially
                           reproduced by Hand, 1956). Most notes refer to the priorate of James de
                           Redenesse (d. 1409). Personal prayers, fol. iii recto. Fol. i is a paper
                           fly-leaf; fols. ii recto and iii verso are blank apart from modern notes.
                        </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <note>[item 2 occupies quire I] </note>
                     <msItem n="2">
                        <locus from="iv-recto" to="ix-verso">(fols. iv recto–ix verso) </locus>
                        <note>Calendar for the use of the Augustinian canons of Christ Church,
                           Dublin, laid out one month per page, written in brown, blue, red, pink
                           and gold, graded to 9 lessons and ‘duplex festum’. Augustine of Hippo is
                           in gold (28 August) with octave and translation in red (11 October). Also
                           in gold are Patrick (17 March, ‘sancti patricii hibernie apostoli’),
                           Columba (9 June), Lawrence O’Toole (14 November, ‘sancti laurencii
                           archiepiscopi dublini’) and Catherine (25 November). The following saints
                           are in red or blue: David (1 March), Cuthbert (20 March), Dunstan (19
                           May), Augustine of Canterbury (26 May, ‘primi anglorum episcopi’),
                           Maculinus (6 September), Fintan Find (10 October) and Mobhi of Glasnevin
                           (12 October). The calendar includes many other Irish saints, such as
                           Itha, patroness of Killeedy, Limerick (15 January), Fursey, abbot of
                           Langy near Paris (16 January), Aedhan, bishop of Ferns (31 January),
                           Brigid of Kildare (1 February), Fintan, abbot of Clonenagh (17 February),
                           Abban, abbot of Kill-Abban and Finan, abbot of Swords, Dublin (both 16
                           March), Brendan (16 May), Kieran, abbot of Clonmacnoise (9 September),
                           Finbar McBindi (10 September), Canice (11 October) (for a full list of
                           Irish saints in the calendar and comparison with the calendar of another
                           Christ Church book, the Martyrology, see Hand, 1956, pp. 312–14). The
                           feast of relics is in red on 31 July. The elevation of the relics of
                           Edward, king and martyr, is added in a 16th-century hand at 20 June
                           (‘Translatio Sancti Edwardi’). The months are headed by verses on the
                           ‘Egyptian’ days, which correspond to Hennig’s (1955) set III, and end
                           with notes on the number of hours in days and nights, e.g. ‘Nox habet
                           horas xvi. dies uero viij.’ (January). In February ‘locus bisextus’ is
                           entered against the 24th with the Dominical letter ‘f’ and there are
                           Latin verses in red in the original hand in the lower margin: Si bisextus
                           erit f. seruetur utrique diei Posteriori die celebratur festum mathie.
                           Verses on psalms in red in the original hand on the page for December,
                           before the start of psalms (fol. ix verso): ‘Centum quingenos dauid canit
                           in ordine psalmos Uersus bis mille sex centum sex canit ille’ (Walther,
                           no. 19209).</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <note> [items 3–7 occupy quires II–XIX] </note>
                     <msItem n="3">
                        <locus from="1r" to="127r">(fols. 1r–127r)</locus>
                        <note> Psalms 1–150, without titles or numbers, written with each verse
                           beginning on a new line. Punctuated throughout, with punctus used to mark
                           the ends of verses, and punctus elevatus used to mark metrum. The psalms
                           are in the biblical order; the subdivisions within psalms are not
                           indicated, apart from psalm 118, subdivided into eleven 16-verse units.
                           Psalms 148–150 are written without breaks as a single text. The psalms
                           are accompanied by antiphons and versicles, with short rubrics and
                           musical notation (square notation on staves of three or four red lines).
                           There are textual divisions at psalms 26, 38, 52, 68, 80, 97 and 109.
                           Roman numerals ii–vii (for days of the week) are written in the margins
                           next to the initials of psalms 26, 38, 52, 68, 80 and 97, possibly in the
                           original workshop. Psalm 109 starts at the beginning of a new quire and
                           the scribe left much of the preceding fol. 96v blank. The text contains
                           corrections, and omitted verses are added in margins in the original or a
                           contemporary hand. </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="4">
                        <locus from="127r" to="134v">(fols. 127r–134v)</locus>
                        <note> Weekly canticles, without titles: <list>
                              <item>(1) Confitebor tibi domine (Isaiah 12);</item>
                              <item>(2) Ego dixi (Isaiah 38: 10–21);</item>
                              <item>(3) Exultauit cor meum (1 Samuel 2: 1–11);</item>
                              <item>(4) Cantemus domino (Exodus 15: 1–20);</item>
                              <item>(5) Domine audiui (Habakkuk 3);</item>
                              <item>(6) Audite celi (Deuteronomy 32: 1–44).</item>
                           </list>
                        </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="5">
                        <locus from="134v" to="139r">(fols. 134v–139r)</locus>
                        <note> Daily canticles, prayers and creeds, without titles: <list>
                              <item>(1) Te deum laudamus (fol. 134v);</item>
                              <item>(2) Benedicite omnia opera (fol. 135v);</item>
                              <item>(3) Benedictus dominus deus (fol. 136r);</item>
                              <item>(4) Magnificat (fol. 136v);</item>
                              <item>(5) Nunc dimittis (fol. 137r);</item>
                              <item>(6) Athanasian Creed (Quicumque uult ...) (fol. 137r).</item>
                           </list> The canticles are followed by antiphons with musical notation,
                           beginning ‘Beati qui ambulant in lege ...’ and ending ‘parce domine parce
                           populo tuo quem redemisti precioso sanguine tuo . et ne des hereditatem
                           tuam in perdicionem’. </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="6">
                        <locus from="139r" to="142r">(fols. 139r–142r)</locus>
                        <note> Litany, including Thomas Becket, Hugh of Lincoln, Edmund, Oswald,
                           Edward and Alban among the martyrs; Augustine, Patrick, Columba and
                           Kieran as the sixth, eighth, ninth and tenth among the confessors; and
                           Brigid (of Kildare (?)) as the twelfth of the virgins. The litany is
                           followed by collects (fols. 140r–142r): <list>
                              <item>(1) Deus cui proprium est misereri semper et parcere suscipe
                                 ...</item>
                              <item>(2) Omnipotens sempiterne deus qui facis mirabilia magna solus
                                 ...</item>
                              <item>(3) Deus uirtutum cuius est totum quod est optimum ...</item>
                              <item>(4) Deus qui caritatis dona per graciam ...</item>
                              <item>(5) Pretende domine famulis et famulabus tuis dexteram celestis
                                 auxilii ut de toto corde ...</item>
                              <item>(6) Ure igne sancti spiritus renes nostros ...</item>
                              <item>(7) Actiones nostras quesumus domine aspirando preueni
                                 ...</item>
                              <item>(8) Ecclesie tue quesumus domine preces placatus admitte ut
                                 destructis ...</item>
                              <item>(9) Deus qui es sanctorum tuorum splendor mirabilis atque
                                 lapsorum subleuator ...</item>
                              <item>(10) Per horum omnium sanctorum angelorum ...</item>
                              <item>(11) Liberator animarum mundi redemptor ihesu criste ...
                                 [masculine forms]</item>
                              <item>(12) Omnipotens sempiterne deus cuius bonitate regimur
                                 ...</item>
                           </list> The last collect is followed by a colophon naming Stephen of
                           Derby, prior of Christ Church Cathedral, Dublin, fol. 142r (see
                           ‘Provenance’). The colophon is in the original hand in coloured inks,
                           changing at the start of every new line, alternating between pink, red
                           and blue: ‘ffrater Stephanus de Derby . Prior ecclesie sancte trinitatis
                           dublinie Cathedralis istud psalterium ordinauit et fieri fecit . Sit
                           benedictus amen’. The lower margin of fol. 142r contains the obits of
                           nine priors of Christ Church Cathedral, Dublin, added in a 16th-century
                           hand, headed by a rubric ‘Successores Steph. de Derby’, beginning with
                           Robert de Lockton with a date ‘1397’, and ending with William Hassard
                           with a date ‘1537’ and Robert Castell without a date (‘Robertus Castell
                           alias Painswick ultimus Prior et primus huius ecclesiae Decanus’).
                        </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="7">
                        <locus from="143r">(fol. 143r)</locus>
                        <note> Added formula for general absolutions, beginning ‘Auctoritate dei
                           patris omnipotentis et beatorum apostolorum Petri &amp; Pauli ...’ and
                           ending ‘... et uiuas in secula seculorum. Amen. In nomine patris et filij
                           et cetera’ (published by Hand, 1956). Initial A is left unfinished. Fol.
                           143v is partially ruled, otherwise blank; fol. 144v is blank; fol. 145 is
                           a paper fly-leaf. </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <p><secFol> Apprehendite disciplinam <locus>(psalter, fol.
                     2r)</locus></secFol></p>
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="perg">
                        <support> parchment; paper fly-leaves</support>
                        <extent> 154 leaves <dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                              <height quantity="395">c. 395</height>
                              <width>250</width>
                           </dimensions>
                           <note>Leaves were trimmed in rebinding causing the loss of decoration.
                           </note>
                        </extent>
                        <foliation> modern, in ink; i–ix + 1–145.</foliation>
                        <collation> (fols. i–iii) fol. i is a paper fly-leaf, originally conjoint
                           with the upper pastedown; fols. ii–iii are two singletons | (fols. iv–ix)
                           I (6) | (fols. 1–136) II–XVIII (8) | (fols. 137–142) XIX (6) | (fols.
                           143–145) fols. 143 and 144 are two singletons; fol. 145 is a paper
                           fly-leaf originally conjoint with the lower pastedown. Catchwords,
                           decorated with scrolls, often survive; leaf signatures occasionally
                           survive (e.g. quire VIII, fols. 49–52)</collation>





                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout rulingMedium="ink" writtenLines="21" columns="1"> Ruled in red ink
                           with single vertical and horizontal bounding lines, extending the full
                           height and width of page, and in faint plummet for tops and bottoms of
                           minims; written below the top line; 21 lines per page; written space:
                              <dimensions type="written" unit="mm">
                              <height quantity="292">c. 292</height>
                              <width>185</width>
                           </dimensions>. </layout>
                        <layout writtenLines="21" columns="2">Fols. 139r–142r, containing the litany
                           and collects, are ruled for two columns of 21 or more lines, with single
                           vertical and horizontal bounding lines extending the full height and
                           width of page. Fol. 143r–v is ruled on each page for two columns with
                           single vertical bounding lines, single horizontal bounding lines at the
                           top of the page and double horizontal bounding lines at the bottom of the
                           page</layout>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc>
                     <handNote script="textualisNorthern" execution="formata">Large formal Gothic book hand; antiphons and versicles are in a
                        smaller script</handNote>
                  </handDesc>
                  <musicNotation>
                     <p>Square notation on staves of three or four red lines</p>
                  </musicNotation>
                  <decoDesc>
                     <summary>Attributed to the <persName role="art" key="person_826">Master of the Egerton Genesis</persName> (London, British
                        Library, Egerton MS. 1894) (Pächt, 1943), the M. R. James Memorial Psalter
                        (London, British Library, Add. MS. 44949) (Millar, 1938; Pächt, 1943) and
                        the Crucifixion and Christ in Majesty miniatures in the Fitzwarin Psalter
                        (Paris, Bibliothèque nationale MS. lat. 765) (Wormald, 1943). Border
                        decoration on fol. 1r is in a different style from the rest of the
                        psalter.</summary>
                     <decoNote type="monogram">Calendar: Pink and blue KL monograms on gold
                        background and borders made of pink, blue and gold bars, decorated with
                        sprays of leaves (both side-margins in January and left margin only in other
                        months). The borders incorporate the Signs of the Zodiac, and a Labour of
                        the Month for January: January: man sitting on a stool, stirring the
                        contents of a cauldron; hybrid Aquarius February: Pisces (man holding two
                        fish) March: Aries April: Taurus May: Gemini (two profile heads and two arms
                        supporting a shield, party per pale, sable and argent) June: Cancer July:
                        Leo August: Virgo September: Libra (man holding scales) October: Scorpio
                        emerging from a bishop’s mitre November: Capricorn December:
                        Sagittarius</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="histInit">5- to 7-line (psalm 1) historiated initials in gold
                        frames at liturgical divisions. Borders made of pink, blue and gold bars,
                        decorated with sprays of leaves and gold discs. Psalms 1 and 109 have a
                        particularly rich border ornament.<list>
                           <item>fol. 1r, Psalm 1 (initial B(eatus)) Blue initial, decorated with
                              white monochrome images (damaged) of David playing harp, the Virgin
                              and Child, and a seated young man. The initial is infilled with young
                              David, holding stones in the skirt of his tunic, and Goliath in
                              armour, with a sword, axe and shield (staining from tarnished silver
                              on Goliath’s armour).</item>
                           <item>(full border) Jesse Tree (reclining Jesse; 12 panels, framed with
                              vines, bearing leaves and grapes, containing twelve crowned figures,
                              including Solomon with a model of the Temple).</item>
                           <item>fol. 20r, Psalm 26 (initial D(ominus)) Christ, seated, holding a
                              book and blessing. Beside the initial is the kneeling figure of
                              Stephen of Derby (?), in a monastic (Augustinian (?)) habit, holding a
                              scroll inscribed with the opening words of the psalm.</item>
                           <item>(full border) Lower corner-pieces with gold roses.</item>
                           <item>fol. 32v, Psalm 38 (initial D(ixi)) King David kneeling, pointing to
                              his mouth; the face of Christ with cruciform halo in clouds
                              above.</item>
                           <item>(border, left, right and lower margins) Animal masks;
                              dragons.</item>
                           <item>fol. 43v, Psalm 52 (initial D(ixit)) Seated tonsured figure in a
                              black (Augustinian (?)) habit, holding a book, finger raised in a
                              gesture of teaching, speaking to the Fool, seated on the floor, in a
                              short white tunic, holding a pouch; the face of God in clouds above.
                              Scrolls with lettering: ‘Non est deus’ (Fool); ‘Tu mentiris aperte’
                              (cleric); ‘Ecce dicit incipiens’ (God).</item>
                           <item>(full border) Grotesque.</item>
                           <item> fol. 54v, Psalm 68 (initial S(aluum)) Crowned nude King David
                              praying in waters; the face and blessing hand of God above.</item>
                           <item>(full border) Animal mask.</item>
                           <item>fol. 68v, Psalm 80 (initial E(xultate)) Seven tonsured Augustinian
                              (?) clerics playing musical instruments; half-figure of God, holding a
                              book and blessing.</item>
                           <item>(full border) Human figures in hoods and cloaks with decorative
                              stems growing out of their bodies; grotesque.</item>
                           <item>fol. 81v, Psalm 97 (initial C(antate)) Tonsured clerics singing from
                              a book with musical notation open on a lectern; two hybrid figures,
                              reading books.</item>
                           <item>(full border) Animal mask.</item>
                           <item>fol. 97r, Psalm 109 (initial D(ixit)) Blue initial, decorated with
                              white monochrome images of praying angels, infilled with the Throne of
                              Grace.</item>
                           <item>(full border) Animal masks; grotesque.</item>
                        </list></decoNote>

                     <decoNote type="decInit">2-line initials in gold frames, decorated with sprays
                        of leaves and gold discs, and borders formed by pink, blue and gold bars,
                        decorated with sprays of leaves, grotesques and animal masks, at the
                        beginnings of psalms, canticles, prayers and litany. Some initials are
                        infilled with the head of Christ with cruciform halo (e.g. fols. 9r–v, 11r,
                        15r–v), heads of bearded men or human profiles (e.g. fols. 31r, 35r,
                        69v).</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="border">Borders: see above.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="flourInit">1-line gold initials on blue and pink background
                        alternating with blue initials decorated with red penwork at the beginnings
                        of verses and periods.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="flourInit">The beginnings of staves with musical notation and
                        capital letters at the start of antiphons are often decorated with arabesque
                        designs, grotesques and human profiles in penwork with pink and yellow
                        wash.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="lineFill">Line-endings made of blue, pink and gold bars with
                        white designs alternate with red and blue penwork line-endings.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="rubrication">Rubrics in red ink.</decoNote>
                  </decoDesc>
                  <bindingDesc>

                     <binding notAfter="1525" notBefore="1500">
                        <p> Dark brown leather (damaged) over oak boards, early 16th century (?).
                           Tooled with four diamond-shaped panels on both covers; at the centre of
                           each panel is a shield with a rose inside. The panels are framed with
                           blind fillet lines, forming a criss-cross pattern with floral
                           corner-pieces. Border made of blind roll floral decoration framed with
                           blind fillet lines round the outer edge of both covers. Rebacked,
                           probably in the Bodleian. Impressions left by the fittings of two clasps
                           on the lower cover. Holes on fol. 144 presumably from a former
                           strap-and-pin binding. The upper and lower pastedowns and paper
                           fly-leaves are leaves from an early printed edition of the Compilatio
                           Sexta, i.e. Raymond of Pennafort’s Decretals of Gregory IX. Fols. ii and
                           144 were formerly pastedowns. </p>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="1368" notBefore="1350">14th century,
                        third quarter (before 1368)</origDate>
                     <origPlace>
                        <country key="place_7002445">English</country>
                     </origPlace>
                  </origin>
                  <provenance>Commissioned by <persName role="pat" key="person_4877">Stephen of Derby, prior of the Augustinian Canons of
                     Christ Church Cathedral, Dublin, 1349–c. 1382</persName>: colophon on fol. 142r; possible
                     portrait (fol. 20r). </provenance>
                  <provenance><orgName key="org_158720589"
                     >Augustinian Canons of Christ Church Cathedral, Dublin</orgName>. The psalter was still in the Priory early in the 15th
                     century when the notes concerning the affairs of the Priory were added. </provenance>
                  <provenance><persName role="fmo" key="person_37790832">Sir James Ware (1594–1666), Irish antiquary and historian</persName>, see ODNB.
                     No. IIII among ‘Libri Theologici’ in his 1648 Catalogue (published by
                     O’Sullivan, 1997). </provenance>
                  <provenance><persName role="fmo" key="person_8813457">Robert Ware (1639–1697)</persName>, younger son of James Ware: inherited after
                     his father’s death. </provenance>
                  <provenance><persName role="fmo" key="person_45071137">Henry Hyde (1638–1709), the second earl of Clarendon</persName>, see ODNB: bought
                     James Ware manuscripts from Robert Ware c. 1685. The psalter was deposited in
                     1687 in the public library at St Martin-in-the-Fields, established in 1684 by
                     Thomas Tenison, see ODNB, but withdrawn between 1692 and 1694 (O’Sullivan,
                     1997). Shelfmark ‘No I || JP’, followed by a cross in a circle (fol. 2v), found
                     in other Ware manuscripts and probably added at the time of their return to
                     Clarendon from St Martin’s (O’Sullivan, 1997, p. 75). No. 253 in his sale
                     catalogue compiled in 1709 by Christopher Bateman (Rawlinson’s annotated copy
                     is Bodleian Library, Mus. Bibl. III. 4o 13). </provenance>
                  <provenance><persName key="person_25708606" role="fmo">James Brydges (1674–1744), first duke of Chandos</persName>, see ODNB: bought
                     Clarendon’s library for £1,200 in 1709. </provenance>
                  <provenance><persName role="fmo" key="person_47563478" >Richard Rawlinson (1690–1755)</persName>, see ODNB: bought parts of Chandos’s
                     collection in 1747. </provenance>
                  <provenance>Booksellers’ (?) markings on fol. ii verso (‘2v Nn Ba. ZZ’ [2v meaning
                     2 vols. (?)], ‘3. 6’, ‘Bmn’) and fol. iii verso (‘11. 2. 8’, ‘vol: 1’). </provenance>
                  <acquisition when="1755">Bodleian Library: bequeathed by Rawlinson in 1755; accessioned in 1756. Known
                     as the Derby Psalter. Former shelfmark: ‘Auctarium Rawlinson BN 185’ (fol. i
                     verso) (see Summary catalogue, vol. 1, pp. xxxviii–xl). ‘527’ written in ink on
                     the upper pastedown. </acquisition>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>Summary description based on Elizabeth Solopova, <title>Latin
                              Liturgical Psalters in the Bodleian Library: A Select
                              Catalogue</title> (Oxford, 2013), pp. 186–95. Previously described in
                           the Summary Catalogue. <listBibl>
                              <bibl facs="aas0390.gif" type="SC">Summary Catalogue, Vol. 3, p.
                                 375</bibl>
                           </listBibl>
                        </source>
                     </recordHist>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <surrogates>
                     <bibl subtype="partial" type="digital-facsimile">
                        <ref
                           target="https://digital.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/objects/a1a8561a-8ed1-4642-b704-386b557ae057/">
                           <title>Digital Bodleian</title>
                        </ref>
                        <note>(34 images from 35mm slides)</note>
                     </bibl>
                  </surrogates>
                  <listBibl type="WRAPPER">
                     <listBibl type="PRINT">
                        <head>Select bibliography to 2004:</head>

                        <bibl>Gilbert, J. T., <title>Facsimiles of national manuscripts of
                              Ireland</title> (Dublin: Public Record Office of Ireland, 1882), part
                           IV, pp. lxxxiv–lxxxvi.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Macray, W. D., <title>Annals of the Bodleian Library, Oxford: with a
                              notice of the earlier library of the University, 2nd edn.</title>
                           (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1890; repr. Bodleian Library, 1984), pp. 244,
                           441.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Frere, no. 169.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Summary catalogue, vol. 3, no. 14902.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Millar, E. G., ‘The Egerton Genesis and the M. R. James
                              Memorial MS’, <title>Archaeologica</title> 87 (1938), pp. 1–5.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Pächt, O., <title>‘A Giottesque episode in English medieval art’,
                              JWCI</title> 6 (1943), pp. 51–70.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Wormald, F., ‘The Fitzwarin Psalter and its allies’, <title>JWCI</title> VI
                              (1943), 71–9, at p. 78; reprinted in J. J. G. Alexander, T. J. Brown
                              and J. Gibbs (eds.), <title>Francis Wormald: collected writings</title>
                           (London; New York: H. Miller in conjunction with OUP; 1984), vol. 2,
                           Studies in English and Continental art of the later Middle Ages, pp.
                           88–102.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Hand, G. I., ‘The psalter of Christ Church, Dublin’,
                              <title>Reportorium novum</title> 1 (1956), pp. 311–22.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Hawkes, W., ‘The liturgy in Dublin, 1200–1500: manuscript
                              sources’, <title>Reportorium Novum</title> 2 (1958), pp. 33–67, at pp.
                           54–7.</bibl>
                        <bibl>S. J. P. van Dijk, <title>Latin Liturgical Manuscripts in the Bodleian
                           Library, Oxford, vol. 2: Office Books</title> (typescript, 1957),
                           <citedRange unit="page" from="126" to="126">p. 126</citedRange>
                        </bibl>
                        <bibl>Pfaff (1970), p. 27 fn. 5.</bibl>
                        <bibl> Pächt and Alexander (1966–73), vol. 3, no. 653, pl. LXVII.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Alexander, J. J. G. and Kauffmann, C. M., <title>English illuminated
                              manuscripts 700–1500</title> (Brussels: Bibliothèque Royale Albert
                           Ier, 1973), no. 68, pl. 33.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Pfaff, R. W., <title>Montague Rhodes James</title> (London: Scolar
                           Press, 1980), p. 309 n. 62.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Marks, R. and Morgan, N., <title>The golden age of English manuscript
                              painting, 1200–1500 (London: Chatto &amp; Windus, 1981), pp. 21–2 and
                              fig. XIV</title> (fol. 68v).</bibl>
                        <bibl>Dennison, L., ‘The Fitzwarin Psalter and its allies: a
                              reappraisal’ in W. M. Ormrod (ed.), <title>England in the fourteenth century:
                              proceedings of the 1985 Harlaxton Symposium</title> (Woodbridge,
                           Suffolk; Dover, NH: Boydell, 1986), pp. 42–66, at p. 44 n. 10.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Sandler (1986), vol. 1, pp. 34, 49; vol. 2, pp. 134, 141, 143, 164,
                           166 and no. 128.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Alexander and Binski (1987), cited at no. 685.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Avril and Stirnemann (1987), p. 162.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Scott, K. L., ‘Caveat lector: ownership and standardization in
                              the illustration of fifteenth-century English manuscripts’, <title>English
                              manuscript studies 1100–1700</title> 1 (1989), pp. 19–63, at p.
                           59.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Tashjian, G. R., Tashjian, D. R. and Enright, B. J., <title>Richard
                              Rawlinson: a tercentenary memorial</title> (Kalamazoo: New Issues
                           Press, Western Michigan University, 1990), pp. 114–15.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Mezger, W., <title>Narrenidee und Fastnachtsbrauch: Studien zum
                              Fortleben des Mittelalters in der europäischen Festkultur, Konstanzer
                              Bibliothek</title> 15 (Constance: Universitätsverlag Konstanz, 1991),
                           p. 231 Abb. 122.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Lucy, F. S., ‘The image of the book-owner in the fourteenth
                              century: three cases of self-definition’ in N. Rogers (ed.), <title>England
                              in the fourteenth century: proceedings of the 1991 Harlaxton
                              Symposium</title> (Stamford: Paul Watkins, 1993), pp. 58–80, figs.
                           51–64, at p. x, fig. 56.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Camille, M.,‘The book as flesh and fetish in Richard de Bury’s
                              Philobiblon’ in D. W. Frese and K. O’Brien O’Keeffe (eds.),  <title>The book
                              and the body</title> (Notre Dame, IN; London: University of Notre Dame
                           Press, 1997), pp. 34–77, at pp. 56, 71.</bibl>
                        <bibl>McDonnell, J., <title>Five hundred years of the art of the book in
                              Ireland: 1500 to the present</title> [accompanying book for the Exhibition at
                              the National Gallery of Ireland, Dublin, 22 May–27 July 1997]
                           (Dublin and London: National Gallery of Ireland in association with
                           Merrell Holberton, 1997), pp. 8–9.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Sandler, L. F., ‘The Wilton Diptych and images of devotion in
                              illuminated manuscripts’ in D. Gordon, L. Monnas and C. Elam (eds.),
                              <title>The regal image of Richard II and the Wilton Diptych</title> (London:
                           H. Miller, 1997), pp. 137–54, at pp. 137, 318 n. 2; fig. 75.</bibl>
                        <bibl>O’Sullivan, W., ‘A finding list of Sir James Ware’s manuscripts’,
                           <title>Proceedings of the Royal Irish Academy, Section C, Archaeology, Celtic
                           Studies, History, Linguistics, Literature</title>, vol. 97, no. 2 (1997), pp. 69–99.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Dennison, L., ‘Monastic or secular? The artist of the Ramsey
                              Psalter, now at Holkham Hall, Norfolk’ in B. Thompson (ed.),
                              <title>Monasteries and society in medieval Britain: proceedings of the 1994
                              Harlaxton Symposium</title> (Stamford: Paul Watkins, 1999), pp.
                           223–61, passim.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Kerby-Fulton, K. and Despres, D. L., <title>Iconography and the
                              professional reader: the politics of book production in the Douce
                              Piers Plowman, Medieval Cultures</title> 15 (London and Minneapolis:
                           University of Minnesota Press, 1999), pp. 99, 101, 234 n. 36.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Buckley, A.,‘Music and musicians in medieval Irish society’,
                               <title>Early Music</title> 28 (2000), pp. 165–90, at p. 187 no. 12.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Dennison, L., ‘The suggested origin and initial destination of
                              London, British Library, Additional MS 44949, the M. R. James Memorial
                              Psalter’ in L. Dennison (ed.), <title>The legacy of M. R. James: papers from
                              the 1995 Cambridge Symposium</title> (Donington, Lincs.: Shaun Tyas,
                           2001), pp. 77–98, at pp. 83–4, 92–4, pls. 22, 26.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Joslin, M. C. and Joslin Watson, C. C., <title>The Egerton
                              Genesis</title> (London: British Library; Toronto: University of
                           Toronto Press, 2001), pp. 2, 5, 138, 176, 189, 191, 198, 203, 230, 231–5,
                           236, 237, 239, 249.</bibl>
                        <bibl> Baschet, J., ‘Pourquoi élaborer des bases de données
                              d’images?’ in A. Bolvig and P. Lindley (eds.), <title>History and images:
                              towards a new iconology</title>, Medieval Texts and Cultures of Northern
                              Europe 5 (Turnhout: Brepols, 2003), pp. 59–106, at pp. 92 and n. 45,
                              93, fig. 5 (fol. 97r detail).</bibl>
                        <bibl>Büttner, F. O., ‘Der illuminierte Psalter im Western’ in
                              Büttner (2004), pp. 1–135, at pp. 70 n. 34, 74 n. 48.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Refaussé, R., ‘Administration and rubrication: the Christ
                              Church psalter in context’, <title>Irish Arts Review</title> (2004), pp.
                           100–103, figs. 1–8.</bibl>
                      
                     </listBibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2024-05">Encode full description from Solopova catalogue.</change>
         <change when="2022-04-04">Add binding information from Summary Catalogue.</change>
         <change when="2019-10-31" xml:id="MMM">
            <persName>Toby Burrows/Mapping Manuscript Migrations</persName>Provenance and
            acquisition information added using <ref
               target="https://github.com/mapping-manuscript-migrations/oxford-tei-updates/blob/master/update_oxford_prov.rb"
               >https://github.com/mapping-manuscript-migrations/oxford-tei-updates/blob/master/update_oxford_prov.rb</ref>
            in collaboration with the <ref target="http://mappingmanuscriptmigrations.org/">Mapping
               Manuscript Migrations</ref> project.</change>
         <change when="2017-07-01">First online publication.</change>
         <change when="2017-05-25">
            <persName>James Cummings</persName> Up-converted the markup using <ref
               target="https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl"
               >https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl</ref>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
