<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/msDesc/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/msDesc/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="manuscript_14225">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>All Souls College MS. 26</title>
            <title type="collection">All Souls College MSS.</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp when="1997">Cataloguer</resp>
               <persName>Andrew G. Watson</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp when="2024">Encoding</resp>
               <persName>Morgan Wilkinson</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </publisher>
            <idno type="msID">All_Souls_College_MS_26</idno>
            <idno type="collection">All Souls College</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:lang="en" xml:id="All_Souls_College_MS_26">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <repository>All Souls College</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">All Souls College MS. 26</idno>
                  <!--ARKS to be added-->
               </msIdentifier>
               <head><hi rend="italic">Tract on the Assumption of the Blessed Virgin</hi>, in Middle English</head>
               <msContents>
                  <textLang mainLang="enm">Middle English</textLang>
                  <!--check-->
                  <msItem n="1" xml:id="All_Souls_College_MS_26-item-1">
                     <rubric>Here begynneth þe tretyse hough our glorious lady virgyn mary passed out of þis mortal lyfe. þat is to say out of þis wrecched world and was assumpt' unto þe blysse of heuen: Drawen out of hebrew in to greke by þe priour of S. John' of þe Rodys: and translated out of greke in to laten by þe subpriour of S. John': and out laten in to englyssh by Ro: Sukare þe yere of grace: 1485: In Westnynstre<locus from="1r" to="1r">fol. 1<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></locus></rubric>
                     <incipit type="preamble">Be it knowe to euery cristen man or woman whatsoeuer he be. of what condicion. state or dignite clerke or layman or woman. beynge in cristen byleue:<locus from="1r" to="1r">fol. 1<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></locus></incipit>
                     <explicit type="preamble">to euerlastynge blisse þe whych shal lest withouten ende. etc.<locus from="1r" to="1r">fol. 1<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></locus></explicit>
                     <incipit type="text">In those dayes and tyme þat our lord ihesu crist shuld suffre passion for al mankynd <locus from="1r" to="1r">fol. 1<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></locus></incipit>
                     <explicit type="text">To þe whych bryng us crist ihesus: whych on þe crosse deyed for us: Amen <locus from="5r" to="5r">fol. 5<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></locus></explicit>
                     <title key="work_5510">Tract on the Assumption of the Blessed Virgin</title>
                     <note>
                        <p>The text is based on the <bibl>Ps.-Joseph of Arimathea, <title>Transitus beate virginis Mariae, Bibliotheca hagiographica Latina: Novum supplementum</title> (Brussels, 1986), no. 5348</bibl>, pr. by <bibl>C. Tischendorf, <title>Apocalypses Apocrypha</title> (Leipzig, 1886), 113-23</bibl> and by <bibl>A. de Santos Otero, <title>Los Evangelios apocrifos</title>, 2nd edn. (Madrid, 1962), 647-59.</bibl></p>
                        <p>The order and proportions of our narrative closely follow those of the Latin text but the English is augmented by additional details and episodes. No other copy is known. Although the translator '<persName key="person_4513" role="trl">Ro: Sukar</persName>' remains unidentified, the rest of the rubric may not be entirely fictitious for although the claim to have used Hebrew source-material may be taken with a grain of salt since even in the 16th century 'Hebrew' was often a magniloquent description of Old Testament scripture in Latin translation (I am indebted to Professor Raphael Loewe for this observation), the <persName key="person_4512" role="ant">Ps.-Joseph of Arimathea</persName> source probably explains it. 'St John of the Rhodes' was a designation for the whole <orgName key="org_146774583">Order of St John of Jerusalem</orgName>, known to (for example) John Stow (see <bibl>John Stow, <title>A Survey of London</title>, ed. C. L. Kingsford, 2 vols. (Oxford, 1908), ii. 84, 143)</bibl>. In an unsuccessful search for Sukar (Seagar, Sygar, etc.), all Westminster Abbey Court Rolls from 1486-1505 were examined and also small samples of Almoner's Accounts (namely 1484-5, 1486-7) and Sacrist's Accounts (namely 1484-5 and 1486-7). <bibl>IMEP 2-3</bibl>.</p>
                     </note>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <p>
                     <secFol>þis wrecched</secFol>
                  </p>
                  <p><!--todo: general comment on structure if necessary--></p>
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="perg">
                        <support>
                             <p>Written on five paper leaves, marked by water-stains, preceded by two modern paper flyleaves and followed by 30 blank supply leaves and two modern paper flyleaves.  Watermark 
                           <watermark>a unicorn</watermark>, not identifiable in <bibl>Piccard, <title>Wasserzeichen Fabeltiere</title></bibl>, but it is of the same, Italian, type as Briquet no. 9972 (Venice, 1479). It is also found in a Glasgow University manuscript written by the same scribe (see Script below), but it is not the type of unicorn found in <bibl>William Caxton's 1477 edition of Raoul le Fevre's <title>Jason</title> (STC 15375)</bibl> as is suggested by an excerpt from an old sale catalogue cited in the catalogue of the Glasgow collection.</p>
                        </support>
                        <extent>
                           <measure type="leaf">5 leaves, followed by 30 blank supply leaves.</measure>
                           <dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                              <height quantity="280">280</height>
                              <width quantity="205">205</width>
                           </dimensions>
                        </extent>
                        <foliation>Numbered in modern pencil.</foliation>
                        <collation>I<hi rend="superscript">6</hi> (wants 6, blank?)</collation>
                        <condition>Water-stains</condition>
                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout columns="1" ruledLines="41 42">
                           Written in one column, <dimensions type="ruled" unit="mm">
                                <height max="215" min="205">205-15</height><width quantity="140">140</width></dimensions>mm, 41-2 lines. <seg type="pricking">Traces of pricking remain in outer margins</seg>. <seg type="ruling">Ruled in crayon. Before writing, the pages were fully ruled, but ruling on written areas was rubbed out; only <locus from="5r" to="5v">the lower half of fol. 5r and all of fol. 5v</locus> remain fully ruled.</seg></layout>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc>
                     <handNote script="hybrida">An archaizing type of late-medieval English hybrida. The f is apparently derived from the Anglo-Saxon form. Punctuation is by low point, comma, and colon. The same scribe wrote <bibl>Glasgow University Library, MS Hunter V.3.8 (410), William Caxton's <title>Life of Jason</title></bibl>, in a very similar though slightly smaller format and with identical decoration.</handNote>
                  </handDesc>
                  <decoDesc>
                     <decoNote type="initial">Eight ten/thirteen-line interlace initials drawn in ink and coloured buff, green, or pink. For similar 
                        initials elsewhere see Script above.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="rubrication">Rubric, red paraphs and stroking. The rubric is twice as long as the four lines left for it and overflows into the outer margin. <bibl>Alexander and Temple, no. 625.</bibl></decoNote>
                  </decoDesc>
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <binding notBefore="1700" notAfter="1800">
                        <p>Eighteenth-century <material>calf</material> with large All Souls arms stamped in gold on front cover and a double gold-stamped fillet round the edges.</p>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notBefore="1485">After 1484</origDate>
                     <origPlace>
                        <country key="place_7002445">England</country>
                     </origPlace>
                  </origin>
                  <provenance><locus from="1r" to="1r">Fol. 1</locus>, <quote><persName key="person_72280327" role="fmo">Nar. Luttrell</persName> His Book <date when="1682">1682</date></quote>: identifiable as no. 73 sold for 3s., in the sale of <persName key="person_9700936" role="fmo">Richard Smith</persName>'s books in that year: see under MS 17 above. <quote>Treatise of ye Assumption of the Virgin Mary into Heaven by R. Sukar. 1485</quote> in Luttrell's hand.</provenance>
                  <acquisition>All Souls library identifications, on which see Introduction, are, on the <locus from="pastedown" to="pastedown">front pastedown</locus>, <quote>vv.3.12</quote> (deleted), <quote>MS. 26.</quote>, <quote>L.R. 1.d.15 (ult)</quote> (pencil); <locus from="1r" to="1r">fol. 1<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></locus>, <quote>13 .. &lt;.&gt;</quote> (pencil), <quote>26</quote>.</acquisition>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>Andrew G. Watson, <title>A Descriptive
                                                  Catalogue of the Medieval Manuscripts of All Souls
                                                  College Oxford</title> (Oxford, 1997)</source>
                     </recordHist>
                     <availability>
                        <p>For enquiries relating to this manuscript please
                                                  contact
                                                  <email>library@all-souls.ox.ac.uk</email>.</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <surrogates>
                     <bibl type="digital-facsimile" subtype="full">
                        <ref target="https://library.asc.ox.ac.uk/manuscripts/ms_27.php">
                           <title>The Library, All Souls College</title></ref>
                        <note>(full digital facsimile)</note>
                     </bibl>
                  </surrogates>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2024">First online publication.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p><!--body provided for validation and future transcription--></p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
