<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/msDesc/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/msDesc/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="manuscript_14239">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>All Souls College MS. 40</title>
            <title type="collection">All Souls College MSS.</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp when="1997">Cataloguer</resp>
               <persName>Andrew G. Watson</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp when="2025">Encoding</resp>
               <persName>Barbora Sojkova</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </publisher>
            <idno type="msID">All_Souls_College_MS_40</idno>
            <idno type="collection">All Souls College</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:lang="en" xml:id="All_Souls_College_MS_40">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <repository>All Souls College</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">All Souls College MS. 40</idno>
                  <!--ARKS to be added-->
                  <altIdentifier type="shelfmark">
                     <idno>LR.6.a.11</idno>
                  </altIdentifier> 
               </msIdentifier>
               <head>Roger Alban (attrib.), <hi rend="italic">Genealogy of the Kings of England</hi>; Justinian, <hi rend="italic">Infortiatum</hi> (frag.)</head>
               <physDesc>
                  <p>
                     <secFol>bilis stature</secFol>
                  </p>
                  <p><!--todo: general comment on structure if necessary--></p>
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="perg">
                        <support>Written on 11 leaves of average-quality membrane, now rather dirty, preceded by a membrane flyleaf originally a bifolium in another manuscript.
                           <p>Foreleaf: fol. i<hi rend="superscript">rv</hi>, text, = *A.</p>
                        </support>
                        <extent>
                           <measure type="leaf">11 leaves</measure>
                           <dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                              <height>475</height>
                              <width>330</width>
                           </dimensions>
                        </extent>
                        <foliation>Numbered in modern pencil.</foliation>
                        <collation>Collation: 1<hi rend="superscript">12</hi> (wants 1). No quire numbers or signatures.</collation>
                      <!--  <condition><!-\-todo-\-></condition>-->
                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout writtenLines="80">Written in two/four columns of variable width, plus narrower marginal columns for popes and emperors, c.375 mm in height. Up to c.80 lines. 
                           Pricked for vertical ruling and ruled in crayon. Folded HSOS.</layout>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <binding notAfter="1625">
                        <p>Stitched into a polished membrane cover, gold-stamped, and with gold fillets (London?, s. xvii<hi rend="superscript">in</hi>).</p>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
                         <history>
                     <origin>
                        <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notBefore="1455" notAfter="1455">1455</origDate>
                        <origPlace>
                           <placeName key="place_7011781">London</placeName>? <country key="place_7002445">England</country>
                        </origPlace>
                     </origin>
                            <provenance>Probably produced, and later given a cover, in London. On the pastedown in <persName key="person_72280327">Narcissus Luttrell's</persName> hand (see below) is <q>Series Genealogica Regum Angliae deducta ab Adamo ad Henricum VI</q>, 
                               which identifies the manuscript with the description of the first of the series of Manuscripts of Heraldry, &amp;c. in Folio in the <persName key="person_88788847">Burghley (Cecil)</persName> sale catalogue of <date>21 November 1687</date> (for which see under <idno type="shelfmark">MS 33</idno> above), 91. 
                               On the covers are Burghley's gold-stamped initials <q>WC.</q> (William Cecil) and on the front cover two titles, <q>12th booke genealogies of Kinges</q> (<date>s. xvi/xvii</date>) and <q>Genealogic of K: Henry. 6<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. from Adam</q> (<date>s. xviii<hi rend="superscript">2</hi></date>). 
                               The first may be a Burghley title; the second is probably a title written by one of Luttrell's descendants. Inside the front cover is <q>Nar. Luttrell: 1687</q>, who acquired other manuscripts from the unidentified <q>Williams</q> who had acquired it at the Burghley sale. 
                               On the College's acquisition of this and other manuscripts from Luttrell's descendants see under <idno type="shelfmark">MS 17</idno> above. Also on the cover is <q>There is a copy of this pedigree w<hi rend="superscript">ch</hi> I found In Winchester Colledge Library July 1755. but Slovenly Kept &amp; not so well embellished as this is.</q> 
                               This note is a reference to <orgName key="org_150825867">Winchester College</orgName>, <idno type="shelfmark">MS 13B</idno> and is in the hand that wrote the second title on the cover.
                               <p>All Souls library identifications, on which see Introduction, are inside the front cover: <q type="pressmark">vv.1 infra 7</q> (deleted), <q type="pressmark">87</q> (pencil), <q type="pressmark"><hi rend="underline">M.S.40.</hi></q>, <q type="pressmark">L.R. 6 a.l1</q></p></provenance>
                  </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>Andrew G. Watson, <title>A Descriptive
                                                  Catalogue of the Medieval Manuscripts of All Souls
                                                  College Oxford</title> (Oxford, 1997)</source>
                     </recordHist>
                     <availability>
                        <p>For enquiries relating to this manuscript please
                                                  contact
                                                  <email>library@all-souls.ox.ac.uk</email>.</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
               </additional>
               <msPart xml:id="All_Souls_College_MS_40-part1">
                  <msIdentifier>
                     <altIdentifier>
                        <idno>All Souls College MS. 40, part *A</idno>
                     </altIdentifier>
                  </msIdentifier>
                  <msContents>
                     <textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>
                     <msItem n="1" xml:id="All_Souls_College_MS_40-part1-item1">
                 
                        <incipit><locus from="ivl">Fol. i<hi rend="superscript">vl</hi>.</locus>
                           || &lt;deduxerit cauere debeat&gt; 
                        </incipit>
                        <explicit>
                           <locus from="ivu">Fol. i<hi rend="superscript">vu</hi>.</locus>
                           in auditorio de huius [<hi rend="italic">sic: recte</hi> huiusmodi] spe ||
                        </explicit>
             
                        <author key="person_88881722">Justinian</author>
                        <title key="work_181447327">Infortiatum</title>
                           
                           <note>XXXV-ii. 95, 2 to XXXVI-i. 22, with the gloss of <persName key="person_102317020">Accursius</persName>, with a gap from XXXV—iii. 3, 6 to XXXVI—i. 16, 13.</note>
                     
                        <listBibl>
                           <bibl>Ed. Mommsen, <hi rend="italic">CIC</hi> 356-634, at 560-7.</bibl>
                           <bibl>For the gloss, early editions, and sources on <persName key="person_102317020">Accursius</persName> see MS 49, item 4 below.</bibl>
                        </listBibl>
                     </msItem>
                  </msContents>
                  <physDesc>
                     <objectDesc form="codex">
                        <supportDesc material="perg">
                           <support>One sheet containing four pages, with its top in the gutter. The correct order of the pages is fol. i<hi rend="superscript">vl</hi>, fol. i<hi rend="superscript">rl</hi>, 
                              fol. i<hi rend="superscript">ru</hi>, fol. i<hi rend="superscript">vu</hi> (<q>vl</q> indicating the lower page of the verso of the leaf as now bound, <q>ru</q> the upper page of the recto, etc.). </support>
                           <extent>
                              <measure type="leaf">11 leaves</measure>
                              The overall size of the sheet is <dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm"><height>350</height><width>230</width></dimensions>(top margin extends into the sewing but lower margin is trimmed).
                           </extent>
                           <condition>Much of the text is rubbed, that on fols. i<hi rend="superscript">ru</hi> and i<hi rend="superscript">vl</hi> being particularly badly affected. 
                              For script and decoration see below.</condition>
                        </supportDesc>
                        <layoutDesc>
                           <layout columns="2" writtenLines="47">In two columns of text <dimensions type="written" unit="mm"><height>230</height><width>55</width></dimensions>
                              47 lines, with gloss filling the margins on all four sides.</layout>
                        </layoutDesc>
                     </objectDesc>
                     <handDesc>
                        <handNote script="textualisNorthern">Gothic rotunda bookhand for the text, a glossing script for the gloss (both <date>s. xiii</date>), perhaps southern French.</handNote>
                     </handDesc>
                     <decoDesc>
                        <decoNote type="initial">Red, and dark blue initials, some flourished, dark blue and red paraphs, rubrics.</decoNote>
                     </decoDesc>
                  </physDesc>
                  </msPart> 
               
               <msPart xml:id="All_Souls_College_MS_40-part2">
                  <msIdentifier>
                     <altIdentifier>
                        <idno>All Souls College MS. 40, part B</idno>
                     </altIdentifier>
                  </msIdentifier>
                  <msContents>
                     <textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>
                     <msItem n="1" xml:id="All_Souls_College_MS_40-part2-item1">
                      
                        <incipit>
                           <locus from="1r">Fol. 1<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>.</locus>
                           [Prologue] Considerans chronicorum pro-lixitatem nec non et difficultatem scolaris... ad henricum sextum originaliter finem perduxi. 
                        </incipit>
                        <incipit>
                           [Text] Adam in agro damascenus formatus et in paradisus vnde quatuor flumina oriuntur translatus.
                        </incipit>
                        <explicit>
                           <locus from="11r">Fol. 11<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>.</locus>
                           de qua genuit edwardum principem qui natus erat in festo translacionis sancti edwardi regis et confessoris anno domini .m<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>. cccc<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>. liij<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>.</explicit>
                        <author key="person_15175690">Roger Alban (attrib.)</author>
                        <title key="work_4423">Genealogy of the Kings of England, Adam to Henry VI.</title>
                        <listBibl>
                           <bibl>Unprinted. One of several known copies of the E text of these genealogies, as classified by A. C. de la Mare, <title rend="italic">Catalogue of the Collection of Medieval Manuscripts Bequeathed to the Bodleian Library Oxford by James P. R. Lyell</title> (Oxford, 1971), 82-5, 
                              but differing from some copies by being in codex and not roll form. </bibl>
                        </listBibl>
                        <note>On the extreme left is the genealogy from Adam to Christ and the succession of popes to Calixtus in (elected 1455, d. 1458) and on the extreme right is the successions of consuls and emperors of Rome and of the Holy Roman Emperors to Albert II (d. 1439).</note>
                     </msItem>
                  </msContents>
                  <physDesc>
                     <objectDesc form="codex">
                        <supportDesc material="perg">
                           <!--<support><!-\-todo-\-></support>
                           <extent><!-\-todo-\-></extent>-->
                        </supportDesc>
                        <!--<layoutDesc>
                           <layout><!-\-todo-\-></layout>
                        </layoutDesc>-->
                     </objectDesc>
                     <handDesc>
                        <handNote>Gothic rotunda bookhand, by a copyist to whom over fifty manuscripts are ascribed in an unpublished list by Jeremy Griffiths, Oxford, who suggests that the production of chronicles of this kind on such a scale would leave the scribe little time to copy anything else. He probably worked in London.</handNote>
                     </handDesc>
                     <decoDesc>
                        <decoNote type="miniature">The text begins with an illuminated C and half-border, and a roundel of Adam, Eve, and the serpent 55 mm in diameter within a thin blue band, then a 5 mm gold band, then a 4mm red band outermost. 
                           Sovereigns' names are in circles 20 mm in diameter surrounded by a dull red or blue band, 5 mm wide with a golden crown on the top. Non-regnant descendants are in small ink circles without a surrounding coloured band.</decoNote>
                           <decoNote type="initial">In the text are one-line gold initials, flourished. <bibl>Alexander and Temple, no. 602 (pl. xxxv no. 602 repr. Adam and Eve roundel on fol. i<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>, slightly reduced).</bibl> 
                              For a fuller description see <bibl>Scott, Later Gothic MSS, no. 80,</bibl> who notes that border decoration is similar in style to manuscripts produced in East Anglia, probably Suffolk, and that the motif of a snail shell or a bird pecking a snail shell is found in manuscripts from the diocese of Norwich and Bury St Edmunds. 
                              The work of the artist of the Adam and Eve roundel (or in some cases possibly an associate) is found in a number of chronicles of the 'Considerans' type.</decoNote>
                     </decoDesc>
                  </physDesc>
                  
               </msPart>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2025">First online publication.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p><!--body provided for validation and future transcription--></p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
