<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/msDesc/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/msDesc/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="manuscript_14229">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>All Souls College MS. 30</title>
            <title type="collection">All Souls College MSS.</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp when="1997">Cataloguer</resp>
               <persName>Andrew G. Watson</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp when="2024">Encoding</resp>
               <persName>Barbora Sojkova</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </publisher>
            <idno type="msID">All_Souls_College_MS_30</idno>
            <idno type="collection">All Souls College</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:lang="en" xml:id="All_Souls_College_MS_30">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <repository>All Souls College</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">All Souls College MS. 30</idno>
                  <!--ARKS to be added-->
                  <altIdentifier type="shelfmark">
                     <idno>LR.6.a.8</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
                  
               </msIdentifier>
               
               <head>Bernard of Clairvaux, <hi rend="italic">Sermones in Cantica Canticorum</hi> 24-86; etc.</head>
               <msContents>
                  <textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>
                 
                  <msItem n="1" xml:id="All_Souls_College_MS_30-item-1">
                     <rubric>
                        <locus from="1r">Fol. 1<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>.</locus>
                        [B]eati bernardi abbatis clareuallis in canticis canticorum sermo xx<hi rend="superscript">us</hi> quintus. Incipit.</rubric>
                     
                     <incipit>
                        Hoc demum tercio fratres reditum ab urbe nostrum.
                     </incipit>
                     
                     <explicit>
                        <locus from="102va">Fol. 102<hi rend="superscript">va</hi>.</locus>
                        Item ad omnes electos. ut filii lucis inquit ambulate.
                     </explicit>
                     
                     <finalRubric>
                        Explicit Sermo. lxxxvij<hi rend="superscript">us</hi>. qui ultimus sancti bernardi. abbatis super cantica canticorum.
                     </finalRubric>
                     
                     <author key="person_59875293">Bernard</author>
                     <title key="work_1049">Sermones XXIV-LXXXVI</title>
                     
                     <listBibl>
                        <bibl><title>Sancti Bernardi opera</title>, ed. J. Leclerq, C. H. Talbot, and H. M. Rochais (8 vols., Rome, 1957-77).</bibl>
                     </listBibl>
                     
                     <note>The A recension, preserved only in English manuscripts (for the criteria for which see ibid. i, pp. xvi—xix). 
                        This is the second volume of a two-volume set with a single medieval foliation and every sermon carries a number one digit higher than the standard numbering, i.e. 25—87 instead of 24-86. 
                        Because of the loss of leaves after fols. 78 and 86 there are two gaps in the text: from fol. 78<hi rend="superscript">v</hi> <q>declinet in ira a ser</q> (sermo 70, edn. ii. 213/13) to fol. 79<hi rend="superscript">v</hi> <q>serit. Non quia uel tunc</q> (sermo 71, edn. ii. 218/4) and from fol. 86<hi rend="superscript">v</hi> <q>eam paternis aspectibus presentari</q> (sermo 75, edn. ii. 252/10) to fol. 87<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> <q>priusquam mundus fieret</q> (sermo 76, edn. ii. 256/23).
                     </note>
                     </msItem>
                  
                  <msItem n="2" xml:id="All_Souls_College_MS_30-item-2">
                     <rubric>
                        <locus from="102vb">Fol. 102<hi rend="superscript">vb</hi>.</locus>
                        Incipiunt meditationes Sancti bernardi.
                     </rubric>
                     
                     <incipit>
                        Multi multa sciunt et seipsos nesciunt 
                     </incipit>
                     
                     <explicit>
                        <locus from="105v">Fol. 105<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>.</locus>
                        Heri in ore leonis. hodie in manum mediatoris. heri in parta inferi. hodie in deliciis paradisi.
                     </explicit>
                    
                     <author key="person_306415749">Ps.-Bernard</author>
                     <title key="work_3952">De cognitione humani conditionis</title>
                     <listBibl>
                        <bibl>Pr. PL 184. 485-508.</bibl>
                     </listBibl>
                     <note>Our text ends at edn. col. 508 / 6, thirteen lines short of the end of the printed text. Authorship is also attributed to <persName key="person_9865788" role="att">Hugo de S. Victore</persName> as I. iv of his <title key="work_2145">De anima</title>
                        (see <bibl>F. Cavallera, in <title rend="italic">Dict. de spiritualité</title>, i. 1500</bibl>) and to <persName key="person_288027459" role="att">Guil. Tornacensis</persName> (see <bibl>Bloomfield, V. &amp; V., no. 3126,</bibl> q.v. also for the many manuscripts, not including this). 
                        It is added here in different hands from item 1 and with a rubric of a different colour, <date>s. xiii</date>.</note>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <p>
                     <secFol>differentes</secFol>
                  </p>
                  <!--<p><!-\-todo: general comment on structure if necessary-\-></p>-->
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="perg">
                        <support> Written on 105 membrane leaves preceded by one incunable leaf and followed by another (fols. i, I) (see Binding below) and preceded by a coarse membrane leaf of half the normal width (fol. ii), apparently half of a former pastedown: 
                           its verso shows signs of having been stuck to wood and at the top left of the recto, i.e. in the inner margin, is a green stain and a hole corresponding to the position of a chain-staple on the binding. 
                           The membrane of the book itself is of average quality with some blemishes and repairs before writing. Hair sides and flesh sides are difficult to distinguish, but the pattern of folding seems to vary. 
                           <p>Fore- and endleaves: fol. i, printed flyleaf; fol. ii<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>, pen-trials (pious phrases); fol. ii<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>, blank; fol. I, printed flyleaf.
                           </p>
                        </support>
                        <extent>
                           <measure type="leaf">105 leaves</measure>
                           <dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                              <height>412</height>
                              <width>280</width>
                           </dimensions>
                        </extent>
                        <foliation>Foliated to 105 in ink (<date>s. xviii</date>), rest of foliation is of s. <date>s. xx</date>. 
                           Medieval foliation, in arabic figures, in the same hand and position (on versos below first column) as in <idno type="shelfmark">MS 13</idno> (see our Pls. 1 and 2); 
                           the figures begin at 71 and continue to 177 on fol. 104<hi rend="superscript">v</hi> omitting 110 and losing 150 and 159 through the excision of leaves.</foliation>
                        <collation> 1-9<hi rend="superscript">8</hi> 10<hi rend="superscript">8</hi> (wants 8) 11<hi rend="superscript">8</hi> (wants 8) 12-13<hi rend="superscript">8</hi> 14<hi rend="superscript">4</hi> (wants 4). 
                           Quire numbers are large black roman figures, similar to but not identical with those in <idno type="shelfmark">MS 13</idno>, sometimes preceded and followed by one or two points. Quires 9, 10, and 11 have no numbers, the last two because the final leaf of the quire has been excised.
                           <catchwords>The only catchwords, written by the scribe, are on fol. 72<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>, on the quire (9) that lacks a quire signature, and, not written by the scribe, on fol. 94<hi rend="superscript">v</hi> (quire 12).</catchwords>
                           For a comparison of some features of this volume and <idno type="shelfmark">MS 13</idno> see our Pl. 2.
                        </collation>
                       
                        <!--<condition><!-\-todo-\-></condition>-->
                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout columns="2" writtenLines="60">
                           Written in two columns, each <dimensions type="written" unit="mm">
                           <height n="300">300</height>
                           <width n="90">90</width>
                        </dimensions>
                           With 41 lines in item 1 and 55-60 in item *2. Pricked in outer and inner margins (in outer margins mostly trimmed off, and no prickings visible for fols. 103-5) and for vertical ruling. Item 1 ruled in crayon, item *2 in pencil. 
                        </layout>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  
                  <handDesc hands="2">
                     <handNote n="1" script="protogothic">Item 1 is in <term type="script">protogothic</term> bookhand turning into <term type="script">gothic</term> bookhand, by a scribe very similar to and perhaps identical with <persName key="person_4523" role="scr">scribe A</persName> of <idno type="shelfmark">MS 13</idno> (our Pl. 2a and for <idno type="shelfmark">MS 13</idno>  cf. Pl. 1).
                        In item 1 some corrections are written in margins with a <term><hi rend="italic">signe de renvoi</hi></term>. 
                        Where rewriting of the text caused text to overrun into the margin that bit was sometimes encircled in red. Punctuation is by <term type="punctuation">punctus elevatus</term>, <term type="punctuation">punctus interrogativus</term>, and <term type="punctuation">low point</term>.
                     </handNote>
                  
                     <handNote n="2" script="protogothic">Item *2 is also in a <term type="script">bookhand</term> but smaller, less careful than in item 1, with documentary elements such as a tendency to split the heads of ascenders and to have spurs on their left shafts; probably three scribes took part, alternating and writing about a column or stints of about twenty lines. 
                        They are best distinguished by the form of g used and by slight changes in the colour of the ink. All wrote above the top line. Punctuation is by <term type="punctuation">low point</term>.
                     </handNote>
                  </handDesc>
                  
                  <decoDesc>
                     <decoNote type="initial">Good arabesque initials, some and perhaps all of which are in the hand of the artist of <idno type="shelfmark">MS 13</idno>: cf. fol. 6<hi rend="superscript">v</hi> Q with <idno type="shelfmark">MS 13</idno>, fol. 31<hi rend="superscript">v</hi> Q; fol. 9<hi rend="superscript">v</hi> T with <idno type="shelfmark">MS 13</idno>, fol. 32<hi rend="superscript">v</hi> L; fol. 14 P with <idno type="shelfmark">MS 13</idno>, fol. 64 O; fol. 31 P with MS 13, fol. 107<hi rend="superscript">v</hi> C, etc.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="initial">The major initial on fol. 1<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> is seven-line with marginal extension.</decoNote> 
                     <decoNote type="initial">Other initials are four/six-line but many have long marginal extensions.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="lineFill">Infilling is as in <idno type="shelfmark">MS 13</idno> in red, green, or blue, and the artist shows a liking for tiny circles in green or blue, as in that manuscript.</decoNote> 
                     <decoNote type="other">This manuscript lacks the use of colourwash on initials as found occasionally in <idno type="shelfmark">MS 13</idno> but it shares with it red linefillers made of minim-like strokes. 
                     Guide letters for the artist are in inner margins but any that existed in outer margins have been trimmed off. 
                     Wording for the rubricator to follow survives only at the top of fol. 77<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>, mostly trimmed off, and at the bottom of fol. 99<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>, erased. <bibl>Alexander and Temple, no. 93.</bibl></decoNote>
                  </decoDesc>
                  
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <binding notAfter="1951">
                        <p>Resewn on four bands between projecting square-edged oak boards covered with white alum-tawed sheepskin. The spine is new (<date>s. xx</date>), with leather from the old binding set into modern leather, and on the back cover the leather is partly renewed. 
                           The construction of the original binding is not visible but two sets of four lacing-in holes are exposed and show that sewing is on single bands, probably on the original sewing stations. 
                           On both covers are holes from four corner-bosses and in the front cover is also a centre hole, all as in <idno type="shelfmark">MS 13</idno>, which came from the same source; but since the general style of the binding of <idno type="shelfmark">MS 13</idno> is typical All Souls binding, the bosses of <idno type="shelfmark">MS 30</idno> presumably dated from after the arrival of these manuscripts there. 
                           On the front cover are the remains of two straps, each held in place by three nails of the usual All Souls type. On the edge, between the remains of the straps, two rectangular recesses c. <dimensions type="other" unit="mm"><height n="20">20</height><width n="12">12</width></dimensions> have been chiselled out of the front board as though to accommodate earlier clasps or straps, but there are no corresponding features on the back board. 
                           At the top right of the front cover are signs of a chain-plate in position 6 and the same is visible on the back cover in position 1. 
                           On the back cover are also two metal catches for the straps, each held by two nails. In the back cover there are also two large nail holes, visible on the inside but filled on the outside. Rust from the nails or from whatever they held caused holes on fols. 104 and 105 and stains on fol. 103. 
                           his may be evidence of a chain-staple from a pre-All Souls binding. 
                           The printed leaves, at the top of the first of which is <q>126</q> and at the bottom of the second of which is <q>131</q> (<date>s. xv<hi rend="superscript">ex</hi></date>), are fols. 126 and 131 from a copy of the <title key="work_186102457"><hi rend="italic">Margarita poetica</hi></title> of <persName role="aut" key="person_22136923">Albrecht von Eyb</persName> of which other leaves are in MSS <idno type="shelfmark">2</idno>, <idno type="shelfmark">12</idno>, <idno type="shelfmark">13</idno>, <idno type="shelfmark">14</idno>14 , <idno type="shelfmark">79</idno>, and <idno type="shelfmark">dd.2.9</idno>: see <idno type="shelfmark">MS 12</idno> for details. 
                           On the front pastedown is <q>Repaired by <orgName key="org_125">Maltby May</orgName>, <date>1951</date></q>. Edges are yellowed and there is a fore-edge title.</p>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="1299" notBefore="1100">s. xii/xiii</origDate>
                     <origPlace>
                        <country key="place_7002445">England</country>
                     </origPlace>
                  </origin>
                  <provenance>The pre-All Souls history of the book is clearly identical with that of <idno type="shelfmark">MS 13</idno>, which shares with it a scribe, the style of decoration, the type of catchwords, the unusual way of numbering leaves, and the same tendency to put elaborately ornamented wavy lines as nota marks in the margins (see our Pl. 2b—d). 
                     The covers of both have had bosses, suggestive of northern rather than southern England and of ownership by a Cistercian house. 
                     Both came to the College by gift of <persName key="person_3315" role="fmo">Richard Andrew</persName>, first Warden (on whom see <bibl><hi rend="italic">BRUO</hi></bibl>, and <bibl>Walker, 'Andrew'</bibl>), in the time of the Founder (<bibl>Ker, <title rend="italic">All Souls</title>, List H, no. 54, with <q>Libri theologie cathenati</q></bibl>), 
                     in whose hand there are quite frequent marginalia (see our Pl. 28), as was suggested by <bibl>E. F. Jacob, <title rend="italic">Acta Congressus juridici internationalis</title> (Rome, 12-17 November 1934), ii. 477</bibl>, and can be confirmed by comparison with a good example of <persName key="person_23238044">Chichele</persName>'s hand in the All Souls manuscript now <bibl>Antwerp, Plantin-Moretus Museum, MS 12, fol. 12<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. No. 1409 (8) in <hi rend="italic">CMA</hi></bibl>. 
                     In the bottom margin of fol. 2<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> is <hi rend="italic">ex libris</hi> style i, <q>Liber Collegij animarum omnium fidelium defunctorum de Oxon.</q>
                     <p>All Souls library identifications, on which see Introduction, are, inside the front cover, bookplate no. 8 on which are <q type="pressmark">vv. 1. to</q> (deleted) and <q type="pressmark">MS 30</q> (figure added), and, on the pastedown, <q type="pressmark">L.R. 6.a.8</q> (pencil); 
                        on fol. 1<hi rend="superscript">v</hi> are <q type="pressmark">v.v.1.10</q>, <q type="pressmark">ww.2.5</q> (both deleted), <q type="pressmark">w&lt;.&gt;2&lt;.&gt;</q>, and <q type="pressmark">&lt;P...&gt;</q>; on fol. 1<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> <q type="pressmark">4..1</q> (pencil). 
                        At the top of fol. 1<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> is also the q-like symbol found in <idno type="shelfmark">MSS 12</idno> and <idno type="shelfmark">14</idno>.
                     </p>
                  </provenance>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>Andrew G. Watson, <title>A Descriptive
                                                  Catalogue of the Medieval Manuscripts of All Souls
                                                  College Oxford</title> (Oxford, 1997)</source>
                     </recordHist>
                     <availability>
                        <p>For enquiries relating to this manuscript please
                                                  contact
                                                  <email>library@all-souls.ox.ac.uk</email>.</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2024">First online publication.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p><!--body provided for validation and future transcription--></p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
