<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/msDesc/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/msDesc/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="manuscript_14245">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>All Souls College MS. 49</title>
            <title type="collection">All Souls College MSS.</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp when="1997">Cataloguer</resp>
               <persName>Andrew G. Watson</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp when="2023">Encoding</resp>
               <persName>Morgan Wilkinson</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </publisher>
            <idno type="msID">All_Souls_College_MS_49</idno>
            <idno type="collection">All Souls College</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:lang="en" xml:id="All_Souls_College_MS_49">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <repository>All Souls College</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">All Souls College MS. 49</idno>
                  <altIdentifier type="shelfmark">
                     <idno>LR.2.c.1</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
                  <!--ARKS to be added-->
               </msIdentifier>
               <head>Justinian, <hi rend="italic">Digestum vetus</hi> I-XXIV. 3, with the gloss of Accursius</head>
               <msContents>
                  <summary>
                     <p>Foreleaves: <locus from="ir" to="ir">fol. i<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></locus>, text, = <ref target="#All_Souls_College_MS_49-item-2">*2</ref>; <locus from="iv" to="iv">fol. i<hi rend="superscript">v</hi></locus>, blank; <locus from="iir" to="iir">fol. ii<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></locus>, text, = <ref target="#All_Souls_College_MS_49-item-3">*3</ref>; <locus>fol. ii<hi rend="superscript">v</hi></locus>, blank.</p>
                  <p>Main text and gloss (= <ref target="#All_Souls_College_MS_49-item-4">4</ref>) <locus from="1r" to="312v">fols. 1<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>-312<hi rend="superscript">v</hi></locus>.</p>
                  <p>Endleaves: <locus from="Ir" to="IVv">fols. I<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>-IV<hi rend="superscript">v</hi></locus>, text, = <ref target="#All_Souls_College_MS_49-item-5">*5</ref>.</p>
                  </summary>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                   <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="perg">
                        <support>Written on 312 pages of good-quality membrane prepared in the Italian manner. They are preceded by two membrane flyleaves (<locus from="ir" to="iiv">fols. i, ii</locus>), fol. i conjugate with the pastedown, fol. ii conjugate with a 60mm pastedown under the main pastedown, and followed by four membrane flyleaves (<locus from="Ir" to="IVv">fols. I-IV</locus>) of which fols. I and II are each conjugate with 35mm pastedowns, fol. III is sewn in and conjugate with its own 60mm stub, and fol. IV is the main pastedown, a single leaf.</support>
                        <extent>
                           <measure type="leaf" quantity="318">ii + 312 + IV</measure>
                        </extent>
                     </supportDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <binding notBefore="1300" notAfter="1700" contemporary="false">
                        <p>Sewn on seven bands between cushionbevelled wooden boards covered with white alumtawed sheepskin. Rebinding led to the trimming of some marginalia. The front pastedown and <locus from="ir" to="iiv">fols. i-ii</locus> have holes and rust stains at top and bottom, presumably from chain-plates, which, since they are not in positions found on All Souls bindings, must have come from the previous binding.</p>
                        <p>Two clasps on the back cover and the remains of two straps on the front cover survive from a strap fastening, all held by nails of the usual type. At the bottom of the inside of the back cover are four holes from a chain-plate (position 1). Towards the bottom of the outer edge are two holes from another chain-clasp (position 5) and on the front cover, towards the top (position 6), are two similar holes.</p>
                        <p>On the spine are the remains of a black leather lozenge-shaped label but no figure survives on it. The endbands are blue and edges are yellowed.</p>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <provenance>The use of anglicana script shows that the book was being used by Englishmen quite early in the 14th century and the pressmark <quote>L.289</quote> at the top right-hand corner of fol. I<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> is clear evidence of a <orgName key="org_150107857" role="fmo">Bury St Edmunds Abbey</orgName> provenance, being in the hand of the Bury librarian <persName key="person_12580271">Henry of Kirkstead, c.1346-78</persName>, on whom see <bibl>R. H. Rouse, <title>'Bostonus Buriensis...', <title>Speculum</title></title>, 41 (1966), 471–99</bibl>. To the left of that is an erased inscription, not recoverable by ultraviolet light, and at the top left corner is another erased inscription, now invisible to the naked eye, which <persName key="person_100180276">Neil Ker</persName> read with ultraviolet light as <quote>Digestum vetus monachorum <unclear>Sancti E</unclear>d<unclear>mun</unclear>d<unclear>i</unclear></quote>. This may be one of the volumes of <bibl>Justinian, <title>Corpus iuris in quinque uoluminibus</title></bibl>, given to the abbey by <persName key="person_4548" role="fmo" cert="unknown">William Rockland (prior 1287-1312)</persName> recorded in the <bibl><title>Registrum coquinarii</title>, now Douai, Bibl. mun., MS 553 (Davis, MC, no. 114, CBMLC, <title>Shorter Benedictine Catalogues</title>, B15.4)</bibl>, or a volume in a similar set given by <persName key="person_4549" role="fmo" cert="unknown">Master John of Batsford</persName>, whose dates, are however, unknown (<bibl>CBMLC vol. cit. B15.7</bibl>).</provenance>
                 <acquisition>The book reached All Souls in time to be included in the Vellum Inventory (MS 399) <date notBefore="1441" notAfter="1458">between 1441 and 1458</date> (<bibl>Ker, All Souls, List XVIII</bibl>, no. 1251, with books 'in tercio desco' in the earliest list of law books; almost certainly identical with no. 251 in his List II, books in the College soon after foundation). All Souls library identifications, on which see Introduction, are, on the front pastedown, <quote>vv.2.1</quote> and <quote>ww:1:7</quote> (both deleted), <quote>M.S 49</quote> (figure added), and bookplate no. 6 on which are written in pencil <quote>158</quote> altered to <quote>157</quote> and <quote>L.R. 2.c.1.</quote></acquisition>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>Andrew G. Watson, <title>A Descriptive
                                                  Catalogue of the Medieval Manuscripts of All Souls
                                                  College Oxford</title> (Oxford, 1997)</source>
                     </recordHist>
                     <availability>
                        <p>For enquiries relating to this manuscript please
                                                  contact
                                                  <email>library@all-souls.ox.ac.uk</email>.</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
               </additional>
               <msPart n="A" xml:id="All_Souls_College_MS_49-part-A">
                  <msIdentifier>
                     <idno type="shelfmark">All Souls College MS. 49 items 1-4</idno>
                  </msIdentifier>
                  <msContents>
                     <textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>
                     <msItem n="1" xml:id="All_Souls_College_MS_49-item-1">
                        <p><locus from="front_pastedown" to="front_pastedown">Front pastedown.</locus> Table of titles of the <title key="work_2890">Digestum vetus</title> in book order, in the hand of the scribe of <ref target="#All_Souls_College_MS_49-item-4">item 4</ref>. Partly concealed by a large All Souls bookplate.</p>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="*2" xml:id="All_Souls_College_MS_49-item-2">
                        <p><locus from="ir" to="ir">Fol. i<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>.</locus> An alphabetic table of titles of the <title key="work_2890">Digestum vetus</title> with references to the books of the <title key="work_2890">Digest</title> in which the titles occur, in anglicana hands of <date notBefore="1300" notAfter="1400">s. xiv</date>.</p>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="*3" xml:id="All_Souls_College_MS_49-item-3">
                        <incipit>abauus est pater proaui uel proauus <locus from="iir" to="iir">fol. ii<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></locus></incipit>
                        <author key="person_88881722">Justinian, I, Emperor of the East, 483?–565</author>
                        <title key="work_2890">Stemma cognationum (frag.)</title>
                        <note>Three lines from the <bibl>'Stemma cognationum', <title>Digestum vetus</title>, III. 6, ed. Mommsen, <hi rend="italic">CIC</hi> i. 32</bibl></note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="4" xml:id="All_Souls_College_MS_49-item-4">
                        <rubric type="text">In nomine domini nostri ihesu Christi imperator iustinianus cesar. flauius. alamanicus. gothicus. francus. germanicus. atticus. alanicus. Wandalicus. affricanus. pius. felix, inclitus. uictor. ac triumphator. semper augustus. theophilo. dorotheo. theodoro. ysidoro et anatholio. et chanaleo et certinо uiris illustribus et antecessoribus et salamino uiro desertissimo antecessori salutem. Rubrica. <locus from="1r" to="1r">fol. 1<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></locus></rubric>
                        <incipit type="text_omnem">Omnem nostre rei publice sanctionem iam esse purgatam <locus from="1r" to="1r">fol. 1<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></locus></incipit>
                        <explicit type="text_omnem">Augusto ter consule <locus from="3r" to="3r">fol. 3<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></locus></explicit>
                        <rubric type="text_liber_primus">In nomine domini nostri ihesu christi domini
                           iustiniani sacrasanctissimi principis perpetui augusti iuris
                           enucleati ex omni ueteri iure collecti digestorum seu pandectarum.
                           Incipit liber primus. De iusticia et iure. Rubrica.  <locus from="3r" to="3r">fol. 3<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></locus></rubric>
                        <incipit type="text_liber_primus">Vlp' <locus from="3r" to="3r">fol. 3<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></locus></incipit>
                        <explicit type="text">idem erit probandum. Explicit Textus Digesti
                           Veteris. Deo Gracias. <locus from="312v" to="312v">fol. 312<hi rend="superscript">v</hi></locus></explicit>
                        <incipit type="gloss">Imperator quia imperat subditis sui <locus from="1r" to="1r">fol. 1<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></locus></incipit>
                        <explicit type="gloss">eam habere non licet ut codice de concubinis lege prima accursius. Explicit apparatus Digesti Veteris. Deo Gracias. <locus from="312v" to="312v">fol. 312<hi rend="superscript">v</hi></locus></explicit>
                        <author key="person_88881722">Justinian, I, Emperor of the East, 483?–565</author>
                        <title key="work_2890">Digestum vetus</title>
                        <note>
                           <p>Justinian, The <title>Digestum vetus</title> to I-XXIV.2, with the <hi rend="italic">Constitutio</hi> 'Omnem' and the gloss of <persName role="cwt" key="person_102317020">Accursius</persName>. Text <bibl type="edition">ed. Mommsen, <title>CIC</title>i. 10-12, 29-926 at 29-356</bibl>; for the gloss see <bibl><title>Corpus iuris civilis</title>, 5 vols. (Venice, 1487-9)</bibl>.</p>
                           <p>For other early editions see <bibl>Hain 9544-59</bibl> etc. On Accursius see <bibl><title>LexMA</title> i (1980), 75 and references</bibl>; <bibl>P. Fiorelli, in <title>Diz. biog. ital.</title> i (Rome, 1960), 11621 (s.v. Accorso) and references</bibl>.</p>
                         </note>
                     </msItem>
                  </msContents>
                  <physDesc>
                     <p>
                        <secFol><note>[text]</note> uirum</secFol>
                        <secFol><note>[gloss]</note> de bonorum.</secFol>
                     </p>
                     <objectDesc form="codex">
                        <supportDesc material="perg">
                           <support>Written on 312 pages of good-quality membrane prepared in the Italian manner. Folding is HSOS (HFFH).</support>
                           <extent>
                              <measure type="leaf" quantity="314">ii + 312</measure>
                              <dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                                 <height>430</height>
                                 <width>260</width>
                              </dimensions>
                           </extent>
                           <foliation>There is a medieval foliation in arabic figures which repeats 113 and by 120, after some missing and illegible figures, has jumped to 122; by 166 it is only one digit ahead and remains so to the end.</foliation>
                           <collation>
                              <formula>1-26<hi rend="superscript">12</hi></formula>
                              <signatures>Several series of quire signatures appear on the first leaves of quires: quires 2, 3, and 8 each have blue lowercase roman figures i-vi; quires 4, 5, 7, 8, 11-13, 21-3 each have blue or black lower-case letters a-f; 6, 10, and 21 (which also has letters, above) each have > followed by lower-case roman figures on their side, i-vi. The other quires have no signatures.</signatures>
                              <catchwords>Catchwords or traces of them, by the scribe of the text, survive on most quires but have been trimmed off others.</catchwords>
                           </collation>
                        </supportDesc>
                        <layoutDesc>
                           <layout>Pages laid out with centre area of text, in two columns of variable height, each 60mm wide, surrounded by gloss in two columns to left and bottom left and to right and bottom right. Some pages are entirely filled. The number of lines of text varies between c. 40 and 55 lines and the number of lines of gloss is c.100. Pricking is mostly trimmed off; only some prickings for verticals remain. Ruling is by crayon. Two lines of gloss occupy the space of one line of text.</layout>
                        </layoutDesc>
                     </objectDesc>
                     <handDesc>
                        <handNote script="gothicoAntiqua"> A good gothic rotunda bookhand, by a scribe trained in the Italian style in Italy or southern France.</handNote>
                        <handNote script="gothicoAntiqua">The hand of the gloss is essentially the same, the only apparent difference, greater angularity, being due to compression: the scribe may be the same.</handNote>
                        <handNote script="cursivaAntiquior">Running titles, at the top right-hand corners of pages, are in anglicana of <date notBefore="1300" notAfter="1320">s. xiv<hi rend="superscript">in</hi></date>.</handNote>
                        <handNote scribe="person_12580271">Head titles to columns throughout are in the hand of Henry of Kirkstead, on whom see History.</handNote>
                     </handDesc>
                     <decoDesc>
                        <decoNote>Although ascribed to Britain by <bibl>Alexander and Temple, no. 262 (pl. xv repr. fol. 1<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>, reduced)</bibl>, the lombards are in the Italian style and the illumination is French, possibly from Avignon.</decoNote>
                        <decoNote type="histInit">The book originally contained twenty-five fine illuminated miniatures but eighteen have been excised. The remaining ones, all by the same artist, some slightly overlying the lombards, are: <locus from="1r" to="1r">fol.1<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></locus>, <hi rend="italic">Constitutio</hi>, Justinian, standing, with two men who cast books on a fire(?); <locus from="3v" to="3v">fol. 3<hi rend="superscript">v</hi></locus>, bk. 1, <hi rend="italic">De iusticia et iure</hi>, Justinian, enthroned, being offered a sword by a female figure wearing a circlet; <locus from="19r" to="19r">fol. 19<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></locus>, bk. II, <hi rend="italic">De iurisdictione</hi>, Justinian, enthroned, expounding, two standing men on either side; <locus from="108r" to="108r">fol. 108<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></locus>, bk. VII, <hi rend="italic">De usufructu</hi>, three men, harvesting(?) and chopping down a branch; <locus from="285v" to="285v">fol. 285<hi rend="superscript">v</hi></locus>, bk. XII, <hi rend="italic">De usuris et fructibus</hi>, Justinian enthroned, expounding to three standing men; <locus from="294r" to="294r">fol. 294<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></locus>, bk. XIII, <hi rend="italic">De sponsalibus</hi>, priest joins a couple in marriage, with three standing figures; <locus from="306r" to="306r">fol. 306<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></locus>, bk. XIV, <hi rend="italic">De donationibus inter virum et uxorem</hi>, man and woman embracing, with two standing figures.</decoNote>
                        <decoNote type="flourInit">Lombards, by one hand, are mostly four/six-line, except when elongated into margins, blue and maroon on a background of the other colour and illuminated, and two-line, blue and maroon flourished in the other colour in the Italian style.</decoNote>
                        <decoNote type="rubrication">Rubrics, red and blue paraphs</decoNote>
                        <decoNote type="marginal">Red-and-blue book numbers in upper margins.</decoNote>
                     </decoDesc>
                  </physDesc>
                  <history>
                     <origin>
                        <origDate calendar="Gregorian" when="1300" cert="low">c. 1300</origDate>
                        <origPlace>
                           <country key="place_1000080">Italy</country> or <country key="place_1000070">France</country>
                        </origPlace>
                        <p>Although the script and pen decoration are entirely Italian in style the illumination is French.</p>
                     </origin>
                  </history>
               </msPart>
               <msPart n="B" xml:id="All_Souls_College_MS_49-part-B">
                  <msIdentifier>
                     <idno type="shelfmark">All Souls College MS. 49 item *5</idno></msIdentifier>
                  <msContents>                    
                     <msItem n="*5" xml:id="All_Souls_College_MS_49-item-5">
                        <textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>
                        <incipit> <supplied>cap</supplied>ita aliena ab eo qui dominium eorum habebat <locus from="Ir" to="Ir">fol. I<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>, lower page, col. a</locus></incipit>
                        <explicit>specialiter edium legatus peti non <locus from="Ir" to="Ir">fol. I<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>, upper page (i.e. outside of same quire) col. b</locus></explicit>
                        <author key="person_88881722">Justinian, I, Emperor of the East, 483?–565</author>
                        <title key="work_2890">Digestum vetus (frag.)</title>
                        <note>
                           <p>Justinian, <title>Digestum vetus</title>, VI-i.3 to VII-i.34, with a few pre-Accursian glosses, <bibl>ed. Mommsen, i. 120-31</bibl>.</p>
                                                           
                        </note>
                     </msItem>
                  </msContents>
                  <physDesc>
                     <objectDesc>
                        <supportDesc material="perg">
                           <support><p>The leaves are from a handsome volume, <date notBefore="1100" notAfter="1125">s. xii<hi rend="superscript">1</hi></date>, three bifolia (<locus from="Ir" to="IIIv">fols. I-III</locus>) plus a fourth bifolium now a pastedown, bound into the book as flyleaves and pastedown with the bottoms of pages at the spine, i.e. fourteen visible pages in all.</p>
                              <p>Original size probably 350 &#215; 215 mm.</p>
                              <p>The correct order of pages is as follows ('ru' indicating, as now bound, the upper page of a recto leaf, 'rl' its lower page, 'vu' the upper page of a verso leaf, and 'vl' its lower page): 
                                 <list>
                                    <item>fol. I<hi rend="superscript">rl</hi></item>
                                    <item>I<hi rend="superscript">vl</hi></item>
                                    <item>II<hi rend="superscript">vu</hi></item>
                                    <item>II<hi rend="superscript">ru</hi></item>
                                    <item>III<hi rend="superscript">rl</hi></item>
                                    <item>II<hi rend="superscript">vu</hi></item>
                                    <item>(verso of pastedown, concealed)</item>
                                    <item>IV<hi rend="superscript">ru</hi></item>
                                    <item>IV<hi rend="superscript">rl</hi></item>
                                    <item>(verso of pastedown, concealed)</item>
                                    <item>III<hi rend="superscript">vu</hi></item>
                                    <item>III<hi rend="superscript">ru</hi></item>
                                    <item>II<hi rend="superscript">rl</hi></item>
                                    <item>II<hi rend="superscript">vl</hi></item>
                                    <item>I<hi rend="superscript">vu</hi></item>
                                    <item>II<hi rend="superscript">ru</hi></item>
                                 </list>
                              </p>
                              <p>Since the concealed sides of the pastedowns presumably contain the text from VI-i.63 to VI-i.78 and V-ii. 13 to VII-i.3, the text is continuous apart from the loss of occasional lines from the bottoms or tops of pages.</p>
                           </support>
                           <extent>
                              <measure type="page">Fourteen visible pages.</measure>
                              <dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm" cert="medium">
                                 <height>350</height>
                                 <width>215</width>
                              </dimensions>
                           </extent>
                        </supportDesc>
                        <layoutDesc>
                           <layout columns="2" writtenLines="55">Written in two columns c. 275 &#215; 60 mm, c. 55 lines.</layout>
                        </layoutDesc>
                     </objectDesc>
                     <handDesc>
                        <handNote script="protogothic">A good protogothic hand</handNote>
                     </handDesc>
                     <decoDesc>
                        <decoNote type="colInit">Plain red initials</decoNote>
                        <decoNote type="rubrication">Rubric</decoNote>
                     </decoDesc>
                  </physDesc>
                  <history>
                     <origin>
                        Presumably from <origPlace key="place_7010914">Bury St Edmunds.</origPlace>
                        <origDate notBefore="1100" notAfter="1125" calendar="Gregorian">s. xii<hi rend="superscript">1</hi></origDate>
                     </origin>
                  </history>
               </msPart>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2024">First online publication.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p><!--body provided for validation and future transcription--></p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
