<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/msDesc/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/msDesc/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="manuscript_14205">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>All Souls College MS. 6</title>
            <title type="collection">All Souls College MSS.</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp when="1997">Cataloguer</resp>
               <persName>Andrew G. Watson</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp when="2024">Encoding</resp>
               <persName>Barbora Sojkova</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </publisher>
            <idno type="msID">All_Souls_College_MS_6</idno>
            <idno type="collection">All Souls College</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:lang="en" xml:id="All_Souls_College_MS_6">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <repository>All Souls College</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">All Souls College MS. 6</idno>
                  <!--ARKS to be added-->
                  
                  <altIdentifier type="shelfmark">
                     <idno>LR.1.d.5</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
                  
               </msIdentifier>
              
               <head><hi rend="italic">Psalterium</hi> (The 'Amesbury' Psalter)</head>
                               
               <msContents>
                  <textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>
                  
                  <msItem n="1" xml:id="All_Souls_College_MS_6-item-1">
                     <locus from="1" to="4">Fols. 1-4.</locus>
                     <note>For the full-page pictures on the rectos see Decoration below; the versos are blank.</note>
                     
                     <locus from="5r" to="10v">Fols. 5<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>-10<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>.</locus>
                     
                     <title type="desc">Calendar, in red, blue, and black, graded up to ix lections.</title>
                     
                     <note>
                        As <hi rend="italic">SM</hi>, pp. xxi—xxxii, with the following principal differences in the original text. 23 Jan., adds Emerentiana, iii lect. and Te Deum; 29 Jan., adds Sabina, iii lect. and Te Deum; 31 Jan., adds Potamion, iii lect. and Te Deum; 6 May, adds Melor; 24 Aug., omits memoria of Audoenus; 31 Aug., adds Cuthburga, iii lect. and Te Deum; 15 Sept., adds octave of Visitation of BVM; 16 Sept., omits Germanus; 1 Oct., reads 'S. Melori martyris. SS. Remigii. Vedasti et Amandi episcoporum'; 4 Oct., omits Francis; 7 Dec., omits octave of Andrew. In addition, there are many omissions of Invitatorium duplex' and 'Te Deum'. 
                        This appears to be the only calendar in which Melor appears at both 6 May and 1 Oct. 
                        The additions of David (1 Mar.), Richard of Chichester (2 Apr.), Anne (26 July), and octave of Andrew (7 Dec.) are in the hand of <persName key="person_16904434">John Grandisson</persName> (see History below), who also deleted the grading of Sabina, 29 Jan. 
                        The reinsertion of the erased transl. of Thomas of Canterbury (7 July), the marginal insertion of the feast of St Peter ad Vincula (I Aug.), and the marginal note, referring to Mary Tudor, d. 1558, <q>obitus Regine marie cuius anime propicietur deus</q> against 17 Nov., are in the hand of <persName>Robert Mandey</persName> (see History below). 
                        <q>Papa</q> etc. was deleted throughout except at 1 Aug. and was sometimes reinserted by <persName>Mandey</persName>.
                     </note>
                  </msItem>
                  
                     <msItem n="2" xml:id="All_Souls_College_MS_6-item-2">
                     
                     <locus from="11r" to="159r">Fols. 11<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>-159<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> (13<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>-161<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>).</locus>
                     
                     <title type="desc">[Psalms.]</title>
                     
                     <note><persName key="person_16904434">John Grandisson</persName>  marked <q>Feria ij<hi rend="superscript">a</hi></q>, usually in red, against the psalms beginning each liturgical division. 
                        The words of antiphons, unnoted, are written in a bookhand of <date>s. xiv<hi rend="superscript">med</hi></date>(probably on <persName key="person_16904434">Grandisson</persName>'s instructions) in the lower margins of nine leaves up to fol. 28<hi rend="superscript">v</hi> (30<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>), and noted, not very neatly, in the same position on forty leaves between fols. 35<hi rend="superscript">v</hi> (37<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>) and 128<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> (130<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>) inclusive. 
                        To connect them with the main text <persName key="person_16904434">Grandisson</persName> marked them <q>Feria iii<hi rend="superscript">a</hi></q> etc. 
                        Robert Mandey, who wrote a note on the numbering of the psalms on fol. iv<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>, added the numbers of the days of the month and <q>M[atins]</q> and <q>V[espers]</q> at the top of each page; against Ps. 9: 21 he noted the end of Ps. to <q>secundum Hebreos</q>; 
                        throughout Ps. 118 (119) he wrote the Hebrew names; against Ps. 147. I, wrote <q>pars psalmi precedentis in bibl. her. [<hi rend="italic">sic</hi>]</q> ; and after Ps. 150 wrote <q>Finis Psalmorum Dauidis.</q></note>
                     
                  </msItem>
                  
                   <msItem n="3" xml:id="All_Souls_College_MS_6-item-3">
                     
                     <locus from="159r" to="173r">Fols. 159<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>-173<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> (161<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>-175<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>).</locus>
                     
                     <title type="desc">Canticles.</title>
              
                     <note>
                        Against the Confitebor (fol. 159<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>) (161<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>) <persName key="person_16904434">Grandisson</persName> wrote <q>Feria ij<hi rend="superscript">a</hi></q>against the Ego dixi (fol. 159') (161")
                        <q>Feria iij<hi rend="superscript">a</hi></q>, and so against all the canticles. Against the Te Deum (fol. 167<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>) (169<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>) he also noted in the side margin <q>Nyceti episcopi Vienne</q> and in the lower margin <q>Quicquid dicatur de isto ympno. to deum laudamus. teste cassiodore [<hi rend="italic">sic</hi>] de institutione sanc-tarum scripturarum I et augustino ad valentinianum Beatus Nycetus viennensis episcopus composuit I et beatus Ambrosius cum Augustino. eum baptizans decantauit.</q> 
                        At the beginning of each canticle <persName>Robert Mandey</persName> wrote its name or the biblical source.
                        </note>
              
                  </msItem>
                  
                     <msItem n="4" xml:id="All_Souls_College_MS_6-item-4">
                     
                     <locus from="173r" to="177v">Fols. 173<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>-177<hi rend="superscript">v</hi> (175<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>-179<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>).</locus>
                     
                     <title type="desc">Kyrie, litany.</title>
                    
                     <note>The litany, containing a double entry for St Peter, is much shorter than that in <hi rend="italic">SM</hi> 423-7 but for the most part agrees with it and with Exeter litanies.</note>
                     
                  </msItem>
                                    
                 <msItem n="5" xml:id="All_Souls_College_MS_6-item-5">
                     
                    <locus from="178r" to="186v">Fols. 178<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>-186<hi rend="superscript">v</hi> (180<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>-186<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>).</locus>
                    
                    <title type="desc">Office of the Dead, Commemoration of Souls.</title>
                    
                    <note>The Office of the Dead has been changed to Sarum/Exeter use: see <bibl><hi rend="italic">Manuale Ebor.</hi> 65-92.</bibl> Commemoration of Souls as <hi rend="italic">SM</hi> 428-30.</note>
                 </msItem>  
                
               </msContents>
               
               <physDesc>
                  <p>
                     <secFol>ego autem</secFol>
                  </p>
                  <!--<p><!-\-todo: general comment on structure if necessary-\-></p>-->
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="perg">
                        <support>Written on 186 leaves of good-quality membrane, preceded by two modern paper flyleaves and two medieval membrane flyleaves, and followed by one medieval membrane and two modern paper leaves. 
                        <p>Fore- and endleaves: fol. fol. i<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>, blank; fol. i<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>, numbers; fol. ii<hi rend="superscript">rv</hi>, blank; 
                           fol. iii<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>, name, number; fol. iii<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>, blank; fol. iv<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>,
                           name, inscription; fol. iv<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>, blank; fols.I<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>-III<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>, blank.
                        </p>
                        </support>
                        <extent>
                           <measure type="leaf">186 leaves</measure>
                           <dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                              <height>305</height>
                              <width>210</width>
                           </dimensions>
                        </extent>
                        <!--<foliation><!-\-todo-\-></foliation>-->
                        <collation> 1<hi rend="superscript">8</hi> 2<hi rend="superscript">4</hi> 3-16<hi rend="superscript">12</hi> 17<hi rend="superscript">12</hi> (wants 9-12, cancelled).
                           <p>When the book was disbound in <date>1989</date> it was seen that the first and last leaves of quire 3, <locus>fols. 11 and 22 (13 and 24)</locus>, are not conjunct but separate and glued together, and that in quire 17 the four leaves that are conjunct with 1-4, <locus>fols. 179—82 (181-4)</locus> which followed <locus>fol. 186 (188)</locus>, 
                              had been cut away along the fold.</p>
                           <signatures>There are no quire numbers or signatures.</signatures>
                           <catchwords>Only one catch¬word remains, low down in the corner of <locus>fol. 22<hi rend="superscript">v</hi> (24<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>)</locus>, not in the scribe's hand.</catchwords>
                        </collation>                
                        <!--<condition><!-\-todo-\-></condition>
                     --></supportDesc>
                     
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout columns="1" writtenLines="20">Written in one column,<dimensions type="written" unit="mm"><height n="190">190</height><width n="120">120 mm</width></dimensions>, 20 lines. 
                           Pricked in inner and outer margins and for verticals. Ruled in pencil and folded FSOS. </layout>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  
                  <handDesc>
                     <handNote script="textualisNorthern">A good gothic <term>quadrata</term> bookhand often verging on <term>prescissa (sine pedibus</term>, perhaps by one scribe except for the rewriting in the Office of the Dead and marginal additions to the psalter. 
                        Punctuation is by low point and <term>punctus elevatus</term>.</handNote>
                  </handDesc>
                  
                  <decoDesc>
                     <decoNote type="miniature">
                        <locus>Fols. 1<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>-4<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> (3<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>-6<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>)</locus> contain four full-page miniatures with burnished gold backgrounds bearing incised patterns: 
                        on fol. i<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> (3<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>) the Annunciation; on fol. 2<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> (4<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>) a nun in a dark blue veil kneeling before the Virgin suckling the Child; on fol. 3<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> (5<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>) the Crucifixion; 
                        on fol. 4<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> (6<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>) a nun in a black veil and a dark blue and blue-green habit kneeling before Christ in Majesty. 
                        Holes pricked across the top of fols. 1-4 (3-6) suggest that sheets of silk were sewn there to protect the miniatures.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="miniature"> On fol. 11<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> (13<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>) is a thirteen-line Tree of Jesse</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="initial">Other large historiated initials are placed at the liturgical divisions and before the first of the canticles.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="initial">An illuminated two-line initial, inhabited or ornamental, begins each psalm and canticle and verses begin with red and blue lombards flourished in the other colour.
                        The first words following major initials are in gold capitals against alternating blue and red grounds.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="lineFill">Linefillers have ornamental patterns in red, blue, green, and occasionally gold, often with bird or animal motifs.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote>For a full description and bibliography see <bibl>N. J. Morgan, <title rend="italic">Early Gothic Manuscripts, ii: 1250-1285</title> (A Survey of Manuscripts Illuminated in the British Isles, 4 / ii; London and Oxford, 1988), no. 101 (pls. 21-4,26,29 repr. details fols. 94<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> (96<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>), 126<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> (128<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>), 2<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> (4<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>), and 64<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> (66<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>) respectively, all reduced, 
                        pl. 29 repr. fol. 3<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> (5) in colour, fig.i repr. fol. 4<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> (6<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>), reduced).</bibl>
                        A detail of fol. 114<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> (116<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>) is repr. in <bibl><title rend="italic">Age of chivalry: Art in Plantagenet England 1200-1400</title>, ed. J. Alexander and P. Binski (London, Royal Academy of Arts, 1984), fig. 74.</bibl> 
                        See also <bibl>Alexander and Temple, no. 215 (pl. XIIA-d repr. fols.2<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> (4<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>), 3<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> (5<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>), 11<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> (13<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>), and 62<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> (64<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>) respectively, reduced).</bibl>
                      </decoNote>
                  </decoDesc>
                  
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <binding notAfter="1899">
                        <p>Sewn on five bands between bevel-edged millboards covered with blind- and gold-stamped and -tooled dark brown morocco leather, <date>s. xix</date>. 
                           In <date>1989</date> the book was repaired (using the 19th-century sewing stations) by <persName>Nicholas Pickwoad</persName>, whose detailed conservation report is kept with the manuscript. 
                           It reveals that the 19th-century binding was the book's third binding; the first and second were both on seven bands.</p>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
                  
               </physDesc>
               
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="1260" notBefore="1250">1250-60</origDate>
                     <origPlace>
                        <country key="place_7002445">England</country>
                        <settlement key="place_7011210">Salisbury</settlement>
                     </origPlace>
                  </origin>
                  <provenance>Probably of <settlement key="place_7011210">Salisbury</settlement> area origin. Evidence of ownership by <orgName key="org_37">the Benedictine priory of Amesbury</orgName>, Wiltshire, a cell of Fontevrault, is (1) that the two feasts of St Melor, one of the patron saints of the house, whose relics were there, are in the calendar (6 May, 1 October) with high colour-gradings; and (2) the figure kneeling before the Virgin and Child in the miniature on fol. 2<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> (4<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>) is probably a nun. 
                     Points militating against a close connection are, however, (1) that the habit of the nun is insufficiently specific to link her with the order of Fontevrault and may indeed suggest that she might be a widow rather than a nun; (2) that the calendar resembles the Amesbury calendar in CUL, MS Ee. 6.16, only in the high grading of Melor; and (3) that the litany, although it does include Melor among martyrs, is not of the indisputably <orgName key="org_37">Amesbury</orgName>—Fontevrault type of litany found in Imola, Biblioteca Comunale MS too (<bibl>Morgan, <title rend="italic">Early Gothic Manuscripts</title>, pt. I (1982), no. 26</bibl>). 
                     This litany is not of Sarum use, nor was the Office of the Dead until it was altered in <date>s. xiv</date>. In spite of the absence of firm evidence an Amesbury connection of some kind seems probable. By the middle of <date>s. xiv</date> the book was in the hands of <persName key="person_16904434">John Grandisson</persName>, bp. of Exeter <date>1327-69</date>, who left much evidence of his use of it (on which see above, and see also <bibl>M. W. Steele, 'A Study of the Books Owned or Used by John Grandisson Bishop of Exeter (1327-1369)', D.Phil. thesis (Oxford, 1994)</bibl>. 
                     This may be the psalter with 2° folio <hi rend="italic">ego autem</hi> listed in the <orgName key="org_127815410">Exeter Cathedral</orgName> inventory of <date>1506</date> published by <bibl>G. Oliver, <title rend="italic">Lives of the Bishops of Exeter, etc.</title> (Exeter, 1861), 333.</bibl> Early in <date>s. xvii</date> it was in the hands of <persName>'Rob. Mandey'</persName> (fol. iv<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> (ii<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>), not Manday, as Morgan), some of whose many annotations, recorded above, evidence a Roman Catholic allegiance. 
                     Perhaps after that it acquired what looks like an institutional pressmark, C.ij.10, on fol. iii<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. 
                     It came to All Souls by gift of <persName>Daniel Lysons</persName>: on fol. iii<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> is <q>DD. Dan. Lysons M. D. Bathoniensis, et Coll. Om. An. quondam Socius. 1772.</q> He died in <date>1800</date>: see <hi rend="italic">DNB</hi>. 
                     All Souls library identifications, on which see Introduction, are, on the front pastedown, bookplate no. 2; on fol. i<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>, <q type="pressmark">MS. 6.</q>, <q type="pressmark">vv.3.2</q> (deleted), <q type="pressmark">L.R. i.d.5 (pencil)</q>; on fol. iii<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>, <q type="pressmark">8.3</q>.
                  </provenance>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>Andrew G. Watson, <title>A Descriptive
                                                  Catalogue of the Medieval Manuscripts of All Souls
                                                  College Oxford</title> (Oxford, 1997)</source>
                     </recordHist>
                     <availability>
                        <p>For enquiries relating to this manuscript please
                                                  contact
                                                  <email>library@all-souls.ox.ac.uk</email>.</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2024">First online publication.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p><!--body provided for validation and future transcription--></p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
