<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/msDesc/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/msDesc/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="manuscript_14212">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>All Souls College MS. 13</title>
            <title type="collection">All Souls College MSS.</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp when="1997">Cataloguer</resp>
               <persName>Andrew G. Watson</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp when="2025">Encoding</resp>
               <persName>Barbora Sojkova</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </publisher>
            <idno type="msID">All_Souls_College_MS_13</idno>
            <idno type="collection">All Souls College</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:lang="en" xml:id="All_Souls_College_MS_13">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <repository>All Souls College</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">All Souls College MS. 13</idno>
                  <!--ARKS to be added-->
                  <altIdentifier type="shelfmark">
                     <idno>LR.6.a.6</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
               
               <head>Radulphus Flaviacensis, <hi rend="italic">In Leviticum</hi></head>
               <msContents>
                  <textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>

                  <msItem n="1" xml:id="All_Souls_College_MS_13-item-1">
                     <rubric>
                        <locus from="1r">Fol. 1<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>.</locus>
                        Incipit prologus Domini Radulfi ilaiacensis monachi in explanatione super leuiticum.</rubric>
                     <incipit>Cum inter sotios [<hi rend="italic">sic</hi>] aliquando sermo de iudeorum contentionibus haberetur</incipit>
                     <explicit>
                        <locus from="2vb">Fol. 2<hi rend="superscript">vb</hi>.</locus>
                        quia perfidia iudeorum.
                     </explicit>
                     <finalRubric>Explicit prologus.</finalRubric>
                     
                     <rubric>Incipiunt capitula libri primi.</rubric>
                     <incipit>i<hi rend="superscript">a</hi>. De holochausto bouis.</incipit>
                     <explicit>x<hi rend="superscript">a</hi>. De primiciis frugum que domino offeruntur.</explicit>
                     
                     <rubric>Item alius prologus.</rubric>
                     <incipit>Tercius in Moysi libris leuiticus appelatur.</incipit>
                     
                     <explicit>
                        <locus from="3ra">Fol. 3<hi rend="superscript">ra</hi>.</locus>
                        in populo tradit dispensanda. 
                     </explicit>
                     <finalRubric>Explicit prologus.</finalRubric>
                     
                     <rubric>Incipit liber Primus explanationis super leuiticum. Vocavit autem dominus.</rubric>
                     
                     <explicit>
                        <locus from="198vb">Fol. 198<hi rend="superscript">vb</hi>.</locus>
                        Panem tamen quendam recentem ||.</explicit>
                     
                     <author key="person_108145542395296640745">Radulphus Flaviacensis (Raoul de Flaix, Fly), OSB</author>
                     <title key="work_4193">In Leviticum</title>
                     <listBibl>
                        <bibl>Pr. Marburg and Cologne, 1536, repr. M. de la Bigne, <title>Maxima bibliotheca Patrum</title>, 7 (Lyons, 1677), 48-246</bibl>
                        <bibl>Stegmüller, <title>Bibl.</title> 7093.</bibl>
                        <bibl>On Radulphus see Aime Solignac, in <title>Dict. de spiritualité</title>, xiii, cols. 1—8 and on the work B. Smalley, 'Ralph of Flaix on Leviticus', <title>RTAM</title> 35 (1968), 35-82.</bibl>
                     </listBibl>
                     <note>Our text ends abruptly in bk. xvii at 216<hi rend="superscript">b</hi>/40 of edn. (see History below).</note>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <p>
                     <secFol>loquente</secFol>
                  </p>
                  <p><!--todo: general comment on structure if necessary--></p>
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="perg">
                        <support> Written on 198 membrane leaves, except in quire 13 mostly of good quality, although with blem¬ishes and sometimes repaired before writing, preceded by one membrane flyleaf and followed by a paper leaf from an incunable. 
                           <p>Fore- and endleaves: fol. i<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>, blank; fol. i<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>, title and 2<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> folio; fol. I, printed flyleaf.</p>
                        </support>
                        <extent>
                           <measure type="leaf">198 leaves</measure>
                           <dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                              <height>400</height>
                              <width>300</width>
                           </dimensions>
                        </extent>
                        <foliation>Foliated in modern pencil. Medieval foliation, in arabic figures, found also in <idno type="shelfmark">MS 30</idno> which evidently has a common history with this volume, is unusual: the figures (repeating 147) appear below the left-hand columns on the versos of leaves (see our Pl. i).</foliation>
                        <collation>1<hi rend="superscript">8</hi> (wants 1) 2-20<hi rend="superscript">8</hi> 21<hi rend="superscript">5</hi> 22-25<hi rend="superscript">8</hi> 26<hi rend="superscript">8</hi>. (sic?: wants 2-8).
                           Quires are numbered with large black roman capital figures, sometimes preceded and followed by a point and often elabo¬rately flourished. xi is written in red and xx is lacking. 
                           <catchwords>Catchwords on fifteen quires, not by the scribe, but lacking on nine quires. Some pages bear running titles (Lib. I, Lib. II, etc.) in the same hand as the majority of the catchwords. Some are in red and others are elaborately flourished in red or in ink. They are rather similar to those in <idno type="shelfmark">MS 30</idno>. For illustrations of folio numbers, quire numbers, and catchwords see our Pl. 1; for comparison with similar features in <idno type="shelfmark">MS 30</idno> see our Pl. 2.</catchwords>
                        </collation>
                        <!--<condition><!-\-todo-\-></condition>-->
                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout columns="2" writtenLines="39" rulingMedium="crayon">
                           Written in two columns, each <dimensions type="written" unit="mm">
                           <height>310</height>
                           <width>90</width>
                        </dimensions>
                           37-9 lines to the page. Writing is above and below top lines, changing even within quires. 
                           Pricked in outer and inner margins and for vertical ruling. Ruled in crayon and folded HSOS.</layout>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc>
                     <handNote script="protogothic">Protogothic bookhand turning into gothic bookhand, written by three scribes. <persName key="person_4523">Scribe A</persName>, whose hand is very similar to and possibly identifiable with that of the scribe of <idno type="shelfmark">MS 30</idno>, wrote to fol. 109<hi rend="superscript">ra</hi>/6 <q>scriptum est</q> (see our Pl. 1), scribe B to fol. 109<hi rend="superscript">rb</hi>/26 <q>est</q>, and scribe C from there. 
                        Thereafter C and B continue, merging indistinguishably. C is the most <term type="script">gothic</term> and the least accomplished in that he tends to be untidy but the difference is more one of neatness and compactness than of letter-forms. 
                        <persName key="person_4523">Scribe A</persName> wrote mostly but not always above the top line, scribe B had no choice but to do the same on the one page he began, and scribe C wrote consistently below the top line. 
                        Corrections are marked in the margin and parts of the text are rewritten. Omissions are written out in the margin with a <hi rend="italic">signe de renvoi</hi> to and in the text. 
                        Punctuation is by low point and punctus elevatus. Hyphens, original, are in the form of small oblique strokes low on the line.
                     </handNote>
                  </handDesc>
                  <decoDesc>
                     <decoNote type="initial">Good arabesque initials. Major initials are of seven-line size or more, red, green, or blue, infilled in various colours and in a few cases colour-washed in blue or buff: see our Pl. 1. On fol. 78<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> the buffwash partly conceals a scribal error. 
                        Smaller initials are red, blue, or green. The initials are partly if not wholly in the hand of the artist of <idno type="shelfmark">MS 30</idno>, q.v. for comparisons.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="lineFill">Linefillers consisting of series of minim-like strokes are in red, green, red-and-green, and red-and-black.</decoNote> 
                     <decoNote type="other">Guide letters for the decorator are in outer and inner margins, the former often trimmed. Directions to the rubricator, who occasionally uses green as well as red (but the green addition to a rubric on fol. 165<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> is evidently a correction), are written in a cursive script low down in bottom margins with a <hi rend="italic">signe de renvoi</hi> beside them and another in a side margin opposite the point of insertion.</decoNote>
                  </decoDesc>
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <binding contemporary="unknown">
                        <p>Resewn on six bands between projecting bevelled oak boards covered with white alum-tawed skin. 
                           On the spine is a black leather lozenge-shaped label with <q>8</q> on it. 
                           Some bands are exposed on both covers and can be seen to have been brought over the outer surface of the back edge of the boards, not through a tunnel in them. On each cover are holes for five bosses as in <idno type="shelfmark">MS 30</idno>, which came from the same source. 
                           On the front cover are the remains of two straps, the upper now held by three out of five nails, the lower by five nails, all of the usual type. At the top of the front cover, inside and outside, are signs of a chain-staple (position 6). 
                           On the back cover are two metal catches for straps and at the bottom are eight holes for a chain-staple or perhaps staples (six holes, position I, and two holes, slightly higher up). 
                           Two leaves at the back of the book, fol. 199 and the pastedown, are fols. 9-11 from a copy of the <bibl><title key="work_5550">Margarita poetica</title> of <persName key="person_22136923" role="aut">Albrecht von Eyb</persName></bibl>, of which other leaves are in <idno type="shelfmark">MSS 2, 12, 14, 30, 79, and dd.2.9</idno>: see <idno type="shelfmark">MS 12</idno> for details. 
                           In the present volume the folds have sewing holes, showing that they came from a bound copy. Edges are yellowed and there is a fore-edge title. There appears to be a residue of staining on the front cover.</p>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="1400" notBefore="1100">s. xii/xiii</origDate>
                     <origPlace>
                        <country key="place_7002445">England</country>
                     </origPlace>
                  </origin>
                  <provenance>The pre-All Souls history of this handsome book is not known but is clearly identical with that of <idno type="shelfmark">MS 30</idno>, which shares with it script, style of decoration, type of catchwords, the unusual way of numbering leaves (in the same hand), and the same frequent use of wavy note marks in the margin. 
                     The covers of both have had bosses, suggestive of northern rather than southern England and of ownership by a Cistercian house (<hi rend="italic">ex info</hi> Michael Gullick). 
                     Both came to the College by gift of <persName key="person_3315">Richard Andrew</persName>, the first Warden (on whom see <hi rend="italic">BRUO</hi> and Walker, 'Andrew'), in the time of the Founder (<bibl>Ker, <title>All Souls</title>, List II, no. 43, with <q>Libri theologie cathenati</q></bibl>). 
                     <bibl>No. 26 in James, <title>Ecloga</title></bibl>, and <bibl>no. 1413 (12) in <title>CMA</title></bibl>. 
                     On fol. i<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>, in a large <term type="script">hybrida formata</term> script, is <q>Exposicio Radulfi flaiacensis Monachi super leuiticum ex donacione Magistri Ricardi Andrew</q> and, below, the 2<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>  folio in the hand that wrote the 2<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> folio in <idno type="shelfmark">MS 12</idno>. 
                     On fol. 2<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> is <hi rend="italic">ex libris</hi> style 1, <q>Liber Collegij animarum omnium fidelium defunctorum de Oxon' ex dono Magistri Ricardi Andrew j<hi rend="superscript">i</hi> custodis</q>. 
                     The book was harshly treated in the <date>1580s</date> when about 36-40 of the final leaves were removed. Sixteen of them, identifiable as coming from quires 27-30, were used as pastedowns in the eight-volume Antwerp edition of the Bible which <persName key="person_91172189" role="dnr">Francis Milles</persName> gave to the College in <date>1584</date>, payment for binding of which, recorded in the College accounts, was made to the Oxford binder <persName key="person_4536">Dominic Pinart</persName>. 
                     Two other leaves from quire 30 were used by <persName key="person_4536">Pinart</persName> in the binding of a book now in <orgName key="org_150825867">Winchester College</orgName> Library, Moberly Library, 60A. 
                     <bibl>For this see Ker, <title>Pastedowns</title>, p. xi and no. 1168</bibl>, who suggests that <persName key="person_4536">Pinart</persName> may have complained that he had no manuscript leaves suitable for use as pastedowns in a book of this size. 
                     <p>In the present volume All Souls library identifications, on which see Introduction, are, on the front pastedown, <q type="pressmark">vv.Infra.6</q> and <q type="pressmark">ww.r.8</q> (both deleted), <q type="pressmark">MS. i3</q>, <q type="pressmark">L.R. 6.a.6</q> (pencil), and bookplate no. 8, on which is <q>163</q> (pencil).</p>
                  </provenance>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>Andrew G. Watson, <title>A Descriptive
                                                  Catalogue of the Medieval Manuscripts of All Souls
                                                  College Oxford</title> (Oxford, 1997)</source>
                     </recordHist>
                     <availability>
                        <p>For enquiries relating to this manuscript please
                                                  contact
                                                  <email>library@all-souls.ox.ac.uk</email>.</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2024">First online publication.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p><!--body provided for validation and future transcription--></p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
