<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/msDesc/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/msDesc/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="manuscript_14208">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>All Souls College MS. 9</title>
            <title type="collection">All Souls College MSS.</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp when="1997">Cataloguer</resp>
               <persName>Andrew G. Watson</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp when="2025">Encoding</resp>
               <persName>Barbora Sojkova</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </publisher>
            <idno type="msID">All_Souls_College_MS_9</idno>
            <idno type="collection">All Souls College</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:lang="en" xml:id="All_Souls_College_MS_9">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <repository>All Souls College</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">All Souls College MS. 9</idno>
                  <!--ARKS to be added-->
                  <altIdentifier type="shelfmark">
                     <idno>LR.1.d.6</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>  
               </msIdentifier>
               <head><hi rend="italic">Epistolae S. Pauli, glosatae</hi></head>
               <msContents>
                  <textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>
             
                  <msItem n="1" xml:id="All_Souls_College_MS_9-item-1">
                     <locus from="iir">Fol. ii<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>-iiii<hi rend="superscript">v</hi> (early flyleaves) and 117<hi rend="superscript">rv</hi> (original blank leaf).</locus>
                     <note>With stains and holes, containing many proverbs, prayers, and other short texts in Italian hands of <date>c.1300</date>, of which one is predominant and is also found in *5 below.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  
                  <msItem n="1.i" xml:id="All_Souls_College_MS_9-item-1.i">
                     <locus from="iir">Fol. ii<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>.</locus>
                     <title type="desc">Proverbs, <hi rend="italic">sententiae</hi>, a prayer, quotations.</title>
                     <note>Proverbs include <q>Restituit pape &lt;solus?&gt; deponit et ipse</q> four lines (<bibl>Walther, <title>Initia</title>, 16687</bibl>); 
                        <q>Spes est exspectatio futurorum bonorum ex meritis cedentibus</q>; <q>Rapine est occupare aliena &lt;re?&gt; violenta.</q> 
                        There are also a list of the signs of the zodiac; a prayer beginning <q>Oremus dilectissimi nobis domini</q>; <q>Anno m. c. c. nonagesimo tercio obiit frater bo&lt;...&gt;enutus die tercio intrante 
                           octabo vigilia sancti &lt;...&gt;</q>;
                        <q>Anno domini M trecesimo feria in translatione(?) Aug. obiit lisi&lt;...&gt;sus filius [...] alexij</q>; 
                        three phrases which connect the book with Bologna, <q>&lt;...&gt;des. sancti Martini in pidriolo d.m. ix. lib'. habuit vj 1. et xvii s. et x d. pro [...] bon.</q>, 
                        <q>...ecclesie sancti marie maioris</q> and <q>ecclesie sancti marie maioris bon' soluit viii .1. m' ij de predicta colecc[...] omnes pro custodia ciuitatis</q>; 
                        and <q>Liber epistolarum beati pauli [... qui ...]</q>, probably an institutional librarian's note.</note>
                     
                     <note>For the identification of some of these churches see History below.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  
                  <msItem n="1.ii" xml:id="All_Souls_College_MS_9-item-1.ii">
      
                     <incipit>
                        <locus from="iiv">Fol. ii<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>.</locus>
                        Pater noster
                     </incipit>
                     <incipit>[Comm.] Monetur nobilis et diues non superbire contra minores</incipit>
                     <explicit>
                        <locus from="iiir">Fol. iii<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>.</locus>
                        quatuor sequencia presentis uite sunt presidia.
                     </explicit>
                
                     <author key="person_3070">Johannes de Pagham, bp. of Worcester (d. 1157)</author>
                     <title key="work_5539">Commentary on the Pater Noster</title>
                     <listBibl>
                        <bibl>Unpr.; Stegmüller, <title>Bibl.</title> 4839, 6. The only copy Stegmüller records is York Minster,
                           MS XVI.1.7, fols. 192<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>-193<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>, which ends at <q>seruare non negligimus</q> some eleven lines before the end of our text. 
                        </bibl>
                     </listBibl>
                     <note>The text of the <hi rend="italic">Pater noster</hi> is on fol. ii<hi rend="superscript">vb</hi> only, with the commentary written between the lines and filling the remaining columns. In an Italian hand, <date>s. xii</date>.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  
                  <msItem n="1.iii" xml:id="All_Souls_College_MS_9-item-1.iii">
                     <locus from="iiiv">Fol. iii<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>.</locus>
                     <title type="desc">Proverbs, verses, etc.</title>
                     <note>Include <q>Sum quod non eram quod sum nunc \modo dicor/ utrumque</q> (<bibl>cf. Walther, <title>Proverbia</title>, 30635a, <title>Initia</title>, 18727</bibl>); 
                        <q>Quod clerici possint habere plura beneficia vel non V<hi rend="superscript">s</hi>...</q>;
                        <q>Quinque libros moysijosue. judicum, samuelem</q> (<bibl>Walther, <title>Initia</title>, 16027</bibl>); 
                        a prayer, <q>Benedictio lapidis pro ecclesia edificando. Or. Benedic domine creaturam istam lapidis... </q>;
                        <q>Contra clericos ad ordines accedentes. et nescientes quid sunt ad necessaria. Isidorus...</q>; 
                        two distinctiones; <q>m.cc.lxxxvi mense madij. destri&lt;...&gt; fuit per cor' bon' ecclesie sancte marie de rusticanis que erat in curia comuni [<hi rend="italic">sic</hi>] et fuit antiquitus ecclesia monialium et vocabatur sancta marie in rosa</q>.
                     </note>
                     <note>For the identification of S. Maria de' Rusticanis see History below.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  
                  <msItem n="2" xml:id="All_Souls_College_MS_9-item-2">
                     
                     <locus from="1r">Fol. 1<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>.</locus>            
                     <title key="work_3509" type="desc">Pauline Epistles, glossed, with some prologues.</title> 
                     <note>(The numbers refer to <bibl>Stegmüller, <title>Bibl.</title></bibl>): 
                        Romans, with prologue (676); [fol. 19<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>] 1 Corinthians, with prologue (685); [fol. 40<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>] 2 Corinthians, with prologue (699); 
                        [fol. 54<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>] Galatians; [fol. 62<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>] Ephesians, with prologue (715); [fol. 69<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>] Philippians, with prologue (728); 
                        [fol. 75<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>] Colossians, with prologue (736); [fol. 80<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>] Thessalonians, with prologue (747); [fol. 84<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>] 2 Thessalonians, with prologue (752); 
                        [fol. 87<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>] Timothy; [fol. 93<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>] 2 Timothy, with prologue (772); [fol. 97<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>] Titus, with prologue (780); 
                        [fol. 99<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>] Philemon, with prologue (783); [fol. 100<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>] Hebrews, with prologue (793).</note>
                     
                     <note>The glosses are an example of the type of early collection that was superseded by the <hi rend="italic">Glossa ordinaria</hi> in the early <date>12th century</date>: 
                        see <bibl>B. Smalley, 'La Glossa ordinaria: Quelques prédecesseurs d'Anselme de Laon', <title>RTAM</title> 9 (1937), 365-400</bibl> and 
                        <bibl>'Les Commentaires bibliques de l'époque romane: Glose ordinaire et gloses périmées', <title>Cahiers de civilisation médiévale x<hi rend="superscript">e</hi>-xii<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> siècles</title>, 4 (1961), 15-22</bibl>. 
                        In quire 6 (fols. 41-9) a miscalculation in the amount of space required has resulted in an irregularity; the original second leaf, conjugate with the seventh, was removed and replaced by a bifolium, now fols. 42-3. 
                        Fol. 43<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> ends in 2 Corinthians 3: 14 <q>in lectione ueteris testamenti</q> followed by four blank lines on that page and a verso that had been blank but now contains glosses from Augustine, Lucius papa, Jerome, Eugenius, Ciprian, Symmachus, Gregory, Ambrose, and Leo iv in a hand of s. xii<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>. 
                        Fol. 44<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> picks up the text after erasure of the first word, which duplicated <q>testamenti</q>, and the quire continues normally to its seventh leaf (fol. 48) which is now sewn into place, preceded by its stub, between the eighth and ninth leaves, fols. 47 and 49. Hebrews ends on fol. 115<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>.
                     </note>
                  </msItem>
                  
                  <msItem n="3.i" xml:id="All_Souls_College_MS_9-item-3">
               
                     <locus from="115v">Fol. 115<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>.</locus>     
                     
                     <incipit>  
                        (i) [D]omine deus omnipotens pater. qui consubstantialem et coeternum 
                     </incipit>
                     <incipit>(ii) [D]omine ihesu christe fili dei uiuj qui es uerus et omnipotens deus</incipit>
                     <incipit>(iii) [D]omine spiritus sancte qui equalis et coeternus et consubstantialis patri filioque existens </incipit>
                     <incipit>(iv) [S]ancta trinitatis atque indiuidua unitas omnipotens</incipit>
                     <explicit>et deprecor ut me a malignis ||</explicit>
                     <title type="desc">Prayers to God the Father, God the Son, God the Holy Spirit, and the Holy Trinity.</title>
                     <note>In a northern Italian protogothic text hand of <date>s. xii</date>, ending imperfectly.</note>
                  </msItem>
                        
                  
                  <msItem n="4" xml:id="All_Souls_College_MS_9-item-4">
                     <incipit>
                        <locus from="116v">Fol. 116<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>.</locus>     
                        || in rebus pessimis sed ipsi post hanc uitam semper lugerunt in eterna miseria. boni autem gaudebunt in eterna uita ubi absterget deus omnem lacrimam ab oculis eorum etc. erit eis gaudium sempiternum ad quem nos perducat dominus christus qui cum patre et filio etc.</incipit>
                     <title type="desc">The end of an unidentified prayer</title>
                     <note>In a small Italian hand of <date>s. xii</date>. Only a roughly triangular fragment from the bottom of the leaf remains, blank on the recto (the upper part of which presumably contained the continuation of *3 above) and originally in two columns on the verso.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  
                  <msItem n="5" xml:id="All_Souls_College_MS_9-item-5">
                     <locus from="117v">Fol. 117<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>.</locus>    
                     <title type="desc">Miscellaneous notes in Italian hands.</title>
                     <note>Including <q>Legimus in ac' apostolorum quod spiritus sanctus hodie appariit in igneis linguis</q>; <q>Post letanias oracio. domine nostras. Clamantium ad to preces dignantur...</q>; 
                        <q>plenus dolorum ihesus fuit obprobriorum atque flagellorum quia uir fuit &lt;...&gt; dolorum</q> (sixteen lines); 
                        a sequence of numbers, below each of which is a word, e.g. vigesima/nobis, septimadecima/sepe, vigesimatercia/mox, vigesima/puto, the purpose of which is made clear by the occurrence of the same words at the bottom of 
                        fol. 117<hi rend="superscript">v</hi> preceded by <q>Ad inueniendum pascha hebreorum</q>; the four-line draft of a short letter <q>Karissimo amico et consanguineo suo Ran domino fadone(?) iudici domini potestatis padue. bondi(?) ecclesie sancte marie maioris bon' canonicus salutem...</q> 
                        and below it, in crayon, <q>Iste liber est recius(?) de sancta maria maioris. p' xxv s.</q> (see History below); 
                        <q>Ratio emendare debet quod furore promulgatam est</q> (also on fol. iii<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>); <q>Misericordia est alterius misere conpasio</q>; [fol. 117<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>] <q>Articulus color est breue membrum diccio greca</q> 
                        and <q>Momentum numerus dubio quocque dicitur esse</q>; a <hi rend="italic">distinctio</hi> <q>De decem preceptis legis</q>, six lines, <date>c.1300</date>; <q>Sere bondie da sancta maria</q>; 
                        the date <q>m cclxxiiij indiccione secunda</q>; a Greek alphabet with the letters spelt out above them <q>alfa, vita, camma, delta,eyete, fi, thi... omega</q> and a rough coat of arms.
                      </note>
                     
                     <note>For the identification of the church of S. Maria Maioris see History, below.</note>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <p>
                     <secFol>stulti</secFol>
                  </p>
<!--                  <p><!-\-todo: general comment on structure if necessary-\-></p>-->
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="perg">
                        <support>Written on 117 membrane leaves, some of which are poorly prepared and many have blemishes, preceded by one modern paper and two original membrane flyleaves and followed by one modern paper flyleaf. 
                           <p>Fore- and endleaves: fol. i<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>, number; fol. i<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>, blank; fols. ii<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>-iii<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>text, =*1 below; fol. I<hi rend="superscript">rv</hi>, blank.</p>
                        </support>
                        <extent>
                           <measure type="leaf">117 leaves</measure>
                           <dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                              <height>270</height>
                              <width>180</width>
                           </dimensions>
                        </extent>
                        <foliation>Numbered iii + 117 + I in modern pencil.</foliation>
                        <collation>1-5<hi rend="superscript">8</hi> 6<hi rend="superscript">8</hi> (2 canc. and replaced by a bifolium: see item 2 above) 7-14<hi rend="superscript">8</hi> 15<hi rend="superscript">4</hi>. 
                           <signatures>Traces of quire signatures remain on a few quires, consisting of a small letter with an ornamental pattern of commas on every side. </signatures>
                           <catchwords>Traces of catchwords also remain, mostly in the scribe's hand.</catchwords></collation>
                        <!--<condition><!-\-todo-\-></condition>-->
                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout columns="1" writtenLines="22" rulingMedium="hardpoint">
                           In one column, c. <dimensions type="written" unit="mm">
                              <height>205</height>
                              <width>95</width>
                           </dimensions> 21-2 lines of text with marginal and interlinear gloss written around them, two lines of gloss to one of text. Pricked in outer margins, ruled in hardpoint, and folded HSOS. 
                        </layout>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc hands="4">
                     <handNote script="minusculeCaroline">Fols. 1-97<hi rend="superscript">v</hi> are in Caroline minuscule, except fol. 43<hi rend="superscript">v</hi> which is in <term type="script">protogothic bookhand</term>;</handNote>
                     <handNote script="protogothic">fols. 98<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>-116<hi rend="superscript">v</hi> are in protogothic bookhand.
                        The glosses are in smaller versions of these scripts, without change in letter-forms.</handNote>
                     <handNote script="cursiva">Italian cursive is used for the miscellaneous notes on fols. ii<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>-iii<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>, 117<hi rend="superscript">rv</hi>. 
                        Punctuation is by low point and punctus elevatus. A later hand has supplemented the original punctuation and has occasionally turned the point into a punctus versus.
                     </handNote>
                  </handDesc>
                  <decoDesc>
                     <decoNote type="initial">Although blank spaces were left for ini¬tials at the beginnings of books many were left empty and those that were filled contain a variety of styles of capital. 
                        Some are plain red, some are crudely touched in crimson, and others have crude interlace infilling. Small capitals in the text are stroked with red.</decoNote>
                  </decoDesc>
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <binding notAfter="1799">
                        <p>Sewn on five bands between millboards covered with blind-ruled and -tooled calf (<date>s. xviii</date>). 
                           On the spine are a black leather lozenge-shaped label with <q>12</q> on it and a brown leather title-label. 
                           Fols. i and ii, original flyleaves, have rust marks and/or holes at all four corners and similar marks are on fol. 117<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>, presumably from the nails of corner pieces of an earlier binding.</p>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="1199" notBefore="1000">s. xi/xii</origDate>
                     <origPlace>
                        <country key="place_1000080">Italy</country>
                     </origPlace>
                  </origin>
                  <provenance>Judging by script and decoration, written in Italy. Around the end of the <date>13th century</date> (see fols. etc.) the book was in <placeName key="place_7004847">Bologna</placeName>: 
                     for the collegiate church of <orgName key="org_234811000">S. Maria Maggiore</orgName> there, to which the book seems to have belonged (fol. 117<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>), 
                     and the church of <orgName key="org_378">S. Maria de' Rusticanis</orgName> (fol. iii<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>), see <bibl>G. Cappelletti, <title>Le chiese d'Italia</title>, iii (Venice, 1845), 567, 568.</bibl> 
                        What may be an institutional librarian's note of c. <date>1300</date> is on fol. ii<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> (see item *1 above). 
                        Nothing is known about when and how it came to All Souls. Two <hi rend="italic">ex libris</hi> inscriptions, <q>Liber Collegii Omnium Animarum Fidelium defunctorum</q> on fol. i<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> and 
                        <q>Liber Collegii Omnium Animarum Oxon</q>, on fol. 19<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>, are in a hand, perhaps of <date>s. xvii</date>, which is not found in other All Souls medieval manuscripts; this may suggest that the book came to the College alone. 
                        <p>All Souls library identifications, on which see Introduction, are, inside the front cover, <q type="pressmark">vv.3.3</q> and <q type="pressmark">ww:4:12</q> (both deleted), <q type="pressmark">95</q> (pencil), 
                           bookplate no. 8 on which is <q type="pressmark"><hi rend="underline">MS.9</hi></q> (figure added), <q type="pressmark">L.R. 1.d.6</q> (pencil); on fol. ir,  <q type="pressmark">6:7</q> (pencil).
               </p></provenance>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>Andrew G. Watson, <title>A Descriptive
                                                  Catalogue of the Medieval Manuscripts of All Souls
                                                  College Oxford</title> (Oxford, 1997)</source>
                     </recordHist>
                     <availability>
                        <p>For enquiries relating to this manuscript please
                                                  contact
                                                  <email>library@all-souls.ox.ac.uk</email>.</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2025">First online publication.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p><!--body provided for validation and future transcription--></p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
