<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="manuscript_3951">
   <teiHeader xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Christ Church MS. 417</title>
            <title type="collection">Christ Church MSS.</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Cataloguer</resp>
               <persName>Ralph Hanna</persName>
               <persName>David Rundle</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </publisher>
            <idno type="msID">Christ_Church_MS_417</idno>
            <idno type="collection">Christ_Church</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="Christ_Church_MS_417">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <repository>Christ Church</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">Christ Church MS. 417</idno>
               <idno type="ieArk">ark:29072/c09z902z14bd</idno><idno type="crArk">ark:29072/c09w03223116</idno></msIdentifier>
               <head>Thomas Vicary, <title>The Anatomy of Man’s Body</title>; London, s. xvi<hi rend="superscript">2/4</hi> (1530 × 1547), with additions of s. xvi<hi rend="superscript">4/4</hi></head>
               <msContents>
                  <textLang mainLang="en">English</textLang>
                  <msItem>
                     <note> Fol. 1<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>: originally blank.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="1" xml:id="Christ_Church_MS_417-item1">
                     <locus from="1v" to="43v">Fols 1<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>–43<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>
                     </locus>
                     <rubric>Here after folowyth a lytyll treatys or tract Of the anathomy of Mans body drawen by M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Thomas Vicare of london Barbour and surgen and sargeant of ye surgeons vnto owre soueren lorde kyng Henry ye viij<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>. for All hys bretheryn of That felyschype practesyng surgery Nott for them yat be expertly sene In ye anothomy . . . exsept my good wyll.</rubric>
                     <incipit><note>[fol. 2] [heading later in upper margin]</note> Wat Is surgere | <supplied>I</supplied>n nomine dei patris amen forasmoche as surgeri Is a syens ye whyche dothe Teche <supplied>a man</supplied> to worke In <note>[the word repeated at the line break]</note> bodis of men</incipit>
                     <explicit defective="true">ye Naylles and thus be There In ye fott xxvj<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>. bons and In ye leg frome the</explicit>
                     <author key="person_52040449">Thomas Vicary</author>
                     <title key="work_5609">Anatomy of the Body of Man</title>
                     <note>Ed. Frederick J. and Percy Furnivall, EETS, extra ser. 53 (1888), 11–86/2, working from the 1577 edition (STC 24713). There is said to have been a 1548 edition (STC 11715.5), for which no witnesses survive, but its existence has been doubted by Duncan P. Thomas, ‘Thomas Vicary and the <title>Anatomie of Mans Body</title>’, <title>Medical History</title>, 50 (2006), 235–46 (see also id., ‘Thomas Vicary, barber-surgeon’, <title>Journal of Medical Biography</title>, 14 (2006), 84–89). The text presented here differs markedly from that recorded in the 1577 edition. The identification of Vicary as ‘sergeant of surgeons’ dates the incipit after 1530, when he was given the reversion of this royal office, and it may suggest a date after 1536 when he actually succeeded to the position. The <foreign rend="italic">terminus post quem non</foreign> for composition and this transcription is presumably 1547, since Henry VIII is described with no suggestion he is now dead. </note>
                     <note> A leaf with the conclusion has been cut out, now replaced by a paper leaf (s. xix, in the foliation ‘44’), which provides the last five lines of the text from the 1577 edition, along with a few notes on the contents of the manuscript; it is all written in the script of F. J. Furnivall. </note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem>
                     <title key="work_13246" type="desc">Medical texts and recipes</title>
                     <msItem n="2" xml:id="Christ_Church_MS_417-item2">
                        <locus from="45" to="48">Fols 45–48</locus>
                        <rubric>[in upper margin] Of Inpostyms and what an Inpostym Is</rubric>
                        <incipit>A Inpostym Is Nothyng elles but a gederyng to Geder of superfluite of humores In sum membris</incipit>
                        <explicit>frome ye whych seknes owre lord kep us amen</explicit>
                        <note> Fol. 48<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>: blank.</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="3" xml:id="Christ_Church_MS_417-item3">
                        <locus from="48v" to="52">Fol. 48<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>–52</locus>
                        <rubric><note>[in upper margin]</note> Of an Inpostym flegmon</rubric>
                        <incipit>A flegmon is an hott Inpostumacion Gendryd</incipit>
                        <explicit defective="true"><locus from="51v" to="51v">[fol. 51<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>]</locus> whyll with a schynyng or a grenues abowt</explicit>
                        <note> The text is incomplete because of the loss of a leaf between fol. 49 and 50, the cutting away of the bottom half of fol. 51, and the fact that fol. 52 is a mere stub, showing only a few letters on the recto. The text is divided into sections (upper margin of fol. 50: ‘Of ye Inpostym seperois and sklirosis and of malencole’, and of fol. 51<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>: ‘A Cancer or a Carbukyll’).</note>
                        <note> Fol. 52<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>: apparently blank.</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="4" xml:id="Christ_Church_MS_417-item4">
                        <locus from="53" to="54v">Fol. 53–54<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>
                        </locus>
                        <rubric><note>[in upper margin]</note> A fystula and wat It is</rubric>
                        <incipit>A fistula is a serten dyssese</incipit>
                        <explicit>grett payn and withowt drawyng of blode if ye bone be corrupe da gloriam deo</explicit>
                        <note> Fols 53–56b<hi rend="superscript">v</hi> are in a hand, perhaps not Geene’s, which has added headings throughout early portions of the MS.</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="5" xml:id="Christ_Church_MS_417-item5">
                        <locus> Fols 55–55b<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>
                        </locus>
                        <rubric><note>[in upper margin]</note> Wat a wunde Is</rubric>
                        <incipit>A wounde is as auncient doctors Testefy is a solusyon</incipit>
                        <explicit>ye whych accedentes happyn most in Grett woundes and In Iountes</explicit>
                        <note> Incomplete through the cutting out of the bottom half of fol. 55b.</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="6" xml:id="Christ_Church_MS_417-item6">
                        <locus> Fols 56–56b<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>
                        </locus>
                        <incipit>Whereas be fore here hathe bene Rede serten chapteres of wondes and of Inpostyms vlcers and fustulles . . . Nowe we schall speke of thynges yat fall to Man a Gaynst kynde . . . Thre thynges there be yat greuis Mans kynde That is for to say Cause of seknes</incipit>
                        <explicit>hottnes and moystnes and Therefore it is goode to lay to ye brusyde plac</explicit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="7" xml:id="Christ_Church_MS_417-item7">
                        <locus from="88v">Fol. 88<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>
                        </locus>
                        <incipit>Of lignum vite Rapyd or Turnid iij. pounde and Stepe It one Nyght In fayre Runy(n)g water</incipit>
                        <note> A medical recipe, perhaps added on a leaf originally left blank.</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="8" xml:id="Christ_Church_MS_417-item8">
                        <locus from="89" to="96">Fols 89–96</locus>
                        <rubric><note>[indented title]</note> The plasters cerclothis cataplasmas and oyntmentes contaynyng In Thys bok The makyng of Them with Ther Operacions</rubric>
                        <rubric><note>[fol. 89<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>; indented title]</note> Your Graces Owne plaster</rubric>
                        <incipit>Tak The Rottes of MercheMallus wash and pyke Them Clene Then slyt them</incipit>
                        <explicit>and helythe vp withowt payne ye excoreacion</explicit>
                        <note> A table of the recipes follows the heading. The initial recipe also appears at the opening of selections printed from BL, MS Sloane 1047, at EETS es 53:220. In the contents table, most of the recipes are marked as ‘secundum M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Buttes’, for whom see the various Sloane recipes, ed. EETS es 53:223–24, 227, where Sir William Butts (d. 1545) is identified as a royal surgeon. MS Sloane 1047 is a large fair-copy recipe book of c. 1550 (it includes one recipe for Anne of Cleves and thus cannot predate 1540). The recipes are presented in categories which roughly correspond to the types of medicines distinguished in Geene’s heading here.</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="9" xml:id="Christ_Church_MS_417-item9">
                        <locus from="96v" to="108v">Fols 96<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>–108<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>
                        </locus>
                        <msItem>
                           <rubric><note>[in upper margin]</note> An Inieccyon for a fystulla In any parte of ye body</rubric>
                           <incipit>Tak a quart of ye Iuce of Maregoldes and a quart of ye Iuce of selendyne</incipit>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <rubric>[indented title] A good medesyn forto pourge ye lyuer and oyer waterry humoures both vp and downe</rubric>
                           <incipit>Tak xij. sponfull of ye Iuce of ye Rott of <note>[blue]</note> bleove flourr delyc and on sponfull</incipit>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <rubric>[fol. 97; indented title] Inplastrum pro <note>[an]</note> vlcera antiqua</rubric>
                           <incipit>Tak Neve wax withowt spott clen clarefyde frome ye hony halffe a pounde</incipit>
                        </msItem>
                        <msItem>
                           <rubric>[indented title] To mak a whytt Incarnat(i)ue</rubric>
                           <explicit>smothe and so mak It vp and mak yowr plaster therwith</explicit>
                        </msItem>
                        <note>A recipe collection. One recipe (fol. 99<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>) is ascribed to ‘My lorde marcus’. Geene has added three recipes on fol. 112<hi rend="superscript">rv</hi>.</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <note>Added texts:</note>
                        <note> Fols 57–88, 109–11<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>: all spaces originally left blank in the MS have been filled with a variety of medical notes in English and Latin, in two hands of s. xvi<hi rend="superscript">ex</hi>. The first hand here attributes specific remedies to individual medical practitioners: ‘Mr Crow’<!-- marked up below under provenance --> (fol. 57; cf. fol. 69<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>, 72<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>), ‘Mr Beddem Surgen of S Barth. hospitall’ (fol. 59<hi rend="superscript">v</hi> [presumably <persName key="person_2649">William Bedon</persName>, surgeon at St Bartholomew’s from 1569 until his death in 1581: Norman Moore, <hi rend="italic">The History of St Bartholomew’s Hospital</hi>, 2 vols (London, 1918), 2:595–6]), ‘<persName key="person_2650">Mr Bullocke</persName>’ (fol. 71<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>; fol. 78), ‘<persName key="person_2651">Mr Archibold</persName>’ (fol. 72<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>; cf. fol. 78, 82<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>, 87), ‘<persName key="person_2652">Mr Glangfeyldes</persName> Rede Balme’ (fol. 74; cf. fol. 82), ‘<persName key="person_2653">Mr Feyldes</persName> lossion’ (fol. 77), ‘<persName key="person_2654">Mr Markam of Colbrooke</persName>’ (fol. 79), ‘<persName key="person_2658">Roger Mr Alcoks servant</persName>’ (fol. 79), ‘<persName key="person_2655">Mr Galles</persName> powder’ (fol. 80<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>), ‘<persName key="person_2656">Mr Yonges</persName> pultus’ (fol. 82). At fol. 83, a date is provided when recording that a particular pultus was ‘made for <persName key="person_2657">andres</persName> 1579’. The second, and less frequently attested, writes (fol. 84<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>, the upper margin) the date ‘Apryll the vij. day 1591’; two of the recipes this hand records are said to have been ‘devised by the counsel of Mr Doctor Baylly her majesties chief phisician’, that is <persName key="person_56957225">Walter Bayley (1529–93)</persName> (fol. 84<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>), on whom, see Sarah Bakewell in <title>Oxford DNB</title>. For the significance of these references, see provenance. </note>
                     </msItem>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <p>
                     <secFol><supplied>I</supplied>n nomine</secFol><secFol>The fourtt <locus from="3" to="3">(fol. 3)</locus></secFol>
                  </p>
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="chart">
                        <support> Paper, folded in quarto. There are two watermarks: <p>A: <watermark>Roue: not in Briquet, but cf. no. 13457 (Bourges, 1509–12; Tours, 1516) and, for the three holly (?) leaves attached to the wheel, no. 13396 (Clermont-Ferrand, 1514–16)</watermark>: the sole stock of quires 1–4, eight full sheets.</p>
                           <p>B: <watermark>Pot: not in Briquet, but most closely resembles no. 12677 (Pontoise, 1523), more distantly no. 12645 (Rouen and Grenoble, 1528)</watermark>: the sole stock of the remainder, before losses 21 full sheets, with three halfsheets (in quires 6, 9, and 16) and an unwatermarked odd leaf added to quire 8.</p>
                           <p>The common paper stocks from fol. 32 suggest that the book was preserved as a (? bound) blank notebook to receive later recipes and medical materials.</p></support>
                        <extent>Fols: iv + 113 + ii. First three opening flyleaves unnumbered, fourth fol. 1; main body runs, then, from fol. 2 to 112, with 8, 55, and 56 repeated (the latter as 55b and 56b), and 44 assigned to a nineteenth-century textual supply pasted to a stub. In the original text, a contemporary foliation by the scribe, in which fols 2–43 = 1–43; in addition, a later s. xvi hand, probably the hand of added materials, has paginated fols 57<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>-88 as 1–64 (omitting 38 and 51) and 96<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>-112<hi rend="superscript">v</hi> as 1–29 (10 and 21 repeated, fol. 111<hi rend="superscript">rv</hi>, following page 27, unnumbered). The lower third of fol. 51 has been torn away, as well as nearly all of fols 52, 65, 73, 79, and 111 (all numbered leaves). <dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                              <height>280</height>
                              <width>190</width>
                           </dimensions>
                           <dimensions type="written" unit="mm">
                              <height max="195" min="190">190–95</height>
                              <width>160</width>
                           </dimensions>
                        </extent>
                        <collation> 1<hi rend="superscript">10</hi> (lacking last, removed after fol. 8bis) 2–4<hi rend="superscript">8</hi> 5<hi rend="superscript">6</hi> 6<hi rend="superscript">8</hi> (lacking sixth, fol. 44, a numbered stub, with pasted on textual supply, s. xix) 7<hi rend="superscript">8</hi> (lacking fourth, a stub before fol. 50) 8<hi rend="superscript">4</hi> (with one added at end as fol. 56b) | 9<hi rend="superscript">6</hi> (lacking third, a stub after fol. 58) 10<hi rend="superscript">8</hi> (lacking second, a stub after fol. 62) 11<hi rend="superscript">8</hi> (lacking fourth and fifth, preceding or following fol. 72) 12<hi rend="superscript">8</hi> (lacking fifth and sixth) 13<hi rend="superscript">8</hi> (lacking first, a stub before fol. 82) [to fol. 88, a production unit] | 14–15<hi rend="superscript">8</hi> 16<hi rend="superscript">10</hi> (lacking first and eight). No catchwords or signatures. In the second production unit, the sews do not always appear to correspond with the evidence of the watermarks.</collation>
                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout columns="1" writtenLines="23 24">In long lines, usually 23–24 lines to the page in the original portions. Bounded in brown crayon (vertically, for the left margin only; the writing extends to the right edge), no rules and so no pricking.</layout>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc>
                     <handNote>Written in mixed anglicana/secretary (with anglicana <hi rend="bold">a</hi> and <hi rend="bold">g</hi>, frequent anglicana <hi rend="bold">r</hi>), with the main and earliest part of the manuscript is in the hand of <persName key="person_2659" role="scr">George Geene</persName>. George Geene (or Genne) was, like the author, Thomas Vicary, a prominent member of the Company of Barber-Surgeons; he appears as no. 37 in a list of 185 freemen of Company in 1537 in the edition of Vicary cited below (244–45), first acted as a Warden in 1538, and the last reference to him as Master of the Company comes from 1560 (Sidney Young, <title>Annals of the Barber-Surgeons of London</title>(London, 1890), 5, 6, 95, 99, 102, 169, 170).</handNote>
                     <handNote>Punctuation by mid point and virgula.</handNote>
                  </handDesc>
                  <decoDesc>
                     <decoNote> Headings in the text ink; no initials or running titles.</decoNote>
                  </decoDesc>
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <binding notAfter="2000" notBefore="1900">
                        <p>Brown cloth over millboards by <orgName key="org_125" role="bnd">Maltby of Oxford</orgName> (s. xx). Sewn on four thongs. Modern paper pastedowns and endleaves, a ChCh bookplate on the front pastedown. At the front, the modern paper flyleaf, a heavy parchment leaf (probably from an older wrapper), a modern paper leaf, and an early modern paper leaf (fol. 1); at the rear, the other half of the wrapper and a modern paper flyleaf.</p>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origPlace><country key="place_7002445">England</country>, <settlement key="place_7011781">London</settlement></origPlace>
                     <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="1600" notBefore="1530">s. xvi<hi rend="superscript">2/4</hi> (1530 × 1547), with additions of s. xvi<hi rend="superscript">4/4</hi>
                     </origDate>
                  </origin>
                  <provenance> Like many physicians, Geene wrote the book for his personal consultation: ‘This was M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                     <persName key="person_2659" role="fmo">George Geene</persName> his booke Chirurgen of the Citie of London’ above an added medical recipe (fol. 1, s. xvi<hi rend="superscript">med.</hi>). If this was produced within the ambit of the Barber-Surgeons, later in the century it had moved into other hands in London: of the names mentioned in the added section only Mr Crow, if he is identifiable with <persName key="person_2661">William Crowe</persName> who was warden of the Company of Barber-Surgeons in 1579 (Young, <title>Annals</title>, 6]), was a significant figure in the Company; the Walter Bayley who is also mentioned was fellow of the College of Physicians from 1581.</provenance>
                  <provenance notAfter="1600" notBefore="1530"> There is another early signature, ‘<persName key="person_2542" role="sgn">Thomas Nicholas</persName>’ (fol. 2, upper margin, s. xvi); he is not one of the scribes of the volume and is not identifiable but it may be noted that he also wrote ‘Mary Nicholles’ at fol. 38.</provenance>
                  <provenance when="1891"> The manuscript’s subsequent descent is uncertain until the ownership inscription, ‘<persName key="person_71467450" role="fmo">F. J. Furnivall</persName> 15 May 1891’ (fol. 1), that is, the promoter of workers’ education (and rowing), and scholar of Middle English (1825–1910), who edited the text for EETS. Presumably Furnivall would have acquired the manuscript for information useful in the promised second volume of his edition (which never appeared). On him, see William Benzie, <title>Dr. F. J. Furnivall: A Victorian Scholar Adventurer</title> (Norman OK, 1983). Of his library, some of his papers and his personal book-collection were donated by his son, Percy, to the English Department of King’s College, London in 1910; he also owned some manuscripts: Lafayette College (Easton, PA) was given by Furnivall a sixteenth-century English manuscript translation of Bernard Trevisan in 1881 (Seymour de Ricci, <title>Census of medieval and Renaissance manuscrips in the United States and Canada</title>, 2 vols (New York, 1935 – 37), 2:2000), and he bequeathed to Harvard University a copy of Frère Laurent of Orléans’s <title>Somme le Roi</title> which is now Houghton Library, MS Fr. 123, ‘in memory of my dear old friend, Prof. F[rancis] James Child [1825–96]’; a digital facsimile of that manuscript is available on their website [last accessed 30<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> December 2015].</provenance>
                  <provenance notAfter="1913"> Also signed by ‘<persName key="person_79390571" role="fmo">John Munro</persName>’ (fol. 1), and with his letter of donation to Christ Church, dated 26 October 1913, and signed J. J. Munro (fol. ii); the gift is also recorded in the Library Report for that year, preserved in MS. 392. Munro (1883–1956) came up to Christ Church in 1913 but left for war service in the eastern Mediterranean; he returned and took degrees, his BA in 1920 and MA in 1921. He edited a collection of memoirs of <title>Frederick James Furnivall. A volume of personal record</title>(Oxford, 1911). He presumably held Furnivall in such admiration because of his own background as a ‘working man’ who became a mature student. He followed Furnivall’s enthusiasms by himself becoming Associate Editor to the Early English Text Society. His career divided between his wartime exploits and his employment in communications; after his retirement, he spent his time in Shakespeare studies (obituary in <title>The Times</title>, 30<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> October 1956, p. 11).</provenance>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>Ralph Hanna and David Rundle, <title>A Descriptive Catalogue of the Western Manuscripts, to c. 1600, in Christ Church, Oxford</title> (Oxford, 2017).</source>
                     </recordHist>
                     <availability>
                        <p>For enquiries relating to this manuscript please contact <ref target="https://www.chch.ox.ac.uk/library-and-archives/contacting-library">Christ Church Library</ref>.</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2017-07-01">First online publication.</change>
         <change when="2017-05-25"><persName>James Cummings</persName> Up-converted the markup using <ref target="https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl">https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl</ref></change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
      <body>
         <p/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>