<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="manuscript_3932">
   <teiHeader xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Christ Church MS. 148</title>
            <title type="collection">Christ Church MSS.</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Cataloguer</resp>
               <persName>Ralph Hanna</persName>
               <persName>David Rundle</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </publisher>
            <idno type="msID">Christ_Church_MS_148</idno>
            <idno type="collection">Christ_Church</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="Christ_Church_MS_148">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <repository>Christ Church</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">Christ Church MS. 148</idno>
               <idno type="ieArk">ark:29072/c06682x348j1</idno><idno type="crArk">ark:29072/c06395w66575</idno></msIdentifier>
               <head>John Gower, <title>Confessio amantis</title>; England (London), s. xv<hi rend="superscript">in</hi> (after 1405)</head>
               <msContents>
                  <textLang mainLang="enm" otherLangs="la">Middle English and Latin. Jeremy J. Smith has discussed the scribe’s linguistic behaviour on several occasions, first in ‘Linguistic Features of Some Fifteenth-Century Middle English Manuscripts’ in Derek Pearsall ed., <title>Manuscripts and Readers in Fifteenth-Century England</title> (Cambridge, 1983), 104–12. The scribe’s ‘native language’ appears that of northern Worcestershire (110) but always in admixture with the language of the texts he copies, especially, given his protracted experience with <title>Confessio amantis</title>, Gower’s own. See further Smith’s contributions in M. L. Samuels and J. J. Smith ed., <title>The English of Chaucer and his contemporaries</title> (Aberdeen, 1988), and the summary report of his findings communicated by Charles A. Owen, <title>Chaucer Review</title>, 23 (1988), 25–26 n5.</textLang>
                  <msItem n="1" xml:id="Christ_Church_MS_148-item1">
                     <locus from="1ra" to="207rb">Fols 1<hi rend="superscript">ra</hi>–207<hi rend="superscript">rb</hi>
                     </locus>
                     <incipit>Torpor hebes sensus scola parua labor minimusque | Causant quo minimis</incipit>
                     <incipit>Of hem þat writen vs tofore | The bookes dwelle</incipit>
                     <explicit>
                        <note>[fol. 206<hi rend="superscript">vb</hi>, the last verse]</note> testament of loue | As þou hast do þy schrift aboue</explicit>
                     <explicit>
                        <locus from="207ra" to="207ra">[fol. 207<hi rend="superscript">ra</hi>]</locus>
                        <hi rend="italic">Explicit iste liber qui transeat obsecro liber | Vt sine liuore</hi>
                     </explicit>
                     <finalRubric>
                        <locus>[fol. 207<hi rend="superscript">rb]</hi>
                        </locus> Tercius iste liber anglico sermone in Octo partes diuisus qui ad instanciam serenissimi principis dicti domini Regis anglie Ricardi secundi conficitur . . . Nomenque presentis opusculi Confessio Amantis specialiter intitulatur Explicit</finalRubric>
                     <author key="person_120695167">John Gower</author>
                     <title key="work_2706">Confessio amantis</title>
                     <note>The so-called first recension (<ref target="https://www.dimev.net/Results.php?imev=2662"><title>IMEV</title> 2662</ref>, this copy unnoted in either the original publication or the Supplement), ed. G. C. Macaulay, EETS es 81–82 (1900–1). Owing to missing leaves, the text lacks Pro.138–594, 1.83–217, 5.3994–4161, 6.1736–1893, 7.1330–1470, 8.2956*-3114*. (At least potentially, some excisions, especially those in the first and last quires, are Lancastrian expurgations of features of the first recension referring to Richard II.) Fol. 207<hi rend="superscript">v</hi> was originally blank but ruled.</note>
                     <note>Added text:</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="a" xml:id="Christ_Church_MS_148-item2">
                     <locus from="i">Fol. i</locus>
                     <incipit>Anno domini M<hi rend="superscript">lo</hi> CCCC<hi rend="superscript">mo</hi> lxxx <gap/> The yer of owr’ lord A M<hi rend="superscript">l</hi> CCCC <gap/> | The Scottis shall aryse</incipit>
                     <note> Bits of a prophecy for 148<gap quantity="1" unit="char"/>, probably verse unrecorded in IMEV, a quatrain and three lines with interspersed Latin, but the ends of all lines cut away; with the incipit, cf. <ref target="https://www.dimev.net/Results.php?imev=3510"><title>IMEV</title> 3510</ref> (<ref target="https://www.dimev.net/record.php?recID=5540"><title>DIMEV</title> 5540</ref>). Written in anglicana, s. xv<hi rend="superscript">ex</hi>.</note>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <p>
                     <secFol>As Nabugodonosor</secFol>
                  </p>
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="perg">
                        <support> Parchment (HSOS?)</support>
                        <extent>Fols: i + 207. Flyleaf is medieval parchment, cut down to the width of a column.<dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                              <height>395</height>
                              <width>270</width>
                           </dimensions>
                        </extent>
                        <collation> 1<hi rend="superscript">8</hi> (lacking second to fourth after fol. 1) 2<hi rend="superscript">8</hi> (lacking first before fol. 6) 3–14<hi rend="superscript">8</hi> 15<hi rend="superscript">8</hi> (lacking eighth after fol. 115) 16–19<hi rend="superscript">8</hi> 20<hi rend="superscript">8</hi> (lacking third after fol. 149) 21<hi rend="superscript">8</hi> (lacking last, a stub after fol. 161) 22–26<hi rend="superscript">8</hi> 27<hi rend="superscript">8</hi> (lacking sixth and last, before and after fol. 207, the last a stub). Catchwords added in an informal hand, s. xv med. No signatures.</collation>
                        <condition>The leading edges cut away on fols 1 (with loss of text), 56, 108, 126, and 130; a bit of fol. 2 cut away and the first four leaves soiled.</condition>
                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout/>
                        <layout columns="2" writtenLines="42">In double columns, each column <dimensions type="column" unit="mm">
                              <height>237</height>
                              <width>80</width>
                           </dimensions> (to the bounds, not the line ends), with 16 mm between the columns, in 42 lines to the column.</layout>
                        <layout>No signs of pricking; bounded and ruled in brown ink.</layout>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc>
                     <handNote>Written in anglicana, by the early London ‘<persName key="person_2839" role="scr">Scribe D</persName>’.</handNote>
                     <handNote>Unpunctuated.</handNote>
                     <handNote> A. I. Doyle and M. B. Parkes, ‘The Production of Copies of the Canterbury Tales and the Confessio Amantis in the Early Fifteenth Century’ in <title>Medieval Scribes, Manuscripts and Libraries</title>, 163–203 (full reference at MS 115 above), offer an extensive analysis of this unusually prolific scribe; see 164, 166, 174–82, 192–96, 200–1, 206–8 (for his apparently close relationship to ‘Scribe Delta’), 208–10. They identify as in this hand part or all of six more Gower MSS: Cambridge: Trinity College, MS R.3.2, fols 66–73<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>, 113<hi rend="superscript">rb</hi>/15–54<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>; BodL, MSS Bodley 294 and Bodley 902, fols 2–16<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>; Oxford: Corpus Christi College, MS 67 (on which see also Scott, 2:109–11 (no. 28), with discussion of the scribe’s artistic connections); New York: Columbia University Library, MS Plimpton 265; BL, MS Egerton 1991; as well as: University of London Library, MS V.88 (the ‘Ilchester’ <title>Piers Plowman</title>, C Version); BL, MS. Add. 27944, fols 2–7<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>, 1 96–335<hi rend="superscript">v</hi> (Trevisa’s <title>Bartholomæus</title>); BL, MS Harley 7334, and Oxford: Corpus Christi College, MS 198 (both <title>Canterbury Tales</title>). The scribe now appears in the on-line database developed by Profs Linne Mooney and Simon Horobin of Late Medieval English Scribes, where he is equated with John Marchaunt, and Princeton: University Library, MS Taylor 5 (<hi rend="italic">olim</hi> Phillipps 8192) added to his oeuvre. The database provides an image of fol. 102<hi rend="superscript">v</hi> [last accessed 29<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> December 2015]. The equation of Scribe D with Marchaunt is proposed in detail by Linne R. Mooney and Estelle Stubbs, <title>Scribes and the City: London Guildhall clerks and the dissemination of Middle English literature, 1375–1425</title>, York Medieval Press (Woodbridge, 2013), 38–65. </handNote>
                  </handDesc>
                  <decoDesc>
                     <decoNote> Headings and Gower’s extensive Latin passages in red, the latter written within the column. At the openings of the books, four-line champes in blue and violet with gold leaf, with vinets, bars of gold with leaves and buds in blue and violet. A decorative hierarchy within the text: at large divisions, two-line gold leaf champes with blue and violet and floral sprays; at smaller divisions, one-line lombards, blue with red flourishing, sometimes alternating with gold leaf lombards with navy flourishing. Line openings frequently ochre-slashed. A reader, s. xvi<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>, has added informal running titles to identify some stories.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote> The opening of the prologue, more ornate, but cut into and damaged, has an armorial (see <hi rend="smallcaps">provenance</hi>) with gold leaf, rather than a champe. See AT no. 388 (39).</decoNote>
                  </decoDesc>
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <binding notAfter="1500" notBefore="1400">
                        <p>Dark brown leather over bevelled wooden boards, s. xv, heavily wormed, with an outline pattern in blind. Bound on six thongs, taken straight into the board, as in Pollard’s Figure 4, but not staggered. The upper board has slots for two straps, but no trace of them; impressions and nail holes from the plates to which they were clasped, about 60 mm in from the edge of the lower board. Evidence of a chain staple at Watson’s position 6, presumably a ChCh intervention (see Appendix I and below). Pastedowns modern paper, a ChCh bookplate on the front pastedown.</p>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origPlace><country key="place_7002445">England</country> (<settlement key="place_7011781">London</settlement>)</origPlace>
                     <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="1425" notBefore="1400">s. xv<hi rend="superscript">in</hi>
                     </origDate>
                  </origin>
                  <provenance> The manuscript was prepared for a younger son of Henry IV, probably <persName key="person_2485" role="fmo">Thomas, duke of Clarence</persName>, identified by the royal arms, including ‘France modern’ (thus post-1405) and with a mark of cadency, in the opening initial (fol. 1). The scribe produced another <title>Confessio</title> manuscript with a similar history of ownership, if not patronage: BodL, MS Bodley 294, with erased ownership inscription of Thomas’s brother, Humfrey, duke of Gloucester; see Doyle and Parkes, 208. Jeanne E. Krochalis, ‘The Books and Reading of Henry V and his Circle’, <title>Chaucer Review</title>, 23 (1988), 50–77 at 57, places the manuscript in the wider context of early Lancastrian book-ownership.</provenance>
                  <provenance> A variety of late medieval and early modern indications of ownership or use occurs: (a) ‘<persName key="person_2669" role="sgn">Champer</persName> (?pro)<gap quantity="3" unit="char"/> (fol. 163, upper margin, washed, s. xv); (b) ‘Nouerunt vniuersie per presentes me <persName key="person_2670" role="sgn">Iohannem hill de Okehampton</persName>’ (fol. 207<hi rend="superscript">rb</hi> following the explicit, s. xv<hi rend="superscript">ex</hi>); (c) ‘This is george coper his hande Record of m’ ni\c/colas amen<gap quantity="1" unit="char"/>’ (fol. 207<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>, amid a mass of pentrails, verses, and drawings, s. xvi<hi rend="superscript">in</hi>). Two small signatures of comparable age ‘<persName key="person_2671" role="fmo">gerg coper</persName> his boke’ and ‘<persName key="person_2672" role="fmo">roger coper</persName> his booke’ (along with several ‘george’ signatures, the front and rear pastedowns). Cf. ‘by me Georg<gap/> | coper’ (fol. 179, s. xvi). </provenance>
                  <provenance> More extensive still are indications of ownership by Cottells: ‘By me <persName key="person_2673" role="sgn">markes Cottell</persName>’ (fol. 132 upper margin, s. xvi<hi rend="superscript">med</hi>); ‘M: Cottell’ also wrote verse ‘The wilde and coulte that Runs in pasture . . .’ and ‘god saue the Quene Elizabeth’ (fol. 175<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>, upper margin); and the verses again fol. 207<hi rend="superscript">rb</hi> (reading ‘wild and wanton’, signed ‘by me markes cottell’). Also ‘Mr. <gap quantity="3" unit="char"/>
                     <persName key="person_2674" role="sgn">Edward Cottell</persName>’, as well as signing his name with Greek lambdas below (the front pastedown, s. xvi/xvii). Of comparable age is the set of notes ‘a remembraunce of such corne as is severall by itself in every close’ (across the foot of fol. 267). Various members of a Devon family of Cottells came up to Oxford c. 1560–1620, but none with these Christian names (<title>AO</title>, 1:333). An early-modern Devon location for this manuscript would suggest it had stayed in the same locality as when it was owned by John Hill (note (b) mentioned above). </provenance>
                  <provenance> Donated by <persName key="person_2675" role="fmo">Henry Byam</persName>: ‘ex dono Henrici Byam’ (fol. 206<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>, lower margin, s. xvii). Cf. also ‘O god my god wherfor doste thu forsak me vtterly . . .’, four lines (fol. 176<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>, upper margin, s. xvii<hi rend="superscript">in</hi>). Henry Byam came up from East Luckham (Somerset), matriculating at Exeter College in 1597/8 and was elected a Student of Christ Church in December 1599; he received four degrees: BA in 1602, MA in 1605, BD in 1612, and (on Charles I’s orders) DD in 1642/3. A royalist divine, he was rector of East Luckham from 1614 and of Selworthy from 1618 until he was sequestered in 1647. Additionally, he was a canon of Exeter in 1632 and of Wells in 1660 and died in 1669 aged about 89 (<title>AO</title>, 225; J. Sears McGee in <title>Oxford DNB</title>, noting further books owned by Byam). His link with Exeter is suggestive of how he came by this book which had been in that diocese. </provenance>
                  <provenance> The manuscript is not recorded in the Donor’s Register so the date of its donation is uncertain but the evidence of its chain staple is suggestive: it in the same position and of the same dimensions as MS 146, which was donated in 1629. The first ChCh record of its presence only comes, however, with the 1676 Catalogue where it has the shelfmark C.3 (see Appendix I). There is a slight difference with what appears in the volume itself where, at the very left centre of the front pastedown, the relevant shelfmark is given as ‘C.2’, though the number may be written over an erasure. At top left of the same pastedown and at the top left of fol. 1, the New Library’s ‘E.5’ (see Appendix IV).</provenance>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>Ralph Hanna and David Rundle, <title>A Descriptive Catalogue of the Western Manuscripts, to c. 1600, in Christ Church, Oxford</title> (Oxford, 2017).</source>
                     </recordHist>
                     <availability>
                        <p>For enquiries relating to this manuscript please contact <ref target="https://www.chch.ox.ac.uk/library-and-archives/contacting-library">Christ Church Library</ref>.</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2017-07-01">First online publication.</change>
         <change when="2017-05-25"><persName>James Cummings</persName> Up-converted the markup using <ref target="https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl">https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl</ref></change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
      <body>
         <p/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>