<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="manuscript_3925">
   <teiHeader xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Christ Church MS. 123</title>
            <title type="collection">Christ Church MSS.</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Cataloguer</resp>
               <persName>Ralph Hanna</persName>
               <persName>David Rundle</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </publisher>
            <idno type="msID">Christ_Church_MS_123</idno>
            <idno type="collection">Christ_Church</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="Christ_Church_MS_123">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <repository>Christ Church</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">Christ Church MS. 123</idno>
               <idno type="ieArk">ark:29072/c04t64gm826r</idno><idno type="crArk">ark:29072/c04q77fq98wp</idno></msIdentifier>
               <head><title key="work_14289" type="desc">Register of writs</title>; England, s. xiv<hi rend="superscript">in</hi>.</head>
               <!-- check: display and indexing of this ok? -->
               <msContents>
                  <textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>
                  <msItem n="1" xml:id="Christ_Church_MS_123-item1">
                     <locus from="1" to="189v">Fols 1–189<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>
                     </locus>
                     <incipit>
                        <supplied>E</supplied>dwardus dei gracia Rex Anglie . . . Balliuis suis de tali loco salutem Precipimus vobis quod sine dilacione plenum Rectum teneatis Willielmo de Sutton</incipit>
                     <explicit>vel perdendum in loquela que est coram vobis in Hustenge nostro london</explicit>
                     <note> A register of writs, listed (like our MS 103 (item 19), but not our MS 102) by de Haas and Hall, xxiii. Only seven lines written on fol. 189<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>; this leaf and the remainder were originally blank; fol. 190 has been bounded and ruled.</note>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <p>
                     <secFol>solidatis</secFol>
                  </p>
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="perg">
                        <support>Parchment (FSOS).</support>
                        <extent>Fols: ix + 190 + iii (numbered fols 191–93). First flyleaf at front and last two at back paper added with <hi rend="smallcaps">binding</hi> (fol. i, 192–93); all others medieval parchment. <dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                              <height>125</height>
                              <width>90</width>
                           </dimensions>
                           <dimensions type="written" unit="mm">
                              <height>94</height>
                              <width>53</width>
                           </dimensions>
                           <note>(with a column 12mm wide along the leading edge to identify the writs)</note>
                        </extent>
                        <collation> 1–23<hi rend="superscript">8</hi> 24<hi rend="superscript">8</hi> (lacking seventh and last, both blanks). Catchwords just right of the inner bounding line, at very foot of page with several cropped. A variety of signature systems, all fragmentary, with most of the signs cut away. From the survivors, all leaves in the first half of each quire were signed /-//// and the fifth leaf marked with a cross, in red and blue ink and brown crayon. Some quires also have letter signatures: quires 1–10 are signed on the first recto and last verso a-k, and quires 19 and 23 are signed with letters, up to aaa and to dddd, respectively (quire 22 was ignored in this sequence).</collation>
                        <condition>The upper corners of leaves after fol. 175 have been eaten away, but without text loss.</condition>
                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout columns="1" writtenLines="23 24">In long lines, usually 24 (sometimes 23) lines to the page.</layout>
                        <layout>No signs of pricking; bounded and ruled in brown crayon, in later portions lead. Double vertical borders, that to left of text reserved for paraph marks; text often extends to the outer of the two right binding lines; all borders and lines extend to the edge of the page.</layout>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc>
                     <handNote>Written in a small anglicana formata. </handNote>
                     <handNote>Punctuation by occasional point only.</handNote>
                  </handDesc>
                  <decoDesc>
                     <decoNote> At the opening of the text, a nine-line space for an initial unfilled. At the opening of individual writs or chapters, alternate red and blue paraphs; the titles for each in the marginal column in text ink, introduced by a paraph of the other colour. In the first fifteen leaves, running titles to identify the writs, added in anglicana, s. xv<hi rend="superscript">2</hi>.</decoNote>
                  </decoDesc>
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <binding notAfter="2000" notBefore="1900">
                        <p>Millboards with rebacked spine in tan leather, half morocco, s. xx. Pastedowns modern paper, a ChCh bookplate on the front pastedown. The first parchment flyleaf at front and that at back (fol. ii and 191) both show signs of having been a pastedown in an earlier binding.</p>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origPlace><country key="place_7002445">England</country></origPlace>
                     <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="1310" notBefore="1300">s. xiv<hi rend="superscript">in</hi>
                     </origDate>
                  </origin>
                  <provenance> It is not possible to reconstruct the early history of this volume. There is a name cancelled at fol. iv, and two erased ownership inscriptions at fol. 189<hi rend="superscript">v</hi> (following the explicit). From the seventeenth century, there is a name ‘<persName key="person_2603" role="sgn">John Rakeby</persName>[?]’ at fol. vi. The first fully identifiable owner writes his name at fol. v: ‘Æ Lanc<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> lee his Booke 1671 | <persName key="person_2604" role="fmo">Eldred lancelott lee</persName>’. He has also signed on fol. 190, above an erased ownership inscription; and on fol. 191. On fol. 190, he follows his name with ‘qui ego hoc petiuit tam pro regni quam pro seipso sequitur ver<gap quantity="3" unit="char"/> et desendit <gap/>‘, the remainder abraded away. In addition, at fol. 189<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>, he writes ‘Rogerus hope vnus clericorum francisci wythini in officio placitorum’, and ‘Iohannes Yonge seruiens <gap/>[the rest overwritten with flourishes]’ (the latter’s name also at fol. 190<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>). Eldred Lancelot Lee (Eldred presumably after the eleventh-century bishop of Worcester in whose diocese the Lee family’s ancestral home of Coton Hall, Shropshire, sat) is a known legal clerk from the reign of Charles II: J. S. Cockburn, ‘Seventeenth-Century Clerks of Assize – Some Anonymous Members of the Legal Profession’, <title>The American Journal of Legal History</title>, 13 (1969), 315–332 (328). The notes mentioning Hope and Yonge appear to be intended as aide-memoires concerning legal staff; that concerning Hope mentions the Tory judge Sir Francis Wythens (on whom see Eveline Cruickshanks in B. D. Henning, <title>The History of Parliament: the House of Commons, 1660–1690</title>(Cambridge, 1983), 3 vols, 3:783–84 and Stuart Handley in <title>Oxford DNB</title>). In 1686, Wythens and Eldred Lancelot Lee sat together on the Maidstone Assize: J. S. Cockburn, <title>Calendar of Assize Records: Kent Indictments, Charles II, 1676–88</title>(Woodbridge, 1997), 243 (no. 1261). It is reasonable to imagine that Lee carried this pocket-sized <foreign rend="italic">registrum brevium</foreign> with him.</provenance>
                  <provenance> The earliest indication of ChCh ownership is the note: ‘The Dean at the request of D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Wheeler one of the Chaplains of Christ Church deposited this Book in the Library June 20 1822’ (fol. ix). The Dean in question was <persName key="person_78639115">Charles H. Hall</persName>; he matriculated at Christ Church in 1779, and received four degrees: his BA in 1783, MA in 1786, BD in 1794, and DD in 1800. He was a canon of Christ Church from 1799, the Regius Professor of Divinity 1807–9, and Dean from 1809 until 1824, when he moved to the deanery of Durham; he died in 1827 aged 70 (<title>AOmod</title>, 587; J. F. A. Mason in <title>Oxford DNB</title>). Charles Wheeler was chaplain of Christ Church 1820–31 and died in 1835, aged 38 (<title>AOmod</title>, 1534). The volume includes the old ChCh shelfmark ‘Arch Sup C.25’ (pencil, fol. iv<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>), suggesting that this was added to the end of the C section which, in the New Library Catalogue, ended at 24 (see Appendix IV).</provenance>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>Ralph Hanna and David Rundle, <title>A Descriptive Catalogue of the Western Manuscripts, to c. 1600, in Christ Church, Oxford</title> (Oxford, 2017).</source>
                     </recordHist>
                     <availability>
                        <p>For enquiries relating to this manuscript please contact <ref target="https://www.chch.ox.ac.uk/library-and-archives/contacting-library">Christ Church Library</ref>.</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2017-07-01">First online publication.</change>
         <change when="2017-05-25"><persName>James Cummings</persName> Up-converted the markup using <ref target="https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl">https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl</ref></change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
      <body>
         <p/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>