<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="manuscript_3948">
   <teiHeader xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Christ Church MS. 344</title>
            <title type="collection">Christ Church MSS.</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Cataloguer</resp>
               <persName>Ralph Hanna</persName>
               <persName>David Rundle</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </publisher>
            <idno type="msID">Christ_Church_MS_344</idno>
            <idno type="collection">Christ_Church</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="Christ_Church_MS_344">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <repository>Christ Church</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">Christ Church MS. 344 = Christ Church Archives, D&amp;C vi.c.4</idno>
               <idno type="ieArk">ark:29072/c09c67wm14gj</idno><idno type="crArk">ark:29072/c09880vq315s</idno></msIdentifier>
               <head>Documents relating to the early history of Oxford Cathedral and of Cardinal College; England, 1542 (I), s. xvi<hi rend="superscript">med</hi> (II, III), with item 6 dated 1529</head>
               <msContents>
                  <textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>
                  <msItem>
                     <locus from="i">fol. i</locus>
                     <note>Table of contents, s. xix, in the hands of the foliation.</note>
                     <note>fol. i<hi rend="superscript">v</hi> – iv: blank</note>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <p>
                     <secFol>howse</secFol><secFol>The manor <locus>(II: fol. 17)</locus></secFol><secFol>nuper prioratus <locus>(III: fol. 27)</locus></secFol>
                  </p>
                  <p>A volume composed of three separate fascicules, with, in addition, three loose leaves, and one document glued to the pages.</p>
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc>
                        <extent>Fols: iv + 56 + iii. All flyleaves are paper (watermark: <watermark>fleur-de-lys above a coat-of-arms with double bend, and ‘CDG’, ie stock of Claude de George (d. 1683)</watermark>).</extent>
                        <foliation>A pen foliation, s. xix, a top right, numbers placed in brackets. In Manuscript III, also a pen pagination, at top outer corner (fol. 26v = ‘2’; fol. 44 = ‘37’).</foliation>
                     </supportDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <binding notAfter="1700" notBefore="1675">
                        <p>Light brown reversed calf over millboards with plain rectangular design, with some dark patches perhaps suggesting it was originally gold tooled, s. xvii<hi rend="superscript">4/4</hi>. Sewn on six thongs. At top of spine, written in black ink: ‘Char-|ters’. Below that, in upper-most compartment of spine, a red leather slip with in gold letters: ‘Charters &amp;c.’ In next compartment down, the remains of a paper slip. In its material, design, red slip and note in pen, this binding is very similar to our D&amp;C vi.c.1 and 2 (= MSS 340 and 338), and thus can be attributed to <persName key="person_2624" role="bnd">Richard Sedgley</persName> and tentatively dated to the 1680s (see D&amp;C vi.c.1, binding).</p>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
                  <accMat>At both front and back, a parchment pastedown, added to the binding at a later date. Each pastedown provides a complete folio, the two folios being consecutive, from one Lectionary, written in textura (England, s. xv<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>), 413mm x 282mm; written space: 262mm x 240mm, in double columns of 47 lines (110mm wide); full ruling in red. The text provides readings for the feasts of 23<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> and 24<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> July (St Apollinaris and Christina) and shows signs of post-Break with Rome ‘cleansing’ of the text by the erasure of ‘pape’ in the title of a Homily of St Gregory.</accMat>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <provenance>Top of front pastedown, in pencil (s. xx<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>): ‘Belonging to the Chapter of Christ Church, Oxford’. Patently, the volume was constructed by bringing together documents of relevance to the foundation’s history, and held in the Chapter House. Two of the documents – items 3 and 5 – were already bound together before this codex was created: an entry in the Disbursement Books from the summer of 1598 records the taking up to London ‘of our brode booke containing our dotacion and foundacion’ (ChCh Archives, xii.b.41, fol. 58). Presumably, the collection of documents as it now stands was brought together at the time of the present binding, when other manuscripts held by the Cathedral were receiving similar attention. The parchment pastedowns, however, were most likely added later; their origin is unclear: they do not relate to any of the fragments preserved in our MS 378.</provenance>
                  <provenance>This manuscript is identifiable in the 1771 catalogue of books in the Chapter House as number 6, ‘A Book of Charters and Donations of Henry the Eighth and Queen Mary. Fol.’: ChCh Archives, D&amp;C iv.a.1, fol. 12, and see the Headnote to Chapter House Manuscripts. </provenance>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>Ralph Hanna and David Rundle, <title>A Descriptive Catalogue of the Western Manuscripts, to c. 1600, in Christ Church, Oxford</title> (Oxford, 2017).</source>
                     </recordHist>
                     <availability>
                        <p>For enquiries relating to this manuscript please contact <ref target="https://www.chch.ox.ac.uk/library-and-archives/contacting-library">Christ Church Library</ref>.</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
               </additional>
               <msPart>
                  <msIdentifier>
                     <altIdentifier>
                        <idno>Manuscript I = fol. 1–15</idno>
                     </altIdentifier>
                  </msIdentifier>
                  <msContents>
                     <textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>
                     <msItem n="1">
                        <locus from="1" to="14">Fol. 1–14</locus>
                        <incipit><supplied>H</supplied> Octavus dei gratia Anglie Francie et hibernie Rex fidei defensor et in terra ecclesie anglicane et hibernice supremum caput. Omnibus ad quos presentes littere pervenerint salutem. Sciatis quod nos de gratia nostra speciali ac ex certa scientia et mero motu nostris dedimus et concessimus ac per presentes damus et concedimus decano et capitulo ecclesie cathedralis christi et beate marie virginis de Oxenford omnia illa maneria nostra de Arnecote Tewe parva</incipit>
                        <explicit>has litteras nostras fieri fecimus patentes Teste me ipso apud haveringe quintodecimo die Septembris Anno Regni nostri tricesimo quarto. | Marten | Per breve de privato sigillo et de dato predicto aucthoritate parliamenti. | M</explicit>
                        <title>Charter of <persName key="person_172419710">Henry VIII</persName></title>
                        <note>A copy of the royal grant of lands to the <orgName key="org_140757625">Dean and Chapter</orgName> of Oxford’s first Cathedral (the former Oseney Abbey), dated 15<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> September 1542. It is calendared, from TNA, C 66/715, m 12, at <title>L&amp;P</title>, 17, no. 881 (26). The original despatched to Oxford, written in a large gothic bookhand, illuminated at its first line and in the initial, but with the seal now missing, is held in Christ Church Archives as DY 7 [listed by N. Denholm-Young, <title>Cartulary of the Mediaeval Archives of Christ Church</title> (Oxford, 1931), 214 (no. 7), with, by <foreign rend="italic">lapsus calami</foreign>, the reference to <title>L&amp;P</title> given as no. 881 (25) rather than no. 881 (26)]. </note>
                        <note>Fol. 15: blank</note>
                        <note>There are annotations noting the place-names, in several hands (s. xvii; fol. 1–7, 11–13<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>).</note>
                     </msItem>
                  </msContents>
                  <physDesc>
                     <objectDesc form="codex">
                        <supportDesc material="perg">
                           <support>Parchment (HSOS)</support>
                           <extent>
                              <dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                                 <height>295</height>
                                 <width>370</width>
                              </dimensions>
                              <dimensions type="written" unit="mm">
                                 <height>240</height>
                                 <width>163</width>
                              </dimensions>
                           </extent>
                           <collation>1–3<hi rend="superscript">4</hi> 4<hi rend="superscript">4</hi> (last removed after fol. 15). No catchwords; small quire signatures (1–4) written just below bottom right of the written space.</collation>
                        </supportDesc>
                        <layoutDesc>
                           <layout columns="1" writtenLines="38">38 long lines (above top line).</layout>
                           <layout>Bounded and ruled in plummet with single borders, all borderlines extending to the edge.</layout>
                           <layout>Signs of full pricking, and a prick-hole at each of the four corners of the written space.</layout>
                        </layoutDesc>
                     </objectDesc>
                     <handDesc>
                        <handNote>Written in one formal secretary script, dated 1542 and with, in display capitals, the name of ‘Marten’, but whether it is unclear that this is the scribe or simply copied from the original, DY 7 (see below).</handNote>
                     </handDesc>
                     <decoDesc>
                        <decoNote>An outline in plummet of the majuscule ‘H’ at fol. 1, within which is drawn the outline of an empty-faced king seated on a throne with sceptre and orb.</decoNote>
                     </decoDesc>
                  </physDesc>
                  <history>
                     <origin>
                        <origPlace><country key="place_7002445">England</country></origPlace>
                        <origDate calendar="Gregorian" when="1542">1542</origDate>
                     </origin>
                  </history>
               </msPart>
               <msPart>
                  <msIdentifier>
                     <altIdentifier>
                        <idno>Manuscript II = fol. 16- 24</idno>
                     </altIdentifier>
                  </msIdentifier>
                  <msContents>
                     <textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>
                     <msItem n="2">
                        <locus from="16" to="24v">Fol. 16–24<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>
                        </locus>
                        <rubric><note>[top left]</note> Primo Octobris Anno Regis H viii xxxviiiº. <note>[top centre]</note> Landes assygne by the kyngs maiestie vnto | thys his highnes Newe erected Cathedrall Church in | Oxforde. |</rubric>
                        <incipit>The scite of the late Colledge of saynte Frydisdwides within the Cytie of Oxforde</incipit>
                        <explicit><locus from="22v" to="22v">[fol. 22<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>]</locus> The some totall of the possessions appointed by the kings ma<hi rend="superscript">ti</hi> vnto his highnes Cahtredrall Church in Oxford is } m<hi rend="superscript">l</hi> m<hi rend="superscript">l</hi> cc iiii<hi rend="superscript">xx</hi> iii li xviij s vijd | ob q. d. | Deducted for a Rent to be paid yerelie – in all things as other viccars have.</explicit>
                        <title>Valuation of lands granted to <orgName key="org_140757625">Christ Church</orgName></title>
                        <note>A listing of the values and rents of the lands given to Christ Church at the time of foundation. The same information, though in a different layout, is presented in a mid-sixteenth-century volume which is now Christ Church Archives, DY 11 [Denholm-Young, <title>Mediaeval Archives</title>, 214 (11)]; that volume is entitled on the limp front cover ‘H Particular and ValeWe of all the landes granted to the Deane and Chapter of Christ Church Oxon in the 38<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> yeare of King Hen: 8. now remaininge amongst the Records of the late Courte of Augmentation.’</note>
                        <note>Between fol. 24<hi rend="superscript">v</hi> and fol. 25 are kept loose three paper leaves (c. 420 × 320mm; watermark: <watermark>hand with star above, ‘RA’ in palm, below which a bunch of grapes; no match in Briquet or Piccard</watermark>), originally folded horizontally in four, now only in half, with, written on one side of each leaf, the draft of the final sections of item 2: that is the sum total, the rental deductions and the concluding set of instructions.</note>
                        <note>Fol. 25 &amp; 25bis: blank, paper of same manufacture as flyleaves.</note>
                     </msItem>
                  </msContents>
                  <physDesc>
                     <objectDesc form="codex">
                        <supportDesc material="perg">
                           <support>Parchment (HSOS)</support>
                           <extent>
                              <dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                                 <height>375</height>
                                 <width>295</width>
                              </dimensions>
                           </extent>
                           <collation>1<hi rend="superscript">4</hi> 2<hi rend="superscript">4</hi> (with one at end added as fol. 24). No catchwords or signatures.</collation>
                        </supportDesc>
                        <layoutDesc>
                           <layout columns="1" writtenLines="26">Writing area: a central text-block of variable size (<dimensions type="written" unit="mm">
                                 <height max="245" min="240">240/245</height>
                                 <width max="178" min="155">155/178</width>
                              </dimensions>), with numbers written in the right margin and some text in left margin; c. 26 long lines, not including the blank lines between each entry.</layout>
                           <layout> No signs of ruling.</layout>
                        </layoutDesc>
                     </objectDesc>
                     <handDesc>
                        <handNote>Written throughout in one secretary script, but at two stages, with fol. 22v (l. 8) – fol. 24v being written in a thinner and smaller version of the script.</handNote>
                        <handNote>Throughout Henry VIII is described as if he were alive, suggesting but not definitely proving that this fascicule was written between 1st October 1546 and 28th January 1547.</handNote>
                     </handDesc>
                     <decoDesc>
                        <decoNote>Large swag initial and extended ascenders on the first line of the list. Each entry opens with the first words in bastard secretary and is marked off to the right by a thick square bracket.</decoNote>
                     </decoDesc>
                  </physDesc>
                  <history>
                     <origin>
                        <origPlace><country key="place_7002445">England</country></origPlace>
                        <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="1560" notBefore="1540">s. xvi<hi rend="superscript">med</hi></origDate>
                     </origin>
                  </history>
               </msPart>
               <msPart>
                  <msIdentifier>
                     <altIdentifier>
                        <idno>Manuscript III = fol. 26–56</idno>
                     </altIdentifier>
                  </msIdentifier>
                  <msContents>
                     <textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>
                     <msItem n="3">
                        <locus from="26" to="43">Fol. 26–43</locus>
                        <incipit>Henricus Octauus dei gratia Anglie Francie et hibernie Rex fidei defensor et in terra ^ecclesia^ Anglicane et hibernice supremum caput Omnibus ad Quos presentes litere pervenerint Salutem. Sciatis qud nos de gratia nostra speciali ac ex <supplied>cext</supplied> certa scientia et mero motu nostris dedimus et confessimus ac per presentes damus et concedimus decano et Capitulo ecclesie Cathedralis christi Oxon ex fundacione nostra</incipit>
                        <explicit>fieri fecimus patentes Teste me ipso ^apud^ westmonasterium <supplied>un</supplied> undecimo die decembris Anno regni <supplied>nostril</supplied> nostri trigesimo octavo.</explicit>
                        <title>Charter of <persName key="person_172419710">Henry VIII</persName></title>
                        <note>The Royal Charter of Dotation to <orgName key="org_140757625">Christ Church</orgName>, dated 11<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> December 1546. Calendared, from TNA, C 66/793, m 19 at <title>L&amp;P</title>, 21:2, no. 648 (25). The original sent to the foundation survives in Christ Church Archives as DY 10 (Denholm-Young, <title>Mediaeval Archives</title>, 214 (10), noting that, by <foreign rend="italic">lapsus calami</foreign>, the date is erroneously recorded as 4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> rather than 11<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> December). Another mid-sixteenth-century copy is held in the Archives as MS Estates 145, fol. 110–128.</note>
                        <note>Fol. 43<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>: blank</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="4">
                        <locus from="44" to="46v">Fol. 44–46<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>
                        </locus>
                        <incipit>Maria die gratia Anglie Francie et hibernie regina fidei defensor Omnibus ad quos presentes littere pervenerint Salutem Sciatis quod nos de gratia nostra speciali ac ex certa scientia et mero motu nostris dedimus et concessimus et per presentes pro nobis heredibus et successoribus nostris damus et concedimus Decano et Capitulo Ecclesie Cathedralis christi Oxon et fundacione Regis henrici octavi totam illam Rectoriam et ecclesiam nostram de Tringe</incipit>
                        <explicit>fieri fecimus patentes Teste me ipsa apud Castrum de Farncham septimo die Julij anno regni nostri secundo per breve de privato sigillo et de dato predicto auctoritate parliamenti.</explicit>
                        <title>Charter of <persName key="person_57408108">Mary I</persName></title>
                        <note>A copy of the Royal Charter donating to <orgName key="org_140757625">Christ Church</orgName> the rectory of <placeName key="place_7011889">Tring</placeName> (Herts) on 7<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> July 1554. Further materials concerning this donation, including a transcript of the Charter made on 29<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> March 1732 not from our copy but from that in the ‘Rolls Chapel’, are held in Christ Church Archives, MS Estates 35. </note>
                        <note>fol. 47: blank</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="5">
                        <locus from="48" to="55">fol. 48–55</locus>
                        <incipit>Henricus Octavus dei gratia Anglie Francie et hibernie Rex fidei Defensor et in terra Anglicane et hibernice supremum caput Omnibus ad quos presentes littere pervenerint Salutem. Cum immensa dei bonitas atque benignitas</incipit>
                        <explicit>fieri fecimus patentes Teste me ipso apud westmonestarium Quarto die Novembris Anno regni nostri tricesimo octavo | per breve de privato sigillo et de dato predicto auctoritate parliamenti</explicit>
                        <title>Charter of <persName key="person_172419710">Henry VIII</persName></title>
                        <note>A copy of the Charter of Foundation of <orgName key="org_140757625">Christ Church</orgName>, dated 4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> November 1546. The original Charter sent to the foundation, with the seal still attached, is held in Christ Church Archives as DY 9 (Denholm-Young, <title>Mediaeval Archives</title>, 214 (9)).</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="6">
                        <note>Fol. 55<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>-56: blank but glued to them a letter patent (parchment, 310mm x 522mm) of <persName key="person_9837370">Cardinal Lorenzo Campeggi</persName> conceding to <persName key="person_22937889">Thomas Wolsey</persName> and to his foundation wood and materials for building Cardinal College, dated 22 September 1529 at London, signed by Campeggi and by ‘<persName key="person_2648">Tho. Martin</persName>’.</note>
                     </msItem>
                  </msContents>
                  <physDesc>
                     <objectDesc form="codex">
                        <supportDesc material="mixed">
                           <support>All but item 6: Paper (watermark throughout: <watermark>crescent and motto</watermark>).</support>
                           <extent>
                              <dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                                 <height max="420" min="415">415–20</height>
                                 <width max="285" min="275">275–85</width>
                              </dimensions>
                           </extent>
                           <collation>Formed of bifolia, with signs of one continuous series of signatures at bottom left (eg fol. 32 = ‘4’, fol. 34 = ‘5’).</collation>
                        </supportDesc>
                        <layoutDesc>
                           <layout columns="1" writtenLines="54 58">Writing area: <dimensions type="written" unit="mm">
                                 <height>373</height>
                                 <width>150</width>
                              </dimensions>, with frequent scribal annotations in the left-hand margin; 54 / 58 long lines, with text often written not on the line but through the line.</layout>
                           <layout>Dry-ruled with borders extending to edge of folios and a further set of vertical binding lines c. 48mm from text-block.</layout>
                        </layoutDesc>
                     </objectDesc>
                     <handDesc>
                        <handNote>Written in one formal secretary script.</handNote>
                     </handDesc>
                  </physDesc>
                  <history>
                     <origin>
                        <origPlace><country key="place_7002445">England</country></origPlace>
                        <origDate calendar="Gregorian" cert="high" notAfter="1560" notBefore="1529">s. xvi<hi rend="superscript">med</hi>, with item 6 dated 1529</origDate>
                     </origin>
                  </history>
               </msPart>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2025-04-22"><persName>Sebastian Dows-Miller</persName>. Regularised measurement formats.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>