<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="manuscript_3949">
   <teiHeader xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Christ Church MS. 372</title>
            <title type="collection">Christ Church MSS.</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Cataloguer</resp>
               <persName>Ralph Hanna</persName>
               <persName>David Rundle</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </publisher>
            <idno type="msID">Christ_Church_MS_372</idno>
            <idno type="collection">Christ Church</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="Christ_Church_MS_372">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <repository>Christ Church</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">Christ Church MS. 372 = ChCh Archives, DP iv.b.3</idno>
               <idno type="ieArk">ark:29072/c09k41zc8139</idno><idno type="crArk">ark:29072/c09g54xg97s7</idno></msIdentifier>
               <head>Balliol College Deed concerning lands transferred to Cardinal College; England (Oxford), 1530</head>
               <msContents>
                  <textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>
                  <msItem n="1">
                     <incipit><supplied>Uniuersis cristi</supplied> Fidelibus ad quos hoc presens Scriptum peruenit Willelmo White sacre theologie bacularius magister [collegii] de Balliolo ... Cum nuper per quamdam Cartam — magistro Johanni Higdon decano Collegii Thomae Wolse[y cardinalis] Eboracensis vulgo appellati Cardynalls College in alma achademia Oxonie</incipit>
                     <explicit>alter in premissis fecerint vel [fecerit in aliquo premissorum ...] magistri et scolaris huic presenti teste [...] quinto die Octobris Anno regni domini Henric[i ...]</explicit>
                     <title>Charter of <orgName key="org_134825322">Balliol College</orgName></title>
                     <note>Much of text is heavily rubbed to the point of illegibility, but enough remains to identify this as a copy of Balliol College Archives, B. 9. 18, dated 5<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> October 1530, and printed in H. E. Salter, <title>The Oxford Deeds of Balliol College</title>, OHS 64 (1913), 128–29. The deed concerns the aftermath of Balliol’s sale to Wolsey’s foundation in 1526 of their tenement of ‘London College’, also known as <placeName key="place_9">Burnel’s Inn</placeName>, which stood to the north of Frideswide Lane (so south of and on the present location of the north range of Tom Quad); they did not receive the expected recompense and attempted to regain possession by this deed. On this incident see Salter, 94–98, and cf. Denholm-Young, <title>Cartulary</title>, 196 (MM. 50 and MM. 50A, presently deposited in the Bodleian as MS. D.D. ChCh c. 40). </note>
                     <note>This copy is not in the same hand as that held in Balliol. Presumably, considering the provenance as discussed below, ours is a fair copy made for <orgName key="org_140757625" role="fmo">Cardinal College</orgName>, a few days before its founder’s death, when the fate of his College was uncertain.</note>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="perg">
                        <support> Parchment</support>
                        <extent>Single leaf <dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                              <height>253</height>
                              <width>382</width>
                           </dimensions></extent>
                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout writtenLines="25">25 lines of text; verso blank.</layout>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc>
                     <handNote>Written in ‘court hand’, i.e. formal legal anglicana.</handNote>
                  </handDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origPlace><country key="place_7002445">England</country> (<settlement key="place_7011931">Oxford</settlement>)</origPlace>
                     <origDate calendar="Gregorian" cert="high" when="1530">1530</origDate>
                  </origin>
                  <provenance>The typescript supplement to Kitchin, produced in 1983/84 by Tessa Webber, describes the provenance as having been ‘given by <orgName key="org_136008125" role="fmo">Corpus Christi College</orgName>, Oxford in 1941. Formerly used as a cover for a bundle of Court Rolls for the Manor of Heyford ad pontem, made up by c. 1540’. The date of donation is confirmed by the Library Records, LR 60, p. 115. However, J. G. Milne and John H. Harvey, ‘The Building of Cardinal College, Oxford’, <title>Oxoniensia</title>, 8 (1943), 137–53 at 138n give a slightly different date for its use as a wrapper. Noting the ‘neglected condition of the Cardinal College deeds at Christ Church in the 17<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> century’, they surmise that some of the records may have been thrown out as waste paper around 1600 and picked up by Christ Church’s neighbour. For this dating, they cite the fact that ‘one set of [Corpus] rolls going down to 1592 was till recently wrapped in a deed conveying the site and buildings of London College to the Dean of Cardinal College from the Master and Fellows of Balliol College’; this clearly refers to our document.</provenance>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>Ralph Hanna and David Rundle, <title>A Descriptive Catalogue of the Western Manuscripts, to c. 1600, in Christ Church, Oxford</title> (Oxford, 2017).</source>
                     </recordHist>
                     <availability>
                        <p>For enquiries relating to this manuscript please contact <ref target="https://www.chch.ox.ac.uk/library-and-archives/contacting-library">Christ Church Library</ref>.</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2017-07-01">First online publication.</change>
         <change when="2017-05-25"><persName>James Cummings</persName> Up-converted the markup using <ref target="https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl">https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl</ref></change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
      <body>
         <p/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>