<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="manuscript_3938">
   <teiHeader xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Christ Church MS. 167</title>
            <title type="collection">Christ Church MSS.</title>
            <respStmt><resp>Cataloguer</resp><persName>Ralph Hanna</persName><persName>David Rundle</persName></respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>TEI P5</edition>
            <editor>Matthew Holford</editor>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Special Collections, Bodleian Libraries</publisher>
            <address>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <street>Weston Library, Broad Street</street>
               <settlement key="place_7011931">Oxford</settlement>
               <postCode>OX1 3BG</postCode>
               <country>United Kingdom</country>
            </address>
            <distributor>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </distributor>
            <!--Availability statement will be added here-->
            <idno type="msID">Christ_Church_MS_167</idno>
            <idno type="collection">Christ Church</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="Christ_Church_MS_167">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <repository>Christ Church</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">Christ Church MS. 167</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <head>Catalogue of part of Archbishop Parker’s donation of books to Corpus
                    Christi College, Cambridge; England, s. xvi/s. xvii</head>
               <msContents>
                  <textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>
                  <msItem xml:id="Christ_Church_MS_167-item1" n="1">
                     <locus>Fol. 1-49<hi rend="superscript">v</hi> 
                     </locus>
                     <rubric rend="roman">Libri in minore bibliotheca</rubric>
                     <incipit>Homerus grece
                Odisse et Ilias</incipit>
                     <explicit>Rotula in pergameno de Anglia tecta in corio rubro</explicit>
                     <title key="work_10825">Catalogue of Archbishop <persName key="person_49234661">Matthew Parker</persName>’s gift of books to <orgName key="org_146606689">Corpus Christi College,
                Cambridge</orgName>
                     </title>
                     <note>Covering only the ‘inward library’ and not including the list of
                books, all printed, in the ‘outward library’ (‘maior bibliotheca’). The full list is
                provided in the so-called Parker Register, Cambridge: Corpus Christi College, MS
                575. That manuscript, and other copies of the catalogue (but not ours), are
                discussed by R. I. Page,
                <title>Matthew Parker and his books</title> (Kalamazoo,
                1993), 2-16 (esp. 3).</note>
                     <note>As in the relevant section of the Register, the list opens with manuscripts,
                described by title with brief incipit placed in right-hand column (fol. 1-14),
                followed by printed books, with a few manuscripts interspersed (fol. 14<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>-49<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>); the printed books
                are described by title, with size (‘fol.’, ‘4<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>, ‘8<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>’) and year of publication placed in right-hand column.
                Again following the Register, the listing of the printed books is divided into
                three, with a blank page (fol. 30<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>) separating first and
                second, while the second, which lists miscellanies (fol. 31-40<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>), is separated by two blank folios (fol. 41 &amp; 42) from the final
                section, which is defined by subject matter (epistolaries, material relating to
                synods, universities and ecclesiastical matters). The opening section also repeats
                the Register’s divisions by place within the ‘inward library’: ‘on the ground under’
                (fol. 13<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>-14); ‘Bookes in parchment closures as they lye
                on heapes’ (fol. 14<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>-21<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>);
                ‘Standing on the shelues within the lockers as here directed by 7 figures’ (fol.
                    22-28<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>); ‘Uppon the shelues top’ (fol. 29-30). The
                listing of manuscripts is also divided with groups being designated a letter, as is
                the first section of miscellanies. </note>
                     <note>Despite all the similarities with the Register, our manuscript is not an identical
                copy of it. At several points, the absence of a volume is noted by the scribe by
                writing ‘deest’ to the left and the initials ‘JP’ to the right of the title; the
                works thus designated in our manuscript do not appear in the Register. The initials
                are those of John Parker, the archbishop’s eldest son, who is known to have checked
                his late father’s collection before it was sent to Corpus in 1593 [R. I. Page, ‘The
                Parker Register and Matthew Parker’s Anglo-Saxon manuscripts’, <title>TCBS</title>, 8 (1981), 1-17 (2)]. As one of the absences is ‘Chronica Abingdone’
                with the incipit ‘Anno a plenitudine’, the manuscript can be identified as CUL, MS
                Dd.ii.5, which was among the volumes given by the Archbishop to the University in
                1574. The prototype of our catalogue, then, must have been produced before that
                gift, and so be slightly earlier than the recension that appears in the Register. </note>
                     <note>The absences, however, cannot all be explained by Parker’s donation to Cambridge
                University. They also include, for instance, ‘Eliensis historia maior’ with the
                incipit ‘Cum Animadverterem’ (fol. 2<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>); this is
                identifiable as the ‘Liber Eliensis’, of which there are four known manuscripts,
                none of which has been identified as Parker’s: see E. O. Blake ed., <title>Liber Eliensis</title> [Camden Society, 3<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> ser., xcii], lx. Of those four, that until recently kept at Ely (and
                now deposited in CUL) can obviously be excluded, as can (because of its contents)
                BL, MS Cotton Domitian XV, leaving the likelihood that either Cambridge: Trinity
                College, MS O.2.1 or Bodleian, MS Laud misc. 647 (both of which include antiquarian
                notes) passed through Parker’s hands. On the partial dispersal of Parker’s
                collection, see Timothy Graham, ‘Matthew Parker’s Manuscripts: an Elizabethan
                library and its use’ in <title>CHLBI</title>, 1: 322-42 (337).</note>
                     <note>Fol. 50-92: blank, with fol. 50-60 ruled. </note>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <!-- secFol not given -->
                 
               
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="chart">
                        <support>Paper (watermark: <watermark>four-leafed flower with basal leaves, within a double oval; no
                match in Briquet</watermark>)</support>
                        <extent>Folios: ii + 92 + i (pencil foliation, top right, added February
                2014: 1-92).
                           <dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                              <height>180</height>
                              <width>139</width>
                           </dimensions>
                           <dimensions type="written" unit="mm">
                              <height>115</height>
                              <width>121</width>
                           </dimensions>
                           <note>(variable)</note>
                        </extent>
                        <collation> Quires of eight: 1-11<hi rend="superscript">8</hi> 12-13<hi rend="superscript">2</hi>. No catchwords, and no leaf or quire
                signatures. </collation>
                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout writtenLines="12 23">Variable number of lines, between 12 and 23, but most pages leave blank space.</layout>
                        <layout>Only
                borders ruled in pencil: one horizontal (30mm from top) and either two or three
                vertical.</layout>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc>
                     <handNote>Two contemporaneous scripts combining italic and secretary features, with
                     first hand writing fol. 1-30 and the second fol. 31-49<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>
                     (ie the final two sections). Kitchin dated the manuscript to ‘saec. xvi’, noting
                     correctly that ‘the latest date of a printed book given is A. D. 1574’; the scripts,
                     however, may be as late as the early seventeenth century.</handNote>
                  </handDesc>
                  <decoDesc>
                     <decoNote type="none">No decoration to
                     this workmanlike copy. The scribes provide letters or headings in the top margin.
                     The first scribe also provides on occasion a pagination in both the part he writes
                     and that provided by his colleague: fol. 31-49 = pp. 69-103, but fol. 21-23 =
                     135-139, and fol. 26-30 = pp. 137-145 [!] and fol. 25 = p. 159 [!]. </decoNote>
                  </decoDesc>
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <binding notAfter="1800" notBefore="1700">
                        <p> Vellum, half-backed in rough card, possibly s.
                xviii. Sewn on two thongs. Pastedowns and conjoint flyleaves later (s. xx?)
                additions, with a rectangle cut out at front pastedown so as to reveal the ChCh
                bookplate. Same paper label stuck to spine with present manuscript number. </p>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origPlace>
                        <country key="place_7002445">England</country>
                     </origPlace>
                     <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notBefore="1590" notAfter="1610">s. s. xvi/s. xvii</origDate>
                  </origin>
                  <provenance> This small volume provides no explicit
                information about either its production or its route to Christ Church. While ChCh
                manuscript numbers do not relate exactly to order of accession, the high number
                within Kitchin’s designation of ‘codices MSS. Anglici’ (though this is only in small
                part in English), the absence of an early shelfmark and its non-appearance in any
                catalogue of the manuscripts before Kitchin all suggest that this did not arrive
                before the nineteenth century or, if it did, it was as part of Archbishop Wake’s
                bequest, which was excluded from Edward Smallwell’s cataloguing of the main archive
                (see Appendix IV). Wake certainly showed interest in his learned predecessor: this
                is evidenced not only by our MS 112 but also by his owning of a copy of the printed
                catalogue of Parker’s donation to Corpus (London, 1722), which now forms the opening
                part of MS 294 (though there is no sign that the printed catalogue and this
                manuscript have been compared). This manuscript, however, does not appear in the
                autograph list of the manuscripts he left to ChCh, MS 352/8, nor in the earliest
                catalogue of the ‘Arch.’ section of the collection as organised in its new home (MS
                LR 21b). However, that catalogue is written by two hands and the second script (s.
                    xviii<hi rend="superscript">3/4</hi>) may be identifiable with that which
                appears on a blue slip sitting within our volume (presently between fols 48 and 49)
                and records a shelfmark: ‘E.1’. Perhaps, then, this was added as a late arrival to
                the Wake collection, with the Wake librarian cognisant of the archbishop’s
                interests. </provenance>
               </history>
            <additional>                   <adminInfo>                      <recordHist>                         <source>Ralph Hanna and David Rundle, <title>A Descriptive Catalogue of the Western Manuscripts, to c. 1600, in Christ Church, Oxford</title> (Oxford, 2017).</source>                      </recordHist><availability><p>For enquiries relating to this manuscript please contact <ref target="https://www.chch.ox.ac.uk/library-and-archives/contacting-library">Christ Church Library</ref>.</p></availability>                    </adminInfo>                </additional>             </msDesc>          </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>          <change when="2017-07-01">First online publication.</change>

         <change when="2017-05-29">
            <persName>James Cummings</persName> Up-converted the markup using <ref target="https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl">https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl</ref>
         </change>
         <change when="2017-05-25">
            <persName>James Cummings</persName> Up-converted the markup using <ref target="https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl">https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl</ref>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
      <body>
         <p><!--Body paragraph provided for validation and future transcription--></p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>