<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="manuscript_3965">
   <teiHeader xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Christ Church MS. 91</title>
            <title type="collection">Christ Church MSS.</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Cataloguer</resp>
               <persName>Ralph Hanna</persName>
               <persName>David Rundle</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </publisher>
            <idno type="msID">Christ_Church_MS_91</idno>
            <idno type="collection">Christ_Church</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="Christ_Church_MS_91">
               <!-- check rend of rubrics -->
               <msIdentifier>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <repository>Christ Church</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">Christ Church MS. 91</idno>
               <idno type="ieArk">ark:29072/c0f4752f8083</idno><idno type="crArk">ark:29072/c0f1881j96z1</idno></msIdentifier>
               <head>Religious miscellany; England, s. xv<hi rend="superscript">med </hi>and s. xv<hi rend="superscript">3/4</hi> (I-III), and s. xiii<hi rend="superscript">med</hi> or s. xiii<hi rend="superscript">2</hi> (IV)</head>
               <msContents>
                  <textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>
                  <msItem xml:id="Christ_Church_MS_91-item1">
                     <note> Fol. i: blank</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="1" xml:id="Christ_Church_MS_91-item2">
                     <locus from="iv">Fol. i<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>
                     </locus>
                     <note>Table of contents for the whole book, s. xv3/4, in the hand of <persName key="person_2618" role="scr">John Lyndon</persName> (see provenance).</note>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <p>Comprising four originally separate MSS, all on parchment (the second HSOS, the remainder FSOS).</p>
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="perg">
                        <extent>Fols: i + 230<dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                              <height>287</height>
                              <width>215</width>
                           </dimensions>
                        </extent>
                     </supportDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <binding notAfter="1500" notBefore="1400">
                        <p>Brown leather over chamfered bevelled wooden boards, s. xv. Sewn on seven thongs, taken straight into the board, as depicted by Pollard, fig. 5. Seatings with stubs of leather straps in the upper board, two and three nails; metal clasps at the edge of the lower board. A single nailhole from a chain staple in Watson’s position 4; and two nailholes from another, in position 5 (this latter a ChCh chain: see Appendix I). Pastedowns heavy waste parchment, a ChCh bookplate on the front pastedown. At the front, one heavy parchment flyleaf, conjoint with the pastedown (fol. i).</p>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <provenance> The initials in the colophon to item 2, ‘C P R Y S’ (fol. 83<hi rend="superscript">ra</hi>), are possibly scribal signature, though an abbreviation of a motto is equally plausible. MLGB3 assigns the book, along with MS 90, to <orgName key="org_55" role="fmo">Crediton (Devon), the collegiate church of the Holy Cross</orgName>; in 1947, Neil Ker read under ultraviolet light the inscriptions ‘Decano Crediton’ and ‘liber <persName key="person_2618" role="fmo">J. Lyndon</persName>’ on fol. i<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>. Lyndon, fellow of Exeter College, Oxford in 1434, rector in 1441–42, was Dean of the church in Crediton from 24<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> February 1442, until his death in or before early 1487. On him and his books, see <title>BRUO</title>, 1191, and James M. W. Willoughby, <title>The Libraries of Collegiate Churches</title>, Corpus of British Medieval Library Catalogues 15, 2 vols (London, 2013), 1:100–101. It is Lyndon who writes the table of contents (fol. i<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>) and provides the running headers, chapter divisions (eg item 22) and annotations throughout the volume. It was presumably him who had the fascicules brought together and bound as one codex; he also provided pieces of string attached to the outer margin of certain pages to provide tabs to the openings of works (fol. 90, 113, 195).</provenance>
                  <provenance> Ker also read on fol. 1 (the upper margin) ‘<persName key="person_2620" role="fmo">Guilihelmi Muggi</persName> liber ex dono <persName key="person_2619" role="fmo">Magistri Georgii Mason</persName>’ and spotted another illegible inscription at the top of fol. 195. For the route of descent from Mason to Mugge to Ballow, see MS 90, provenance.</provenance>
                  <provenance> Like the preceding book, a gift of <persName key="person_2617" role="fmo">William Ballow</persName>: ‘Hunc codicem manuscriptum Ædi Christi in gratiam studiosorum ibidem Guilielmus Ballowe in artibus Magister testificandi amoris sui ergo dono dedit 5º. Octobris anno Domini 1601’ (fol. i<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>). There is a cancelled ChCh shelfmark at the front pastedown, ‘B.<supplied>.</supplied>’, which must relate to the 1676 Catalogue, though this manuscript receives no entry there (see Appendix I). Immediately below that note, and below the donation note at fol. i<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>, Edward Smallwell added the New Library shelfmark of ‘F.14’ (see Appendix IV); this also appears stamped on a tiny tab on the spine.</provenance>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>Ralph Hanna and David Rundle, <title>A Descriptive Catalogue of the Western Manuscripts, to c. 1600, in Christ Church, Oxford</title> (Oxford, 2017).</source>
                     </recordHist>
                     <availability>
                        <p>For enquiries relating to this manuscript please contact <ref target="https://www.chch.ox.ac.uk/library-and-archives/contacting-library">Christ Church Library</ref>.</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
               </additional>
               <msPart xml:id="Christ_Church_MS_91-part1">
                  <msIdentifier>
                     <altIdentifier>
                        <idno type="part">Manuscript I = fols 1–134</idno>
                     </altIdentifier>
                  </msIdentifier>
                  <msContents>
                     <textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>
                     <msItem n="2" xml:id="Christ_Church_MS_91-part1-item1">
                        <locus from="1ra" to="90va">Fols 1<hi rend="superscript">ra</hi>–90<hi rend="superscript">va</hi>
                        </locus>
                        <rubric>sermo jº <note>[in central margin ]</note>
                        </rubric>
                        <incipit>Dicite filie syon ecce rex . . . Mathei 21 Verba ista sumpta sunt a zacharia propheta quia zacharie</incipit>
                        <explicit>
                           <locus from="83ra" to="83ra">[fol. 83<hi rend="superscript">ra</hi>]</locus> Gaudia leticie vite dulcedis perhennis Gloria laus requies amor et concordia dulcis ad illa gaudia ducat nos cristus. amen. </explicit>
                        <finalRubric>Expliciunt sermones de temporali per totum annum secundum Nicholaum de Aquavilla aliter Lugdinensem quod C P R Y S ^et erat de ordine minorum^.</finalRubric>
                        <incipit type="index">Abhominacio peccati</incipit>
                        <explicit type="index">facto libro sit laus et gloria cristo</explicit>
                        <author key="person_66805034">Nicholas de Aquavilla</author>
                        <title key="work_3283">Sermones dominicales</title>
                        <note>Sharpe no. 1076 [383], the sermons enumerated Schneyer, 4:189–95, ed. Jean Quentin (Paris, c. 1505) (BodL, Douce QQ 5), but lacks the epilogue, in the print, sig. z vii<hi rend="superscript">rv</hi>. Followed, as in the print, by an alphabetical index.</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="3" xml:id="Christ_Church_MS_91-part1-item2">
                        <locus from="90vb" to="112va">Fols 90<hi rend="superscript">vb</hi>–112<hi rend="superscript">va</hi>
                        </locus>
                        <rubric>Incipit de vita beati Pauli primi heremite Iste floruit anno cristi 258 <note>[these headings added later in upper margin, the first perhaps by the scribe of the text, in a less formal hand]</note>
                        </rubric>
                        <incipit>Paulus primus heremita cum sexdecim esset annorum fugit in desertum propter metum decij</incipit>
                        <explicit>
                           <locus from="111rb" to="111rb">[fol. 111<hi rend="superscript">rb</hi>]</locus> corpus eius requiescebat benedixerunt deum et vsque ad deus oracionibus sancte virginis multa facit mirabilia. Agnos deus scit</explicit>
                        <rubric>Narraciones et exhortaciones notabiliter extracte de vitis patrum cum tabula secundum Ieronimum <note>(so the table to the volume, fol. i<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>)</note>
                        </rubric>
                        <title key="work_15484">Vitas Patrum</title>
                        <note>Excerpts, with further bits added in the lower margins. Our manuscript presents excerpts from (in order):</note>
                        <note> (a) fols 90<hi rend="superscript">vb</hi>-92<hi rend="superscript">rb</hi>: the saints’ lives which comprise <title>Vitas patrum</title> 1: Paul the first hermit (Jerome, ed. <title>PL</title> 23:20–28 passim), Antony, Hillarion, and Thais (<title>PL</title> 73:127–67?, 29–54, 661–62 passim).</note>
                        <note> (b) fols 92<hi rend="superscript">rb</hi>-98<hi rend="superscript">va</hi>: <persName key="person_77679446" role="aut">Rufinus of Aquileia</persName>, <title>Historia monachorum</title> 1–2, 5–11, 14–17, 19, 29–32 (<hi rend="italic">PL</hi> 21:391–407, 408–32, 441–42, 455–60 passim). One set of excerpts, concerning Amo (fol. 96<hi rend="superscript">ra-va</hi>), resembles Rufinus’s source, <persName key="person_61550437" role="aut">Palladius</persName>, <title>Historia lausiaca</title> 53 (<title>Vitas patrum</title> 8, <title>PL</title> 73:1163–64) more closely than it does Rufinus 8 (<title>PL</title> 21:420–22). At the foot of fol. 98<hi rend="superscript">vab</hi>, a later s. xv hand, probably that responsible for informal marginal rubrics and running titles, has added an account of ‘Emerenciana’: ‘Venit ad abbatem arsenium vna materna virgo de Roma diues valde et timens dominum . . .’, from <title>Vitas patrum</title> 3.65 or 5, libellus 2.7 (<title>PL</title> 73:771 and 858–59, respectively).</note>
                        <note> (c) fols 98<hi rend="superscript">va</hi>-109<hi rend="superscript">ra</hi>: ‘adortaciones translate de greco per Pelagium diaconem’ (the index to the text), i.e. the ‘Verba seniorum’, <title>Vitæ patrum</title> 5, selections from libelli 1–10, 13, 15–18 (<title>PL</title> 73:855–933, 943–47, 953–88 passim).</note>
                        <note> (d) fols 109<hi rend="superscript">ra</hi>-10<hi rend="superscript">va</hi>: ‘Ab hinc transtulit Iohannis subdiaconus’ (the index), <title>Vitas patrum</title> 6, selections from 1. l8–4.11 (<title>PL</title> 73:994–1017 passim).</note>
                        <note> (e) fols 110<hi rend="superscript">va</hi>-11<hi rend="superscript">rb</hi>: ‘vita sancte marine virginis’, from <title>Vitas patrum</title> 1 (<title>PL</title> 73:691–94).</note>
                        <note> Two indexes follow the text, an alphabetical one of topics treated ‘Agnos deus scit-Zenio’ (keyed to numbering of the selections, with letters for the parts, all provided marginally) and a list of the selections (fols 111<hi rend="superscript">rb</hi>-12<hi rend="superscript">va</hi>).</note>
                        <note> For a useful survey of such collections, see Columba M. Batlle, <title>Die “Adhortationes sanctorum patrum” (“Verba seniorum”) im lateinischen Mittelalter</title>, Beiträge zur Geschichte des altes Mönchtums und des Benediktinerordens 31 (Münster i. W., 1971), which overlooks our manuscript. Running titles and headings added, s. xv<hi rend="superscript">ex</hi>. </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="4" xml:id="Christ_Church_MS_91-part1-item3">
                        <locus from="112va" to="116va">Fols 112<hi rend="superscript">va</hi>–16<hi rend="superscript">va</hi>
                        </locus>
                        <incipit>Visitacionis gracia Nepoti meo carissimo morienti extremum vale dicturus hesterna die pro<locus from="112vb" to="112vb">[fol. 112<hi rend="superscript">vb</hi>]</locus>cessi</incipit>
                        <explicit>[fol. 114<hi rend="superscript">rb</hi>] et requiescam qui in trinitate perfecta viuis et regnas deus per omnia secula seculorum.</explicit>
                        <rubric>
                           <note>[in margin]</note> Alius tractatus de eodem. </rubric>
                        <incipit>Superioris tractatus cursum me clausisse putaueram tamen quidam de fratribus illum accipientes</incipit>
                        <explicit>peccatori vt ascendas iustus ad deum iustificatus ab ipso qui viuit <note>[form ending]</note> amen</explicit>
                        <finalRubric>
                           <note>[in margin:]</note> Explicit liber sancti Augustini episcopi de visitacione infirmorum</finalRubric>
                        <author key="person_7386286">Ps.-Augustine (<persName key="person_61654660" role="aut">Baudri de Bourgeuil</persName>, bishop of Dol (d. 1130))</author>
                        <title key="work_3882">De visitacione Infirmorum</title>
                        <note>Here attributed to ‘Augustinus’ (also the table, fol. i<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>); <hi rend="italic">PL</hi> 40:1147–58.</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="5" xml:id="Christ_Church_MS_91-part1-item4">
                        <locus from="116vab">Fol. 116<hi rend="superscript">vab</hi>
                        </locus>
                        <incipit>Vt homo possit amplius proficere et deo magis placere ista 10. que secuntur in se studeat habere Primum est vt studeat quantum possit se vilissimum reputare</incipit>
                        <explicit>in altari exhibitum sibi in cibum et potum omnis saporis suauitatem habentem </explicit>
                        <finalRubric>Explicit Extractum de libro qui vocatur Florarium Bartholomei capitulo de vita perfecta</finalRubric>
                        <author key="person_84812388">John Mirfield OSA</author>
                        <title key="work_5612">Florarium Bartholomei</title>
                        <note>(selection)</note>
                        <note>Sharpe no. 808 [284], selections ed. Percival H. Hartley and Harold R. Aldredge, <title>Johannes de Mirfield of St. Bartholomew’s Hospital, Smithfield: His Life and Works</title> (Cambridge, 1936), 114–64. The selection here paraphrases part of ch. 172, ‘de vita perfecta’, in the full copy, BL, MS Royal 7 F.xi, fols 254<hi rend="superscript">va</hi>/6–55<hi rend="superscript">ra</hi>/20.</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="6" xml:id="Christ_Church_MS_91-part1-item5">
                        <locus from="117ra" to="118va">Fols 117<hi rend="superscript">ra</hi>–18<hi rend="superscript">va</hi>
                        </locus>
                        <rubric rend="roman">
                           <note>[the scribes informal heading in upper margin]</note> Tractatus de militia spirituali</rubric>
                        <incipit>Sicut miles temporalis armis munitus est temporalibus sic miles spiritualis debet armis munitus</incipit>
                        <explicit>Valde itaque vt prediximus sunt necessaria spirituali militi sua arma</explicit>
                        <author key="person_78673926">Alexander of Canterbury (Ps.-Anselm)</author>
                        <title key="work_5613" type="desc">Liber Anselmi de humanis moribus per similitudines</title>
                        <note>(extract)</note>
                        <note>Section 193 ed. R. W. Southern and F. S. Schmitt, <title>Memorials of St. Anselm</title>, Auctores Britannici Medii Ævi 1 (Oxford, 1969), 97–102. Followed without break by an extra paragraph:</note>
                        <incipit>Si hinc inquit <persName key="person_100187025" role="aut">Anselmus</persName> peccati fetorem et illic inferni demonum horrorem et necessario vni eorum haberem immergi prius me</incipit>
                        <explicit>liberare vel perdere quemadmodum de rege terreno si quis suos incarceratos conteret</explicit>
                        <note>At the end, the note ‘uel hic finis’ and eight lines left blank.</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="7" xml:id="Christ_Church_MS_91-part1-item6">
                        <locus from="118va" to="121va">Fols 118<hi rend="superscript">va</hi>–21<hi rend="superscript">va</hi>
                        </locus>
                        <incipit>Angelis suis mandauit de te . . . psalmi 90. secundum cursum et disposicionem quam deus vnicuique rei in sui creacione</incipit>
                        <explicit>portaretur ab angelis in sinum Abrahe id est ad requiem glorie ad quam nos perducat etc.</explicit>
                        <rubric rend="roman">Sermo notabiliter de custodia angelica super illo Angelis suis deus Mandauit de te <note>[Ps. 90:11] (the table, fol. i<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>)</note>
                        </rubric>
                        <title key="work_14583">Sermon</title>
                        <note>See Siegfried Wenzel, <title>Latin Sermon Collections from Later Medieval England</title> (Cambridge, 2005), 130. Fol. 121<hi rend="superscript">va</hi> has only fifteen lines, and the remainder of the leaf is blank.</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="8" xml:id="Christ_Church_MS_91-part1-item7">
                        <locus from="122ra" to="132ra">Fols 122<hi rend="superscript">ra</hi>–32<hi rend="superscript">ra</hi>
                        </locus>
                        <incipit>Cristus passus est vobis . . . prima petri 2º. anglice sic Cryst yn hys passion exempel hath yeue how ye schold don</incipit>
                        <explicit>eius hereditatem scilicet regnum ce<supplied>lo</supplied>rum quod nobis concedat ihesus cristus qui nos suo sanguine redemit Amen</explicit>
                        <rubric rend="roman">Sermo notabiliter de passione cristi sic incipiens cristus passus est pro nobis <note>(the table, fol. i<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>)</note>
                        </rubric>
                        <title key="work_14583">Sermon</title>
                        <note>Unpublished, but, according to Siegfried Wenzel, <title>Macaronic Sermons: Bilingualism and Preaching in Late-Medieval England</title> (Ann Arbor MI, 1994), 43–44 and passim, other copies appear at Oxford: Balliol College, MS 149, fols 1–15<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>; BL: MS Harley 331, fols 80–99; Arras: Bibliothèque municipale, MS 184 (254), fols 51<hi rend="superscript">vb</hi>-61<hi rend="superscript">va</hi>; Worcester Cathedral, MS F.10, fols 18–26<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>. Following the explicit is an added note referring to Chrysostom and Holcot. Originally fol. 132<hi rend="superscript">rb-vb</hi> was left blank.</note>
                        <note> At the top of fol. 122 is an added contemporary note: ‘Chambernowne quondam socius in Collegio Exon’ et postea frater de ordine Minorum composuit et dixit hunc sermonem Oxon’ et iacet apud Wtton’ vnder hegge [i.e. Wotton-under-Edge, Glocs.] et fuit ibi Oxon’ in tempore Wodeford olim prioris sancti Iohannis Exon’’, information not included in the accounts of <persName cert="low" key="person_2627" role="aut">Henry Chambernown</persName> (or Chambron) at <title>BRUO</title>, 2:xiii and Sharpe no. 442 (165). ‘Wodeford’ is not the great adversary of Wycliffe, but Richard Wodeford, a Devon man who was a Fellow of Exeter College 1378 × 1383; from 1384 (probably until his death in 1428), he was prior of St John the Baptist, a hospital in Exeter (<title>BRUO</title>, 2071).</note>
                        <note> Chamber(n)own is known through a Middle English ‘nine points’ text, ascribed to him in Hereford Cathedral, MS P.i.9, fols 150<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>-51<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>, a book from the Oxford Franciscan convent; for copies, see P. S. Jolliffe, <title>A Check-List of Middle English Prose Writings of Spiritual Guidance</title> (Toronto, 1974), 111 (I.26). In addition, he is ascribed two sermons, at Oxford: Balliol, MS 149, fols 84–86<hi rend="superscript">v</hi> (for Easter on the passion) and 90–92<hi rend="superscript">v</hi> (for the third Sunday in Lent). The first sermon also appears in Arras: Bibliothèque municipale, MS 184 (254), fols 1<hi rend="superscript">ra</hi>-4<hi rend="superscript">rb</hi> (its delivery there dated 1382, which accords with Wodeford’s dates in Oxford). But as Wenzel notes (<title>Macaronic Sermons</title>, 44), the sermon here cannot be Chambernown’s, since it actually quotes him: ‘Hic secundum ymaginacionem illius deuoti doctoris Chamberoun potest respondere pater’ (fol. 126<hi rend="superscript">rb</hi>; cf. Balliol 149, fol. 6<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>); the ascription appears a confusion between two similar sermons.</note>
                        <note> Fol. 132<hi rend="superscript">rb-vb</hi>: originally blank, now with added texts (a) and (b).</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="9" xml:id="Christ_Church_MS_91-part1-item8">
                        <locus from="133ra" to="134va">Fols 133<hi rend="superscript">ra</hi>–34<hi rend="superscript">va</hi>
                        </locus>
                        <rubric rend="roman">
                           <note>[title in upper margin]</note> In Die ascensionis.</rubric>
                        <incipit>Euntes in mundum vniuersum etc. Marci vltimo Narrat beatus marcus in euangelio hodierno quando dominus noster deus debuit ascendere</incipit>
                        <explicit>Vnde in signum huius euangelista dicit quod postquam dominus locutus est assumptus est in celum Rogemus igitur etc.</explicit>
                        <rubric rend="roman">Sermo bonus pro die ascensionis <note>(the table, fol. i<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>
                           </note>
                        </rubric>
                        <title key="work_14583">Sermon</title>
                        <note>See Wenzel, <title>Latin Sermon Collections</title>, 130.</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="10" xml:id="Christ_Church_MS_91-part1-item9">
                        <locus from="134vb">Fol. 134<hi rend="superscript">vb</hi>
                        </locus>
                        <rubric rend="roman">
                           <note>[title in upper margin]</note> De Beata Maria</rubric>
                        <incipit>Quomodo preces beate Marie exaudiuntur semper penes deum pro quocunque orauerit nota in distinccionibus holcote</incipit>
                        <note>a series of theological notes on the Virgin, used to fill partially the blank final column.</note>
                        <note> Added texts, written on blank leaves in anglicana, s. xv<hi rend="superscript">2</hi>:</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="a" xml:id="Christ_Church_MS_91-part1-item10">
                        <locus from="132rb">Fol. 132<hi rend="superscript">rb</hi>
                        </locus>
                        <rubric rend="roman">Carta Redempcionis humane</rubric>
                        <incipit>Hec quicumque sciant presentes atque futuri | Et memores fiant</incipit>
                        <explicit>Hanc cartam scripsi proprio cum sanguine puro | Et pro secura proprium cor penditur ipsi</explicit>
                        <note><ref target="http://webserver.erwin-rauner.de/php_ancarm/ancarm_refwerke.php?opus=1000&amp;var=WIC&amp;nr_char=7576"><title>WIC</title> 7576</ref>, who cites copies in Cambridge: St John’s College, MSS 83, fol. 174<hi rend="superscript">v</hi> and 127, fol. 22 (though, by <hi rend="italic">lapsus calami</hi>, he states Oxford). Next to the title, a note in the hand which supplies headings, and typical of a variety of supplied marginalia: ‘Sentencia huius carte secundum quod prerecitatur habetur in fasciculus morum partis 2ᵉ. capitulo 7b.’, i.e. <hi rend="italic">Fasciculus Morum: A Fourteenth-Century Preacher’s Handbook</hi>, ed. and tr. Siegfried Wenzel (University Park PA, 1989), 147/80–98.</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="b" xml:id="Christ_Church_MS_91-part1-item11">
                        <locus from="132v">Fol. 132<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>
                        </locus>
                        <rubric rend="roman">
                           <note>[title in upper margin:]</note> litera vel epistola domino ihesu directa et dirigenda post eius ascensionem per modum oracionis anime suspirantis</rubric>
                        <incipit>
                           <note>[word in outer margin:]</note> Salutacio O summi patris sine principio generate | Virginis et matris fili</incipit>
                        <explicit>quam sepe proternum | Nunc vtinam dignum gratum placitumque benignum</explicit>
                        <note> Not in Walther; another copy appears at Dublin: Trinity College, MS 44, fols viii<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>-ix.</note>
                     </msItem>
                  </msContents>
                  <physDesc>
                     <p>
                        <secFol> principale </secFol>
                     </p>
                     <objectDesc form="codex">
                        <supportDesc material="perg">
                           <support>Parchment (FSOS)</support>
                           <extent>Fols 134</extent>
                           <collation> 1–10<hi rend="superscript">12</hi> 11<hi rend="superscript">14</hi>. Catchwords, usually boxed, frequently in the decorative textura used for headings, sometimes red-slashed. All leaves in the first halves of each quire originally signed with an arabic numeral, although most cut away; unusually, in quires 7 and 8, fragments of a second set, in brown crayon, a letter (g, ?h) and roman numeral.</collation>
                        </supportDesc>
                        <layoutDesc>
                           <layout columns="2" writtenLines="62">fols 1<hi rend="superscript">ra</hi>-116<hi rend="superscript">vb</hi> (items 1–5), scribe A: in double columns, each column <dimensions type="column" unit="mm">
                                 <height>227</height>
                                 <width>70</width>
                              </dimensions> (some variation), with 15mm between columns, in about 62 lines to the column. Very faintly bounded but not ruled, with some signs of prick-holes in top and outer margin in line with borders.</layout>
                           <layout columns="2">fols 117<hi rend="superscript">ra</hi>-34<hi rend="superscript">vb</hi> (items 6–10), scribe B: in double columns, each column <dimensions type="column" unit="mm">
                                 <height>215</height>
                                 <width max="65" min="63">63–65</width>
                              </dimensions>, with 14mm between columns, in between 44 and 52 lines to the column. Bounded in black ink, no rules, with only signs of prick-holes being in the outer margin in line with top and bottom borders.</layout>
                        </layoutDesc>
                     </objectDesc>
                     <handDesc>
                        <handNote>Two scribes in differing formats: <p>A = fols 1<hi rend="superscript">ra</hi>-116<hi rend="superscript">vb</hi> (items 1–5). Written in anglicana with secretary <hi rend="bold">a</hi>, s. xv med. Punctuation by point and virgula.</p>
                           <p>B = fols 117<hi rend="superscript">ra</hi>-34<hi rend="superscript">vb</hi> (items 6–10). Written in anglicana with double-bowled <hi rend="bold">a</hi>, s. xv<hi rend="superscript">3/4</hi>. Punctuation by occasional point.</p>
                        </handNote>
                     </handDesc>
                  </physDesc>
                  <history>
                     <origin>
                        <origPlace><country key="place_7002445">England</country></origPlace>
                        <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="1475" notBefore="1440">s. xv<hi rend="superscript">med </hi> and <hi rend="superscript">3/4</hi>
                        </origDate>
                     </origin>
                  </history>
               </msPart>
               <msPart xml:id="Christ_Church_MS_91-part2">
                  <msIdentifier>
                     <tei:altIdentifier>
                        <idno type="part">Manuscript II = fols 135–65</idno>
                     </tei:altIdentifier>
                  </msIdentifier>
                  <msContents>
                     <textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>
                     <msItem n="11" xml:id="Christ_Church_MS_91-part2-item1">
                        <locus from="135ra" to="142rb">Fols 135<hi rend="superscript">ra</hi>–42<hi rend="superscript">rb</hi>
                        </locus>
                        <rubric rend="roman">
                           <note>[in upper margin]</note> Sermo De Beata Maria</rubric>
                        <incipit>Erat nauis in medio mari etc. Sicut dies dominica dedicata est dominice resurreccioni et feria vjª. dominice passioni</incipit>
                        <explicit>quia euaserunt tam horrendum consorcium demonum et assecuti sunt consorcium ang<expan>e</expan>lorum</explicit>
                        <rubric rend="roman">7. sermones de beata Maria secundum Ianuensem in opere quadragesimali’ <note>(the table, fol. i<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>)</note>
                        </rubric>
                        <author key="person_100198644">Jacobus da Voragine</author>
                        <title key="work_2334">Sermones quadragesimales</title>
                        <note>(extract: seven 'sermones de beata Maria')</note>
                        <note>Kaeppeli no. 2157 [2:348, 364–67], in order Schneyer nos 203, 217, 230, 244, 258, 272, 286 (3:239–44 passim), ed. <title>Sermones quadragesimales</title> (Brescia, 14[9]3) (Proctor 6975, ISTC ij00186000), sigs. b iii<hi rend="superscript">rb</hi>-iiii<hi rend="superscript">rb</hi>, d vi<hi rend="superscript">ra-vb</hi>, g [ii]<hi rend="superscript">rb</hi>-iii<hi rend="superscript">vb</hi> (the first leaf misnumbered ‘g iii’), i vii<hi rend="superscript">rb</hi>-k i<hi rend="superscript">ra</hi>, m iiii<hi rend="superscript">va</hi>-vi<hi rend="superscript">ra</hi>, p iiii<hi rend="superscript">va</hi>-vi<hi rend="superscript">va</hi>, s iiii<hi rend="superscript">va</hi>-vi<hi rend="superscript">ra</hi>, respectively. </note>
                        <note> Fol. 142<hi rend="superscript">v</hi> is blank but bounded.</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="12" xml:id="Christ_Church_MS_91-part2-item2">
                        <locus from="143ra" to="146ra">Fols 143<hi rend="superscript">ra</hi>–46<hi rend="superscript">ra</hi>
                        </locus>
                        <rubric rend="roman">
                           <note>[in upper margin]</note> Oracio Dominica</rubric>
                        <incipit>De oracione videndum est sub qua forma specialiter est orandum Pro quo notandum est</incipit>
                        <explicit>et liberet nos a malo culpe in presenti et in futuro perducat nos ad gloriam sempiternam Amen</explicit>
                        <rubric rend="roman">Declaracio bona Oracionis dominice secundum Magistrum Alexandrum Cortys <note>(the table, fol. i<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>)</note>
                        </rubric>
                        <author key="person_293088495">Alexander Carpenter</author>
                        <title key="work_5627">Destructorium vitiorum</title>
                        <note>(extract)</note>
                        <note>Sharpe no. 97 [49]; pr. Cologne, 1485 (Hain 650*, <title>BMC</title> 1:266, ISTC ia00392000), 4.37, sigs. o vi<hi rend="superscript">vb</hi>-p ii<hi rend="superscript">vb</hi> (corresponding to Oxford: Balliol College, MS. 81, fols 130<hi rend="superscript">va</hi>/10–33<hi rend="superscript">ra</hi>/23). Bloomfield cites the text as no. 8171 and as if a unique work. There are only ten written lines on fol. 146<hi rend="superscript">ra</hi>.</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="13" xml:id="Christ_Church_MS_91-part2-item3">
                        <locus from="146rb" to="151va">Fols 146<hi rend="superscript">rb</hi>–51<hi rend="superscript">va</hi>
                        </locus>
                        <rubric rend="roman">
                           <note>[in upper margin]</note> Salutacio Angelica</rubric>
                        <incipit> | Pro eo quod commendabilis consuetudo matris nostre ecclesie in omnibus horis canonicis premittendo oracionem dominicam</incipit>
                        <explicit>quem fructum si quis digne degustauerit viuet in eternum etc.</explicit>
                        <note> ‘Declaracio bona Salutacionis angelice’ (the table, fol. i<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>), in fact <hi rend="smallcaps">Carpenter</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Destructorium</hi> 4.38, ed. sigs. p ii<hi rend="superscript">vb</hi>-vi<hi rend="superscript">vb</hi> (in Balliol, MS. 81, fols 133<hi rend="superscript">ra</hi>/24–38<hi rend="superscript">ra</hi>/12). Half of fol. 151<hi rend="superscript">va</hi> blank.</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="14" xml:id="Christ_Church_MS_91-part2-item4">
                        <locus from="151vb" to="164ra">Fols 151<hi rend="superscript">vb</hi>–64<hi rend="superscript">ra</hi>
                        </locus>
                        <incipit>Nunc de fide est disserendum quia nulla oracio neque obsecracio nec postulacio <note>[est]</note> sine fide est acceptabilis</incipit>
                        <explicit>pro presenti de fide formata et de fide informi et de infidelitate pr<add place="above">i</add>mo modo dicta etc.</explicit>
                        <rubric>Declaracio bona super Simbolo apostolico Ibi nota bene de Fide <note>(the table, fol. i<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>
                           </note>
                        </rubric>
                        <note>More clearly identified in an added note at the foot of fol. 164<hi rend="superscript">ra</hi>: ‘Hec extracta sunt de Destructorio viciorum partis 6 capitulis 32 33 34 35 36 37 et 38’ </note>
                        <author key="person_293088495">Alexander Carpenter</author>
                        <title key="work_5627">Destructorium vitiorum</title>
                        <note>(extract)</note>
                        <note>6.32–37, ed. sigs. D iii<hi rend="superscript">ra</hi>-E iii<hi rend="superscript">rb</hi> (in Balliol, MS. 81, fols 268<hi rend="superscript">ra</hi>/46–79<hi rend="superscript">vb</hi>/50, preceded by a few sentences based upon 4.39). The remainder of the quire was originally blank.</note>
                        <note>Added text, written in anglicana, s. xv<hi rend="superscript">ex</hi>; in 41 lines to the column:</note>
                        <msItem n="c" xml:id="Christ_Church_MS_91-part2-item4-item1">
                           <locus from="164rb" to="165ra">Fols 164<hi rend="superscript">rb</hi>–65<hi rend="superscript">ra</hi>
                           </locus>
                           <rubric>
                              <note>[in outer margin:]</note> Nota de 6. speciebus sacrificij spiritualis</rubric>
                           <incipit>Notandum quod sicut dicit Parysensis sub auctoritate beati augustini 16. de ciuitate sex sunt species sacrificij spiritualis</incipit>
                           <explicit>dubitaret quin virtute verbi d<gap quantity="2" unit="char"/> possint panis et vini conuerti in carnem et sanguinem cristi etc</explicit>
                           <note> Two theological notes from <persName key="person_41951136" role="aut">William Peraldus</persName>, ed. as <title>Summa aurea de virtutibus et vitijs</title> (Venice, 1497) (Hain 12391*, <title>BMC</title> 5:459, ISTC ip00087000), the first from ‘de virtutibus’ 8.5, sig. p vi<hi rend="superscript">rb</hi>, the second ‘De Corpore cristi’ unidentified. Fol. 165 has been cut down to the single written column; the verso is blank but bounded.</note>
                        </msItem>
                     </msItem>
                  </msContents>
                  <physDesc>
                     <p>
                        <secFol>alieno <locus from="136" to="136">(fol. 136)</locus>
                        </secFol>
                     </p>
                     <objectDesc form="codex">
                        <supportDesc material="perg">
                           <support>Parchment (HSOS)</support>
                           <extent>Fols 31</extent>
                           <collation> 12<hi rend="superscript">14</hi> 13<hi rend="superscript">12</hi> 14<hi rend="superscript">8</hi> (-6 to -8, all stubs and presumably blank). No catchwords or signatures.</collation>
                        </supportDesc>
                        <layoutDesc>
                           <layout columns="2" writtenLines="46">In double columns, each column <dimensions type="column" unit="mm">
                                 <height>222</height>
                                 <width max="65" min="63">63–65</width>
                              </dimensions>, with 14 mm between columns, in 46 lines to the column.</layout>
                           <layout>No signs of pricking; bounded in brownish black ink, no rules; the bounding lines extend to the edge of each page.</layout>
                        </layoutDesc>
                     </objectDesc>
                     <handDesc>
                        <handNote>Written in anglicana with secretary <hi rend="bold">r</hi>, s. xv<hi rend="superscript">med</hi>.</handNote>
                        <handNote>Punctuation by point and occasional double point; double virgulae, probably instructions for a parapher, have only been red-slashed.</handNote>
                     </handDesc>
                  </physDesc>
                  <history>
                     <origin>
                        <origPlace><country key="place_7002445">England</country></origPlace>
                        <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="1460" notBefore="1440">s. xv<hi rend="superscript">med</hi>
                        </origDate>
                     </origin>
                  </history>
               </msPart>
               <msPart xml:id="Christ_Church_MS_91-part3">
                  <msIdentifier>
                     <altIdentifier>
                        <idno type="part">Manuscript III = fols 166–94</idno>
                     </altIdentifier>
                  </msIdentifier>
                  <msContents>
                     <textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>
                     <msItem n="15" xml:id="Christ_Church_MS_91-part3-item1">
                        <locus from="166" to="194v">Fols 166–194<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>
                        </locus>
                        <incipit>Domum tuam domine decet sanctitudo in psalmo Nulla quies exterior potest delectare quamdiu consciencia habet vnde poterit</incipit>
                        <explicit>
                           <locus from="192v" to="192v">[fol. 192<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>]</locus> omnes gentes et sapiencie 12. propter hoc tanquam pueris insensatis iudicium derisum dedisti | Beda Omnia fera</explicit>
                        <rubric>Quoddam extractum de Holcote in lectura cum tabula <note>(the table, fol. i<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>)</note>
                        </rubric>
                        <author key="person_9841479">Robert Holcot</author>
                        <title key="work_4391">Super Sapientiam Salamonis</title>
                        <note>(selections)</note>
                        <note>Sharpe no. 1475 [553–58]. A series of selections, not in text order, but the ‘lectio’ from which each is excerpted is usually noted in the margin. The incipit corresponds to the printed text (Speier, 1483) (Hain 8757*, <title>BMC</title> 2:493, ISTC ih00289000) of lectio 115, sig. Z vii<hi rend="superscript">vb</hi>; and the explicit at fol. 192<hi rend="superscript">v</hi> to that of lectio 60, sig. N iiij<hi rend="superscript">va</hi>. Following the explicit are two further notes, one from <persName key="person_61539765" role="aut">Bede</persName>, one from a ‘narratio’ identified as taken from <persName key="person_9841479" role="aut">Holcot</persName>’s ‘sermo 11’. The index follows after an originally blank leaf at fols 194<hi rend="superscript">ra-vb</hi>, in double columns; at the end, a note in red explains its use. </note>
                        <note> The scribe left both fol. 190<hi rend="superscript">v</hi> and all of fol. 193<hi rend="superscript">rv</hi> blank but he subsequently added a text at the second verso:</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="16" xml:id="Christ_Church_MS_91-part3-item2">
                        <locus from="193v">Fol. 193<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>
                        </locus>
                        <rubric>
                           <note>[in upper margin]</note> ihc est amor meus <note>| [in outer margin]</note> In Die Palmarum</rubric>
                        <incipit>Ecce rex tuus venit Mathei 21. Commemorat ecclesia in presenti dominica duplicem cristi aduentum vnum quo venit in ierusalem cum honore</incipit>
                        <explicit>ipse enim accedit a fine usque ad finem fortiter et disponit omnia suauiter Omnia enim quecumque voluit fecit . . .</explicit>
                        <title key="work_14583" type="desc">Sermon</title>
                        <note> Wenzel, <title>Latin Sermon Collections</title>, 130.</note>
                     </msItem>
                  </msContents>
                  <physDesc>
                     <p>
                        <secFol>et verberat <locus from="167" to="167">(fol. 167)</locus>
                        </secFol>
                     </p>
                     <objectDesc form="codex">
                        <supportDesc material="perg">
                           <support>Parchment (FSOS)</support>
                           <extent>Fols 29. <dimensions type="written" unit="mm">
                                 <height>230</height>
                                 <width>160</width>
                              </dimensions>
                           </extent>
                           <foliation>separately foliated by a medieval hand 1–28, [29]</foliation>
                           <collation> 15–16<hi rend="superscript">12</hi> 17<hi rend="superscript">6</hi> (-5, a stub, probably blank). Catchwords near the gutter; no signatures. At final verso (fol. 194<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>) a catchword, not by the scribe, providing the first words of the following manuscript.</collation>
                        </supportDesc>
                        <layoutDesc>
                           <layout columns="1" writtenLines="53">In long lines, 53 lines to the page.</layout>
                           <layout>Bounded in brown and black ink, no rules; rare signs of two prick-holes at very bottom of folio in line with vertical borders.</layout>
                        </layoutDesc>
                     </objectDesc>
                     <handDesc>
                        <handNote>Written in anglicana with frequent secretary <hi rend="bold">a</hi>, s. xv<hi rend="superscript">3/4</hi>.</handNote>
                        <handNote>Punctuation by point and virgula, occasional punctus elevatus and double virgula.</handNote>
                     </handDesc>
                  </physDesc>
                  <history>
                     <origin>
                        <origPlace><country key="place_7002445">England</country></origPlace>
                        <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="1475" notBefore="1450">s. xv<hi rend="superscript">3/4</hi>
                        </origDate>
                     </origin>
                  </history>
               </msPart>
               <msPart xml:id="Christ_Church_MS_91-part4">
                  <msIdentifier>
                     <altIdentifier>
                        <idno type="part">Manuscript IV = fols 195–230</idno>
                     </altIdentifier>
                  </msIdentifier>
                  <msContents>
                     <textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>
                     <msItem n="17" xml:id="Christ_Church_MS_91-part4-item1">
                        <locus from="195ra" to="197rb">Fols 195<hi rend="superscript">ra</hi>–97<hi rend="superscript">rb</hi>
                        </locus>
                        <rubric rend="roman">
                           <note>[the heading added, s. xv]</note> Augustinus de 12. Abusionibus</rubric>
                        <incipit> Primo si sine operibus bonis sapiens et predicator fuerit quia quod sermone docet actibus explere negligit</incipit>
                        <explicit>Non faciamus itaque sine cristo aliquid in hoc tempore transitorio ne sine nobis cristus esse incipiat in future <note>[added, s. xv]</note>
                           <hi rend="italic">explicit</hi>
                        </explicit>
                        <author key="person_7386286">Ps.-Augustine</author>
                        <title key="work_3885">De xii abusionibus</title>
                        <note>
                           <ref target="https://clavis.brepols.net/clacla/OA/link.aspx?clavis=CPL&amp;number=1106"><title>CPL</title> 1106</ref>, ed. S. Hellman, <title>TU</title> 34, 1 (1909), 32–60.</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="18" xml:id="Christ_Church_MS_91-part4-item2">
                        <locus from="197rb" to="197va">Fol. 197<hi rend="superscript">rb–va</hi>
                        </locus>
                        <rubric>
                           <note>[the heading added in the margin, s. xv]</note> De dignitate natu<supplied>re</supplied> humane</rubric>
                        <incipit>Qvanta dignitas humane condicionis esse cognoscitur ut non solum iubentis sermone</incipit>
                        <explicit>qui se mirabiliter ad <note>[ymaginem]</note> et similitudinem suam in primo adam condidit mirabilius se reformauerit amen</explicit>
                        <author key="person_7386286">Ps.-Augustine</author>
                        <title key="work_3874">De creatione primi hominis</title>
                        <note>Ed. <title>PL</title> 40:1213–14 (and mostly incorporated into ‘De spiritu et anima’ 35, ed. <title>PL</title> 40:805–6), also <persName key="person_2349" role="aut">ps.-Alcuin</persName>, ‘Dicta Albini de imagine dei’, ed. John Marenbon, <title>From the Circle of Alcuin to the School of Auxerre</title> (Cambridge, 1981), 158–61. This copy is no. 25 in Marenbon’s list of thirty-one witnesses (149–50).</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="19" xml:id="Christ_Church_MS_91-part4-item3">
                        <locus from="197va" to="198rb">Fols 197<hi rend="superscript">va</hi>–98<hi rend="superscript">rb</hi>
                        </locus>
                        <rubric>
                           <note>[the heading added in the margin, s. xv]</note> Augustinus de Cognicione vere vite</rubric>
                        <incipit>Sapiencia dei que os muti aperuit et ruditili animali humana uerba formare tribuit</incipit>
                        <explicit>pugillo includit Si autem sempiternus predicetur et cunta tempora disponere astruetur</explicit>
                        <author key="person_100201145">Honorius of Autun</author>
                        <title key="work_2081">De cognitione veræ vitæ</title>
                        <note>(extract)</note>
                        <note>Ed. <title>PL</title> 40:1005–8. This copy is listed among copies of the work by Johannes Diviak and Franz Romer, <title>Scriptorium</title> 30 (1976), 107; they note Sion College, MS L.23 (now a Lambeth Palace Library deposit) as including the same excerpt. Lower half of fol. 198<hi rend="superscript">rb</hi> blank. </note>
                        <note> Fol. 198<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>: blank.</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <!-- check incipits etc of this entry -->
                     <msItem n="20" xml:id="Christ_Church_MS_91-part4-item4">
                        <locus from="199ra" to="206vb">Fols 199<hi rend="superscript">ra</hi>–206<hi rend="superscript">vb</hi>
                        </locus>
                        <incipit type="table">De miseria hominis</incipit>
                        <explicit type="table">Quod nichil proderit dampnandis</explicit>
                        <incipit>Domino patri karissimo P <note>[i.e. Petro]</note> portuensi episcopo Lotarius indignus diaconus graciam in presenti et gloriam in futuro Modicum ocij quod inter multas angustias . . . [fol. 199<hi rend="superscript">rb</hi>] Quare de uulua matris mee egressus sum ut uiderem laborem et dolorem et consumerentur</incipit>
                        <explicit>et terrores fames et sitis frigus et cauma sulphur et ignis ardens in secula seculorum amen</explicit>
                        <author key="person_16017787">Innocent III</author>
                        <title key="work_2191">De miseria condicionis humane</title>
                        <note>Ed. Michele Maccarrone (Lucca, 1955) 3–98 (this manuscript noted in the list of witnesses, xvi). Preceded by a table of chapters. </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="21" xml:id="Christ_Church_MS_91-part4-item5">
                        <locus from="206vb" to="213ra">Fols 206<hi rend="superscript">vb</hi>–13<hi rend="superscript">ra</hi>
                        </locus>
                        <rubric rend="roman">Incipit liber de mendacio beati Augustini episcopi</rubric>
                        <incipit>Magna questio est de mendacio que nos in ipsis cotidianis actibus nostris sepe conturbat</incipit>
                        <explicit>nos sinet temptari supra quam potestis ferre sed faciet cum temptatione etiam exitum ut possitis sustinere. </explicit>
                        <finalRubric>Explicit liber de mendacio</finalRubric>
                        <author key="person_66806872">Augustine</author>
                        <title key="work_770">De mendacio</title>
                        <note>
                           <ref target="https://clavis.brepols.net/clacla/OA/link.aspx?clavis=CPL&amp;number=303"><title>CPL</title> 303</ref>, ed. Zycha, 413–66.</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="22" xml:id="Christ_Church_MS_91-part4-item6">
                        <locus from="213ra" to="218vb">Fols 213<hi rend="superscript">ra</hi>–18<hi rend="superscript">vb</hi>
                        </locus>
                        <rubric>Incipit liber Augustini contra mendacium ad consencium</rubric>
                        <incipit> Multa michi legenda misisti consenti frater karissime quibus rescripta dum prep<expan>ar</expan>o et aliis</incipit>
                        <explicit>ut uix ad eius terminum quem loco isto finximus ueniremus </explicit>
                        <finalRubric>Explicit liber contra mendacium</finalRubric>
                        <author key="person_66806872">Augustine</author>
                        <title key="work_745">Contra mendacium</title>
                        <note>
                           <ref target="https://clavis.brepols.net/clacla/OA/link.aspx?clavis=CPL&amp;number=304"><title>CPL</title> 304</ref>, ed. Zycha, 469–528.</note>
                        <note> Last nine lines of fol. 218<hi rend="superscript">vb</hi> blank (though covered, as is the bottom margin, of the remains of s. xiii notes).</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="23" xml:id="Christ_Church_MS_91-part4-item7">
                        <locus from="219ra" to="221vb">Fols 219<hi rend="superscript">ra</hi>–21<hi rend="superscript">vb</hi>
                        </locus>
                        <rubric>
                           <note>[title in upper margin, s. xv]</note> liber Augustini de penitencia</rubric>
                        <incipit>Quam sit utilis et neccesaria penitencie medicina facillime homines intelligunt qui se homines esse meminerunt</incipit>
                        <explicit>labor minor imponitur et nullo temporalis mortis periculo mors eterna uitatur</explicit>
                        <author key="person_66806872">Augustine</author>
                        <title key="work_805">Sermo 351</title>
                        <note>
                           <ref target="https://clavis.brepols.net/clacla/OA/link.aspx?clavis=CPL&amp;number=284"><title>CPL</title> 284</ref>, ed. <title>PL</title> 39:1535–49. Later (s. xv) divided by marginal notation into chs 1–23.</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="24" xml:id="Christ_Church_MS_91-part4-item8">
                        <locus from="221vb" to="222ra">Fols 221<hi rend="superscript">vb</hi>–22<hi rend="superscript">ra</hi>
                        </locus>
                        <incipit>Penitentes penitentes penitentes Si tamen estis penitentes et non estis irridentes mutate uitam</incipit>
                        <explicit>Quid horum tibi futurum sit nescio Ergo dimitte incertum et tene certum Finitur</explicit>
                        <author key="person_7386286">Ps.-Augustine</author>
                        <title key="work_3907">Sermo 393</title>
                        <!-- (indexed under 'sermons') -->
                        <note><title>CPL</title>284, now ascribed to <persName key="person_54538580" role="aut">Geoffrey of Babio</persName>, ed. <title>PL</title> 39:1713–15; a later heading now erased and treated as continuous with the previous (numbered ch. 24 in the s. xv notation).</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="25" xml:id="Christ_Church_MS_91-part4-item9">
                        <locus from="222rb" to="230vb">Fols 222<hi rend="superscript">rb</hi>–30<hi rend="superscript">vb</hi>
                        </locus>
                        <rubric rend="roman">
                           <note>[heading added in outer margin, s. xv]</note> Prologus ad intelligendum difficilis quia verbis exoticis est vndique inuolutus</rubric>
                        <incipit>Cum nocte hiemali multe lugubrationis peruigilio plurimo in lignis oliue depasto usque ad . . . [fol. 222<hi rend="superscript">va</hi>] <supplied>A</supplied>mo amas maui are matus matu Verbum actiuum est inde hic amator oris</incipit>
                        <explicit defective="true">Boglossa lingua bouina Boblossus herba ad instar bouine lingue Bucerus bouinus</explicit>
                        <rubric>quedam deriuacio gramaticalis incompleta cum prologo difficili <note>(the table, fol. i<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>)</note>
                        </rubric>
                        <author key="person_54503605">Osbern Pinnock of Gloucester</author>
                        <title key="work_3409">Panormia seu Liber derivationum</title>
                        <note>Sharpe no. 1142 [407–8], ed. Paola Busdraghi et al., <title>Osberno Derivazioni</title>, Biblioteca di “medioevo latino” 16, 2 vols (Spoleto, 1996), 1:5–85. The editors misidentify the location (xiii) as Corpus Christi College (whence Sharpe’s reference). See R. W. Hunt, ‘The “Lost” Preface to the <hi rend="italic">Liber derivationum</hi> of Osbern of Gloucester’ in G. L. Bursill-Hall ed., <title>Collected Papers on the History of Grammar in the Middle Ages</title> (Amsterdam, 1980), 151–66, who notes our MS among the four English copies (152).</note>
                     </msItem>
                  </msContents>
                  <physDesc>
                     <p>
                        <secFol>constare <locus from="196" to="196">(fol. 196)</locus>
                        </secFol>
                     </p>
                     <objectDesc form="codex">
                        <supportDesc material="perg">
                           <support>Parchment (FSOS)</support>
                           <extent>Fols 36</extent>
                           <collation> 18–20<hi rend="superscript">12</hi>. No catchwords; all leaves in the first half of the final quire signed with a roman numeral. This last unit, beginning with item 23, might be construed as a separate booklet.</collation>
                        </supportDesc>
                        <layoutDesc>
                           <layout columns="2" writtenLines="54">In double columns, each column <dimensions type="column" unit="mm">
                                 <height>198</height>
                                 <width>55–60</width>
                              </dimensions>, with 8 mm between columns, in 54 lines to the page, below top line.</layout>
                           <layout>Bounded and ruled in lead; no signs of pricking.</layout>
                        </layoutDesc>
                     </objectDesc>
                     <handDesc>
                        <handNote>Written in gothic textura quadrata, s. xiii<hi rend="superscript">med</hi> or xiii<hi rend="superscript">2</hi>.</handNote>
                        <handNote>Punctuation by point, occasional punctus elevatus, punctus interrogativus, and double point.</handNote>
                     </handDesc>
                     <decoDesc>
                        <decoNote> Most typically two- and three-line blue lombards with red flourishing at the openings of and at divisions within texts (in the last MS, both red and blue lombards, unflourished, with many unfilled spaces). Lemmata and authorities underlined in red. The texts are divided by red-slashed capitals and red paraphs. Added running titles (s. xv ex.), usually only numbers for chapters or sermons, but intermittently text titles.</decoNote>
                     </decoDesc>
                  </physDesc>
                  <history>
                     <origin>
                        <origPlace>
                           <country key="place_7002445">England</country></origPlace>
                        <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="1300" notBefore="1240">s. xiii<hi rend="superscript">med </hi> or s. xiii<hi rend="superscript">2</hi>
                        </origDate>
                     </origin>
                  </history>
               </msPart>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2017-07-01">First online publication.</change>
         <change when="2017-05-25"><persName>James Cummings</persName> Up-converted the markup using <ref target="https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl">https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl</ref></change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
      <body>
         <p/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>