<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="manuscript_4936">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>MS. Gough London 10</title>
            <title type="collection">MSS. Gough</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp when="2026-02">Cataloguer</resp>
               <persName>Matthew Holford</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </publisher>
            <idno type="msID">MS_Gough_London_10</idno>
            <idno type="collection">Gough</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="MS_Gough_London_10" xml:lang="en">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <region type="county">Oxfordshire</region>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <institution>University of Oxford</institution>
                  <repository>Bodleian Library</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">MS. Gough London 10</idno>
                  <idno type="ieArk">ark:29072/x0jd472w36zn</idno><idno type="crArk">ark:29072/x0pc289h927z</idno><altIdentifier type="internal">
                     <idno type="SCN">18035</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
               <head>Chronicle of London with civic and guild documents; England (London), late 15th century</head>
               <msContents>
                  <msItem n="1" xml:id="MS_Gough_London_10-item1">
                     <locus>[contemporary addition] (fol. 3v)</locus>
                     <title type="desc">Form for proceding in a plea of mistreatment of an apprentice</title>
                     <rubric>Yff so be apprentes be mysse entreated or onlawfully chasted by his master</rubric>
                     <incipit>Vpon the which compleynt the chamberleyn shall call a seriaunt of the chambre and comaund hym to somon to appere before the seid chamberleyn vj oneste persones of the next aioynaunt to appere afore the seid cort by a day lymeted by the seid chamberleyn </incipit>
                     <explicit>The secund þat he is nott informed nor tawth in his occupacion. Also that he hath vnlawfull watche. Also that he hath nott his meate &amp; drynke at due tymes.</explicit>
                     <note>Perhaps breaks off unfinished. Added afterwards: 'Also ye shall truly enquere of all suche thynges as ye shalbe charged opon so'. An addition: fol. 3 is an original parchment endleaf, with the recto blank.</note>
                     <textLang mainLang="enm">Middle English</textLang>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="2" xml:id="MS_Gough_London_10-item2">
                     <locus>(fol. 4r)</locus>
                     <title type="desc">Notes of six obits in London at which the city chamberlain receives bequests.</title>
                     <incipit>The secund day of October the obite of John Carpenter holden at Geldhall chapell at which obite the chamberleyn is bequest vj s. viij d.</incipit>
                     <explicit>The xix day of August the obite of Water Nele holden at seynt Jemes in Garlykhyth at whiche obite the chamberleyn is bequest iij s. iiij d.</explicit>
                     <note>2 Oct., John Carpenter; 2 Nov., Henry Barton; 4 Nov., John Maldon grocer; Monday after Palm Sunday, William Olyvere; Friday in Whitsun week, John Reynwell; 19 August, Walter Nele.</note>
                     <textLang mainLang="enm">Middle English</textLang>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="3" xml:id="MS_Gough_London_10-item3">
                     <locus>(fol. 4v)</locus>
                     <title type="desc" key="work_10988">Chronicle of London for 1-10 Henry IV</title>
                     <rubric>Nomina maiorum et vicecomitum tempore regis Henrici Quarti ...</rubric>
                     <note>Discussed Mary-Rose McLaren, <title>The London Chronicles of the Fifteenth Century: A Revolution in English Writing</title> (D. S. Brewer, 2002), pp. 131-132. The only event noted in addition to the succession of officers is the battle of Shrewsbury: 'The same yere was the batell of Shrewysbery on Mary Magdeleyns even'.</note><textLang mainLang="la" otherLangs="enm">Latin and Middle English</textLang>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="4" xml:id="MS_Gough_London_10-item4">
                     <locus>(fols. 5r-8r)</locus>
                     <title type="desc">Lists of civic ordinances, almost all from London Letter Books G, H, I, K, L</title>
                     <rubric>Ordynaunces in the boke of .G.</rubric>
                     <incipit>Ordynaunces for weying from the comon beame, folio CCiiij<hi rend="superscript">xx</hi> xviij. Ordynaunces of pynnars, fol. xlviij. Ordynaunces of fullers, fol. cxvj. Ordynaunces of fullers, fol. ccxlij.</incipit>
                     <explicit>[ordenaunces in the booke off .L.]  Ordenaunc' of haberdasshers &amp; hurers in the joyernall when maister Hampton was maier the xxiiij day of Septembre. Ordenaunce for castyng donge in the Thamyse, folio lxxxv.</explicit>
                     <note>The latest ordinance is dated 1481. Rest of fol. 8r blank. Fols. 8v-9v ruled, blank; some text has been erased on fol. 9v. </note>
                     <textLang mainLang="enm">Middle English</textLang>
                     <!-- check: some may be recoverable -->
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="5" xml:id="MS_Gough_London_10-item5">
                     <locus>(fol. 10r)</locus>
                     <title type="desc">Notes of ordinances made in 13 Edw. IV (1474)</title>
                     <incipit>The xj day of Ianyvere anno Edwardi iiijti xiij Mathew Philip maier graunted an ordynaunce that all the ledder shulde be solde at Leden Hall. The vijth day of Septembre master Verney meyer made an ordenaunce that euery man that brought ledder to leden hall shulde paie for a dyker j d.</incipit>
                     <note>Given in full. Rest of fol. 10r blank.</note>
                     <textLang mainLang="enm">Middle English</textLang>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="6" xml:id="MS_Gough_London_10-item6">
                     <locus>(fols. 10v-19r)</locus>
                     <title type="desc">London civic and other oaths</title>
                     <note>Fols. 13r-19r are oaths of the Goldsmiths' Company and occur in a different order in the company's Book of Ordinances begun in 1478 by Miles Adys (for whom see Provenance) and others; printed in modern English translation in T. F. Reddaway and L. E. M. Walker, <title>The early history of the Goldsmiths' Company, 1327-1509</title> (1975), pp. 212-221.</note>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fol. 10v)</locus>
                        <rubric>Thys ys the othe of the chamberleyn of London</rubric>
                        <incipit>Ye shall swere that ye shall well and laufully serue the Cite of London in the office of chamburleyn, and all that ye haue in warde touchyng the cite, safely ye shall kepe. And the counsell of the cite ye shall nat discouer</incipit>
                        <explicit>And in all other thynges to youre office perteynyng, well and laufully ye shall haue yow. As god you helpe and all seyntes and by the boke.</explicit><!-- check "haue" (checked) -->
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fol. 11r-v)</locus>
                        <rubric>Thys ys the othe of fremen of London</rubric>
                        <incipit>Ye shall swere that ye shall be good and trewe vnto oure lyege lord kyng of Englond, and to hys heyres kynges, obeysaunt and obedient vnto the meyre and to the mynystres of the cite, the fraunchises and the customes therof ye shall meynteyne</incipit>
                        <explicit>so helpe yow god and holydom and by thys boke. I admyt yow into the lyberte of the cite of London as a freman. God yeue yow ioy therof.</explicit>
                        <listBibl><bibl>IPMEP 858</bibl><bibl>Pr. (from Mercers' wardens accounts), Blades, <title>Life and Typography of Caxton</title>, I, 86</bibl></listBibl>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fol. 11v)</locus>
                        <rubric>The presentement by byrthe</rubric>
                        <incipit>Maistyrs, here ys A. B. desyreth to be admyttyd into the liberte of thys cyte by hys byrthe. Ye wyll witnes here to the court that the sayd A. B. ys the son of C. D. and fre born wythyn the liberte of thys cyte, thys ye wyll wytnes. And also that the same A. B. neuyr offendyd syth he was made fre whereby he shuld lese hys liberte by, to your vnderstandyng and knowlege.</incipit>
                        <note>Given in full. </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fol. 12r)</locus>
                        <rubric>The presentment by redempcioun</rubric>
                        <incipit>Maistyr' wardeyns, here ys A. B. desyreth to be admyttyd into the liberte of thys cyte. Ye wyll witnes here to the court that the sayd A. B. ys an able man, and a man of good name and fame for to be of youre felyshyp. And that hys commyng in ys nat to deceue the kyng of hys custom, ne noon other felyshyp of thys cyte, but all suche thyngys as shall be leyde to hys charge in tyme commyng, as another freman doth accordyng to the custom of thys cite he shall do.</incipit>
                        <note>Given in full. </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fol. 12r)</locus>
                        <rubric>The presentment of translacioun</rubric>
                        <incipit>Masteris wardeyns here is A. B. citezein of London before this tyme was admitted into the liberte of the citee into the craft of C. D. Now the same A. B. desirith to be translate from the sayde craft of C. D. in to the felyship of E. F. ye well witnesse.</incipit><note>Given in full. </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fol. 12v)</locus>
                        <rubric>This ys the othe of the wardens of mercers</rubric>
                        <incipit>Ye shall swere that ye shalbe trew vnto oure liege lord the kyng and to his eyres kynges. Ye shall also wele &amp; truly obserue &amp; kepe all the goode and polityke rules and ordynaunces yn &amp; by the feliship of the mercery of olde ordeyned &amp; made.</incipit>
                        <explicit>And all the poyntes &amp; premisses afore rehersed ye shall wele &amp; truly kepe to youre power. So help you god &amp; holydom and by this boke.</explicit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fol. 13r)</locus>
                        <rubric>The othe of the wardens off goldsmythes</rubric>
                        <incipit><supplied reason="omitted">Y</supplied>e shall swere yat ye shall be feithfull &amp; trew to our lord the kyng and to his heyres kynges, and good &amp; trewe assay make of gold &amp; siluer and no thyng of gold and siluer touche but it be good &amp; lefull.</incipit>
                        <explicit>ne no man resceiue in to the companye withoute assent of the companye, so god you helpe and all seyntes and by the boke.</explicit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fol. 13v)</locus>
                        <rubric>The othe off newmen</rubric>
                        <incipit><supplied reason="omitted">Y</supplied>e shall swere that ye shall be feithfull and trew to our lord the kyng and to his heyres kynges and the peas of this citee well kepe to your power. And good &amp; trewe gold &amp; siluer withoute deceite ye shall werke and do werke, and no glasses nor counterfete stones sett in gold. </incipit>
                        <explicit>&amp; of noo bonde men, all which premysses aforeseid ye shall kepe in your behalff, so helpe you god &amp; all seyntes and by the boke.</explicit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fol. 14r)</locus>
                        <rubric>The othe off the rentars</rubric>
                        <incipit><supplied reason="omitted">Y</supplied>e shall swere that ye shal be feithfull and trewe to our lord the kyng and to his heyres kynges, and well and truly gader or do to be gadered the rent appertenyng to the company, and ouersee all the reparacions, vacacions and empcions of the same rentys when &amp; as ye be commaunded by your wardens, and all the rente that ye shall gader or do to be gadered with the reparacions, vacacions and empcions that shal be in your tyme, ye shall therof trewe accomptz make &amp; yelde when and as ye be commaunded by your wardens. So god you helpe and all seyntes and by the boke.</incipit>
                        <note>Given in full.</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fol. 14r)</locus>
                        <rubric>The othe of the clerke of the halle</rubric>
                        <incipit><supplied reason="omitted">Y</supplied>e shall swere that ye shal be feithfull &amp; trewe to the kyng &amp; to his heyres kynges, and that ye shal be good and trewe to the company and good and trewe counseill geve in tho thynges touchyng the nedes of the company after your cunnyng &amp; power</incipit>
                        <explicit>and truly entre tho thynges þat arne to entre touchyng þe company, and the profite off the companye ye shall do in as moche as ye may. So god you help &amp;c.</explicit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fol. 14v)</locus>
                        <rubric>The othe of goldbeters</rubric>
                        <incipit><supplied reason="omitted">Y</supplied>e shall swere that ye shal be feithfull &amp; trewe to our liege lord the kyng and to his heyres kynges, and good and trewe serche &amp; assay make of gold &amp; siluer appertenyng to your crafte, sparyng no man for loue nor fauour nor no man grevyng for hate or ivell will</incipit>
                        <explicit>And ye shall redely come to the somons of the wardens of goldsmythes when ye are warned iff ye ne haue resonable excusacion, so god you helpe and alle seyntes and by the booke.</explicit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fol. 15r-v)</locus>
                        <rubric>The othe of the collectour of the lyvelode</rubric>
                        <incipit><supplied reason="omitted">Y</supplied>e shall swere þat ye shall be feithfull and trewe to our liege lord the kyng &amp; to his heyres kynges, and that by all the tyme of your occupyeng ye shall well and truly gader the rent perteynyng to the company and ouersee all the tenementz and rentes pertynyng to the seid company</incipit>
                        <explicit>and do the most profite ye can in byeng of all maner stuff and letyng of houses and tenementes longyng to the company, so god you helpe &amp; all seyntes and by the boke.</explicit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fol. 15v)</locus>
                        <rubric>The othe of the preestys</rubric>
                        <incipit><supplied reason="omitted">Y</supplied>e shall swere that ye shall be feithfull and trewe to the kyng &amp; to his heyres kynges, and yee shall serue the company well &amp; truly for the tyme that ye be wytholde, and ye shall be redy atte warnyng of the brocours to come &amp; go wyth the wardens to all obitz and dirigees, and euery weke ones sey placebo &amp; dirigee for all the soules that haue been of the companye, so god you helpe and all seyntes and by the boke.</incipit>
                        <note>Given in full.</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fol. 16r-17r)</locus>
                        <rubric>The othe of thassayer</rubric>
                        <incipit><supplied reason="omitted">Y</supplied>e shall swere þat ye shall be feithfull and trewe to the kyng &amp; to his heyres kynges, &amp; trewe ye shal be in the office of comon assayer for the crafte of goldsmythes, and ye shall trewe assayes make of all such gold &amp; siluer as shal be brought vnto you to assaye</incipit>
                        <explicit>for the feleship &amp; euery membre therof ye shall do it iustly &amp; truly to your power wythoute any deceite, so god you helpe and all seyntys and by the boke.</explicit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fol. 17r-v)</locus>
                        <rubric>The othe of the bedell</rubric>
                        <incipit><supplied reason="omitted">Y</supplied>e shall swere þat ye shall be feithfull and trewe to the kyng &amp; to <sic>heyres</sic> kynges, and that ye shal be trewe and obedyent to your wardeins and of good beryng to the company, and ye shall do all suche thynges as the wardeins commaunde you to do for the nedes of the company</incipit>
                        <explicit>And all other goodys of the company comyng to your handys ye shall truly kepe &amp; deliuere to the wardeyns, and no profitz take to your selff, oute take that that is to you assigned by the wardeins. Soo god you helpe &amp;c.</explicit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fol. 17v)</locus>
                        <rubric>The othe off the brocours</rubric>
                        <incipit><supplied reason="omitted">Y</supplied>e shall swere that ye shal be feithfull and trewe to the kyng &amp; to his heyres kynges, and that yee shal be trewe to your wardeins and to all the companye, and to no man selle no thyng of golde ne siluer, stone ne perle, but to fremen of the same crafte</incipit>
                        <explicit>nor no profitz take to yourselff other wise than is assigned you by the wardens &amp; feleship. So god you &amp;c.</explicit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fol. 18r)</locus>
                        <rubric>The othe of the goldsmyth that shall vse the crafte of fynyng</rubric>
                        <incipit><supplied reason="omitted">Y</supplied>e shall swere that ye shall be feithfull &amp; trewe to the kyng &amp; to his heyres kynges, and all siluer that ye deliuere &amp; selle into the feleship, it shall mowe bere peny weight of allay, that it may be as good and accordyng to the kynges standard in fynesse.</incipit>
                        <explicit>wythoute any availe or profitt therof takyng to your selff, oute take that the owner shall yeve you for suche wasshyng, fynyng or partyng. So god you helpe &amp;c.</explicit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fol. 18v)</locus>
                        <rubric>The oothe of the turnour</rubric>
                        <incipit><supplied reason="omitted">Y</supplied>e shall swere that ye shal be feithfull and trewe to the kyng &amp; to his heyres kynges, and ye shall no werke of gold &amp; siluer turne &amp; clense in no placys but there as ye shal be assigned by the wardeins</incipit>
                        <explicit><sic>outee</sic> take that the owner shall yeve you by couenaunte for such turnyng &amp; clensyng. So god you helpe and all seyntys &amp; by the boke.</explicit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>[contemporary addition] (fol. 18v)</locus>
                        <incipit><supplied>Y</supplied>e shall swere that ye shal be feithfull and trewe to the kyng &amp; to his eyres kynges, and ye shall be trew &amp; obedient to your master as long as ye be hered with hym </incipit>
                        <explicit>and no profit take to your self out take <del>is</del> <sic>yeven you</sic> or your wages to you assigned so &amp;c.</explicit>
                        <note>No heading: the oath of a servant (see the following item); contemporary addition in a less formal hand. Not in the Goldsmiths' Book of Ordinances.</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>[later addition] (fol. 19r)</locus>
                        <rubric>The oothe of a seruant</rubric>
                        <incipit>Ye shall swere that ye shal be obedient feithfull and trew to your master, as long as ye be hered wyth hym, and ye shall do all suche thyng as a seruaunt ought to doo, to the most profyte of your master</incipit>
                        <explicit>out take your wagis or rewarde that is yeven or assigned yow, so god you helpe and all seyntys, and by the booke.</explicit>
                        <note>Later addition (s. xvi) in a less formal hand. Not in the Goldsmiths' Book of Ordinances.</note>
                     </msItem><textLang mainLang="enm">Middle English</textLang>
                        
                  </msItem>
                  
                  <msItem n="7" xml:id="MS_Gough_London_10-item7">
                     <locus>(fols. 19v-52r)</locus>
                     <title key="work_10988" type="desc">Chronicle of <placeName key="place_7011781">London</placeName> ending incomplete in 1470</title>
                     <incipit>The coronacion of kyng Richard the first was the iijde day of Septembre the yere of oure lord M<hi rend="superscript">l</hi>Clxxxix. Heere follewen the names of  all those persones that hath been custofes and baylyfs of the Cyte of London in the tyme off kyng Richard the first and kyng John that is to say: Henry Cornhyll, Richard Reyner - anno j<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>. The same day of coronacion all þe iues that were founde or myȝt be take were distroyed with wepyn or fire bothe by day and by nyght.</incipit>
                     <explicit defective="true">Richard Lee maior - Richard Gardener, Robert Droope - anno ix<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>. This yere after alhaloutide there was proclamacions made in London by þe kyngis commaundement that the kyng had pardoned all the northyn men for their rysyng <gap reason="editorial"/> and at þat tyme the Erle of Warwik was at Warwik and had reysed moche people</explicit>
                     <listBibl><bibl>For discussion of the text see Mary-Rose McLaren, ‘The Textual Transmission of the London Chronicles’, <title>English Manuscript Studies 1100-1700</title>, 3 (1992), 38-72 at 50-52; ead., <title>The London Chronicles of the Fifteenth Century</title>, pp. 113-115 and 253-255.</bibl>
                     <bibl><title>Six Town Chronicles of England</title>, ed. R. Flenley (1911), pp. 153-164, prints extracts from 1459-1470.</bibl>
                     <bibl>IPMEP 365</bibl></listBibl>
                     <textLang mainLang="enm">Middle English</textLang>
                    </msItem>
                  <msItem n="8" xml:id="MS_Gough_London_10-item8">
                     <locus>[later addition] (fols. 51r-52r)</locus>
                     <title type="desc">Added entries for 1495</title>
                     <incipit>Also on Fryday the xxxti day off Ianyvere the seid yere satt in the seid Guyhalde on a determyn' the maier, the duke off Bukkynggam, the lorde Markes, the erle off Aroundell, the erle off Derby, the erle of Suffolke, the erle off Essex, the erle of Surrey, the erle off Vrmond </incipit>
                     <explicit>Also the xvj day off Feueryere Moneday was Sir William Stanley lorde Chamberleyne pardoned off the kyng off hangyng &amp; drawyng and the seid day bytwene xj &amp; xij at noone was he ledde from the towre of London to the towre hyll &amp; there his hed smytten off and is beryed at <add>Saint Donnstones in th</add></explicit>
                     <note>Breaks off. Followed by a cancelled entry for 16 May 1550 </note>
                    <listBibl> <bibl>Printed Flenley, ed. cit., pp. 164-166.</bibl></listBibl>
                     <textLang mainLang="enm">Middle English</textLang>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="perg">
                        <support>Parchment of good quality. Irregular edge on the front endleaf, fol. 3, made good with a scarf repair before the text on fol. 3v was written.</support>
                        <extent>ii (paper) +  1 (parchment) + 49 + 1 (parchment) + ii (paper). Paper endleaves of the date of the binding.
                           <dimensions unit="mm" type="leaf">
                              <height quantity="245">c. 245</height>
                              <width quantity="185">c. 185</width>
                           </dimensions></extent>
                        <foliation>1-55 in (20th-century?) pencil</foliation>
                        <collation>one original endleaf (fol. 3), the stub wrapped around the first quire; 1(8-1) (second leaf missing, torn out (?), after fol. 4) (fols. 4-10), 2(8)-6(8) (fols. 11-50), 7(2) (fols. 51-2, a bifolium), one original endleaf (fol. 53). No catchwords or leaf signatures visible.</collation>
                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout rulingMedium="ink" columns="2" writtenLines="24">The main part of the manuscript, fols. 4r-50v, uniformly ruled in ink for two columns of 24 lines, with single vertical and double horizontal bounding lines the full width and height of the page, no ruling between columns, and double horizontal lines in the upper margin for running heads. Fol. 16r: (18 + [6] + 14 + [151] + 52) × (23 + [60 + 11 + 60] + 30). On fols. 10v-19r the text (for which the layout seems to have been designed) comprises headings in the upper margin and text in the central ruled space, so the written area is <dimensions unit="mm" type="ruled">
                              <height quantity="155">c. 155</height>
                              <width quantity="135">c. 135</width>
                        </dimensions>.</layout>
                        <layout columns="1" writtenLines="27" rulingMedium="ink">Elsewhere in the manuscript, notably in the chronicle section, the lines in the upper margin are used to contain the first line of the text, giving an overall written area of <dimensions unit="mm" type="ruled">
                              <height quantity="170">c. 170</height>
                              <width quantity="135">c. 135</width>
                        </dimensions>, and a total of usually 27 lines, with the division into columns generally ignored, except where it is used to structure the lists of mayors and bailffs, with mayors in the left column and bailiffs in the right.</layout>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc>
                     <handNote script="cursiva">Fols. 5r-10r, one hand, secretary with anglicana /a/.</handNote>
                     <handNote script="cursivaAntiquior">Fols. 10v-19r: several formal cursive hands, predominantly anglicana <!--one of which resembles a hand in the Goldsmiths' Book of Ordinances (Reddaway and Walker, pl. 15)--></handNote>
                     <handNote script="cursiva">The chronicle, fols. 19v-50v, in one hand, predominantly secretary in aspect but with anglicana /a/.</handNote>
                  </handDesc>
                  <decoDesc>
                     <summary><ref target="https://catalog.hathitrust.org/Record/000468709">Pächt and Alexander</ref> iii. 1129: 'Good initials'.</summary><decoNote type="decInit">2- to 3-line initials in gold, blue and rose on fols. 10v-12v; lettering in gold on fols. 11v-12v. The initials on fols. 10ra-12ra are attributed to the artist of MS. Douce 322 by Holly James-Maddocks, 'Scribes and booklets: the 'Trinity Anthologies' reconsidered', in <title>Scribal Cultures in Late Medieval England: Essays in Honour of Linne R. Mooney</title>, ed. Margaret Connolly, Holly James-Maddocks, and Derek Pearsall (Boydell &amp; Brewer, 2022), pp. 146-179 at p. 178.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="flourInit">Blue initials flourished in red, fol. 11r-v.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="unfilled">Spaces left for decorated initials on fols. 13r-18v, not filled in.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="rubrication">Red paraphs and underlining of proper names in the chronicle, and initials touched in red, otherwise no decoration.</decoNote>
                  </decoDesc>
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <binding notAfter="1800" notBefore="1700">
                        <p>18th-century calf with gilt tooling; gilt decoration on the spine, with 'CVSTOMES OF LONDON' and '.T. 5:5:'</p>
                        <p>Wormholes indicate a previous binding in wooden boards.</p>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="1500" notBefore="1470">15th century, late (1470 × 1495, perhaps c. 1477)</origDate>
                     <origPlace>
                        <country key="place_7002445">England</country>, <settlement key="place_7011781">London</settlement>
                     </origPlace>
                  </origin>
                  <provenance>Erased inscription (?), fol. 3r; other erasures, fols. 9v, 49v-50r (?).</provenance>
                  <provenance>The contents of fols. 4r-19r suggest that the volume was compiled for a chamberlain of London who was also a goldsmith. Flenley's suggestion of <persName role="fmo" key="person_861">Miles Adys (d. c. 1497)</persName> has been elaborated by Caroline Barron ('What did medieval London merchants read?', in <title>Medieval merchants and money. Essays in honour of James L. Bolton</title>, ed. Martin Allen and Matthew Davies (London, 2016), pp. 43-70 at 53-4). Adys was warden of the Goldsmith's Company 1477-8, chamberlain of London 1479-1484, and controller of the Goldsmith's Company in 1492.</provenance>
                  <provenance><persName role="fmo" key="person_90497252">Algernon Capel, earl of Essex</persName>; his armorial bookplate, dated 1701.</provenance>
                  <provenance notBefore="1795" notAfter="1809"><persName role="fmo" key="person_41970552">Richard Gough, 1735-1809</persName></provenance>
                  <acquisition when="1809">Bequeathed by him to the Bodleian.<!-- Former shelfmark Gough Missal 198. check this--></acquisition>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>Description by Matthew Holford (Febrary 2026). Previously described in the Summary Catalogue. <listBibl>
                              <bibl facs="aaz0259.gif" type="SC">Summary Catalogue, vol. 4, p. 240</bibl>
                           </listBibl>
                        </source>
                     </recordHist>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl><title>Six Town Chronicles</title>, ed. Ralph Flenley (1911), pp. 74-82</bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2026-02">Description revised.</change>
         <change when="2017-07-01">First online publication.</change>
         <change when="2017-05-25"><persName>James Cummings</persName> Up-converted the markup using <ref target="https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl">https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl</ref></change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>