<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="manuscript_4910">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>MS. Gough Eccl. Top. 5</title>
            <title type="collection">MSS. Gough</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Description</resp>
               <persName>Elizabeth Solopova</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Revision</resp>
               <persName>Andrew Dunning</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </publisher>
            <idno type="msID">MS_Gough_Eccl_Top_5</idno>
            <idno type="collection">Gough</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="MS_Gough_Eccl_Top_5" xml:lang="en">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <region type="county">Oxfordshire</region>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <institution>University of Oxford</institution>
                  <repository>Bodleian Library</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">MS. Gough Eccl. Top. 5</idno>
                  <idno type="ieArk">ark:29072/x09z903021r9</idno><idno type="crArk">ark:29072/x0ks65hc2655</idno><altIdentifier type="internal">
                     <idno type="SCN">17681</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents>
                  <textLang mainLang="enm" otherLangs="la">Middle English with Latin</textLang>
                  <msItem>
                     <note>Four originally blank parchment flyleaves at the beginning, the last three numbered i–iii (see Provenance).</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="1">
                     <locus from="1r" to="235r">(fols. 1r–235r)</locus>
                     <title key="work_13437" type="desc">New Testament in the Later Version of the Wycliffite Bible with usual prologues and rubrics</title>
                     <note>E.g., <q>Her endiþ þe gospel of matheu and bigynneþ þe prologe on þe gospel of mark</q>; <q>þis seiþ Ierom in his prologe on Mark. Her bigynneþ þe gospel on mark</q>, fol. 31r–v). Running titles on both rectos and versos, most consisting of abbreviated titles and chapter numbers of biblical books, in red, preceded by blue paraphs. Chapter numbers in red, usually <q>c<ex>apitulu</ex>m</q> followed by a Roman numeral. Red and blue paraphs at the start of sections within the text. Corrections in the original or contemporary hands; some omitted passages are added in the margins in red frames. A passage omitted at Luke 1 <locus from="50v" to="50v">(fol. 50v)</locus> is added by the original scribe on a narrow leaf inserted after fol. 50. Some omitted words and passages are added in the margins in an early modern hand (e.g., fols. 40v, 119v, 126v, 128v, etc.). No marginal glosses; added material within the text is not underlined; occasionally cross-references to biblical books in the margins. Indexing letters entered in the margins at the beginnings of lections, rather than consistently. The beginnings of lections are also often marked within the text with red wash, and red or blue paraphs. Some lections are accompanied by added notes in Latin in a 15th-century hand, specifying the liturgical occasion (e.g., fols. 4v, 55r, 57r, 111r, 160r, etc.). <q>Nota</q> marking didactic and moral passages, but also 1 Corinthians 14:18: <q>I thanke my god for I speke in þe langage of alle ȝou…</q>
                        <locus from="126r" to="126r">(fol. 126r)</locus>.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="2">
                     <locus from="235v" to="243r">(fols. 235v–243r)</locus>
                     <title type="desc">Table of lections of Type II</title>
                     <rubric>þe pistlis &amp; þe gospels of þe newe testament vn to seint andrewes euyn</rubric>
                     <note>Containing only New Testament readings. Written in a different ink, and probably by a scribe different from the scribe of the New Testament, on pages ruled for one or two columns, but not specially for a table of lections. Contains the temporal, followed by a short sanctoral (rubric: <q>ffrom andrewis euyn vnto þe comune þe proper pistlis &amp; gospelis</q>) that includes the feasts of Nicholas, George, Thomas Becket, Martin, Lawrence, Denis and Clement. The sanctoral is followed by a detailed common (rubric: <q>ffrom heþen þe pistlis &amp; þe gospels of þe comune</q>) and commemorations of the Virgin Mary, Trinity, Cross, the Holy Ghost, brothers and sisters, peace, clear weather, rain, battle and pestilence, angels, <q>for hym silf</q>, <q>for pestilence of beestis</q>, <q>ffor weyferynge men</q>, sins, sick, weddings, pilgrims, <q>Masse of requiem</q>. The entries consist of the name of a liturgical occasion in black or red, abbreviated reference to a book and chapter of the Bible, an indexing letter, the opening words of a reading, <q>ende</q> and the closing words of a reading, all in black.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="3">
                     <locus from="243r">(fol. 243r)</locus>
                     <title type="desc">A list of New Testament books in English</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem>
                     <note>Fols. 243v–246v were originally blank (see Provenance).</note>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="perg">
                        <support>parchment</support>
                        <extent>251 leaves, <foreign rend="italic">c.</foreign><dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                              <height>195</height>
                              <width>138</width>
                           </dimensions>, trimmed in rebinding</extent>
                        <foliation>modern in pencil and ink, unnumbered leaf, i–iii + 1–49 + 50a + 50* + 51–246</foliation>
                        <collation>(unnumbered leaf, fols. i–iii) I (8–4) missing 5–8 | <locus from="1" to="48">(fols. 1–48)</locus> II–VII (8) | <locus from="49" to="56">(fols. 49–56)</locus> VIII (8+1) 3rd inserted | <locus from="57" to="240">(fols. 57–240)</locus> IX–XXXI (8) | <locus from="241" to="246">(fols. 241–246)</locus> XXXII (8–2) missing 4, 5. Catchwords survive; quire signatures run consecutively a–p <locus from="1" to="120">(fols. 1–120)</locus>, followed by two quires without signatures <locus from="121" to="136">(fols. 121–136)</locus>, followed by quires signed r–z <locus from="137" to="192">(fols. 137–192)</locus>, &amp; (abbreviation for ‘and’), abbreviation for ‘con-’ <locus from="193" to="208">(fols. 193–208)</locus> and 1–4 <locus from="209" to="240">(fols. 209–240)</locus>. <secFol><q>apperide in</q>
                              <locus from="2r" to="2r">(fol. 2r)</locus></secFol>
                        </collation>
                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout columns="2" writtenLines="31">ruled in plummet for two columns, with single vertical and double horizontal bounding lines, extending the full height and width of page; additional sets of two bounding lines in the upper, lower and outer margins; 31 lines per page; written space: <foreign rend="italic">c.</foreign><dimensions type="ruled" unit="mm">
                              <height>128–130</height>
                              <width>90</width>
                           </dimensions>; prickings survive</layout>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc>
                     <handNote script="textualisNorthern">textura, black and brown ink; the table of lections is probably by a different scribe</handNote>
                  </handDesc>
                  <decoDesc>
                     <decoNote type="flourInit">4- to 8-line blue initials with red penwork and penwork borders at the beginning of books; 3- to 4-line similar initials at the beginning of prologues, and 3- to 6-line similar initials at the beginning of chapters.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="rubrication">Rubrics in red ink; blue paraphs at the start of sections within the text.</decoNote>
                  </decoDesc>
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <binding contemporary="true">
                        <p>Medieval oak boards covered with blue marbled paper. ‘John Wyklif’s <lb/> Translation of <lb/> The New Testament <lb/> MS.’ handwritten in ink on spine; fragmentary paper label with ‘90(?)1’ on spine.</p>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origPlace>
                        <country key="place_7002445">England</country>
                     </origPlace>
                     <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="1425" notBefore="1400">15th century, first quarter</origDate>
                     <p>Dialect survey: <list>
                           <item>ony(9)/any(1), ech(9)/eche(1), fire(3)/fier(7), ȝyue<ex>n</ex>(3)/ȝoue<ex>n</ex>(7), lyf(10), lyk(5)/lik(5), myche(10), siȝ(7)/syȝ(1)/sayȝ(1) (sg.), sayen(3)/siȝen(3) (pl.), silf(9)/self(1), siche(10), þouȝ(8), þorou(3)/þoruȝ(3)/þorouȝ(4)</item>
                           <item>-iþ(5)/-eþ(5) (pres.ind.3sg.), -en(10) (pres.ind.pl.), -ynge(7)/-yng(1)/-inge(2) (pres.part.) sche(10) (3sg.fem.pronoun, nom.), þei(10) (3pl.pronoun, nom.), hem(10) (3pl.pronoun, oblique), her(10) (3pl.pronoun, possessive)</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                  </origin>
                  <provenance>Copy of the Latin will of <persName role="sgn">Robert Thoft of St Botulph’s at Lincoln</persName> (?), dated 11 April 1415 <locus from="244v" to="244v">(fol. 244v)</locus>. Mentions hospital of St Catherine <q>iuxta Lincoln</q>, Richard Eston, Thomas Godney (or Gedney), guild of St Trinity, guild of the Assumption of the Virgin Mary, Juliana (wife) and William (son).</provenance>
                  <provenance>A 15th-century clerical (?) owner who marked the lections within the text and added Latin notes specifying the liturgical occasions when they were appointed to be read (see Text).</provenance>
                  <provenance><persName key="person_2755" role="fmo">William Turner</persName> (1509/10–1568), naturalist and religious controversialist, dean of Wells, 1563; see <title>Oxford Dictionary of National Biography</title>: <q>Amen W T</q>
                     <locus from="96r" to="96r">(fol. 96r)</locus>; ‘1563’, <q>Docter turner <lb/> in Welles. 12. daye auguste <lb/> Dean of Welles</q>
                     <locus from="243v" to="243v">(fol. 243v)</locus>. Also <q><persName key="person_2756" role="sgn">Jane Turner</persName></q>
                     <locus from="1r" to="1r">(fol. 1r)</locus> and <q><persName role="sgn">Wennyfred Turner</persName></q>
                     <locus from="246v" to="246v">(fol. 246v)</locus>. Corrections in the margins in an early modern hand (see Text).</provenance>
                  <provenance><q><persName role="sgn">William Mylett</persName> est nomen eius</q>
                     <locus from="246r" to="246r">(fol. 246r)</locus>, 16th century (?).</provenance>
                  <provenance><persName key="person_15121725" role="fmo">Daniel Waterland</persName> (1683–1740), theologian, rector of Walesby and Flixborough, Lincolnshire; see <title>Oxford Dictionary of National Biography</title>: note on fol. iii verso may be in his hand.</provenance>
                  <provenance><persName key="person_4939150" role="fmo">John Lewis</persName> (1675–1747), Church of England clergyman and antiquary; see <title>Oxford Dictionary of National Biography</title>: received the manuscript from Waterland and made it the base text of the gospels in Lewis (1731).</provenance>
                  <provenance><persName key="person_3499" role="fmo">Ebenezer Mussel</persName> of Bethnal Green in London: purchased from the executors of Lewis for £4-0-0 <locus from="iii-verso" to="iii-verso">(fol. iii verso)</locus>.</provenance>
                  <provenance><persName key="person_41944166" role="fmo">William Herbert</persName> (1718–1795), bibliographer and printseller; see <title>Oxford Dictionary of National Biography</title>: bought at Mussell’s sale (Langford of Covent Garden) in May 1766 <locus from="iii-recto" to="iii-recto">(fol. iii recto)</locus> (see de Hamel (1997), p. 90 and n. 13). Lot 901 in his sale on 21 November 1798.</provenance>
                  <provenance><persName key="person_41970552" role="fmo">Richard Gough</persName> (1735–1809); see <title>Oxford Dictionary of National Biography</title>.</provenance>
                  <acquisition when="1809">Bodleian Library: bequeathed by Gough; received in 1809.</acquisition>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>Elizabeth Solopova, <title><ref target="https://jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1gn6cmr">Manuscripts of the Wycliffite Bible in the Bodleian and Oxford College Libraries</ref></title>, Exeter Medieval Texts and Studies (Liverpool: Liverpool University Press, 2016), no. 24. Previously described: <listBibl>
                              <bibl facs="aaz0200.gif" type="SC">Summary Catalogue, vol. 4, p. 181</bibl>
                           </listBibl>
                        </source>
                     </recordHist>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl type="WRAPPER">
                     <listBibl type="PRINT">
                        <bibl>Lewis, J. (ed.), <title>The New Testament of our Lord and Saviour Jesus Christ translated out of the Latin Vulgat by John Wiclif</title> (London: John March, 1731).</bibl>
                        <bibl>Forshall, J. and Madden, F. (eds), <title>The Holy Bible … in the earliest English versions made from the Latin Vulgate by John Wycliffe and his followers</title>, 4 vols (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1850), vol. 1, pp. i, l.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Madan, F., <title>Summary catalogue of western manuscripts in the Bodleian Library at Oxford</title>, vol. 4 <title>(collections received during the first half of the 19th century) nos. 16670–24330</title> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1897), no. 17681.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Fristedt, S. L., <title>The Wycliffe Bible</title>, 3 vols (Stockholm: Almquvist &amp; Wiksells, 1953–73), vol. 1, p. 2.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Hudson, A., ‘Lollard book production’, in Griffiths, J. and Pearsall, D. A. (eds), <title>Book production and publishing in Britain 1375–1475</title> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1989), pp. 125–42, p. 140 n. 29. de Hamel, C., ‘The selling and collecting of manuscripts of Nicholas Love’s <title>Mirror of the Blessed Life of Jesus Christ</title> since the Middle Ages’ in Oguro, S., Beadle, R. and Sargent, M. G. (eds), <title>Nicholas Love</title> at <title>Waseda</title>: <title>proceedings of the international conference, 20–22 July 1995</title> (Cambridge: D. S. Brewer, 1997), pp. 87–97 at p. 90.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Scott, K. L. (gen. ed.), <title>An index of images in English manuscripts from the time of Chaucer to Henry VIII, c.1380–c.1509: the Bodleian Library, Oxford</title>, 3 vols (Turnhout: Harvey Miller Publishers, 2000–02), vol. 2, p. 50, no. 525.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Dove, M., <title>The first English Bible: the text and context of the Wycliffite versions</title> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2007), pp. 61 n. 124, 75 n. 48, 300.</bibl>
                     </listBibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2023-03-24">Add Solopova description.</change>
         <change when="2017-07-01">First online publication.</change>
         <change when="2017-05-25"><persName>James Cummings</persName> Up-converted the markup using <ref target="https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl">https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl</ref></change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
