<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xml:id="manuscript_4783" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>MS. Duke Humfrey d. 2</title>
            <title type="collection">MSS. Duke Humfrey</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Description</resp>
               <persName>David Rundle</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editing</resp>
               <persName>Andrew Dunning</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </publisher>
            <idno type="msID">MS_Duke_Humfrey_d_2</idno>
            <idno type="collection">Duke_Humfrey</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="MS_Duke_Humfrey_d_2" xml:lang="en">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <region type="county">Oxfordshire</region>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <institution>University of Oxford</institution>
                  <repository>Bodleian Library</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">MS. Duke Humfrey d. 2</idno>
                  <idno type="ieArk">ark:29072/x0t435gc57zh</idno>
                  <idno type="crArk">ark:29072/x0t148fg74nn</idno>
                  <altIdentifier type="internal">
                     <idno type="SCN">Not in SC (late accession): no detailed description available</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
               <head>Palladius, <title>De agricultura</title>, in English translation</head>
               <msContents>
                  <textLang mainLang="enm">Middle English</textLang>
                  <msItem n="1" xml:id="MS_Duke_Humfrey_d_2-item1">
                     <locus>(fols x recto-xviii verso)</locus>
                     <title type="desc">Alphabetical index to the work by folio number and stanza</title>
                     <incipit>Ayer water londe and gouernance</incipit>
                     <explicit>for to keep 74.a.b.</explicit>
                     <finalRubric>Explicit tabula. Deo gratias.</finalRubric>
                     <note>Lettered by folio, A–H.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="2" xml:id="MS_Duke_Humfrey_d_2-item2">
                     <locus>(fols xix recto–118v)</locus>
                     <author key="person_54143112">Palladius</author>
                     <title key="work_3435">On husbondrie</title>
                     <note>Middle English verse translation of <title key="work_3435">Opus agriculturae</title>, dedicated to <persName key="person_30785585" role="pat">Humfrey, Duke of Gloucester</persName>.</note>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fols xix recto–xxi recto)</locus>
                        <bibl>Proem</bibl>
                        <incipit>Agriculture as in nature and art <lb/> Tendure of creature</incipit>
                        <explicit>and his consideraunce.</explicit>
                        <finalRubric>Explicit prohemium id est pro emulis</finalRubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus>(fol. 14v)</locus>
                        <rubric>De preceptis rei rustice capitulum primum.</rubric>
                        <incipit>Consideraunce is taken</incipit>
                        <explicit>sentence as the same</explicit>
                        <finalRubric>Deo gracias.</finalRubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <incipit>Laude ymne honour</incipit>
                        <explicit>his honour est preconise.</explicit>
                        <finalRubric>Explicit.</finalRubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <note>After the proem (fol. xix–xxi), the work divides into thirteen books, the first (fol. 1–21) on general rules, followed by an envoi (fol. 22), then each is dedicated to a month, beginning with January, and dividing: II, fol. 23–30; envoi, fol. 31; III, fol. 32–53; envoi, fol. 53r–v; IV, fol. 54–71; envoi fol. 71v; V, fol. 72–75v, including envoi; VI, fol. 76–80, including envoi; VII, fol. 80–84v, envoi at fol. 85; VIII, fol. 85–88, including envoi; IX, fol. 88–92, including envoi; X, fol. 92–96, including envoi; XI, fol. 96–106, including envoi; XII, fol. 106–117, including envoi; XIII, fol. 117–118v.</note>
                     <note>Edited by M. H. Liddell (Berlin, 1896).</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="3" xml:id="MS_Duke_Humfrey_d_2-item3">
                     <locus>(fol. 119)</locus>
                     <note>Blank but ruled.</note>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="perg">
                        <support>Smooth, thin yellowish parchment (FSOS). All flyleaves, except fol. iii (tipped in, 19th century), were added with the present binding; pastedowns and their conjoints are marbled.</support>
                        <extent>ix + 131 + viii; <dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                              <height>223</height>
                              <width>152</width>
                           </dimensions>
                        </extent>
                        <foliation>Pen foliation by scribe, integral to layout, omitting opening index and proem: 1–118. Intermittent pencil foliation, 20th century, including flyleaves, index and proem: i–xxi, 119–127. <secFol>Cucumber [fol. xi]; Who kan [fol. xx]; De terre [fol. 2]; Fecundite [fol. 2]</secFol>
                        </foliation>
                        <collation mainStructures="8">Quires of eight: i<hi rend="superscript">10</hi> with first removed, ii–iii<hi rend="superscript">8</hi>, iv<hi rend="superscript">8</hi> with one added at end as fol. 22, v<hi rend="superscript">8</hi> with one added at end as fol. 31, vi–vii<hi rend="superscript">8</hi>, viii<hi rend="superscript">6</hi>, ix–xvi<hi rend="superscript">8</hi>, xvii<hi rend="superscript">2</hi>. <catchwords>Horizontal catchwords, centrally placed in lower margin where present; fol. 61v boxed low in margin towards inner bounding lines.</catchwords>
                           <signatures>Some signs of leaf signatures in text ink, by a single hand, and placed prominently in the intersection of outer offset column with bottom pair of horizontals; they are in one continuous series, in which fol. xx = ‘2’, fol. 1 = ‘4’, fol. 23 = ‘10 1’, fol. 40 = ‘9 1’, fol. 62 = ‘2 1’, fol. 70 = ‘3 1’ (but, by lapsus calami, fol. 73 = ‘2 4’), fol. 102 = ‘7 1’ etc. Some signs of another (?earlier) system so, e.g., fol. 94 is both ‘6 1’ and (cropped in outer lower corner) ‘m1’.</signatures>
                        </collation>
                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout columns="1" writtenLines="28">At fol. 6, ruled space: <dimensions type="ruled" unit="mm">
                              <height n="160">(18 + [160] + 45)</height>
                              <width n="79">(22 + [79] + 51)</width>
                           </dimensions>. Complex ruling in red with double vertical bounding lines, additional verticals toward gutter and fore-edge, and paired horizontals for running headers and catchwords/signatures. Ruling allows 32 lines, but one blank line between each seven-line stanza means usually 28 written lines.</layout>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc>
                     <handNote script="cursivaAntiquior">Written mainly in one small bookhand combining anglicana and secretary features: double-bowled a, slanted-backed d, anglicana g but r always short, sometimes ‘z-shaped’; no secretary slant. Somewhat changeable both in floridity—cf. fol. 5v with fol. 6 —in thickness—cf. fol. 31v with fol. 32r; each of these openings are across a quire-divide, and the differences led de la Mare to propose a change of scribe but the shifting styles within quires suggest they are a change of session rather than hand. Another scribe does take over for fol. 54–61 (quire ix), similar but with double-bowled d and more ornate w. Written in black with section headings rubricated by each scribe; the main scribe employs multi-coloured script (green, purple, blue and red) for all the proem, and then for the envois between ‘books’ (with gold also used at fol. 118v). The main scribe also provides marginal notes in Latin, as well as interlinear Latin glosses in a smaller script.</handNote>
                  </handDesc>
                  <decoDesc>
                     <decoNote type="decInit">Largest decoration is the 12-line initial opening the proem (fol. xix), gold on pied blue/pink field, with white filigree. Book 1 opens with a 7-line initial containing Humfrey's coat of arms.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="flourInit">Sections open with 2-line pen-flourished initials (blue on red). Stanzas open with alternating blue/red coloured letters.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="colInit">A stanza opens with a coloured letter, alternating blue and red, and each line’s majuscule is shaded in red, as are other majuscules.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="rubrication">The extra lines in top margin provide space for book number, ‘L’ in blue on verso, Roman number in red on recto, both centred; and for the section of the work (Table, Prohemium, Gouernance, and then month) plus, after Prohemium, the folio number at right.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote>If there was a leaf before the present fol. i, it may have had a frontispiece or ornamented title.</decoNote>
                  </decoDesc>
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <binding notAfter="1767" notBefore="1750">
                        <p>Morocco over thin wood (1750s × 1767), double fillet at edges and a fleuron in each corner. Set in the upper board is an enamel (115 × 87 mm) depicting a young lady in red cap and dress, with a dark sheet hanging down from her forearms which are partly covered by it. An identification is proposed by the inscription in gilt capitals on dark green around it: <q>Jaqueline Duchess of Bavaria Countess of Holland Zealand &amp; Henault, Wife of Humphrey Duke of Glocester 1427</q>. The lower board has a rectangle of similar size, with dark green surround with gilt floral features, the centre rectangle divided into four and the subdivided by a diagonal, so creating a central lozenge, all decorated with small floral ornaments. For context of this binding, see James West’s note (fol. ii verso).</p>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origPlace>
                        <country key="place_7002445">England</country>
                     </origPlace>
                     <origDate calendar="Gregorian" cert="high" notAfter="1444" notBefore="1439">1439 × 1444</origDate>
                     <p>This manuscript announces itself, with the inclusion of Humfrey’s coat-of-arms, to be the dedication copy to him of this translation. It was produced with care: indeed, the preparation of parchment, the fact that the first quire is a quinion and the attention to scholarly paratexts suggests that engagement with the humanist agenda went beyond the author’s knowledge of Italians in Humfrey’s circle. Textual evidence helps date its production to a five year period: a scribal marginal note mentions that the Duke had given the University of Oxford ‘plures s. CXXX’ volumes, a number which shows it was after his first major donation in 1439 but before 1444, by when the number became nearly triple that. The author of the work is less certain, though Howlett has made an interesting proposal of it being Thomas Norton. It is not clear whether the author was involved in the making of this book which so manifestly articulated the learned ambitions of the work. It may be suggestive of the milieu of its making that whoever was in charge of its production could call on a second scribe as an assistant.</p>
                  </origin>
                  <provenance><persName key="person_30785585" role="fmo">Humfrey, Duke of Gloucester (1390–1447)</persName>. The manuscript lacks the duke’s ex libris though it is not implausible that it may have appeared at the putative lost first folio. Howlett (p. 246) suggested that Humfrey may have been an annotator of this book but this has recently been rejected by Rundle. Its eighteenth-century owner, James West (see below), assumed that the book had been given by the Duke to the University of Oxford but there is no evidence for this and, given the near-complete lack of vernacular books in his donations to what was an institution of Latin learning, it is prima facie unlikely (Humfrey did give a copy of the Latin original to the University: Thomson ed., Oxford, UO1.101). The present manuscript presumably was among the residue of his collection which was dispersed following his death (on the process, see Rundle, ‘Habits’).</provenance>
                  <provenance>There is no internal evidence for its provenance immediately post-Humfrey. What can be reconstructed of the later history of the manuscript has been elucidated by A. C. de la Mare. She noted the presence at fol. 119v of three names, each written in a different but similar upright round hand: <q><persName key="person_1271" role="sgn">William Hodgkin</persName></q> (cropped at top), <q><persName key="person_391" role="sgn">Georg Hodgkin</persName></q> and <q><persName key="person_339" role="sgn">Fely: [? or July:] Hodgkin</persName></q>. She dated these to the seventeenth century; the script suggests that, if so, it was towards the end of the century or into the eighteenth. It has not proven possible to identify this Hodgkin family.</provenance>
                  <provenance><persName key="person_46572341" role="fmo">James West (1703–1772)</persName>, signed <q>J West 1767</q> (fol. ii recto); he records rebinding and incorporation of the enamel in the covers. As de la Mare notes, this is identifiable as James West, lawyer, politician and President of the Royal Society (1768 until death), who was an avid book-collector. He describes the situation in which he found the book: <q>This very Curious MS of Husbandry … was in Rotten Wood binding, almost destroyed by worms</q> (there are several holes at fol. 119 and a few at fol. x which corroborate this claim). West goes on to explain the unusual presence of the enamel on the replacement binding he gave the book: <q>The Enamel of Jaqueline is well preserved &amp; was found wrapt up with the Manuscript &amp; by the Judicious &amp; Laborious Mr Stillingfleet judged proper to make a part of the New binding</q> (fol. ii verso). From this we can take it that West acquired this manuscript by private transaction rather than at auction, and that he soon showed it to Benjamin Stillingfleet (1702–1771), the grandson of Bishop Stillingfleet and himself a botanist interested in agriculture. Following West’s death, his collection was sold at auction in two sales by Messrs Langford of Covent Garden—<title>The Large and Justly Admired Museum of Curiosities</title>, which contained several manuscripts, mainly missals (beginning 27 February 1773), and <title>Bibliotheca Westiana</title>, mainly of printed books (beginning 29 March 1773)—but this manuscript was in neither sale.</provenance>
                  <provenance><persName key="person_1131" role="fmo">Sixth Earl Fitzwilliam, of Wentworth Woodhouse</persName>, by 1862. Shelfmarks <q>E. 4. 41</q> (crossed out) and <q>Z.1.22</q>. The latter was the shelfmark in use when it was seen by Henry Joseph Moule, who served as a tutor in the household. In a note published in the Athenaeum on 17 November 1888, he broadcast its existence, and mentioned that he himself had penned a note in 1862; this was tipped in as fol. iii but later torn and so survives only partially.</provenance>
                  <provenance notBefore="1902"><persName key="person_26959327" role="fmo">William Charles de Meuron, seventh Earl Fitzwilliam (d. 1943)</persName>, who succeeded to the title in 1902. His book plate at the inner board.</provenance>
                  <acquisition when="1984-10">Allocated to the Bodleian in October 1984 in lieu of death duties, as explained by de la Mare.</acquisition>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>Description by David Rundle, edited by Andrew Dunning (2026).</source>
                     </recordHist>
                     <availability status="restricted">
                        <p>To ensure its preservation, access to this item is restricted, and readers are asked to work from reproductions and published descriptions as far as possible. If you wish to apply to see the original, please click the request button above. When your request is received, you will be asked to contact the relevant curator outlining the subject of your research, the importance of this item to that research, and the resources you have already consulted.</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <surrogates>
                     <bibl subtype="partial" type="digital-facsimile"><ref target="https://digital.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/objects/a4593fe2-94d4-4f3e-9161-d2080bb35471/"><title>Digital Bodleian</title></ref><note>(3 images from 35mm slides)</note></bibl>
                     <bibl type="microfilm">Microfilm available in the open shelf collections in the Weston Library (R. Films 101)</bibl>
                  </surrogates>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>Howlett, David R., ‘<ref target="https://doi.org/10.2307/43628272">The Date and Authorship of the Middle English Verse Translation of Palladius’ <title>De re rustica</title></ref>’, <title>Medium Ævum</title>, 46/2 (1977), 245–52.</bibl>
                     <bibl>Mare, Albinia C. de la, ‘<ref target="https://doi.org/10.3828/blr.1985.12.1.39">Duke Humfrey’s English Palladius (MS. Duke Humfrey d. 2)</ref>’, <title>Bodleian Library Record</title>, 12/1 (1985), 39–51.</bibl>
                     <bibl>Moule, H. J., <q><ref target="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/njp.32101077276499?urlappend=%3Bseq=482">A MS. of the Metrical Translation of Palladius’ <title>De re rustica</title></ref></q>, <title>Athenaeum</title> (July–December 1888), 664.</bibl>
                     <bibl>Rundle, David, ‘Habits of Manuscript-Collecting: The Dispersals of the Library of Humfrey, Duke of Gloucester’, in James Raven, ed., <title>Lost Libraries: The Destruction of Great Book Collections since Antiquity</title> (Houndmills, 2004), 106–24.</bibl>
                     <bibl>Rundle, David, ‘The Library of Humfrey, Duke of Gloucester and His Reading Habits’, in M. A. Michael, ed., <title>England and France before 1500: Proceedings of the 2023 Harlaxton Symposium Held in Honour of Jenny Stratford</title>, Harlaxton Medieval Studies, 34 (Donington, 2025), 226–54.</bibl>
                     <bibl>Thomson, Rodney M., ed., <title>The University and College Libraries of Oxford</title>, with James G. Clark, 2 vols, Corpus of British Medieval Library Catalogues, 16 (London, 2015).</bibl>
                     <bibl>Wakelin, Daniel, <title><ref target="https://doi.org/10.1093/acprof:oso/9780199215881.001.0001">Humanism, Reading, and English Literature, 1430–1530</ref></title> (Oxford, 2007).</bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2026-02-24">New description by David Rundle.</change>
         <change when="2017-07-01">First online publication.</change>
         <change when="2017-05-25"><persName>James Cummings</persName> Up-converted the markup using <ref target="https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl">https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl</ref></change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
