<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xml:id="manuscript_9796" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>MS. Duke Humfrey c. 1</title>
            <title type="collection">MSS. Duke Humfrey</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Description</resp>
               <persName>David Rundle</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Revision</resp>
               <persName>Andrew Dunning</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </publisher>
            <idno type="msID">MS_Duke_Humfrey_c_1</idno>
            <idno type="collection">Duke_Humfrey</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="MS_Duke_Humfrey_c_1" xml:lang="en">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <region type="county">Oxfordshire</region>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <institution>University of Oxford</institution>
                  <repository>Bodleian Library</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">MS. Duke Humfrey c. 1</idno>
                  <idno type="ieArk">ark:29072/x041687k15gw</idno>
                  <idno type="crArk">ark:29072/x044558f98sk</idno>
                  <msName>The Duke Humfrey New Testament</msName>
               </msIdentifier>
               <head>Old French New Testament, ‘version du xiiiᵉ siècle’</head>
               <msContents>
                  <textLang mainLang="fro" otherLangs="la">Old French with Latin</textLang>
                  <msItem>
                     <locus from="1r" to="98v">(fols 1r–98v)</locus>
                     <title key="work_13448" type="desc">New Testament, Old French translation, ‘version du xiiiᵉ siècle’</title>
                     <note>Unprinted; described by Samuel Berger, <title>La Bible Française au moyen âge</title> (Paris, 1884), 109–56; but for important revisions, see the works of Clive R. Sneddon.</note>
                     <note>This volume does not open (as does <ref target="https://medieval.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/catalog/manuscript_3939">Oxford, Christ Church, MS. 178</ref>) with a table of contents; as the one surviving quire signature shows, there was once two quires at the front, that table and any other paratext may have been included there.</note>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="1r" to="14v">(fols 1r–14v)</locus>
                        <title>Matthew</title>
                        <rubric>Liber generationis ihesu christi filij dauid filij abraham abraham autem.</rubric>
                        <incipit>Li livres de la generacion</incipit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="14v" to="24r">(fols 14v–24r)</locus>
                        <title>Mark</title>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="24r" to="39r">(fols 24r–39r)</locus>
                        <title>Luke</title>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="39r" to="50v">(fols 39r–50v)</locus>
                        <title>John</title>
                        <finalRubric>Ci finent les saintes euuangiles.</finalRubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="50v" to="55v">(fols 50v–55v)</locus>
                        <title>Romans</title>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="55v" to="60r">(fols 55v–60r)</locus>
                        <title>1 Corinthians</title>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="60r" to="63r">(fols 60r–63r)</locus>
                        <title>2 Corinthians</title>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="63r" to="64v">(fols 63r–64v)</locus>
                        <title>Galatians</title>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="64v" to="66r">(fols 64v–66r)</locus>
                        <title>Ephesians</title>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="66r" to="67r">(fols 66r–67r)</locus>
                        <title>Philippians</title>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="67r" to="68v">(fols 67r–68v)</locus>
                        <title>Colossians</title>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="68v" to="69v">(fols 68v–69v)</locus>
                        <title>1 Thessalonians</title>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="69v" to="70r">(fols 69v–70r)</locus>
                        <title>2 Thessalonians</title>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="70r" to="71r">(fols 70r–71r)</locus>
                        <title>1 Timothy</title>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="71r" to="72r">(fols 71r–72r)</locus>
                        <title>2 Timothy</title>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="72r" to="72v">(fol. 72r–v)</locus>
                        <title>Titus</title>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="72v" to="73r">(fols 72v–73r)</locus>
                        <title>Philemon</title>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="73r" to="76r">(fols 73r–76r)</locus>
                        <title>Hebrews</title>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="76r" to="88r">(fols 76r–88r)</locus>
                        <title>Acts</title>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="88r" to="89r">(fols 88r–89r)</locus>
                        <title>James</title>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="89r" to="90v">(fols 89r–90v)</locus>
                        <title>1 Peter</title>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="90v" to="91r">(fols 90v–91r)</locus>
                        <title>2 Peter</title>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="91r" to="92v">(fols 91r–92v)</locus>
                        <title>1 John</title>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="92v">(fol. 92v)</locus>
                        <title>2 John</title>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="92v">(fol. 92v)</locus>
                        <title>3 John</title>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="92v" to="93r">(fols 92v–93r)</locus>
                        <title>Jude</title>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="93r" to="98v">(fols 93r–98v)</locus>
                        <title>Apocalypse</title>
                        <explicit>soit o uos touz amen.</explicit>
                        <note>[8 lines blank]</note>
                        <finalRubric>Explicit librum. Qui scripsit sit <sic>bene dictum</sic>.</finalRubric>
                        <note>Added to the final rubric, ?s. xvi, but later crossed out: <q>mccciii</q>.</note>
                        <note>Chapter numbering goes awry at fol. 94r where it jumps from ‘III’ to ‘V’ but is corrected by having two chapters ‘VI’.</note>
                     </msItem>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="perg">
                        <support>Thin parchment, suede-like on both sides, disposition regular (hair-side outermost). Opening recto and final verso both worn; a single restitched blemish (fol. 38, in lower margin, stitching lost), and a slip of parchment repairing at hole at fol. 22 (top right, made before writing). Significant water and wax damage at fols 41r–42r (John 6–8), perhaps a reflection of chapel use; further wax marks at fol. 75v (lower margin) and fol. 76 (outer margin), and cf. fols 89v–92r (at fol. 90, I Peter 3–5 also an ?ink smudge at bottom right corner); it also seems that a round ?hot object was placed on the lower inner margin of fol. 68 or 69, causing a crinkled circle to surrounding pages.</support>
                        <extent>ii + 98 + ii leaves. All flyleaves are paper added with binding <watermark>(watermarks: fleur-de-lys, ‘IV’)</watermark>. <dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                              <height>306</height>
                              <width>215</width>
                           </dimensions>
                           <secFol>lors fu (fol. 2); honore (fol. 3)</secFol>
                        </extent>
                        <foliation>Pencil foliation added by Andrew Dunning, January 2025: i–ii, 1–100, including right flyleaves.</foliation>
                        <collation>Quires of twelve: i–viii¹² ix². Only one catchword partially visible (fol. 48v, cropped). In quire vi (from fol. 61), there is, centre foot, a quire signature (h) and signs of leaf signatures as a simple letter, placed in the outer corner (fol. 64 = ‘d’ cropped; cf. fol. 77 = ‘e’ with a superscript ‘i’).</collation>
                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout columns="2" writtenLines="50" topLine="below"><dimensions type="written" unit="mm">
                              <height max="209" min="24">(24 + [209] + 73)</height>
                              <width max="66" min="14">(30 + [65 + 14 + 66] + 40)</width>
                           </dimensions> (measurements taken from fol. 40). Ruled in lead with single vertical bounding lines but with an extra vertical in the gutter (13 mm to left), and two extra in outer margin (first 12 mm to right, width between 4 mm), and with two extra horizontals in upper margin (for running headers, lower 14 mm above, width between 4 mm) and lower (33 mm below, 4 mm between). All verticals, the top two and bottom two horizontals as well as the extra tramlines all reach the edge of the folio, while all other horizontals cross the central reservation but are confined by the bounding lines. No signs of full pricking but prick holes often visible in line with the tramlines for running headers and top two lines (10mm right of column b), and in lower margin for all verticals (17 mm from edge). 50 lines to the column, below top line. 2 cols., 54 lines, column space.</layout>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc>
                     <handNote script="textualisNorthern">Written in a single large ‘pearl script’ (4 mm between lines, minims 2mm, ascenders 3mm), with final <q>s</q> oscillating between tall and angular double bowled; there is a propensity to hairline approach strokes at the heads of ascenders. The script is close in style but independent from that found in Oxford, Christ Church, MS. 178.</handNote>
                  </handDesc>
                  <decoDesc>
                     <decoNote type="histInit">Fol. 1 opens with a tree of Jesse from which grows four roundels, on a gold base, with green leaves, but with the roundels having figures in red and white on a blue background, hashed with white and red. Each book opens with an eleven-line historiated initial, with a thin border often running the height of the written space. The palette is dominated by pink and blue, with a little use of gold, red and green. In each case, the depiction is of the author, with each evangelist having his symbol. There are occasional marginal grotesques and lions (e.g. fol. 68v); other grotesques float in the margin near chapter openings. Scot McKendrick attributed the decoration to the Cholet Master. Each chapter has a three-line initial in the same palette. Running headers in majuscules, alternating red and blue, as do chapter numbers. On the artist, see M. A. Stones, ‘Les manuscrits du cardinal Jean Cholet et l'enluminure beauvaisienne vers la fin du XIIIème siècle’ in <title>L'Art gothique dans l'Oise et ses environs: Architecture civile et religieuse, peinture murale, sculpture et arts précieux, etc. …; Colloque international organisé à Beauvais les 10 et 11 octobre 1998 par le G.E.M.O.B. (Groupe d’Etude des Monuments et Oeuvres d'Art de l'Oise et du Beauvais)</title> (Beauvais, 2001), pp. 239-66. See also her discussion of Padua, Biblioteca Capitolare, MSS D 34 and C 47 in <title>Gothic Manuscripts</title>, i/2, pp. 54-57 and ii/2, fig. 110–115.</decoNote>
                  </decoDesc>
                  <additions>There are several layers of early marginalia. Some readers provide textual corrections, interlinear (fol. 3; cf. note in margin at fol. 44v) and in lower margin (two hands: fol. 10v, s. xv¹ – cf. fol.17, 28v; fol. 12v, s. xiv² – also fol. 13v erased, and in outer margin at fol. 15v). This last hand, writing in a thin small secretary script in gray adds some annotations in the early folios, e.g. fol. 5 (‘de saint J. B’ against Matthew 11.i), to which a thicker and darker script of the same style and date adds further a note (cf. also this hand’s ‘nota’ mark at fol. 26v and 27); it also marks up the text on occasion for liturgical use (fol. 1v: ‘fer. s. i in adventum ebdo. i’, next to Matthew 3.i; fol. 5: ‘doc’ 3 in aduen¦¦’, next to Matthew 11.i; fol. 14v: ‘fer’ iiij in adu’, next to opening of Mark; fol. 38v: ‘fer’ 2 post pasc’’ next to Luke 24.xiii; fol. 54v: ‘¦¦l doc’ i adventus’; fol. 56: ‘doc’ 3 in aduent’; cf. fol. 65: ‘dc’ 16 epl’’, next to Ephesians 3.xii). The presence in this script of an anglicana descending <q>r</q> suggests these notes were added after its arrival in England. There is also a small secretary script (s. xiv/xv) in both gutter and outer margin: fol. 2-3. There is no sign of Humfrey annotating this manuscript. Annotations are concentrated in the first twenty leaves.</additions>
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <binding notAfter="1700" notBefore="1650">
                        <p>Plain brown leather over pasteboards (s. xvii ex.). Only decoration is gold-stamped patterns in each compartment on the spine, interrupted in the first compartment with the words ‘Novum Testame MSS.’ The second tool from the foot has three ostrich feathers with a bend on which there are three roundels. This is identifiable as stamp 3 found on the books of Joseph Gulston (with thanks to David Pearson in making this identification). Edges of the folios gilded. No sign of previous binding except for worm-holes in the last seven pages of the book (and just one in the first).</p>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="1275" notBefore="1250">13th century, third quarter</origDate>
                     <origPlace>
                        <country key="place_1000070">France</country>
                     </origPlace>
                  </origin>
                  <provenance>There is no evidence to identify with any certainty the first owner of this book. It may be that the lost two opening quires provided some provenance information, and they may have been removed for that reason.</provenance>
                  <provenance notAfter="1350" notBefore="1345">The earliest ownership note is that of <persName key="person_42632679" role="fmo">Jean ‘le Bon’</persName>, future king of France, who wrote his <foreign>ex libris</foreign> below the explicit: <quote>Ceste Bible est le Duc de Normendie et Guiene <lb/> Jehan</quote>. The inscription is presumably datable to between 1345, when he received those duchies, and 1350, when he became king as Jean II. It has been assumed that the manuscript was lost to the English at Poitiers, as was another of Jean’s (London, British Library, Royal MS 19 D. ii). The manuscript certainly does not appear in the inventories of the French royal library drawn up under his successors, but those lists are not a full record of what belonged to the French kings. There is a gap in the sequence of inscriptions which allows the possibility that it travelled with Jean to England and remained after his death, or that it crossed the Channel either before his capture or later.</provenance>
                  <provenance>The next ownership note sits directly below John II’s: <quote>Thomas de Lancastre <gap n="7" unit="char"/> regine</quote>. If this implies that it was given it to him by a queen, it could plausibly be his stepmother, <persName key="person_58160208665048621726" role="fmo">Joan of Navarre (1368-1437)</persName>, whom Henry IV married in 1403; perhaps, then, this manuscript arrived in England with her.</provenance>
                  <provenance notAfter="1412">The volume presumably reached <persName key="person_2485" role="fmo">Thomas of Lancaster</persName> before 1412, since he does not mention the title he received that year of duke of Clarence.</provenance>
                  <provenance><persName key="person_60226121" role="fmo">Margaret Holland (1385–1439)</persName> married Thomas of Lancaster in 1412. Scot McKendrick notes that she was the mother of Edmund Beaufort.</provenance>
                  <provenance><persName key="person_304925209" role="fmo">Edmund Beaufort (c. 1406–1455)</persName> received the title of count of Mortain after the death of John, duke of Bedford in 1435, giving a <foreign>terminus ante quem non</foreign> for his gift of the book to Humfrey, as inscribed on fol. 98v.</provenance>
                  <provenance><persName key="person_30785585" role="fmo">Humfrey, duke of Gloucester (1390–1447)</persName>: inscription between the last line of text and the explicit, fol. 98v: <quote>Cest livre est de moy Homfrey <lb/> duc de Gloucestre du don mon <lb/> treschier et tresame cousin le conte <lb/> de Mortaing Edmund</quote>. Humfrey also added his ‘Loyale et belle’ motto at the top of fol. 98v (he leaves no markings earlier in the manuscript: it would have been characteristic of him to add some words at the start of the volume, so perhaps when he owned it, it had its first two quires).</provenance>
                  <provenance>Humfrey’s inscriptions and all others have been erased in the same style of light scratching, leaving only that of Jean le Bon. It appears that one hand wrote at top left and bottom left of the folio in a large cursive secretary script: might these predate Humfrey’s ownership? If so, all inscriptions might have been removed soon after his death. It would, then, be one of those manuscripts which were dispersed by the commissioners put in charge of his goods, with <persName key="person_4119">John Somerseth</persName> being crucial among them. There is no definite evidence of the book’s whereabouts until the eighteenth century. The addition of a spurious date of 1304 to the explicit may hint that someone in the early modern world was attempting to increase its value.</provenance>
                  <provenance><persName key="person_310519476" role="fmo">Joseph Gulston (1745–1786)</persName> provided the present binding. It does not appear in the sale of his books by Compton of Conduit Street (8 May 1783).</provenance>
                  <provenance>The book may have passed during Gulston’s lifetime to <persName key="person_39249508" role="fmo">Thomas Martin of Palgrave (1696/7–1771)</persName> whose signature is at upper left of the left pastedown and monogram (‘TMS’) on right pastedown (with thanks to Matthew Holford for identifying the latter). Similarly to Gulston, this manuscript is not mentioned in the auction catalogue drawn up after Martin’s death so was presumably sold in his lifetime. At the head of the left pastedown is also, to the left, ‘96’; to right, ‘S.Biblia’. Below that, a round label with the number ‘187’ (s. xix?). At the head of fol. i recto, right: <q>Novum Testamentum MSS</q> (?s. xviii²); top right corner torn away. Top right of fol. ii recto: <q>/-/-</q>.</provenance>
                  <provenance><persName key="person_48313490" role="fmo">Sir George Augustus William Shuckburgh Evelyn (1751–1804)</persName>: armorial bookplate, left pastedown, with added number ‘M 2’; below that in pencil, ‘3D’. The book subsequently remained in his family’s ownership.</provenance>
                  <acquisition when="2024">Purchased by private treaty sale via Christie’s, London, 2024, with support from the National Heritage Memorial Fund, Art Fund (with a contribution from The Wolfson Foundation), Friends of the Nations’ Libraries, Mr Julian Blackwell, Mr Antonio Bonchristiano and Mrs Patricia Bonchristiano, and the Friends of the Bodleian.</acquisition>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>Description by David Rundle (December 2023); edited by Andrew Dunning (March 2025).</source>
                     </recordHist>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <surrogates>
                     <bibl type="digital-facsimile" subtype="full">
                        <ref target="https://digital.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/objects/d5298278-6c9f-4eeb-a5a7-b6a3afa10720/">
                           <title>Digital Bodleian</title></ref> <note>(full digital facsimile)</note>
                     </bibl>
                  </surrogates>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl><ref target="https://archive.org/details/bim_eighteenth-century_bibliotheca-elegans-cu_compton-auctioneer_1783"><title>Biblioteca elegans et curiosa. A Catalogue of the Genuine, Curious and Magnificent Library of an Eminent Collector</title></ref>. The catalogue of Gulston’s sale, undated; as it states it started on ‘Thursday May 8’, it must be 1783 (not 1786 as sometimes suggested, when 8 May fell on a Monday).</bibl>
                     <bibl><ref target="https://armorial.bibsoc.org.uk/stamp-owners/GUL002.html"><q>Gulston, Joseph (1745–1786)</q></ref>, <title>British Armorial Bindings</title>, 2025.</bibl>
                     <bibl>Department for Culture, Media and Sport, <q>Case 9: The Old French New Testament, formerly owned by Jean le Bon</q>, <ref target="https://www.artscouncil.org.uk/supporting-arts-museums-and-libraries/supporting-collections-and-cultural-property/reviewing-committee-0/export-works-art-and-objects-cultural-interest-2023-24"><title>Export of Works of Art and Objects of Cultural Interest 2023-24</title></ref> (Arts Council England, November 2024), 20–21.</bibl>
                     <bibl><title>A catalogue of the library of Mr. Thomas Martin, of Palgrave in Suffolk, lately deceased</title> (King’s Lynn, 1772).</bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2025-04-22"><persName>Sebastian Dows-Miller</persName>. Added measurement value and topLine encoding.</change>
         <change when="2025-03-11">Revise description by David Rundle.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
