<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xml:id="manuscript_4782" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>MS. Duke Humfrey d. 1</title>
            <title type="collection">MSS. Duke Humfrey</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Description</resp>
               <persName>David Rundle</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Revision</resp>
               <persName>Andrew Dunning</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </publisher>
            <idno type="msID">MS_Duke_Humfrey_d_1</idno>
            <idno type="collection">Duke_Humfrey</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="MS_Duke_Humfrey_d_1" xml:lang="en">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <region type="county">Oxfordshire</region>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <institution>University of Oxford</institution>
                  <repository>Bodleian Library</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">MS. Duke Humfrey d. 1</idno>
                  <idno type="ieArk">ark:29072/x0sx61dk91bs</idno>
                  <idno type="crArk">ark:29072/x0st74cq0817</idno>
                  <altIdentifier type="internal">
                     <idno type="SCN">2934</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
               <head>Pliny the Younger, <title>Letters</title> (8 books)</head>
               <msContents>
                  <textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>
                  <msItem n="1" xml:id="MS_Duke_Humfrey_d_1-item1">
                     <locus>(fols 1r–101r)</locus>
                     <author key="person_10638270">Pliny the Younger</author>
                     <title key="work_3703">Epistolae</title>
                     <bibl>Books I–VII &amp; IX</bibl>
                     <rubric>PLINII SECUNDI VERONENSIS NEPOTIS EPISTOLARUM LIBER PRIMUS <lb/> INCIPIT SECUNDUS SECUNDO SUO SALUTEM DICIT.</rubric>
                     <incipit>FREQUENTER hortatus es ut epistolas</incipit>
                     <explicit><locus>[fol. 101r]</locus> de nocte parvulum acquirunt. Vale. <lb/> Plinij secundi nepotis veronensis oratoris eloquentissimi Epi<lb break="no"/>stolarum liber octavus &amp; ultimus finit.</explicit>
                     <note>R. A. B. Mynors ed., <title>C. Plinii Caecilii Secundi Epistolarum Libri Decem</title> (Oxford, 1963), with this manuscript noted disparagingly at p. xiii n. 1; it is a witness to the Eight-Book tradition which Mynors designates the γ family.</note>
                     <note>Books divide at fol. 12v, 25a verso, 37r, 49v, 61v, 75v, 88r.</note>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="perg">
                        <support>Excepting flyleaves, crisp parchment, prepared like that in London, British Library, Harley MS 1705 and Oxford, Magdalen College, MS lat. 37 (B), with skin-side usually very smooth and hair-side slightly coarse; skin, hair-hair, skin-skin. <watermark>All flyleaves and pastedowns are paper (17th c.) with a watermark (armoirie, not in Briquet: a variant on the arms of Burgundy, lacking a castle in the bottom section; cf. Briquet 1476 &amp; 1477, Churchill 264).</watermark></support>
                        <extent>iii + 104 + iii; <dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                              <height>271</height>
                              <width>191</width>
                           </dimensions></extent>
                        <foliation>Foliation (pencil, 20th c.?, top right): iii + 104, including final flyleaves; this foliation is three less than the actual foliation, with fol. 9, 25 and 28 each counted twice. There is a twentieth century pencil note of the actual foliation at fol. 104. </foliation>
                        <collation>Quires of eight: i–xiii<hi rend="superscript">8</hi>. <catchwords>Simple horizontal catchwords placed in the inner margin just below text.</catchwords> No sign of quire or leaf signatures. <secFol>Non me hercule</secFol></collation>
                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout columns="1" writtenLines="26">26 long lines, below top line. Full ruling and single border (Derolez 13.11), lightly drawn leaving a greyish brown mark. <dimensions type="written" unit="mm">
                              <height>160–162</height>
                              <width>108–110</width>
                           </dimensions></layout>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc>
                     <handNote script="humanistica">Written throughout in one small, humanist-influenced script identifiable as that of <persName key="person_7483748" role="scr">Pier Candido Decembrio</persName>. Many of the distinctive features seen in London, British Library, Harley MS 1705 are seen here, for example the ampersand floating above the line with its tongue descending to the line, and the <q>g</q> with its pronounced diagonal descender and horizontal top to its bottom bowl which extends to the right of the top bowl. One notable difference is the tendency in the present manuscript for the final <q>s</q> rarely to be tall but to be short, with a tail often descending below the line. In this codex, Decembrio writes in brownish black ink, with the opening protocol of each letter added in bright red; the opening majuscule of each letter, painted alternately in blue and red, is written in an eclectic or experimental style (see, for example, the various types of <q>A</q>: fols 8v, 14v, 16v, 19v, 24v, 33v, 35r, 36v, 38r etc). Greek phrases are included by the scribe (eg. fols 9v–10r), though there are sometimes absent with at one point Decembrio noting in the margin: <q>deficit grecum nec in aliquibus exemplaribus potuit inveniri</q> (fol. 97r). Throughout the manuscript, Decembrio provides copious marginalia, in the form of notes (both corrections and comments), a characteristic light <foreign>manicula</foreign>, and a tall <foreign>nota</foreign> monogram; these have occasionally been cropped (e.g. fol. 66).</handNote>
                  </handDesc>
                  <decoDesc>
                     <decoNote type="decInit">Each book opens with a simple four- or five-line initial, with the letter in gold and with Milanese-style <foreign>bianchi girari</foreign> decoration of which the palette is dominated by light green and blue with a small addition of darkish pink (fols 1r, 12v, 25a verso, 37r, 49v, 61v, 75v, 88r); these are in the same design as the initials in Oxford, Magdalen College, MS lat. 37 (B) and Paris, Bibliothèque Nationale de France, ms. lat. 7805.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="colInit">Each epistle opens with the initial majuscule alternating in colour between blue and red.</decoNote>
                  </decoDesc>
                  <additions>Apart from scribal marginalia, there are few annotations and what there are are late. One late sixteenth century reader, writing in a script close to Decembrio’s own, adds some notes on the subject matter, as well as a couple of doodles in English (fols 19v, 25b recto, 33r, 38r, 46r, 65r?, 96r). Another reader, perhaps writing in the seventeenth century, annotates in pencil in an elegant script (fols 43v, 44r, 58r, 75v?, 77v, 78v). There is also a capital <quote>B</quote> written twice at the bottom of fol. 92v, and a further doodle at fol. 47v.</additions>
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <binding notAfter="1700" notBefore="1600">
                        <p>Leather binding (17th c.) with a simple double rectangle tooled both plainly and in gold on each board; also each board has a gilt centrepiece of the coat-of-arms of the University of Oxford, depicting an open book inscribed <q>Sapientia fælicitas</q>, a version of a motto used by the University between 1587 and 1623 \[Macray, <title>Annals</title>, p. 17n\]. At both boards there are also the remains of two pieces of green cloth, presumably used to tie the volume closed. The first recto and last verso of the manuscript are both moderately rubbed.</p>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="1442" notBefore="1441">1441/2</origDate>
                     <origPlace>
                        <country key="place_1000080">Italy</country>, <settlement key="place_7005903">Milan</settlement>
                     </origPlace>
                     <p>This manuscript has followed a comparatively uneventful career. It was produced in Milan by <persName key="person_7483748">Pier Candido Decembrio</persName>, who sent it to Duke Humfrey.</p>
                     <p>The manuscript is unusual among the surviving codices that were produced for Humfrey by Decembrio for being written entirely by the humanist himself. The nearest parallel is the presentation copy of the first five books of his own translation of Plato’s <title>Republic</title>; but in the two other extant manuscripts of works by authors other than himself, Decembrio employed scribes to do the transcription. Perhaps his willingness to copy Pliny’s <title>Letters</title> reflected his own interest in the text: after all, he assiduously compiled his own epistolary, which it appears he also sent to Humfrey. On the other hand, it may simply be a function of time-pressures: he was having a series of manuscripts produced for Humfrey over a relatively short period, and perhaps this forced him to act himself as scribe.</p>
                     <p>This may not be the only occasion in his life on which Decembrio was involved in transcription of a classical work: BL, Burney MS 200 is a copy of Livy, <title>Decades III, I &amp; IV</title>, signed and dated by one of its four scribes, Leo de Domo, in 1440. The script of fol. 132r–291va l. 30 may well be that of Decembrio, writing a slightly more cursive variety of his hand, with the addition of a <foreign>littera antiqua-</foreign>style <q>g</q> with a sharply-pointed descender. This manuscript incidentally also includes marginalia by Antonio Beccaria (providing textual additions at fols 29r and 81r; see also fols 13v, 21r, 27v, 28v, 34r, 50v, etc). This manuscript has an early Italian provenance being owned by a certain Melchio de Squassis (fol. 348v) [<title>D&amp;DBL,</title> no. 501; M. Zaggia, <quote>La traduzione latina da Appiano di Pier Candido Decembrio per la storia della tradizione</quote>, <title>Studi Medievali,</title> 3rd ser., xxxiv (1993), pp. 193–243 at p. 234n].</p>
                     <p>The production of this manuscript is datable to a period of at most four years, from the late 1430s to the early 1440s, when Decembrio was acting as a book-factor for Humfrey. It is possible, however, that we can give an even narrower dating: as this manuscript shares significant similarities in its construction with Oxford, Magdalen College, MS lat. 37 (B), both in terms of illumination and of mise-en-page, this codex, like the copy of Ptolomey, might be datable to 1441/2. Yet, whenever he received this book, Humfrey did not enjoy ownership of the manuscript for long as it appears in the list of his final and largest gift to the University of Oxford, in 1444.</p>
                  </origin>
                  <provenance><persName key="person_30785585" role="fmo">Humfrey, Duke of Gloucester</persName>: recorded his ownership by inscribing, just below the final colophon at fol. 101r, his short <foreign>ex libris</foreign>: <q>Cest livre est A moy homfrey duc de glou/cestre.</q></provenance>
                  <provenance>The Duke presented the book to the <orgName key="org_142129514" role="fmo">University of Oxford</orgName> in 1444. There is little evidence for this manuscript being consulted during its first stay in the University Library; there is little early marginalia and there do not appear to be any surviving codices transcribed from it. The one other extant manuscript of Pliny’s <title>Epistulae</title> which was in Oxford in the fifteenth century—that owned and partially written by <persName key="person_258392640">Robert Flemyng</persName>, now Oxford, Lincoln College, MS lat. 77—was also of the Eight-Book tradition but it definitely was not derived from Humfrey’s copy. On Flemyng’s manuscript, see Alexander &amp; Temple, no. 591; <title>DH &amp; EH,</title> p. 37 [no. 6]. Flemyng’s text and that in Humfrey’s copy share idiosyncrasies of the γ family (the Eight-Book tradition), but there are also significant differences: see the appendix below.</provenance>
                  <provenance>At some point in the sixteenth century, the manuscript must have left the University’s library but it is not clear when this happened or what its fate was before 1620. There are only two pieces of internal evidence to assist us in reconstructing this missing period: first, the opening and last folio are rubbed, suggesting the manuscript was for some time left unbound. Second, at the top centre of fol. 1r, the words <q>operibus credite</q> are written in a sixteenth century hand; this Gospel phrase [John 10 v.38] is perhaps the motto of a presumably Catholic owner. Other inscriptions are unrevealing. The word <q>opus</q> is written at top right in a late fifteenth or early sixteenth century script; while at the final verso, there are several notes: one hand has written <q>magister</q> at the top left, while another has written just to the right, <q>Suaua paies</q>; written vertically at the outside edge of the page is the word <q>benedictus</q>.</provenance>
                  <provenance><persName key="person_3884" role="dnr">Robert Master (1565–1625)</persName>: inscribed, at the foot of fol. 1r: <q>Anno Domini MDCXX 8bris 3º. / Robertus Master LL Doctor Cancellarius Episcopi / Coven: et <sic>Lichfeild</sic> Oxoniensi Bibliothecae Dono Dedit &amp; restituit / hunc librum olim ad Humphredum Ducem Glocestriae / pertinentem ut videre est propria ipsius manu scriptum in / ultima pagina huius Libri.</q> Robert was an Oxford man: a student of Trinity College (matriculated March 1578/9), he became a Fellow and Deputy Warden of All Souls, and, from 1599 to 1603, Principal of St Alban’s Hall. Outside the University, he was a M.P. in 1601, and, as his inscription states, the Chancellor of both Coventry and Lichfield dioceses. He made at least one gift of printed books to All Souls, but it is unclear how much of a bibliophile he was or how he came by this manuscript. See J. Foster, <title>Alumni Oxonienses: the members of the University of Oxford, 1500–1714,</title> iii (Oxford, 1891), p. 986; P. W. Hasler ed., <title>The House of Commons 1558–1603,</title> iii (London, 1981), p. 34. He gave, in 1598, to All Souls a four volume printed edition of the works of Zwingli [N. Ker, <title>Records of All Souls College Library, 1437–1600</title> [Oxford Bibliographical Society, new series, vol. xvi] (Oxford, 1971), pp. 104, 158].</provenance>
                  <acquisition when="1620"><p>The 1620 donation was not considered worthy of inclusion in the Bodleian’s Register of Benefactors but there are signs that it was treated as a prized possession. The Benefactors’ Register is Oxford, Bodleian Library, Library Records b. 903, with pp. 229–231 covering the relevant year. Our manuscript is listed in <title>Summ. Cat,</title> i, p. 104 as no. 947. The inscription just quoted was added to the volume by a professional scribe, presumably paid for by the Library (<title>Summ. Cat.</title>). Similarly, the unusual binding was provided probably soon after the manuscript returned to Oxford.</p>
                     <p>After its return to the University’s library, the manuscript did receive some attention. This is reflected not just in the set of pencil annotations visible in the margins, but also in the use made of it by Thomas Hearne. He employed this codex for his edition of Pliny’s <title>Letters</title>, and at fol. i recto, there is a note in his script commenting: <q>Libri, qui in Impressis VIII &amp; X in hoc <add>codice</add> desiderantur.</q> Hearne cites this manuscript as <quote>Bod. 1</quote> in his edition of <title>C. Plinii Caecilii Secundi Epistolae</title> (Oxford, 1703).</p>
                     <p>Hearne did not note in his edition that this manuscript had belonged to Humfrey, but he does record the presence of his <foreign>ex libris</foreign> in his notebooks. (C. Doble ed., <title>Remarks &amp; Collections of Thomas Hearne,</title> ii [Oxford Historical Society, vii] (Oxford, 1886), p. 339 &amp; iii [Oxford Historical Society, xiii] (Oxford, 1889), p. 355. On this, see also my article in J. Raven ed., <title>Lost Libraries.</title>) That ownership note was later regarded as its most significant feature: at some point in the 1880s, the volume was added to the Bodleian’s permanent exhibition and placed alongside other examples of autographs of historical figures. The manuscript is absent from the listing of the glass-cases’ contents in [F. Madan], <title>List of Books, Manuscripts, Portraits &amp;c</title> (Oxford, 1881) but noted by Macray, p. 458n. See also Vickers, p. 426. Emphasis on its original provenance was also enhanced by the decision, probably made in 1897, to give it its present shelfmark. However, when the glass-case exhibition was discontinued in 1921 and replaced with the <quote>select</quote> manuscript listing, our codex was effectively demoted; it only joined the ranks of the <quote>select</quote> in c. 1975. It was perhaps <quote>promoted</quote> because of its being displayed in the 1975 <title>Survival of Ancient Literature</title> exhibition. At the same time, MS Canon. Class. lat. 30 (Catullus; 14th c.) was also added to the list; see the hand-list held in Duke Humfrey’s. (I would like to thank William Hodges and Bruce Barker-Benfield for their assistance on this matter.)</p>
                     <p>There are several former Bodleian shelfmarks in the manuscript. At the front pastedown written in pencil (in a twentieth century script) and crossed out: Auct. F. 2. 23. Also in pencil is: Arch. F. d. 41. Written in pen at the first flyleaf (fol. i recto): Bodl. Arch. A. 151 (2934). The bracketed number is the number by which it is recorded in Bernard, and in the Summary Catalogue.</p></acquisition>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>Description by David Rundle (March 2025); edited by Andrew Dunning (December 2025). Previously described: <listBibl>
                              <bibl facs="aap0573.gif" type="SC">Summary Catalogue, Vol. 2 Part 1, p. 552</bibl>
                           </listBibl>
                        </source>
                     </recordHist>
                     <availability status="restricted">
                        <p>To ensure its preservation, access to this item is restricted, and readers are asked to work from reproductions and published descriptions as far as possible. If you wish to apply to see the original, please click the request button above. When your request is received, you will be asked to contact the relevant curator outlining the subject of your research, the importance of this item to that research, and the resources you have already consulted.</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <surrogates>
                     <bibl subtype="partial" type="digital-facsimile">
                        <ref target="https://digital.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/objects/218af45e-eae3-4579-97d1-e7ed813c0dac/">
                           <title>Digital Bodleian</title>
                        </ref>
                        <note>(7 images from 35mm slides)</note>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl type="microfilm">Microfilm available in the open shelf collections in the Weston Library (R. Films 101)</bibl></surrogates>
                  <listBibl type="WRAPPER">
                     <listBibl type="INTERNET">
                        <head>Online resources:</head>
                        <bibl>
                           <ref target="http://mlgb3.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/mlgb/book/4255">
                              <title>MLGB3: Medieval Libraries of Great Britain</title>
                           </ref>
                        </bibl>
                     </listBibl>
                     <listBibl>
                        <bibl>[Bodleian Library exhib. cat..] <title>Autographs of Italian Humanists</title> (Oxford, 1974), no. 7</bibl>
                        <bibl><ref target="https://catalog.hathitrust.org/Record/001165248"><title>Pietas Oxoniensis in Memory of Sir Thomas Bodley, Knt. and the Foundation of the Bodleian Library</title></ref> (Oxford, 1902), 11n</bibl>
                        <bibl><title>DH &amp; EH,</title> no. 12</bibl>
                        <bibl><title>DHL,</title> no. 35</bibl>
                        <bibl>Ferrari, M., <q>Dalle antiche biblioteche domenicane a Milano: codici superstiti nell’Ambrosiana</q>, <title>Ricerche storiche sulla Chiesa Ambrosiana,</title> viii (1978–79), 180–197 at 191</bibl>
                        <bibl>Hunt, R. W., et al., <ref target="https://catalog.hathitrust.org/Record/000710664"><title>The Survival of Ancient Literature: Catalogue of an Exhibition of Greek and Latin Classical Manuscripts Mainly from Oxford Libraries Displayed on the Occasion of the Triennial Meeting of the Hellenic and Roman Societies, 28 July–2 August 1975</title></ref> (Oxford, 1975), no. 152</bibl>
                        <bibl>Macray, William Dunn, <ref target="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/mdp.39015017672042"><title>Annals of the Bodleian Library, Oxford: With a Notice of the Earlier Library of the University</title></ref> (2nd edn, Oxford, 1890), 9</bibl>
                        <bibl>Mare, Albinia C. de la, ‘<ref target="https://doi.org/10.3828/blr.1989.13.2.112">Manuscripts given to the University of Oxford by Humfrey, Duke of Gloucester</ref>’, pt 2, <title>Bodleian Library Record</title>, 13/2 (1989), 112–21 at 118–21</bibl>
                        <bibl>Pächt, Otto, and J. J. G. Alexander, <ref target="https://catalog.hathitrust.org/Record/000468709"><title>Illuminated Manuscripts in the Bodleian Library, Oxford</title></ref>, (Oxford, 1966), vol. 2, no. 697</bibl>
                        <bibl>Rogers, D., <title>The Bodleian Library and its Treasures, 1320–1700</title> (Henley-on-Thames, 1991), 11 [plate of top half of fol. 101r]</bibl>
                        <bibl>Ullman, B. L., ‘Manuscripts of Duke Humfrey of Gloucester’, in <title>Studies in the Italian Renaissance</title>, Storia e Letteratura, 51 (2nd edn, Rome, 1973), 345–56 at 353 [no. 3]</bibl>
                        <bibl>Vickers, Kenneth Hotham, <ref target="https://archive.org/details/humphreydukeofgl05vickuoft"><title>Humphrey, Duke of Gloucester: A Biography</title></ref> (London, 1907), 426</bibl>
                        <bibl>Zaggia, Massimo, <q>La traduzione latina da Appiano di Pier Candido Decembrio per la storia della tradizione</q>, <title>Studi Medievali,</title> 3rd ser., 34/1 (1993), 193–243 at 234n</bibl>
                     </listBibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2025-12-12">New description by David Rundle.</change>
         <change when="2021-12-14">Add provenance information from MLGB3.</change>
         <change when="2017-07-01">First online publication.</change>
         <change when="2017-05-25">
            <persName>James Cummings</persName> Up-converted the markup using <ref target="https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl">https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl</ref>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
