<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="manuscript_358">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>MS. Ashmole 60</title>
            <title type="collection">MSS. Ashmole</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp when="2025-06">Cataloguer</resp>
               <persName>Charlotte Ross</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </publisher>
            <idno type="msID">MS_Ashmole_60</idno>
            <idno type="collection">Ashmole</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="MS_Ashmole_60" xml:lang="en">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <region type="county">Oxfordshire</region>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <institution>University of Oxford</institution>
                  <repository>Bodleian Library</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">MS. Ashmole 60</idno>
                  <idno type="ieArk">ark:29072/x00p096812rj</idno><idno type="crArk">ark:29072/x00k225c29fx</idno><altIdentifier type="internal">
                     <idno type="SCN">6922</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
               <head>Single-text codex of <title>The Prick of Conscience</title> with expansions; late 14th century</head>
               
               <msContents>
                  <msItem n="1" xml:id="MS_Ashmole_60-item1">
                        <locus>(fols. 1r-138v)</locus>
                        <title key="work_13981">The Prick of Conscience</title>
                        <rubric>Incipit stimulus consciencie a Ricardo heremite de hampole compositus gracie dei subdito terminatur (fol. 8r)</rubric>
                        <incipit><hi rend="bold">T</hi> he myȝt of þe fadir almyȝtty <lb/> The wisdom of þe sone al wytty</incipit>
                        <explicit defective="true">ȝif he hope þat god is almyȝtty <lb/> And he þat shal it here oþer see</explicit>
                        <note>Imperfect, lacking leaves in the first quire, one leaf (between folios 23 and 24) and a final leaf (after folio 138) containing the last twenty one lines. Text expanded: 11,020/9,526 lines. Belongs to the Main Version of <title key="work_13981">The Prick of Conscience</title>, Group II. A member of the so-called Lollard subgroup, which contains two interpolations and one rearrangement with an attack on the clergy, Latin prose also incorporating anti-clerical sentiment, and the transferal of some text from Book V (6346-409) to the end of Book VII (between lines 9474 and 9475) - on this group see Allen, 1927, pp. 387-94. 
                           <p>Recorded as MV 61 in Lewis and McIntosh (1982), who also note that this manuscript is related to London, Society of Antiquaries, MS 687; <ref target="https://www.digitalcollections.manchester.ac.uk/view/MS-ENGLISH-00090/1">Manchester, John Rylands University Library, MS English 90</ref>; and <ref target="https://medieval.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/catalog/manuscript_9161">Oxford, Bodleian Library, MS e. Musaeo 76</ref> (the other surviving Lollard subgroup texts). See Killian (2017). </p>
                           <p>Ashmole 60 is one of five manuscripts that attributes the poem to Richard Rolle of Hampole.</p>
                           <p>e-LALME and Lewis and McIntosh note the dialect of the scribe is located to the Isle of Ely.</p>
                           <p>Edited in <title>Richard Morris's Prick of Conscience: A Corrected and Amplified Reading Text</title>, Early English Text Society Original Series 342, eds Ralph Hanna and Sarah Wood (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2013).</p>
                           <p><ref target="https://www.dimev.net/record.php?recID=5398#wit-5398-3">DIMEV 5398</ref></p><note>Interpolations:</note>
                        </note>
                           <msItem>
                              <locus>(fols. 1r-7v)</locus>
                              <title type="desc">In reproof of worldiness in the clergy</title>
                              <incipit defective="true">non desit <damage>nec sel</damage>us boni nec sciencia</incipit>
                              <incipit>But þis ston up shal turned be</incipit>
                              <explicit>For þanne shal no mede wiþ outen merre <lb/> Be mettid for deeþ bon bettre or werre</explicit>
                              <note>Imperfect, lacking material at the beginning and after folio 3. (For the text lost, Manchester, John Rylands Library, MS English 90 fols. 1r-3v). Middle English rhyming couplets intermixed with Latin prose. In this copy, the interpolation is inserted before the beginning of the poem, line 1, in a separate quire; in the other copies it occurs between lines 192 and 193 of the prologue.
                                 <p>The passage at fols. 4v (line 8 from bottom) - 5r (line 5 from bottom) ('Ful litil pris sette thei therby ... soule amendable'), printed in <title>The Thornton romances</title>, ed. J. O. Halliwell-Phillipps (1844), pp. 260 (line 3)-261, is also found in <ref target="https://medieval.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/catalog/manuscript_9110">BodL, MS e Musaeo 198</ref> fol. 173r (line 21) - 173v (cf. <ref target="https://www.dimev.net/record.php?recID=5398#wit-5398-3">DIMEV 2385</ref>) </p>
                                 <p> (from MS. e Mus. 198); and extracts in Hope Emily Allen, <title>Writings Ascribed to Richard Rolle</title> (New York: Modern Language Association of America, 1927), 391-2.</p></note>
                              <note>Rest of fol. 7v blank.</note>
                           </msItem>
                           <msItem >
                              <locus>(fols. 88r-104r)</locus>
                              <title type="desc">The pains of hell</title>
                              <incipit>Nunc sequit<ex>ur</ex> de pena que est mutua visio dampnator<ex>um</ex></incipit>
                              <explicit>vobis tribuat <ex>et</ex> vera<ex>m</ex> penitenciam anteq<ex>uam</ex> vos de hoc s<ex>e</ex>c<ex>u</ex>lo tollat . Amen . </explicit>
                              <note>The largest addition, of 33 <hi rend="superscript">1/2</hi> folios, in the middle of the discussion of the seventh and eighth pains of hell in Book VI (between lines 6894 and 6895). Primarily sermonizing Latin prose with quotations from the scriptures and the fathers, interspersed with short extracts of Middle English rhyming couplets. Among the Middle English verse is a passage (fol. 97r-98r (line 5 from bottom), beginning 'ȝif lorel lordes' and ending at 'blynne'), pr. Frederick J. Furnivall, <title>Ballads from Manuscripts</title> (London: Ballad Society, 1863; repr. New York: AMS, 1968), 1.63, also found in MS. e Mus. 198, fols. 172r-173r (line 12) (cf. <ref target="https://www.dimev.net/record.php?recID=5398#wit-5398-3">DIMEV 2385</ref>).</note>
                           </msItem>
                              <msItem>
                              <note>This copy also contains a Book VIII, which is made of material normally in Book V (lines 6346-409) which has been transposed to the end of Book VII (after line 9475) to form a new Book (on fols. 136r-138v).</note>
                             
                              </msItem> <textLang mainLang="enm" otherLangs="la">Middle English and Latin</textLang>
                  </msItem>         
               </msContents>
               
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="perg">
                        <support>parchment</support>
                        <extent>i (modern end leaf, paper) + 138 + viii (modern end leaves, paper)
                           <dimensions unit="mm" type="leaf">
                              <height quantity="290">c. 290</height>
                              <width quantity="190">c. 190</width>
                           </dimensions>
                        </extent>
                        <foliation>Modern pencil.</foliation>
                        <collation>
                           1<hi rend="superscript">seven</hi> (structure unclear, apparently missing two leaves at beginning with loss of text (signatures iii, iiij on fols. 1-2), one (?) leaf after fol. 3 with loss of text, and two (?) leaves after fol. 4 without less of text) | 2-3<hi rend="superscript">8</hi> (fols. 8-23), 4<hi rend="superscript">8-1</hi> (first leaf missing with loss of text, fols. 24-30), 5-11<hi rend="superscript">8</hi> (fols. 31-86), 12<hi rend="superscript">6+4</hi> (fols. 87-96: fols. 91-94 are a quire of four leaves inserted after fol. 90), 13-17<hi rend="superscript">8</hi> (fols. 97-136), 18<hi rend="superscript">2+1-1</hi> (now bifolium, lacking final folio which was a singleton addition, text lost, fols. 137-138). Leaf signatures visible, starting at a on fol. 1r and following a-p thereafter.</collation>
                        <condition>Some wear to fol. 1r and damage to the bottom of 35. Sections of the margins excised from fols. 56, 103, 119, 122, and 135-138. </condition>
                           
                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout columns="1" writtenLines="40">Middle English verse in one column, Latin prose extends to the width of the page, also in a single column. Consistently 40 lines per page, fully ruled. Pricking visible. Ruled in fine leadpoint, ruled space: 
                           <dimensions type="written" unit="mm">
                              <height max="215" min="210">c. 210-5</height>
                              <width quantity="120">c. 120</width>
                           </dimensions></layout>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc hands="1">
                     <handNote script="cursivaAntiquior">One hand throughout, anglicana formata.</handNote>
                  </handDesc>
                  <decoDesc>
                     <decoNote type="colInit">The first letter of every line of Middle English verse is highlighted with a subtle yellow colour wash.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="flourInit">The beginning of each Book is marked with a four to six-line decorated blue initial with elaborate red flourishes, extending into a three-sided red and blue bar border with red flourishes. The only exception of Book VI (fol. 82v), which opens with a less ornate three-line initial in the same style. All initials are accompanied by a rubricated Incipit.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="rubrication">Rubricated rhyming braces on Middle English couplets throughout.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="rubrication">Rubricated Book numbers given in the upper left margin of every leaf.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="rubrication">As is typical in the corpus, the section on the fifteen days before Christ's coming (Book V ll.4758-4817) is annotated with rubricated roman numerals 1-15 in the margin of fols. 63v-64r. Similar numerals are given for the ten things men may see at the day of dread (Book V ll.3966-3990, fols. 54v-55r), and the fourteen pains (Book VI ll.6547-6578).</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="rubrication">The first three glosses are given in the margin and rubricated. Thereafter glosses are given in-line with Middle English verse and rubricated, with the exception of the second interpolation (fols. 88r-104r), in which some of the glosses are marginal.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="other">Blue paraphs mark the start of Latin prose extracts, and alternating red and blue paraphs mark moments of textual division within Middle English verse extracts.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="flourInit">One decorated initial mid-Book, a six-line blue lombardic capital with red flourishes, on fol. 100v.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="rubrication">Some passages of Latin prose underlined in red.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="lineFill">Decorative rubricated line fillers in Latin prose.</decoNote>
                  </decoDesc>
                  <additions>Bookmark or <q>cut-and-fold-tab</q> (following Sawyer, 2016) on fol. 77 in which a strip of parchment has been cut from the page, folded, and fed through a slit.
                  <p>A sixteenth-century hand annotates four lines of verse at the foot of fol. 1r: <q>While I am poore, to riche men will not give . <lb/> Lest iustly fole, men terme me whilst I live . <lb/> Or y<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> the woorlde suspitious will say . <lb/> The poore man beges, when he dothe give away .</q>. It is signed below <q>W.A.</q>.</p>
                  <p>A note recording Rolle's death appears in the upper margin of fol. 8r, in a sixteenth century hand(?). A different hand of a similar period annotates <q>Ricardus Rolle Eremita de Hampoll</q> on the final folio.</p>
                  <p>Pen trials on fol. 38v.</p>
                  <p>Medieval <hi rend="italic">nota bene</hi> marks, possibly by the scribe, at fols. 47v (3398), 48r (3446), and throughout the second interpolation (fols. 88r-104r).</p></additions>
                     
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <binding notAfter="1692" notBefore="1617">
                        <p>Late seventeenth-century calf binding over pasteboards, typical of Elias Ashmole's style, rebacked. The edges of both boards are decorated with concentric tool framing, with triple tooling on the margin closest to the spine on both boards. The board edges are tooled with a repeating semi-circle pattern, also typical of Ashmole's bindings.</p> 
                        <p>The spine has been rebacked, and shows five raised sewing supports covering thick cords which support both composite parts. The shelf mark <q>ASH. 60</q> is embossed on the central spine panel. The typeset of the shelf mark is similar, but not identical, to Ashmole's typeset (varying in the height of letters and thickness of vertical strokes in characters <q>A</q> and <q>H</q>), and Ashmole's embossed crest is missing from the second panel (see e.g. MS Ashmole 44). The board-covers also show evidence of having been lifted up at the spine-edge to allow for the spine-cover to be adhered beneath them. </p>
                          <p>The sewing stations of Ashmole's binding do not follow the original sewing stations. There is evidence of a prior binding that included at least seven sewing stations.</p>
                        <p>There are no end bands. The sewing supports are laced into the boards using shortened single-hole lacing without channels. The board edges are tooled with a repeating zig-zag pattern typical of Ashmole's bindings. The inner rear board bears an inscription typical of the Bodleian's in-house bindery, with the initial <q>H</q> and the date, partially obscured, <q>3 - 12 - 00</q></p>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="1400" notBefore="1385">14th century, end</origDate>
                     <origPlace>
                        <country key="place_7002445">English</country>
                     </origPlace>
                  </origin>
                  <provenance>The name <q>Wyllyam Harrys</q> is recorded twice in a pen-trial on folio 30r in a sixteenth century hand. Harrys also leaves an erased note in the margin of folio 28v, illegible under UV. </provenance>
                  <provenance>The manuscript was owned by <persName key="person_27215170" role="fmo">Elias Ashmole</persName> (1617–1692) in the seventeenth century. It is uncertain when Ashmole acquired the manuscript, but he is responsible for its current binding. Ashmole also purchased another copy of <title>The Prick of Conscience</title>, MS Ashmole 52. He does not mention acquiring either manuscript in his diary or correspondence.</provenance>
                  <provenance>Bequeathed to the Ashmolean Museum by <persName key="person_27215170" role="fmo dnr">Elias Ashmole</persName> in 1692 as part of his donation of 1,100 printed books and 600 manuscripts.</provenance>
                  <acquisition>The manuscript was kept in the Ashmolean until 1860, when the collection was transferred to the Bodleian Library .</acquisition>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>Description by Charlotte Ross (June 2025). Previously described in the Quarto Catalogue (W. H. Black, <title>A descriptive, analytical, and critical catalogue of the manuscripts bequeathed unto the University of Oxford by Elias Ashmole Esq....</title>, Quarto Catalogues X, 1845). Decoration, localization and date follow Pächt and Alexander (1973). <listBibl>
                           <bibl facs="aeh0057.gif" type="QUARTO">Quarto Catalogue, col. 103</bibl>
                           <bibl facs="aeh0058.gif" type="QUARTO">Quarto Catalogue, col. 104</bibl>
                           <bibl facs="aaq0482.gif" type="SC">Summary Catalogue, vol. 2, part 2, p. 1123</bibl>
                        </listBibl>
                        </source>
                     </recordHist>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl type="WRAPPER">
                     <listBibl type="PRINT">
                        <head>Printed resources:</head>
                        <bibl>Allen, Hope Emily, <title>Writings Attributed to Richard Rolle</title> (New York: Modern Language Association of America, 1927).</bibl>
                        <bibl>Furnivall, Frederick James, <title>Ballads from Manuscripts</title> (London: Ballad Society, 1863; repr. New York: AMS, 1968), 1.63.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Killian, Ann, <q>Menacing Books: The Prick of Conscience and the Rhetoric of Reproof</q>, <title>Yearbook of Langland Studies</title> 31 (2017): 5–41.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Lewis, Robert E., and Angus McIntosh, <title>A Descriptive Guide to the Manuscripts of the Prick of Conscience</title> (Oxford: Society for the Study of Mediaeval Languages and Literature, 1982)</bibl>
                        <bibl><title>Richard Morris's Prick of Conscience: A Corrected and Amplified Reading Text</title>, Early English Text Society Original Series 342, eds Ralph Hanna and Sarah Wood (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2013)</bibl>
                        <bibl>Sawyer, Daniel, <q>Navigation by Tab and Thread: Place-Markers and Readers' Movement in Books</q>, <title>Spaces for Reading in Later Medieval England</title>, ed. C. Griffin (New York: Palgrave Macmillan, 2016), 99-114</bibl>
                        <bibl></bibl>
                     </listBibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2025-06-01"><persName>Charlotte Ross</persName>, revised with consultation of original.</change>
         <change when="2017-07-01">First online publication.</change>
         <change when="2017-05-25"><persName>James Cummings</persName> Up-converted the markup using <ref target="https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl">https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl</ref></change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>