<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xml:id="manuscript_351" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>MS. Ashmole 46</title>
            <title type="collection">MSS. Ashmole</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp when="2022-09">Cataloguer</resp>
               <persName>Charlotte Ross</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </publisher>
            <idno type="msID">MS_Ashmole_46</idno>
            <idno type="collection">Ashmole</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="MS_Ashmole_46" xml:lang="en">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <region type="county">Oxfordshire</region>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <institution>University of Oxford</institution>
                  <repository>Bodleian Library</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">MS. Ashmole 46</idno>
                  <altIdentifier type="internal">
                     <idno type="SCN">6930</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
               <head>Anthology of Lydgate's verse. xv.</head>
               <msContents>
                  <msItem n="1" xml:id="MS_Ashmole_46-item1">
                     <locus>(fols. 1r-49r)</locus>
                     <author key="person_22158282">John Lydgate</author>
                     <title key="work_2726">The life of St Edmund</title>
                     <incipit>THe noble story to putte in reme<ex>m</ex>bra<ex>u</ex>nce <lb/> Off Seint Edmond mayde martir &amp; kyng</incipit>
                     <explicit>As kyng and martir wheer he may not mysse <lb/> Externally ffor to Rayne in blysse</explicit>
                     <note>Opens with a lavish illuminated miniature (badly worn) of the author presenting his book to the King (see <q>Decoration</q>). Stanzas cancelled on folios 5v, 6r, 12v, and 17r. <title>The life of St Edmund</title> is sometimes, but not always, compiled in manuscripts with <title>The life of St Fremund</title>. Both texts are edited in <title>John Lydgate's Lives of Ss Edmund &amp; Fremund and the Extra miracles of St Edmund</title>, eds Anthony Bale and A. S. G. Edwards (2009). <p>DIMEV 5422.</p></note>
                     <textLang mainLang="enm">Middle English</textLang>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="2" xml:id="MS_Ashmole_46-item2">
                     <locus>(fols. 49r-69v)</locus>
                     <author key="person_22158282">John Lydgate</author>
                     <title>The life of St Fremund</title>
                     <incipit>NOw gloryous martir which of gret meknesse <lb/> ffor Coystes seith Suffredyst passyo<ex>u</ex>n</incipit>
                     <explicit>The which stoory a complysshed of oold date <lb/> I am purpoosyd in Englyssh to Translate</explicit>
                     <note>Begins with a three stanza prologue on folio 49v, followed by the main text on folio 50r. Ends with a three stanza invocation to the saint on folio 69v, which also introduces the following text. Edited in <title>John Lydgate's Lives of Ss Edmund &amp; Fremund</title>, eds Bale and Edwards (2009). <p>DIMEV 5422.</p></note>
                     <textLang mainLang="enm">Middle English</textLang>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="3" xml:id="MS_Ashmole_46-item3">
                     <locus>(fols. 70r-96v)</locus>
                     <author key="person_22158282">John Lydgate</author>
                     <title key="work_2727">Miracles of St. Fremund</title>
                     <incipit>A thousand yeer Reknyd and threttene <lb/> ffolwyng Crystes Incarnacio<ex>u</ex>n</incipit>
                     <explicit>Wolde interupte his Royal signite <lb/> Be deregacio<ex>u</ex>n doon to his ffra<ex>u</ex>nchysse</explicit>
                     <note>The text begins on folio 70r and is followed by an invocation to the saint on folio 84v. Edited in <title>John Lydgate's Lives of Ss Edmund &amp; Fremund</title>, eds Bale and Edwards (2009).</note>
                     <textLang mainLang="enm">Middle English</textLang>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="4" xml:id="MS_Ashmole_46-item4">
                     <locus>(fols. 97r-160v)</locus>
                     <author key="person_2581859">PS. Aristotle</author>
                     <title key="work_3859">Secreta secretorum (Middle English translation by <persName key="person_22158282">John Lydgate</persName> and <persName key="person_39764993">Benedict Burgh</persName>)</title>
                     <incipit>GOd almyghty save and cons<ex>er</ex>ve our kyng <lb/> In al vertu to his Encrees of glorye</incipit>
                     <explicit>Which the mvt graunte the lord moost Imp<ex>er</ex>ial <lb/> A bove alle hevenys supra celestial</explicit>
                     <finalRubric>Amen</finalRubric>
                     <note>Glosses rubricated in margin. On folio 131r the poem is interrupted by the rubric <q>Here deyed this translatour and <lb/> nobyl poete , And the yonge folwere <lb/> gan his prologe on this wyse</q>. <p>DIMEV 1544.</p></note>
                     <textLang mainLang="enm">Middle English</textLang>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="5" xml:id="MS_Ashmole_46-item5">
                     <locus>(fols. 161r-163v)</locus>
                     <note>blank.</note>
                     <textLang mainLang="xxz">No linguistic content.</textLang>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="perg">
                        <support>parchment</support>
                        <extent>i (modern end leaf, parchment) + i (modern end leaf, paper) + 163 (parchment) + i (modern end leaf, parchment)<dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                              <height>215</height>
                              <width>170</width> </dimensions>
                           </extent>
                        <foliation>Modern pencil foliation throughout, flyleaves unfoliated.</foliation>
                        <collation>***1-4<hi rend="superscript">8</hi> (fols. 1-33), 5<hi rend="superscript">6</hi> (fols. 34-39), 6<hi rend="superscript">8</hi> (fols. 40-49), 7<hi rend="superscript">6</hi> (fols. 50-55), 8<hi rend="superscript">10</hi> (fols. 56-65), 9<hi rend="superscript">6</hi> (fols. 66-71), 10<hi rend="superscript">10</hi> (fols. 72-81), 11<hi rend="superscript">6?</hi> (fols. 82-87), 12<hi rend="superscript">8</hi> (fols. 88-95), 13<hi rend="superscript">10</hi> (fols. 96-104), 14<hi rend="superscript">6</hi> (fols. 105-110), 15<hi rend="superscript">10</hi> (fols. 111-120), 16<hi rend="superscript">6+1</hi> (fols. 121-127, seventh leaf singleton?), 17-19<hi rend="superscript">8</hi> (fols. 128-151), 20<hi rend="superscript">10-1</hi> (fols. 152-160, with the loss of the first leaf without loss of text. Stub visible.), 21<hi rend="superscript">4-1</hi> (fols. 161-164 (blank), with the loss of the fourth leaf. Stub visible.).</collation>
                        <condition>Good. Minor wear to gutters. Brown staining on folios 22v-23r,51r, 80r, 131v-132r, and to the outer edges of the last six folios. </condition>
                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout columns="1" ruledLines="24" writtenLines="21">Ruled in lilac ink with frame. Ruled for 24 lines, regularly 21 long lines of text in 3 stanzas. Glosses unruled. Ruled space: <dimensions type="ruled" unit="mm">    <height>145</height>
                           <width>95</width></dimensions>
                        </layout>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc hands="1">
                     <handNote script="cursivaAntiquior">Anglicana Formata with Secretary influence, in a consistent professional hand of the late fifteenth century. Typical double-compartment <q>a</q>, looped ascenders on <q>d</q>, <q>l</q>, <q>b</q>, and <q>h</q>, and sigma-shaped <q>s</q>. The <q>g</q> closed with a separate crossbar and the angular looped <q>d</q> with a triangular lower lobe suggest a hand with Secretary influences of the second half of the fifteenth century, perhaps the fourth quarter. <p>In their edition of Lydgate's <title>Lives of Ss Edmund and Fremund</title> (2009), Anthony Bale and A.S.G. Edwards identify this scribe's hand in two other fifteenth century manuscripts of this text: British Library, MS Yates Thompson 47 and an un-numbered manuscript owned by the Duke of Norfolk. Bale and Edwards suggest this scribe was based in Bury St Edmunds, either within the Abbey or in a secular environment.</p>
                     <p>The Quarto Catalogue suggests the manuscript shares a scribe with the presentation copy of <title>The Lives of Ss Edmund and Fremund</title>, British Library MS Harley 2278, however a comparison of the scripts suggests they were copied by different individuals, although likely in the same environment in Bury St Edmunds. MS Harley 2278 can confidently be dated to between 1434 and 1444 (due to its connection to Henry VI and his sojourn at Bury St Edmunds Abbey in 1434), whereas MS Ashmole 46 suggests a date of several decades later after 1461 (due to the replacement of references to Henry VI with the name of Edward IV). The dates therefore also make it unlikely that these two manuscripts shared a scribe.</p></handNote>
                  </handDesc>
                  <decoDesc>
                     <decoNote type="other">Bale and Edwards suggest the artists who decorated MS Ashmole 46 also decorated British Library, MS Yates Thompson 47 and an un-numbered manuscript owned by the Duke of Norfolk, which also share a scribe with MS Ashmole 46. They also note similarities in the decoration of British Library MS Harley 2278 (the presentation copy of <title>The Lives of Ss Edmund and Fremund</title> for Henry VI).</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="miniature">Fine miniature on folio 1r of a poet (presumably John Lydgate) in monk's habit with an empty scroll kneeling before a king (Henry VI or Edmund IV) who holds an arrow and scepter and sits on a canopied throne. Figures coloured in white, grey, blue, and gold, on a ground of red and green with gold designs. Framed by blue and gold bars on three sides. The same miniature, in the same style and colours, appears in British Library MS Yates Thompson 47 and the un-numbered manuscript owned by the Duke of Norfolk. The miniature in MS Ashmole 46 is significantly worn over the figure of the poet, likely post-reformation damage provoked by his monk's habit.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="border">Borders are partial on three-sides (upper, left and lower margins) which develop from a three-line decorated initial (in the style below), with bars on the left-hand side of the text in gold, pink, and blue, decorated with sprays of foliage and gold disks, on folios 1r, 4v, and 97r.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="decInit">Two and three-line decorated initials throughout in gold on a quartered red and blue ground with white designs, with extended spray work ending in gold balls and leaf motif along the inner margin.(See <ref target="https://catalog.hathitrust.org/Record/000468709">Pächt and Alexander</ref> iii. 895, pl. LXXXVI.)</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="other">Two line paraphs mark each stanza throughout, alternating blue with red flourishes and gold with green flourishes. </decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="other">Edge gilding in gold.</decoNote>
                  </decoDesc>
                  <additions>Folio 72v contains the Latin palindrome <q>Rome tibi subito motibus ibit amor</q> written twice in the upper margin, in a seventeenth century (?) hand.
                  <p><q>A.46</q> in lower margin of folio 158r, presumably the Bodleian shelf-mark.</p>
                  <p>On the blank folios at the rear of the manuscript (fols. 161r-163v), there are several inscriptions: <q>***E/T?ge auge oherforwe</q> (161r), <q>A man withe out marsi no marsi shall <lb/> haue in tyme of ned when he dothe it <lb/> crave but all his lyive go lick a slaue</q> and <q>Questa altra sorte</q> (162v), <q>***E/T?ge auge</q> (163r). Folio 163v is now blank but once contained many fifteenth century inscriptions, some of which are legible under UV light: a small drawing of a shield with illegible writing, <q>boke</q>, <q>Clerk</q>, <q>Est liber</q>, <q>John h????ill</q></p></additions>
                  <bindingDesc><binding notAfter="1700" notBefore="1500"><p>The binding is made of gilt punched leather, using the technique whereby repetitive patterns of geometrical shapes were punched onto the parts of the design that would be left unpainted. It has been coloured with a yellow-gold glaze or tinted varnish, and is decorated with abstract floral designs and a mixture of overlapping punch patterns. The leather covers paste boards and shows remnants of two metal clasps with leather straps. The punched leather is recycled from a larger piece, likely a sixteenth century Italian panelled wall hanging or screen. Similar designs are found on sixteenth century Italian wall hangings in the V&amp;A Collection (items O304822, O304824, and O369581). The binding does not match the style of Sir Thomas Tresham, who owned the manuscript in 1588, who embossed his family crest onto his bindings.</p></binding></bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="1500" notBefore="1461">Second half of the fifteenth century, after 1461 due to the replacement of references to Henry VI with the name of Edward IV.</origDate>
                     <origPlace cert="high">
                        <country key="place_7002445">English</country>, <settlement key="place_7010914">Bury St Edmunds</settlement> (see Kathleen Scott, <title>Later Gothic Manuscripts</title> II, no.112).<!--ORIGINAL: English, Bury St. Edmunds (?)--></origPlace>
                  </origin>
                  <provenance>In 1588 the manuscript was owned by Sir Thomas Tresham (1543-1605), a prominent member of the landed gentry and recusant. Folio 49r contains his ownership inscription dated <date>1588</date>: <q>T. Tresami . M . <lb/> et Amicorum <lb/> credo <lb/> eh</q>. The <q>et Amicorum</q> (<q>and of friends</q>) was a popular formulation of ownership by an individual collector which implied that he shared the book with his circle of friends. <q>Credo</q> was Tresham's personal motto. Tresham leaves the same style of inscription in his copy of the 1589 edition of Antonio of Nebrissa’s <title>Dictionarium latino-hispanicum</title> (see Barker and Quentin, <title>Library of Thomas Tresham</title>, 50). Tresham was sheriff of Northamptonshire in <date>1573</date> and knighted in <date>1575</date>. When he acquired the manuscript, Tresham had just emerged from a long period of imprisonment from 1581 for recusancy. It is not listed in his inventories, edited in Barker, Quentin, and Robinson, <title>The Library of Thomas Tresham &amp; Thomas Brudenell</title>.</provenance>
                  <provenance>The margin of folio 93r contains the erased name <q>Thomas by<gap></gap>ns</q> in a fifteenth century hand, now only legible under UV light.</provenance>
                  <provenance>The name <q>Edward Moorsoppe me tenet</q> is recorded on folio 49r in a sixteenth century (?) hand.</provenance>
                  <provenance>Owned by the poet <persName key="person_18015860">William Brown(e)</persName>, author of <title>Britannia’s Pastorals</title> (1613–16) and Oxford alumnus (matriculated 30 April 1624). His name appears on folio 1r: <q>W. Browne</q> (and his annotations on the parchment flyleaves and throughout the text block?). Browne is known to have owned other manuscripts with Lydgate and Lydgatean material, such as BodL MS Ashmole 45, MS Ashmole 40, MS Ashmole 59, BL Additional MS 34360, BL Lansdowne MS 699, Durham V ii 15, and Durham V ii 16.</provenance>
                  <provenance>The manuscript was later owned by <persName key="person_27215170">Elias Ashmole</persName> (1617–1692), who acquired other manuscripts from Brown(e), for instance MS Ashmole 59 and MS Ashmole 40.</provenance>
                  <provenance>Bequeathed to the Ashmolean Museum by <persName key="person_27215170">Elias Ashmole</persName> in 1692 as part of his donation of 1,100 printed books and 600 manuscripts.</provenance>
                  <acquisition>The manuscript was kept in the Ashmolean until 1860, when the collection was transferred to the Bodleian Library .</acquisition>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source><ref target="https://medieval.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/about">Summary description</ref> abbreviated from the Quarto Catalogue (W. H. Black, <title>A descriptive, analytical, and critical catalogue of the manuscripts bequeathed unto the University of Oxford by Elias Ashmole Esq....</title>, Quarto Catalogues X, 1845). Decoration, localization and date follow Pächt and Alexander (1973). Additional description of decoration by Elizabeth Solopova, c. 2000. <listBibl>
                              <bibl facs="aeh0041.gif" type="QUARTO">Quarto Catalogue, cols. 71–2</bibl>
                              <bibl facs="aeh0042.gif" type="QUARTO">Quarto Catalogue, col. 73</bibl>
                              <bibl facs="aaq0482.gif" type="SC">Summary Catalogue, vol. 2, part 2, p. 1123</bibl>
                           </listBibl>
                           <listBibl type="WRAPPER">
                              <listBibl type="PRINT">
                                 <head>Printed descriptions:</head>
                                 <bibl>Barker, Nicolas, David Quentin, and John Martin Robinson, <title>The Library of Thomas Tresham &amp; Thomas Brudenell</title> (London, 2006).</bibl>
                                 <bibl><title>John Lydgate's Lives of Ss Edmund &amp; Fremund and the Extra miracles of St Edmund</title>, eds Anthony Bale and A. S. G. Edwards, Middle English Texts 41 (Heidelberg, 2009).</bibl>
                                 <bibl>Scott, Kathleen L., <title>Later Gothic Manuscripts, 1390-1490</title>, Survey of Manuscripts Illuminated in the British Isles V.6., in 2 volumes (London, 1996), vol.II no.112.</bibl>
                                 <bibl>Scott, Kathleen L., <q>Lydgate's Lives of Saints Edmund and Fremund: A Newly-Located Manuscript in Arundel Castle</q>, <title>Viator</title> 13 (1982), 335-66.</bibl>
                              </listBibl>
                           </listBibl>
                        </source>
                     </recordHist>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <surrogates><bibl subtype="partial" type="digital-facsimile"><ref target="https://digital.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/objects/f873335e-5c67-4f2d-af36-ba82a4682889/"><title>Digital Bodleian</title></ref>
                        <note>(2 images from 35mm slides)</note></bibl></surrogates>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2023-06-30"><persName>Charlotte Ross</persName> Revised with consultation of original.</change>
         <change when="2017-07-01">First online publication.</change>
         <change when="2017-05-25"><persName>James Cummings</persName> Up-converted the markup using <ref target="https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl">https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl</ref></change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
