<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xml:id="manuscript_319" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>MS. Ashmole 33</title>
            <title type="collection">MSS. Ashmole</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp when="2023-01">Cataloguer</resp>
               <persName>Charlotte Ross</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </publisher>
            <idno type="msID">MS_Ashmole_33</idno>
            <idno type="collection">Ashmole</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="MS_Ashmole_33" xml:lang="en">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <region type="county">Oxfordshire</region>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <institution>University of Oxford</institution>
                  <repository>Bodleian Library</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">MS. Ashmole 33</idno>
                  <altIdentifier type="internal">
                     <idno type="SCN">25166</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
                  <altIdentifier type="internal">
                     <idno type="SCN">25167</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
               <head>Middle English <title>Sir Ferumbras</title> (corrected holograph with drafts); England, xiv second half</head>
               
               <physDesc><p n="composite">The text of <title>Sir Ferumbras</title> is now bound in a volume and the parchment wrappers are stored in a separate box under the same shelfmark.</p>
                  <p>The wrappers consist of two sheets, and outer and an inner, both limp parchment bindings made from recycled papal documents with an early draft of a portion of <title>Sir Ferumbras</title> added later.</p></physDesc>
               <history>
               <origin><origDate calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="1400" notBefore="1357">second half of the 14th century</origDate>
                  <origPlace><country key="place_7002445">English</country></origPlace>
               </origin>
               </history>
               
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source><ref target="https://medieval.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/about">Summary description</ref> abbreviated from the Quarto Catalogue (W. H. Black, <title>A descriptive, analytical, and critical catalogue of the manuscripts bequeathed unto the University of Oxford by Elias Ashmole Esq....</title>, Quarto Catalogues X, 1845). <listBibl>
                              <bibl facs="aeh0012.gif" type="QUARTO">Quarto Catalogue, col. 14</bibl>
                              <bibl facs="aeh0013.gif" type="QUARTO">Quarto Catalogue, col. 15</bibl>
                              <bibl facs="aam0117.gif" type="SC">Summary Catalogue, vol. 5, p. 82</bibl>
                           </listBibl>
                        </source>
                     </recordHist>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <surrogates><bibl subtype="partial" type="digital-facsimile"><ref target="https://digital.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/objects/1bdb3aa4-bd6c-408b-a4c9-bde6cfec15c3/"><title>Digital Bodleian</title></ref>
                        <note>(1 image from 35mm slides)</note></bibl></surrogates>
                  <listBibl type="WRAPPER">
                     <listBibl type="PRINT">
                        <head>Printed descriptions:</head>
                        <bibl>Beadle, Richard, <q>English Autograph Writings of the Later Middle Ages: some preliminaries</q>, <title>Gli Autografi Medievali: Problemi Palaeografici e filologici</title>, eds. Paolo Chiesa and Lucia Pinelli (Spoleto, 1994), 249-68.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Ryley, Hannah, <q>Redrafted &amp; Double-Wrapped: Binding a Medieval English Romance</q>, <title>New Bookbinder</title> 39 (2019), pp. 17-23.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Shepherd, S., <title>Four Middle English Charlemagne Romances: a Revaluation of the Non-Cyclic Verse Texts and the Holograph Sir Ferumbras</title>, unpublished doctoral thesis (Oxford, 1988).</bibl>
                        <bibl><title>The English Charlemagne Romances</title>,ed. Sidney J. H. Herrtage, Early English Text Society os 75(London, 1879, repr. 1966).</bibl>
                     </listBibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
                    
                     <msPart xml:id="MS_Ashmole_33-part1">
                        <msIdentifier>
                           <altIdentifier type="partial">
                              <idno type="part">MS. Ashmole 33 (1) - codex</idno>
                           </altIdentifier>
                        </msIdentifier>
                        <msContents>
                           <textLang mainLang="en" otherLangs="la">Middle English with Latin marginal notes</textLang>
                           <msItem class="#romances" n="1" xml:id="MS_Ashmole_33-item1">
                              <locus>(fols. 1r-77v)</locus>
                              <title key="work_14652">Sir Firumbras</title>
                              <note>The author's holograph of a Middle English translation of the Old French <title>Fierabras</title>. The translation is not faithful to the original, but the narrative content of many lines is maintained. The author's corrections of the text suggest this is a working draft. The text is incomplete due to the loss of the first leaf and the outer pair of leaves belonging to the last quire. The dialect is of Exeter, Devonshire identified by Richard Beadle (1994).</note>
                              <incipit> <gap></gap> Charles dog <gap></gap> as þay awayward <gap></gap> [...]edde <lb/> Mo þan a þousand werrou <gap></gap> slowe þa as <gap></gap> [...]fledde</incipit>
                              <note>Text begins imperfectly. Due to the damage on the first folio, the first line is predominantly illegible.</note>
                              <explicit>Was non of he<abbr>m</abbr> þ<abbr>a</abbr>t ys fleche ne raas <lb/> noþ<abbr>er</abbr> kyng ne baron<abbr>e</abbr> ne non þ<abbr>a</abbr>t was } sche was so fair a þynge </explicit>
                              <note>The verse form and metre change at line 3411 (see <q>Layout</q> below). Beneath the last stanza on fol. 77v are four lines of verse, each pair bracketed with a line of verse in the right margin (as above). The text is partly illegible, even under Ultraviolet light, and is written in the scribe's hand but in a lighter shade of ink. A later hand has traced over some of the letters in a darker ink. Similar marginal verse additions are on fols. 32v, 33r, 69r, 71v, 72r-v, and the same ink is used for interlinear corrections throughout. The scribe also leaves Latin editorial instructions, presumably to himself, in the margins (for instance, 'ponatur in loco isto' on folio 77v).</note>
                              <bibl>DIMEV 972</bibl>
                              <note>Printed by the Early English Text Society, ed. Sidney J. H. Herrtage (1879), with some variants witnessed in the drafts recorded in the footnotes.</note>
                           </msItem>
                        </msContents>
                        <physDesc>
                           <objectDesc form="codex">
                              <supportDesc material="chart">
                                 <support>Paper. The gutter of the middle bifolium of quires 1-4 has been reinforced with parchment. <watermark>One watermark throughout: similar to 'Fleur de lis' (Briquet, 7024).</watermark></support>
                                 <extent>i (modern endleaf, paper, foliated with roman numeral) + 1-77 + i (modern endleaf, paper, foliated 78)
                                    <note>A printed article by John Shelley from 1870 entitled <title>On an Early English Version of Sir Ferumbras (Ashm. MS 33) &amp; the Charlemagne Romances Generally</title> has been glued to the inner back board of the codex and foliated 79-82 as a continuation of the manuscript. At the top of the first page of the article is written <q>To be placed with Ashm. MS. 33 <lb/> With Mr Shelley's compliments</q> and dated <q>1870</q> at the foot of the page in the same hand.</note>
                                    <dimensions type="binding" unit="mm">
                                       <height>240</height>
                                       <width>150</width>
                                    </dimensions>
                                 </extent>
                                 <foliation>Uniform modern pencil.</foliation>
                                 <collation>1<hi rend="superscript">16-1</hi> (fols. 1-15, first folio (and beginning of the text) wanting), 2-4<hi rend="superscript">16</hi> (fols. 16-63), 5<hi rend="superscript">16-2</hi> (fols. 64-77, first and sixteenth folios wanting, with loss of text)</collation>
                                 <condition>Damage to fol. 1 around edges which has been repaired with a paper patch. Similar patch on fol. 2. Staining on fol. 1r around the perimeter of the text block with old repairs. Staining to edges of all pages. Paper delicate and corners worn. Ink faded in parts. </condition>
                              </supportDesc>
                              <layoutDesc>
                                 <summary>The layout changes half way down folio 45r (Herrtage l. 3411), when the verse form and metre change:</summary>
                                 <layout columns="1" writtenLines="38">Fols. 1r-45r: unruled, 35-38 long lines per page in a single column. Long lines in rhyming couplets with rhyming half-lines. Written space <dimensions type="ruled" unit="mm">
                                    <height>185-190</height>
                                    <width>115-125</width>
                                 </dimensions>
                                 </layout>
                                 <layout columns="2" writtenLines="38"> Fols. 45r-77v: unruled, 37-39 lines per page in two columns. Short lines in rhyming couplets, where each couplet is connected with a brace with an accompanying line of verse in a second column. These braced lines are themselves braced in pairs. The rhyme scheme thus reads aabccb. Written space<dimensions type="written" unit="mm">
                                    <height>185-195</height>
                                    <width>115-120</width>
                                 </dimensions>
                                 </layout>
                              </layoutDesc>
                           </objectDesc>
                           <handDesc hands="1">
                              <handNote script="cursivaAntiquior">One hand throughout in a neat consistent anglicana.</handNote>
                           </handDesc>
                           <decoDesc>
                              <decoNote type="flourInit">Large decorated lombardic capitals in the same brown ink as the text mark major textual divisions, occasionally rubricated. Smaller flourished lombardic capitals appear throughout. Reproduced to scale in Herrtage's edition (1879).</decoNote>
                              <decoNote type="marginal">Paraphs in the left margin are spaced intermittently to mark moments of textual division, rather than stanza division. Occasionally rubricated.</decoNote>
                              <decoNote type="marginal">On fol. 46v, the first letters of two lines are decorated with animal heads to highlight the correction of two transposed lines.</decoNote>
                           </decoDesc>
                           <additions><q>This enduenture</q> is written inverted in the lower margin of folio 8r, in a sixteenth-century hand. An alphabet in a fifteenth-century hand is found on folio 63v, in the lower margin and inverted.</additions>
                           <bindingDesc>
                              <binding notAfter="1900" notBefore="1800">
                                 <p></p>
                              </binding>
                           </bindingDesc>
                        </physDesc>
                        <history>
                           <origin>
                              <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="1400" notBefore="1377">last quarter of the 14th century</origDate>
                              <origPlace>
                                 <country key="place_7002445">English</country>
                              </origPlace>
                           </origin>
                           <provenance>The provenance of the two parchment wrappers (see <q>MS. Ashmole 33 (2)</q> below), and the location of the poem's dialect to Exeter, also point to an origin in the Exeter area for the manuscript. The parchment wrappers also suggest a date of the last quarter of the 14th century, after 1377, for the main text, which was written after the earlier drafts which appear on the parchment wrappers. Herrtage's suggestion of a clergyman author is probable, as the poet would have had access to papal documents and a manuscript of the Old French poem <title>Fierabras</title> from which he was translating, and would have been sufficiently educated to be literate in French, English, and Latin.</provenance>
                           <provenance>There is substantial evidence of ownership and circulation of the manuscript in the sixteenth and seventeenth centuries which suggest the codex changed hands several times. Several names are recorded in the lower margins and inverted in multiple (sixteenth-century?) hands, which have been erased but are visible under UV. The name <q>John baske</q> is written on folio 12r. A different, later hand writes <q>In the name of god amen I John</q> in brown ink on folio 37v. Another hand adds the phrase <q>Thomas Miler gent of charite(?) in the(not sure I see a t though) counti(?) of Here[ford]</q> in the margin of folio 23r. Illegible notes in several hands are found on folios 22v, 26v, 27v, 42v, and 62r.</provenance>
                           <provenance>The names <q>Thomas Harrison</q> (64r) and <q>Edm Davies</q> (51r) are recorded in the margins in different seventeenth-century hands. Davies' name appears again in the same hand in the lower margin of folio 26v. </provenance>
                           <provenance>The manuscript was owned by <persName key="person_27215170">Elias Ashmole</persName>, aho bequeathed it to the Ashmolean Museum in 1692 as part of his donation of 1,100 printed books and 600 manuscripts.</provenance>
                           <acquisition>The manuscript was kept in the Ashmolean until 1860, when the Bodleian Library acquired the collection.</acquisition>
                        </history>
                     </msPart>
               
               <msPart type="wrapper">
                  <msIdentifier>
                     <altIdentifier>
                     <idno type="part">MS. Ashmole 33 (2) - outer parchment wrapper</idno>
                       <note>Recycled sheet of thick parchment folded in three around the codex to make an enveloping limp binding. The contents are described in chronological order.</note>
                     </altIdentifier>
                  </msIdentifier>
                  <msContents>
                     <textLang mainLang="lat" otherLangs="en">Latin with remnants of Middle English script</textLang>
                     <msItem>
                        <note>The inside of the outer sheet (here called verso) is a letter executory addressed to the Bishop of Exeter and dated to 3 May 1357. It contains the bull of pope Innocent VI for the presentation of Thomas de Silton to the vicarage of Columpton, in the diocese of Exeter. The post was vacant in 1357 after the death of Peter Moleyns. The bull is addressed to the Abbots of Schirbourne and Cerne and to John de Silvis, dean of the collegiate church of St Agricola in Avignon. Similar papal letters granted by John de Silvis are held in the National Archives (e.g. E 326/9027). </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <note>The outside of the outer sheet (here called recto), which was originally the outermost cover of the book, once contained a part of the author's autograph draft of <title>Sir Ferumbras</title>. In its current folded state, this is the outermost side. This side of the sheet has been substantially worn and discoloured, but shows evidence of erased Middle English script which is still visible on the edges. A few lines of this text carry over to the inside of the outer sheet and are still legible around the margin of the letter executory. It is identifiable as the same hand as the main text of <title>Sir Ferumbras</title> in the codex. The contents and author's corrections of these lines suggest that the poem on this sheet is an early draft of the poem in the codex. </note>
                     </msItem>
                  </msContents>
                     <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc form="sheet">
                        <supportDesc material="perg">
                           <support>Parchment</support>
                           <extent><dimensions type="binding" unit="mm">
                              <height>255</height>
                              <width>424</width>
                           </dimensions></extent>
                        </supportDesc>
                           <layoutDesc>
                              <layout columns="1" writtenLines="38"> 38 long lines on the recto, unruled. Written space <dimensions type="written" unit="mm">
                                 <height>250</height>
                                 <width>430</width>
                              </dimensions></layout>
                           </layoutDesc>
                     </objectDesc>
                     </physDesc>
                  <history>
                     <origin>
                        <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="1358" notBefore="1356">The letter executory is dated 1357. The date of the author's early draft on the verso is uncertain.</origDate>
                        <origPlace>
                           <country key="place_7002445">English</country>
                        </origPlace>
                     </origin>
                     <provenance>The wrapper's original purpose as a bull of the diocese of Exeter suggests the parchment would have first been deposited in the Exeter area soon after 1357. Herrtage notes that this is not a document which would have been carefully preserved by the cathedral, but equally that it would not have travelled outside of the diocese, and therefore it is probably that the <title>Sir Ferumbras</title> poet was a clergyman in the Exeter area who would have had access to unwanted parchment documents (1879).</provenance>
                  </history>
               </msPart>
               
               <msPart type="wrapper">
                  <msIdentifier>
                     <altIdentifier>
                        <idno type="part">MS. Ashmole 33 (2) - inner parchment wrapper</idno>
                        <note>Recycled sheet of thin parchment folded double and then triple around the codex to make a limp binding with a vertical folded flap. The contents are described in chronological order.</note>
                     </altIdentifier>
                  </msIdentifier>
                  <msContents>
                     <textLang mainLang="lat" otherLangs="en">Latin and Middle English</textLang>
                     <msItem>
                        <note>The outside of the inner sheet (here called recto) contains a long and imperfect public announcement in Latin dated 1377, pertaining to the chapel of Holne, in the diocese of Exeter. It describes a disagreement between the rector Roger Langman and the vicar John Brygge over a burial ground adjacent to the chapel. In its current folded state, this side comprises both the inside and outside of the wrapper.</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem>
                        <note>The inside of the inner sheet (here called verso) contains 392 lines of the author's autograph draft of <title>Sir Ferumbras</title>. Like the outer sheet, it appears to be an earlier draft of the text. As this side of the parchment was on the inside of both the fold and the outer sheet, it is remarkably preserved and legible, although faded in parts. The verso contains 4 large columns of text, equivalent to two and a half pages of the codex. It has been trimmed from a larger sheet of parchment on the left and lower margin which resulted in the loss of text.
                        <p>The discrepancy between the inner sheet draft and the codex draft are substantial, with differences in orthography, vocabulary, and even the phrasing of verse. As with the codex, the draft is heavily corrected by the same hand. </p></note>
                     </msItem>
                  </msContents>
                  <physDesc>
                     <objectDesc form="sheet">
                        <supportDesc material="perg">
                           <support>Parchment</support>
                           <extent><dimensions type="binding" unit="mm">
                              <height>450</height>
                              <width>415</width>
                           </dimensions></extent>
                        </supportDesc>
                        <layoutDesc>
                           <layout columns="1" writtenLines="38">The recto contains 79 long lines, unruled. Written space <dimensions type="written" unit="mm">
                              <height>455</height>
                              <width>413</width>
                           </dimensions></layout>
                           <layout columns="4" writtenLines="2">The verso contains 4 columns of 98 lines each, unruled. Written space <dimensions type="written" unit="mm">
                              <height>450</height>
                              <width>412</width>
                           </dimensions></layout>
                        </layoutDesc>
                     </objectDesc>
                  </physDesc>
                  <history>
                     <origin>
                        <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="1400" notBefore="1377">14th century, not before 1377</origDate>
                        <origPlace>
                           <country key="place_7002445">English</country>
                        </origPlace>
                     </origin>
                     <provenance>The wrapper's original purpose as a public announcement linked to Holne in the diocese of Exeter similarly suggests the parchment would have been deposited in the Exeter area soon after 1377. </provenance>
                  </history>
               </msPart>
               
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2023-02-03"><persName>Charlotte Ross</persName> Revised with consultation of original.</change>
         <change when="2017-07-01">First online publication.</change>
         <change when="2017-05-25"><persName>James Cummings</persName> Up-converted the markup using <ref target="https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl">https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl</ref></change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
