<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xml:id="manuscript_322" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>MS. Ashmole 34</title>
            <title type="collection">MSS. Ashmole</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp when="2022-12">Cataloguer</resp>
               <persName>Charlotte Ross</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </publisher>
            <idno type="msID">MS_Ashmole_34</idno>
            <idno type="collection">Ashmole</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="MS_Ashmole_34" xml:lang="en">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <region type="county">Oxfordshire</region>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <institution>University of Oxford</institution>
                  <repository>Bodleian Library</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">MS. Ashmole 34</idno>
                  <altIdentifier type="internal">
                     <idno type="SCN">6915</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
               <head>Fifteenth-century single text codex of John Harding's <title>Chronicle</title>.</head>
               
               <msContents>
                  <msItem n="1" xml:id="MS_Ashmole_34-item1">
                     <locus>(fols. 1r-177v) </locus>
                     <author key="person_90770122">John Harding</author>

                     <title key="work_2715">Chronicle (second version)</title>
                     <note>(also known as the <title>Metrical Chronicle</title>)</note>
                     <incipit><hi>T</hi> he most substaunce of power and of myght <lb/> Thurgh age destelled in to debelyte</incipit>
                     <explicit>For langer þan ye haue hem in subjeccyon<abbr>e</abbr> <lb/>Trest neuer truthe in hem ne p<abbr>er</abbr>feccyon<abbr>e</abbr></explicit>
                     <rubric>In the upper right margin of fol. 1r is a note in a fifteenth century hand <q>John Hardyng maker of thyse cronycles</q></rubric>
                     <colophon>Fol. 177v <q>bought the 14<hi>th</hi> day of februarie 1604 pretiu<abbr>m</abbr> 20s. Pe: Manwood.</q></colophon>
                     <note>There are a significant number of blank spaces throughout, of both single and multiple lines. This manuscript also lacks the chapter on the King’s title to his lands, the author’s excusation, and the itinerary of Scotland. Prose passages present in other manuscripts of the text (MS Arch. Selden B. 10, MS Harley 661) are also omitted.</note>
                     <note>This manuscript shares many visual and textual similarities (and potentially a scribe) with MS Douce 345.</note>
                     <bibl type="repertory"><title>DIMEV</title> 1174</bibl>
                     <textLang mainLang="en">English</textLang>

                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="perg">
                        <support>parchment</support>
                        <extent>ii (paper endleaves, seventeenth century) + 180 (parchment) + ii (paper endleaves, seventeenth century).
                        <dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                           <height>335</height>
                           <width>245</width>
                        </dimensions>
                        </extent>
                        <foliation>Paper flyleaves unfoliated. Three blank parchment flyleaves at the end of the manuscript foliated. Modern pencil foliation throughout in the lower outer corner. The same hand has foliated fols. 2r-11r incorrectly in the upper outer corner, beginning their count on fol. 2. These numbers have been crossed out. Leaf signatures trimmed but are partially visible. Catchwords consistently present, in lower inner margin and predominantly enclosed in banderoles.</foliation>
                        <collation>1<hi>1</hi> (single leaf containing woodcut), 2-17 <hi>8</hi> (fols. 2-129), 18 <hi>6</hi> (fols. 130-135), 19-23<hi>8</hi> (fols. 136-175), 24<hi>2</hi> (fols. 176-177), 25<hi>4-1</hi> (fols. 178-180, first folio excised) </collation>
                        <condition>Board attachment to spine is fragile. Some holes in parchment but overall in good condition. First leaf (containing woodcut) loosely attached.</condition>
                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc><layout columns="1" ruledLines="35">
                        <p>Text ruled in graphite, interlinear in 40 lines.</p> 
                        <p>Page ruled in red ink: horizontal double enclosing top and bottom margins, vertical double at either side of text, inner margin frame ruled, a separate ruled column in the outer margin for glosses. The width of this outer column varies depending on the gloss. Each stanza is divided by a horizontal line. Occasionally, when a single line is missing, the gap is rubricated, suggesting the red ruling was added after the text had been written. Glosses (both rubricated and black) are predominantly frame ruled.</p>
                        <p>35 long lines of text. Pricking (for both graphite and red ruling) occasionally visible in outer and lower margins.</p>
                        <dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                           <height>225</height>
                           <width>125</width>
                        </dimensions>
                     </layout></layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc hands="1">
                     <handNote script="cursivaAntiquior">Anglicana formata, in a professional and consistent hand</handNote>
                  </handDesc>
                  <decoDesc>
                     <decoNote type="woodcut"> Fol. 1v contains a full-page pastedown woodcut, hand-coloured, which depicts a priest with a book and prayer-beads on a blue background. The border has been painted with a thick black paint, but traces of green leaves are visible beneath. In each corner are pasted fragments of parchment with illuminated decoration (likely from a border, of the second quarter of the fifteenth century) in red, blue, green, and gold. These fragments cover four coats of arms which were original to the woodcut, likely in an attempt to repurpose the woodcut for its present context. (<ref target="https://catalog.hathitrust.org/Record/000468709">Pächt and Alexander</ref> iii. 1069, pl. C) At the figure’s foot is a shield party per bend sinister argent and gules - comparison with an unmutilated copy of this woodcut in a 1577 edition of <title> Des Hochwirdigen</title> reveals this shield is original. Above the figure is a pastedown strip of parchment which reads ‘The portratvre of Iohn Harding maker of these chronicles’. D.R. Woolf identifies the woodcut as a portrait of the German prince George III, Prince of Anhalt-Dessau (1507-1553) by <persName key="person_24706489" role="art">Lucas Cranach the younger</persName>.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="miniature">Heraldic shields are drawn in the margins of fols. 34r (argent a cross gules) and 38v (argent a cross gules with bars).</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="border">Fol. 2r opens the text with a six-line illuminated decorated initial, red and blue on gold background, from which extends a two-side spray border with red and blue leaves. 
                     Kathleen Scott identifies other manuscripts that originate from the same workshop, including MS Arch. Selden B.10. (<ref>Scott, <title>Later Gothic Manuscripts, 1390-1490</title>, vol.ii, 354</ref>).</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="decInit">Illuminated initials on a blue and red background with spray work extending along the margin on fols. 6r, 8v, 12r, and 100r.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="paraph">Paraphs mark the start of almost every stanza, inconsistently alternating between red and blue.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="initial">Stanzas occasionally begin with two, three, or four-line lombardic capitals, blue with red flourishes that extend along the margin. The first letter of each line has a yellow wash. Ascenders occasionally flourished.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="gloss">Glosses in red and black. Rubricated glosses marked with a blue paraph with red flourishes.</decoNote>
                  </decoDesc>
                  <additions>A fifteenth century hand in black ink has annotated the margins and expanded glosses throughout. In the second half of the manuscript, the names of the kings mentioned in the text are copied in the margin.</additions>
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <binding notAfter="1692" notBefore="1617">
                        <p>Late seventeenth-century calf binding typical of Elias Ashmole's collection.</p>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
                  
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="1475" notBefore="1464">15th century, third quarter (after 1464)</origDate>
                     <origPlace>
                        <country key="place_7002445">English</country>
                     </origPlace>
                  </origin>
                  <provenance>The manuscript was owned by the judge and antiquary <name>Sir Peter Manwood</name> (1571-1625), who purchased the volume in 1604. Fol. 177v contains his note: <q>bought the 14th day of februarie. 1604. pretium – 20s. Pe: Manwood</q>. Another manuscript owned by Manwood, now MS Bodl. 885, contains a similar ownership note in the same hand. 
                     <p>Manwood was acquainted with <persName key="person_27215170">Elias Ashmole</persName> and is known to have gifted him manuscripts. A colophon on fol. 1r of MS Ashmole 1511 notes (in Ashmole's hand) <q>This booke was gyven mee by my good freinde William Man esquire, this thirde day of August 1609. Peter Manwood</q>. Another of Manwood's manuscripts ended up in Ashmole's collection: now MS Ashmole 849. It is not certain when MS Ashmole 34 entered Ashmole's collection. </p></provenance>
                  <provenance>Ashmole bequeathed the manuscript to the Ashmolean Museum in 1692 as part of his donation of 1,100 printed books and 600 manuscripts.</provenance>
                  <acquisition>The manuscript was kept in the Ashmolean until the 1830’s, when the Bodleian Library acquired the collection.</acquisition>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source><ref target="https://medieval.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/about">Summary description</ref> abbreviated from the Quarto Catalogue (W. H. Black, <title>A descriptive, analytical, and critical catalogue of the manuscripts bequeathed unto the University of Oxford by Elias Ashmole Esq....</title>, Quarto Catalogues X, 1845). Date follows Pächt and Alexander (1973). <listBibl>
                              <bibl facs="aeh0013.gif" type="QUARTO">Quarto Catalogue, col. 15</bibl>
                              <bibl facs="aaq0482.gif" type="SC">Summary Catalogue, vol. 2, part 2, p. 1123</bibl>
                           </listBibl>
                        </source>
                     </recordHist>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <surrogates><bibl subtype="partial" type="digital-facsimile"><ref target="https://digital.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/objects/53c3f27c-068c-4f92-b30a-7b5aad5db700/"><title>Digital Bodleian</title></ref>
                        <note>(1 image from 35mm slides)</note></bibl></surrogates>
                  <listBibl type="PRINT">
                     <head>Printed:</head>
                     <bibl>Edwards, A.S.G., <title>The Manuscripts and Texts of the Second Version of John Hardyng's Chronicle</title>, England in the Fifteenth Century, ed. Daniel Williams (Woodbridge, 1987), 75-84.</bibl>
                     <bibl>Scott, Kathleen, <title>Later Gothic Manuscripts, 1390-1490, Survey of Manuscripts Illuminated in the British Isles</title>, vol.ii (London, 1996).</bibl>
                     <bibl>Woolf, D.R., <title>Reading History in Early Modern England</title>, (Cambridge, 2005).</bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2022-12-22"><persName>Charlotte Ross</persName> Revised with consultation of original.</change>
         <change when="2017-07-01">First online publication.</change>
         <change when="2017-05-25"><persName>James Cummings</persName> Up-converted the markup using <ref target="https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl">https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl</ref></change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
