<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="manuscript_1966">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>MS. Broxb. 85.7</title>
            <title type="collection">MSS. Broxb. (Broxbourne)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Preliminary description</resp>
               <persName>Peter Kidd</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </publisher>
            <idno type="msID">MS_Broxb_857</idno>
            <idno type="collection">Broxbourne</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="MS_Broxb_857" xml:lang="en">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <region type="county">Oxfordshire</region>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <institution>University of Oxford</institution>
                  <repository>Bodleian Library</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">MS. Broxb. 85.7</idno>
                  <idno type="ieArk">ark:29072/x06w924c61nh</idno><idno type="crArk">ark:29072/x06t053g78b6</idno><altIdentifier type="internal">
                     <idno type="SCN">Not in SC (late accession)</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents>
                  <msItem n="1" xml:id="MS_Broxb_857-item1">
                     <author key="person_44293577">Giovanni Sabadino degli Arienti</author>
                     <title key="work_1785">Trattato della Pudicizia</title>
                     <incipit>Havendo vn giorno fra gli altri nel mio studio</incipit><note>Dated 1487 by Chandler (see under literature). For details of dedication, see under provenance.</note>
                     <textLang mainLang="ita">Italian</textLang>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <p><secFol>quando conseguiriti</secFol></p>
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="perg">
                        <support>parchment</support>
                        <extent>i + 62 leaves <dimensions unit="mm" type="leaf">
                           <height>196</height>
                           <width>138</width>
                        </dimensions></extent>
                        <collation mainStructures="10">front pastedown and fol. i conjoint; I(12-1) (fols. 1-11), stub after fol. 11 an original cancellation; II-VI(10); fol. 62 and back pastedown conjoint. <catchwords>Catchwords written vertically in the inner lower margin of each quire.</catchwords> </collation>
                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout rulingMedium="ink" columns="1" writtenLines="22" topLine="above">Ruled in pale pink, single column, 22 lines per page, ruled space <dimensions unit="mm" type="ruled">
                           <height max="134" min="133">133–4</height>
                           <width min="81" max="92">81–2</width>
                        </dimensions>, writing above top line.</layout>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc>
                     <handNote script="humanistica">Formal humanistic hand, possibly of <persName key="person_44293577" role="scr">the author</persName>; brown ink. </handNote>
                  </handDesc>
                  <decoDesc>
                     <decoNote>(fol. 1v) monumental dedication page, inscription in white capitals on a black ground enclosed within an arched frame with marbled pink base and arch, green pilasters, and blue architrave, a coat of arms within the arch (see under provenance)</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="border">(fol. 2r) opening of text: plain violet four-line initial on gold ground; frame border with panels containing blue or green laurel wreaths, flowers and cornucopiae on a background of gold ornamental scrolls, and in the centre of each side a dove, one flying, the other on the ground; a coat of arms in the centre panel of the lower border (see under provenance). </decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="decInit">Two-line gold chapter initials in blue, green, and red framed particoloured panels heightened with white.</decoNote>
                  </decoDesc>
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <binding notAfter="1600" notBefore="1575">
                        <p>Venice?; 16th cent., third quarter. Red morocco richly tooled in gold on both covers with azured and solid leafy tools, small rosettes and dots within the central panel and border; the inner and outer frames formed by double lines, those of the inner shaped into crescents at the corners. A foliate cartouche in the centre of each cover encloses the initials  S. (above) L. (left)  A. (right)  M. (below). Remains of four crimson silk strings on each cover, two on the fore-edge and one each at top and bottom. Three raised bands and four raised half-bands divide the spine into eight panels; the head and tail panels, larger than the others, are further divided into two by triple gold lines, making a total of ten, each containing a pair of leaf motifs tooled in gold. The raised bands are decorated with triple horizontal gold lines; the half-bands are hatched with pairs of gold lines filled with dots. Both the bands and half-bands also have a single or double horzontal gold line immediately above and below them. Red and yellow headbands. Spine liner from a late medieval manuscript. Edges of leaves gilt and gauffered.
                        </p>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origDate calendar="Gregorian" when="1487">c. 1487</origDate>
                     <origPlace>
                        <country key="place_1000080">Italian</country>, <settlement key="place_7004847">Bologna</settlement>
                        <!--ORIGINAL: Italian, Bologna-->
                     </origPlace>
                  </origin>
                  <provenance>Dedicatory inscription of fol. 1v: 'IOANN . SA . ARGENTEVS . CLARIS . SIMAE . AC . PVDICIS . D . MINO . CRE . AFFINI . CARISS . S . P . D . '. Within the lunette above is an unidentified coat of arms, described by Warner as 'per fess gules and or, the first charged with an estoile of the second' and found by Chandler in two manuscripts containing other works by Sabadino. They are not the Arienti arms. <!-- or are they? http://badigit.comune.bologna.it/books/bollettino/pdf/2004-11.pdf  --> The arms in the centre of the lower border on fol. 2r are those of the Leonesi family of Bologna. Chandler suggests that the text was dedicated to Colomba, the sister of Sabadino's wife Francesca Bruni.</provenance><provenance>Initials on binding: S. (above) L. (left)  A. (right)  M. (below)</provenance>
                  <provenance>Inscriptions in black ink on the binding: 'A'(?) at the top of the spine, '10πs'(?) at the top of the upper cover.</provenance>
                  <provenance>
                     <persName key="person_37807295" role="fmo">Charles Fairfax Murray</persName>: book-plate, front pastedown. Acquired from Leo S. Olschki in Florence after 1900. Pencil note '37', front pastedown, in an unidentified hand. 
                  </provenance>
                  <provenance>
                     <persName key="person_20486290" role="fmo">C. W. Dyson Perrins</persName>: bought from Fairfax Murray, 1906. Book-plate, front pastedown. Three labels: bottom of spine, circular, inscribed '80'; front pastedown, printed 'C.W. Dyson Perrins', inscribed '80'; back pastedown, circular, printed 'Perrins Collection', inscribed '3'. No. 80 in Warner's catalogue (see under literature). Pencil notes by Dyson Perrins, fol. ir.</provenance>
                  <provenance><persName role="fmo" key="person_53056049">Albert Ehrman</persName>: bought at the Dyson Perrins sale, Sotheby's, 1 Dec. 1959, lot 84. Sale label, front pastedown. Ehrman book-plate, front pastedown. Formerly Broxbourne ledger no. R 1672.</provenance>
                  <acquisition when="1978">Presented to the Bodleian by his son, John Ehrman, in 1978 through the Friends of the National Libraries.</acquisition>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>Draft description by Martin Kauffmann, 1990s. </source>
                     </recordHist>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <surrogates><bibl subtype="partial" type="digital-facsimile"><ref target="https://digital.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/objects/cdf96ca9-e5a9-4d21-abcb-4bd4c8a718ec/"><title>Digital Bodleian</title></ref>
                        <note>(2 images from 35mm slides)</note></bibl></surrogates>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>Peter Kidd, <title>Checklist of Medieval Western Manuscripts Acquired 1916-</title> (typescript, c. 1996–2000) </bibl>
                     <bibl>C. Mazzi, 'Il Trattato della Pudicizia di Sabatino degli Arienti', <title>La Bibliofilia</title> 2 (1900-01), 269-74, reproducing upper cover and fol. 2r.</bibl>
                     <bibl>G. Warner, <title>Descriptive Catalogue of Illuminated Manuscripts in the Library of C.W. Dyson Perrins</title> (Oxford, 1920), no. 80.</bibl>
                     <bibl>S.B. Chandler, 'Il Trattato della Pudicizia di Sabadino degli Arienti', <title>La Bibliofilia</title> 56 (1954), 110-13.</bibl>
                     <bibl>A.C. de la Mare, 'Further Italian Illuminated Manuscripts', no. 19, reproducing fols. 1v-2r.</bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2025-02">Encode description by Martin Kauffmann.</change>
         <change when="2017-07-01">First online publication.</change>
         <change when="2017-05-25"><persName>James Cummings</persName> Up-converted the markup using <ref target="https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl">https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl</ref></change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>