<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="manuscript_6120">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>MS. Holkham Gr. 102</title>
            <title type="collection">MSS. Holkham Gr. (Holkham Hall Greek)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp when="2020">Cataloguer</resp>
               <persName>Dimitrios Skrekas</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp when="2020">Encoding</resp>
               <persName>Matthew Holford</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </publisher>
            <idno type="msID">MS_Holkham_Gr_102</idno>
            <idno type="collection">Holkham gr</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="MS_Holkham_Gr_102" xml:lang="en">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <region type="county">Oxfordshire</region>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <institution>University of Oxford</institution>
                  <repository>Bodleian Library</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">MS. Holkham Gr. 102</idno>
                  <idno type="ieArk">ark:29072/x0kk91fk59w4</idno><idno type="crArk">ark:29072/x0kh04dp76kp</idno><altIdentifier type="internal">
                     <idno type="SCN">Not in SC (late accession)</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno type="diktyon">48170</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
               <head>Cleomedes, On the circular movement of heavenly bodies, and an Anonymous Treatise on the Astrolabe.</head>
               <msContents>
                  <msItem n="1">
                     <locus>(fols 1r-42v)</locus>
                     <author key="person_265395062">Cleomedes</author>
                     <title key="work_1294">De motu circulari corporum caelestium</title>
                     <note>Ed. R. Todd, <title>Cleomedis Caelestia (Μετέωρα)</title>, Leipzig, 1990, pp. 1–84: i) fols 1r-22v: Book 1, ed. Todd, pp. 1–43; ii) fols 23r-42v: Book 2, ed. Todd, pp. 44–84. fol. 39r: space of six lines, with no text loss, maybe left for an image. Ed. Todd, p. 77, Book 2. 5. 151 ff. </note>
                     <textLang mainLang="grc">Greek</textLang>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="2">
                     <locus>(fols 43r-45v)</locus>
                     <title key="work_16371">De astrolabio</title>
                     <note>Anonymous, tit. Ἐξήγησις μερικὴ περὶ τοῦ ἀστρολάβου σαφεστάτη καὶ σύντομος, inc. Εἰ βούλει γινώσκειν τὴν τοῦ ἀστρολάβου μέθοδον, … des. καὶ ταῦτα μὲν περὶ τῆς μεθόδου τοῦ ἀστολάβου. Ed. E. Hiller, ‘Miscellen A. Mittheilungen aus handschriften. Der codex Marcianus 303’, <title>Philologus</title> 31 (1872) 177.9–180. 39. Cf. ed. H. Hase, ‘Joannis Alexandrini, cognomine Philoponi, de vsu (sic) astrolabii ejusque constructione libellus. E. Codd. Mss, Regiae bibliothecae Parisiensis marmorum Dresdensium regius custos᾽, <title>Rheinisches Museum für Philologie</title> 6 (1839) 158–159 (Αἰγυπτίου ἑρμηνεία τῆς τοῦ ἀστρολάβου χρήσεως); ed. A. Delatte, <title>Anecdota Atheniensia et alia</title>. vol. 2. Liège, Paris, 1939, pp. 254–262 (IV. Anonyme, Ἑτέρα ἐξήγησις περὶ τοῦ ἀστρολάβου.).</note>
                     <textLang mainLang="grc">Greek</textLang>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="3">
                     <locus>(fols 46r, 47r (pasted paper))</locus>
                     <note>Notes in Latin (post 1630) on Cleomedes MS and similar editions with dates (cf. <title>Procli de sphaera liber. Cleomedis de mvndo, sive circularis inspectionis meteororum libri duo. Arati Solensis Phænomena, siue Apparentia. Dionysii Aphri descriptio orbis habitabilis</title>, Antwerp, 1553, <title>Uranologion, sive Systema variorum authorum qui de sphaera ac sideribus eorumque motibus graece commentati sunt. Sunt autem horum libri Gemini, Achillis Tatii Isagoge ad Arati Phaenomena, Hipparchi libri tres ad Aratum, Ptolemaei de apparentiis, Theodori Gazae de mensibus, Maximi, Isaaci Argyri... S. Andreae Cretensis Computi, omnia vel graece ac latine nunc primum edita, val ante non edita, cura... Dionysii Petavii,... Accesserunt variarum dissertationum libri octo ad authores illos intelligendos... utiles, eodem authore</title>, Paris, 1630 : i) fol. 46r: (in pencil, newer hand, 18th c. :1000); in brown ink: inc. Cleomedes etiam … des. I. II c. XVII; ii) fol. 47r: (in pencil, newer hand, 18th c. :1000); in brown ink: inc. Quorum quaedam … des. reprititis? /nd. Jun. S(?)at. 6. (the last three words in black ink). </note>
                     <textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="chart">
                        <support> Paper</support>
                        <extent><dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                              <height>222</height>
                              <width>163</width>
                           </dimensions>
                        </extent>
                        <collation> 1 × 2–1 (i), 1 × 2 (iii), 2 × 8 (16), 7 × 4 (44), 1 × 6–1 (49), 1 × 2–1 (50 + 1 endleaf paper pasted)</collation>
                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout ruledLines="25"> 25 lines per page.</layout>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc hands="1">
                     <handNote> One scribe. </handNote>
                  </handDesc>
                  <decoDesc>
                     <decoNote> Decorative head-pieces preceding each sections: (in red ink): fol. 1r, fol. 23r, fol. 43r</decoNote>
                  </decoDesc>
                  <additions>Explanatory diagrams throughout the text: fol. 4v, 10v, 17r. fol. 22r: Τέλος τοῦ πρώτου. Fol. 45v: (in red ink, very faint): τέλος τέλος/ τέλος /τῶ θ<ex>ε</ex>ῶ δόξα/ ἀμἠν/ τέλος. </additions>
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <binding notAfter="1825" notBefore="1800">
                        <p>Typical Holkham binding of brown leather, with Coke family ostrich crest in gilt in the centre of the upper cover; Date: early nineteenth century. Rebound by John Jones of Liverpool (worked for Holkham 1816–1823. The spine lettered in gilt: / CLEOMEDI<supplied>S</supplied>/OP./ GR.–//MS./; in pasted black leather: MS. /HOLK./ Gr. 102/</p>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="1600" notBefore="1500">16th century</origDate>
                  </origin>
                  <provenance>
                     <p>Ownership Notes: fol. 1r in black ink: signature of <persName key="person_8145335" role="fmo">Th<ex>oma</ex>s Wil<ex>lia</ex>m Coke</persName>.- ; right bottom: in pencil note with a date 1690. Catalogue Numbers: Catalogue Nrs: Seidel, quarto, no. 54, p. 17. See <title>Catalogus Librorum Bibliothecae Seidelianae Catalogus librorum bibliothecae Seidelianae: pro parata pecunia divendendorum quorum auctio hic Francofurti ad Viadr. die 23. Febr. 1712,</title>, Frankfurt 1712; <title>Bibliotheca Insignis &amp; Numerosa Viri Piè Defuncti, Generosissimi &amp; Doctissimi Dni. Dni. Andr. Erasmi de Seidel ...: Continens Non Solum Libros Manuscriptos Variar. Materiar. &amp; Lingvar. Nempe Germanicae, Latin. ...</title> Sed Etiam Typis Excusos in Aliis, Praeter Jam Dictas, Linguis Materiis, &amp; Gacultaib. Non Postremos, Quorum Aucito Habebitur Die I.Mo &amp; Seqq. Augusti ... Laurentius, 1718, p. 17: ‘Cleomedis, Autoris Græci, Commentarius de Sphæra ac Syderibus eorumque motibus Græcè’. See also R. Förster, 'Handschriften in Holkham', <title>Philologus</title> 42 (1884) 161–162 and 164. Förster identifies part of the description in Seidel’s catalogue, folio, n. 195, p. 77 (namely of MS. Holkham Gr. 67, olim cod. CCXCVII), as referring to the MS Holkham Gr. 102 (olim cod. CCXCI): … Est Codex egregius Graecus in charta bombycina non inelegander conscriptus ante plus quam quingentos, ut videtur, annos’’, but while omitting the rest of the reference from Seidel’s catalogue, because it describes MS. Holkham Gr. 67: Perpauca quædam Folia passim, tum in medio tum in fine, desiderantur, he fails to explain how the entry makes a mixture of two codices and more importantly why the MS under question has a separate entry in Seidel’s catalogue (n. 54, p. 17); See also S. de Ricci, <title>A handlist of manuscripts in the library of the Earl of Leicester at Holkham Hall: abstracted from the catalogues of William Roscoe and Frederic Madden</title> (Supplement to the Bibliographical Society's Transactions, 7, Oxford, 1932), p. 24: From the <persName key="person_35523287" role="fmo">A. E. Seidel</persName> sale (Berlin, 1718, no. 54). However, S. de Ricci was unable to see Seidel’s sale catalogue(s). See S. de Ricci, p. xi, esp. fn. 1. Front paste-down (in pencil), fol. i (v): MS. Holkham Gr. 102/ bottom left: 662. b.; fol. ii(r): D2<hi rend="superscript underline">B.9</hi> No <del>286</del> (sup lin 291) (= <orgName key="org_8" role="fmo">Libr. of the Earl of Leicester</orgName>, 291).</p>
                  </provenance>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>Description by Dimitrios Skrekas (2020), with the support of the Leventis Foundation, the Oxford Centre for Byzantine Research, the Yerolemou Trust and the Michael Marks Charitable Trust.</source>
                     </recordHist>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl type="WRAPPER">
                     <listBibl type="INTERNET">
                        <head>Online resources:</head>
                        <bibl><ref target="http://pinakes.irht.cnrs.fr/notices/cote/48170/"><title>Pinakes | Πίνακες: Textes et manuscrits grecs</title></ref></bibl>
                     </listBibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2020-09-22">New description by D. Skrekas.</change>
         <change when="2017-07-01">First online publication.</change>
         <change when="2017-05-25"><persName>James Cummings</persName> Up-converted the markup using <ref target="https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl">https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl</ref></change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>