<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="manuscript_6126">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>MS. Holkham Gr. 108</title>
            <title type="collection">MSS. Holkham Gr. (Holkham Hall Greek)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp when="2020">Cataloguer</resp>
               <persName>Dimitrios Skrekas</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp when="2020">Encoding</resp>
               <persName>Matthew Holford</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </publisher>
            <idno type="msID">MS_Holkham_Gr_108</idno>
            <idno type="collection">Holkham_gr</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="MS_Holkham_Gr_108" xml:lang="en">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <region type="county">Oxfordshire</region>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <institution>University of Oxford</institution>
                  <repository>Bodleian Library</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">MS. Holkham Gr. 108</idno>
                  <idno type="ieArk">ark:29072/x0ms35t859m0</idno><idno type="crArk">ark:29072/x0mp48sc7694</idno><altIdentifier type="internal">
                     <idno type="SCN">Not in SC (late accession)</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno type="diktyon">48176</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
               <head>Aetius of Amida, Libri Medicinales</head>
               <msContents>
                  <textLang mainLang="grc">Greek</textLang>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS_Holkham_Gr_108-item1">
                     <author key="person_79115278">Aetius of Amida</author>
                     <title key="work_282">Libri medicinales I-VIII</title>
                     <msItem n="1">
                        <locus from="1r" to="1v">(fols 1r–1v)</locus>
                        <note><supplied>Synopsis of the 16 Books of Aetius</supplied>, ed. A. Olivieri, <title>Aëtii Amideni libri medicinales i-iv</title>, Corpus medicorum Graecorum 8.1, Leipzig, 1935, pp. 8–9.</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="2">
                        <locus from="1v" to="47v">(fols 1v–47v)</locus>
                        <note>Book I: i) fols 1v-3v: Table of Contents, tit. Πίναξ τοῦ πρώτου λόγου κ<ex>α</ex>τ<ex>ὰ</ex> στοιχεῖον. ἠτ<ex>οι</ex> κ<ex>α</ex>τ<ex>ὰ</ex> α<ex>λφα</ex>β<ex>ητον</ex>, ed. A. Olivieri, Aëtii Amideni libri medicinales i-iv, pp. 10–16, for the title, see apparatus, p. 10. fols 3v-47v: main text, tit. (in red ink): Σύνοψις τῶν τριῶν βιβλίων ὀριβασίου, λέγω δὴ τῶν πρὸς Ἰουλιανὸν καὶ τ<ex>ῆς</ex> πρὸς Εὐστάθιον καὶ τοῦ πρὸς Εὐνάπι<ex>ον</ex> καὶ τῶν θεραπευτικ<ex>ῶν</ex> βιβλίων Γαληνοῦ καὶ Ἀρχιγένους καὶ Ῥούφου καὶ ἑτέρων τινῶν ἀρχαίων ἐπισήμ<ex>ων</ex>. Σύνοψις τῶν ἁπλῶν Γαληνοῦ πρῶτον. Ἀετίου Ἀμιδηνοῦ βιβλίον πρῶτον. ed. A. Olivieri, <title>Aëtii Amideni libri medicinales i-iv</title>, pp. 17–146. </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="3">
                        <locus from="47r" to="89v">(fols 47r–89v)</locus>
                        <note>Book II: i) fols 47v-49r: Table of contents, tit. Κεφάλαια τοῦ δευτέρου βιβλίου; ii) fols 49r-79r: Main text, tit. (in red ink) περὶ ἐκλογῆς τῶν καλλιστευόντων φαρμάκων iii) fols 79r-89v: Book II, ed. A. Olivieri, Aëtii Amideni libri medicinales i-iv, pp. 152–255. fol. 79r: certain lines are not written after φακὸς ὁ ἐπὶ τελμάτων (σις´, 6) and the text starts from what is indicated as σιθ΄as if σιζ΄-σιη΄ were missing from the scribe’s exemplar. That σιθ΄ is however labelled as σιη΄ in ed. A. Olivieri, Aëtii Amideni libri medicinales i-iv, p. 231. Fol. 89v: Book ending with ἰώδη τὴν χρόαν ἐμφαίνουϲα. ed. A. Olivieri, <title>Aëtii Amideni libri medicinales i-iv</title>, p. 226, 9 (ρϟς´). </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="4">
                        <locus from="89v" to="129r">(fols 89v–129r)</locus>
                        <note>Book III: i) fols 89v-90v: Table of Contents, tit. Κεφάλαια τοῦ τρίτου βιβλίου. ii) fols 91r-129r: Main text, tit. περὶ τρίψεως παρασκευαστικῆς, ed. A. Olivieri, <title>Aëtii Amideni libri medicinales i-iv</title>, pp. 260.9–355.</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="5">
                        <locus from="129r" to="150r">(fols 129r–150r)</locus>
                        <note>Book IV: i) fols 129r-130r: Table of Contents, tit. Κεφάλαια τοῦ δ´ βιβλίου ἀετίου. ii) fols 130r-150r: Main text: ed. A. Olivieri, Aëtii Amideni libri medicinales i-iv, pp. 358–408. fol. 130r: tit. διαιτητικὸν ὑγιεινῶν παραγγελμάτων ἐκ τῶν γαληνοῦ τί ἐστιν ὑγεία, καὶ τίνες οἱ ἄριστα κατεσκευασμένοι, see apparatus in ed. A. Olivieri, <title>Aëtii Amideni libri medicinales i-iv</title>, p. 358.</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="6">
                        <locus from="150r" to="198r">(fols 150r–198r)</locus>
                        <note>Book V, i) fols 150r-152r: Table of Contents, tit. Κεφάλαια τοῦ εου· τάδε ἔνεστιν ἐν τῶ εω´ λόγω: ii) fols 152r-198r: Main text, ed. A. Olivieri, <title>Aëtii Amideni libri medicinales v-viii</title>, Corpus medicorum Graecorum 8.2. Berlin, 1950, pp. 6–119. Fol. 152r: tit. περὶ τῆς τῶν πυρετῶν διαγνώσεως καὶ θεραπείας λόγος εος. fol. 198r: des. μόρια κεκτημένων. (in red ink): τέλος τοῦ πέμπτου λόγου περὶ τῆς τ<ex>ῶν</ex> πυρετῶν διαγνώσε<ex>ως</ex> καὶ θερμασίας. </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="7">
                        <locus from="198r" to="252v">(fols 198r–252v)</locus>
                        <note>Book VI: i) fols 198r-199v: Table of Contents, tit. τάδε ἔνεστιν ἐν τῶ ςω´ λόγω; ii) fols 199v-252v: ed. A. Olivieri, <title>Aëtii Amideni libri medicinales v-viii</title>, pp. 125.4–249. Fol. 199v: tit. (in red ink): περὶ τῶν περὶ τὴν κεφαλὴν συνισταμένων παθῶν πάντων ἀετίου λόγος ςος´ tit. cap. Περὶ φρενίτιδος ἐκ τῶν ποσειδωνίου; inc. ἡ φρενῖτις φλεγμονή … des. ἀδύνατον πτάρνυσθαι. (πτάρνυσθαι᾽᾽. Τέλος τοῦ ἕκτου λόγου. ed.)</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="8">
                        <locus from="253r" to="312r">(fols 253r–312r)</locus>
                        <note>Book VII: i) fols 253r-254v: Table of Contents, tit. τάδε ἔνεστιν ἐν τῶ ζω´ λόγω; fols 254v-312r: ed. A. Olivieri, <title>Aëtii Amideni libri medicinales v-viii</title>, pp. 253–399. Fols 254v: tit. Περὶ τῶν ἐν ὀφθαλμοῖς παθῶν ἀετίου λόγος· ζος´· tit. cap. περὶ φύσεως ὀφθαλμῶν. inc. ἡ κ<ex>α</ex>τ<ex>ὰ</ex> τοὺς ὀφθαλμοὺς … </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="9">
                        <locus from="312r" to="368r">(fols 312r–368r)</locus>
                        <note>Book VIII: i) fols 312r-313r: Table of Contents, tit. Τάδε ἔνεστιν ἐν τῶ ὀγδόῳ λόγῳ ἀετίου ii) fols 313r-368r: ed. A. Olivieri, <title>Aëtii Amideni libri medicinales v-viii</title>, pp. 403–554. fol. 313r: tit. περὶ τῶν ἐν τῶ προσώπω καὶ στόματι καὶ παρ᾽ ἰσθμίοις παθῶν λόγος η· ὑπετάγη δὲ τῶ λόγῳ περὶ κατάῥῥου καὶ βηχὸς, καὶ τῶν τῆς τραχείας ἀρτηρίας καὶ πνεύμονος καὶ θώρακος παθῶν: fol. 313v: tit. Πρὸς τὰς τῶν ὀφρύων διακοσμήσεις. Inc. Προείρηται μὲν περὶ τούτου … des. καρύου ποντικοῦ μέγεθος. p. 553.20. </note>
                     </msItem>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="chart">
                        <support> Paper</support>
                        <extent> <seg type="leaf"><measure type="laterEndleaf" quantity="2">ii</measure> + <measure type="leaf" quantity="370">370</measure></seg> leaves<dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                              <height>315</height>
                              <width>220</width>
                           </dimensions>
                        </extent>
                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout ruledLines="30"> 30 lines per page.</layout>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc>
                     <handNote>
                        <persName key="person_3375" role="scr">Νικόλαος</persName>, RGK I, 330; RGK II, 447. </handNote>
                  </handDesc>
                  <additions> fol. 1r (contemporary modern hand in pencil): Should have been labelled/ Aetii Amideni/ Libri Medicinales.</additions>
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <binding notAfter="1825" notBefore="1800">
                        <p>Holkham binding of light brown leather, with Coke family ostrich crest in gilt in the centre of the upper cover; Date: early nineteenth century. Rebound by <persName key="person_707" role="bnd">John Jones of Liverpool</persName> (worked for Holkham 1816–1823). The spine lettered in gilt: / ORIBASII/PERGAMENSIS/OPERA/MEDICA //M.S./ SÆC. XIV./; in pasted black leather: MS. /HOLKHAM/ Gr. 108/</p>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="1600" notBefore="1500">16th century</origDate>
                  </origin>
                  <provenance><p><orgName key="org_243863172" role="fmo">Monastery of San Giovanni di Verdara in Padua</orgName>. See J. P. Tomasini, <title>Bibliothecae Patavinae manuscriptae publicae &amp; privatae, quibus diversi Scriptores hactenus incogniti recensentur, ac illustrantur […]</title>, Utini, 1639, p. 20, col. 2, XVI, item 3. The MS is to be identified with ‘Bibl. S. Joannis in Viridario ad. dextr. plut. XVI’. See H. Diels, <title>Die Handschriften der antiken Ärzte, II. Teil: Die übrigen griechischen Ärzte außer Hippokrates und Galenos</title>, Abh. d. Königl. Preuß. Akademie d. Wiss. Berlin, 1906, phil.-hist. Kl. 1, Berlin, 1906, p. 6, where it is regarded as lost, but it is to be identified with Holkham 283 (= old number before the MSS were moved to Oxford), a manuscript known to Diels. For the latter see in his H. Diels, <title>Bericht über den Stand des interakademischen Corpus medicorum antiquorum und Erster Nachtrag zu den in den Abhandlungen 1905 und 1906 veröffentlichten Katalogen: Die Handschriften der antiken Ärzte, I. und II. Teil</title>, Abh. d. Königl. Preuß. Akademie d. Wiss. 1907, Berlin, 1908, p. 43. See also M. R. Formentin, <title>I codici greci di medicina nelle tre Venezie</title>, Padua, 1978, p. 20, and A. Touwaide, <title>A census of Greek medical manuscripts: from Byzantium to the Renaissance</title>, Medicine in the medieval mediterranean 6, London, New York, 2016, p. 89 [0404], p. 192 [0901].<!-- After the dissolution of the Monastery of San Giovanni in
                    1783 all its books and MSS were moved to the Biblioteca Marciana in Venice
                    (1783-1784). See M. R. Formentin, I codici greci di medicina
                        nelle tre Venezie, p. 19.-->
                     </p>
                     <p>Ownership Notes: Connection with Pietro Floriani da Montagnana †1478 was erroneous. Pietro’s MSS, now Holkham Gr. 84, 90, 103 and BL Additional MS 47674 were bequeathed to the Monastery of San Giovanni di Verdara in Padua by him, but there is no evidence about MS Holkham Gr 108. This wrong identification was mainly due to a typo which appeared in R. W. Hunt, ‘Pietro da Montagnana: a Donor of Books to san Giovanni di Verdara in Padua’, Bodleian Library Record 9 (1973) 18. There Hunt speaks about ‘Philostratus Heroica (108)’, but apparently is referring to MS Holkham gr. 103. This typo is repeated in N. G. Wilson, ‘The Book Trade in Venice ca. 1400–1515’, in <title>Venezia centro di mediazione tra Oriente e Occidente (secoli XV-XVI). Aspetti e problemi</title>, eds H.-G. Beck et al., Florence, 1977, vol. II, p. 389, and F. Pontani, <title>Sguardi su Ulisse: la tradizione esegetica greca all'Odissea</title>, Sussidi eruditi 63, Rome, 2011, p. 439. Gamba however corrects the erratum in her thesis: E. Gamba, 'Pietro Da Montagnana: La Vita, Gli Studi, La Biblioteca Di Un Homo Trilinguis', unpublished PhD. thesis, 29 January 2016, pp. 345, 534 <ref target="http://paduaresearch.cab.unipd.it/9396/">http://paduaresearch.cab.unipd.it/9396/</ref>.</p>
                     <p>Catalogue Nrs: Olim Padua, [S. Giovanni in Viridario, ad dextr. plut. XVI]; front paste-down (in pencil): MS. Holkham Gr. 108; fol. i(r): No 289 (sup. lin. 3) D H G2 (= <orgName key="org_8" role="fmo">Libr. of the Earl of Leicester</orgName>, 283).</p></provenance>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>Description by Dimitrios Skrekas (2020), with the support of the Leventis Foundation, the Oxford Centre for Byzantine Research, the Yerolemou Trust and the Michael Marks Charitable Trust.</source>
                     </recordHist>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl type="WRAPPER">
                     <listBibl type="INTERNET">
                        <head>Online resources:</head>
                        <bibl><ref target="http://pinakes.irht.cnrs.fr/notices/cote/48176/"><title>Pinakes | Πίνακες: Textes et manuscrits grecs</title></ref></bibl>
                     </listBibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2020-09-22">New description by D. Skrekas.</change>
         <change when="2017-07-01">First online publication.</change>
         <change when="2017-05-25"><persName>James Cummings</persName> Up-converted the markup using <ref target="https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl">https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl</ref></change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>