<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="manuscript_6268">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>MS. Holkham misc. 40</title>
            <title type="collection">MSS. Holkham misc. (Holkham miscellaneous)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Description</resp>
               <persName>Elizabeth Solopova</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Revision</resp>
               <persName>Andrew Dunning</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </publisher>
            <idno type="msID">MS_Holkham_misc_40</idno>
            <idno type="collection">Holkham misc</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="MS_Holkham_misc_40" xml:lang="en">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <region type="county">Oxfordshire</region>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <institution>University of Oxford</institution>
                  <repository>Bodleian Library</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">MS. Holkham misc. 40</idno>
                  <idno type="ieArk">ark:29072/x0kp78gg437g</idno><idno type="crArk">ark:29072/x0kk91fk59xh</idno><altIdentifier type="internal">
                     <idno type="SCN">Not in SC (late accession)</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents>
                  <textLang mainLang="enm" otherLangs="la">Middle English with Latin</textLang>
                  <msItem>
                     <note>Fols. i–iii are paper flyleaves, blank apart from modern notes.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="1">
                     <locus>(fols. 1r–133r)</locus>
                     <title key="work_13326">Prose <title>Mirror</title></title>
                     <note>A collection of sermons with a prologue translated from <persName key="person_66899957">Robert of Gretham</persName>’s Anglo-Norman verse <title>Mirror</title> (Paues (1904), pp. xiv–xv; Blumreich (2002); Duncan and Connolly (2003); O’Mara and Paul (2007)). Rubrics in red, most are not filled in after fol. 112r; corrections in a contemporary hand; medieval <q>nota</q> and pointing hands in the margins; Latin notes in the margins (16th century (?)).</note>
                     <incipit type="preface">Many men hyt ben þat inwysse to heren</incipit>
                     <incipit type="text"><q>Cum appropinquasset Iesus Iherosolimam …</q> Ihesus cam ner a cyte</incipit>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="2">
                     <locus>(fols. 133r–162va)</locus>
                     <title key="work_10850" type="desc">Middle English translation of the General and Pauline epistles</title>
                     <note>(Paues (1904), pp. 18–122; Morey, J. H., <title>Book and verse: a guide to Middle English biblical literature</title> (Urbana: University of Illinois Press, 2000), pp. 346–50) in the following order: 1 Peter, 2 Peter, James, 1 John, 2 John, 3 John, Jude, the epilogue to the Catholic epistles (<q>Suster þus haueþ…</q>), Romans, 1 Corinthians, 2 Corinthians, Galatians, Ephesians, Philippians, Colossians, 1 Thessalonians, 2 Thessalonians, Hebrews, 1 Timothy, 2 Timothy, Titus.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="3">
                     <locus>(fols. 162va–257rb)</locus>
                     <title key="work_12118" type="desc">Four gospels in the Earlier Version of the Wycliffite Bible with usual prologues</title>
                     <note>Only some of the prologues, but not the gospels, have rubrics (e.g., <q>here bygynneþ þe prologe of Ion</q>). The text is complete, but subdivided into readings for the temporal, Sarum sanctoral and commemorations. The beginning of each reading is marked with a rubric in red, specifying the day on which it is appointed to be read; the end of each reading is marked with <q>ende</q> in red. Includes readings for Thomas Hereford <locus>(fol. 218r)</locus> and Bavo of Ghent (220r), non-Sarum saints. Chapter numbers in red as Arabic numerals, usually in the form <q>c<ex>apitulu</ex>m 3ᵐ</q>. Running titles in red on both rectos and versos, consisting of the name of the evangelist or <q>prologus</q>. Added material within the text is underlined in brown ink. Corrections in contemporary hands. Occasionally cross-references to biblical books in the margins in red by the rubricator (e.g., fols. 167r, 170r, 195v). Added glosses in the margins in a medieval hand, e.g., <q>n<ex>ot</ex>a wat crist badde his apostlys</q>
                        <locus>(fol. 168v)</locus>. At the beginning of gospels notes on the number of chapters in each (e.g., <q>luc h<ex>ab</ex>et xxiiij cᵐ</q>), 15th century.</note>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="perg">
                        <support>parchment (of mediocre quality with numerous rough edges and flaws), paper flyleaves</support>
                        <extent>iii (paper) + 257 + iii (paper) leaves, <foreign rend="italic">c.</foreign><dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                              <height>282</height>
                              <width>189</width>
                           </dimensions>; leaves were cropped in rebinding, occasionally causing the loss of text in the margins</extent>
                        <foliation>modern in pencil, i–iii + 1–260; contemporary in ink, in Roman and Arabic numerals, up to fol. 179 (Matthew 23), I–XXVIIII + XXIX + XXX–CIII + 104–179</foliation>
                        <collation><locus>(fols. i–iii)</locus> paper flyleaves | <locus>(fols. 1–256)</locus> I–XXXII (8) | <locus>(fol. 257)</locus> single leaf | <locus>(fols. 258–260)</locus> paper flyleaves. <catchwords>Catchwords survive;</catchwords>
                           <signatures>quire signatures run consecutively a–z, a–i.</signatures>
                           <secFol><q>mirrour makeþ</q>
                              <locus>(fol. 3r)</locus></secFol>
                        </collation>
                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout columns="1" writtenLines="37 45">Leaves occupied by <title>Mirror</title> are ruled in plummet for a single column.</layout>
                        <layout columns="2" writtenLines="37 45">Leaves occupied by epistles and gospels are ruled for two columns. The switch happens on fol. 133v, the second page of the epistles, presumably to avoid having different ruling on facing pages. The written space is similar throughout. Single vertical and double horizontal bounding lines extending the full height and width of page; prickings survive; 37–45 lines per page (varies from quire to quire); written space: <foreign rend="italic">c.</foreign><dimensions type="ruled" unit="mm">
                              <height>145–89</height>
                              <width>123–125</width>
                           </dimensions></layout>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc>
                     <handNote script="textualisNorthern">five scribes: (1) fols. 1r–16v; (2) fols. 17r–25r; (3) fols. 25r–133r; (4) fols. 133r–162v (epistles); (5) fols. 162v–257r (gospels); textura, black and brown ink</handNote>
                  </handDesc>
                  <decoDesc>
                     <decoNote type="colInit">2- to 3-line plain red initials at the beginnings of gospels; similar 1- to 3-line initials at the beginnings of prologues and chapters.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="rubrication">Rubrics in red ink.</decoNote>
                  </decoDesc>
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <binding notAfter="1900" notBefore="1800">
                        <p>Typical Holkham binding of light brown straight-grained morocco over wood boards, 19th century. Gilt and blind decoration round the outer edge of both covers. Four raised bands on spine; gilt decoration on the raised bands and on the panels between the bands. Gilt crest of Thomas William Coke on the front cover. Gilt lettering on spine: ‘THE MYRROUR <lb/> &amp; GOSPELS’ and ‘MS. <lb/> MEMB. 672’. Gilt edges of textblock.</p>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origPlace>
                        <country key="place_7002445">England</country>
                     </origPlace>
                     <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="1425" notBefore="1400">15th century, first quarter</origDate>
                     <p>Dialect survey (gospels): <list>
                           <item>eny(9)/ony(1), iche(2)/eche(7)/ech(1), fijr(8)/fyer(2), lyfe(1)/lyf(1)/lyif(1)/lijf(7), lyic(1)/lijc(5)/liche(4), miche(2)/myche(8), see(1)/seeȝ(1)/saw(3) (sg.), seyen(3)/ sayen(1)/seyne(1) (pl.), self(10), siche(7)/syche(2), þouȝ(3), þoru(8)/þurȝ(1)/ þerwȝ(1)</item>
                           <item>-eþ(6)/-eth(1)/-iþ(3) (pres.ind.3sg.), -en(9)/-yn(1) (pres.ind.pl.), -yng(9)/ing(1) (pres.part.), sche(10) (3sg.fem.pronoun, nom.), þai(1)/þei(9) (3pl. pronoun, nom.), hem(10) (3pl.pronoun, oblique), her(9)/þeire(1) (3pl. pronoun, possessive)</item>
                           <item>According to Hanna (2003, p. 148), the fourth scribe of the <title>Mirror</title>, who copied more than 70 per cent of its text, wrote Type III London English, but with some Type II relics, probably inherited from the exemplar, e.g., <q>hij</q>, <q>-ande</q> in pres. part. (Hanna (2003), pp. 148–9).</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                  </origin>
                  <provenance><persName key="person_1390" role="fmo">John Forest, rector of Ramsden Bellhouse</persName>: <q>Iohannes Forestius rector de Ramseton in Comitatu essex est proprius et indubitatus possessor huius libri 1552</q>
                     <locus>(fol. 7r)</locus>.</provenance>
                  <provenance><persName key="person_27099070" role="fmo">Sir Edward Coke</persName> (1552–1634); see <title>Oxford Dictionary of National Biography</title>: autograph on fol. 1r; item 212 in the catalogue of his books (Hassall (1950), p. 15).</provenance>
                  <provenance><persName key="person_8145335" role="fmo">Thomas William Coke</persName>, first earl of Leicester of Holkham (1754–1842); see <title>Oxford Dictionary of National Biography</title>: name and crest on the book-plate on the upper pastedown; crest on the binding.</provenance>
                  <acquisition>Bodleian Library: acquired from the collection of the Earls of Leicester at <orgName key="org_8">Holkham Hall</orgName>, near Wells, Norfolk. Former shelfmark: Holkham Hall MS. 672.</acquisition>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>Elizabeth Solopova, <title><ref target="https://jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1gn6cmr">Manuscripts of the Wycliffite Bible in the Bodleian and Oxford College Libraries</ref></title>, Exeter Medieval Texts and Studies (Liverpool: Liverpool University Press, 2016), no. 26; with additions from notes by Peter Kidd.</source>
                     </recordHist>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl type="WRAPPER">
                     <listBibl type="PRINT">
                        <bibl>Paues, A. C., <title>A fourteenth century English Biblical version</title> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1904).</bibl>
                        <bibl>Hassall, W. O., <title>A catalogue of the library of Sir Edward Coke</title> (New Haven, Conn. and London: Yale University Press/Oxford University Press, 1950).</bibl>
                        <bibl>Ker, N. R., Piper, A. J., Watson, A. G. and Cunningham, I. C., <title>Medieval manuscripts in British libraries</title>, 5 vols (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1969–2002), vol. 3, p. 420.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Hudson, A. and Spencer, H. L., ‘Old author, new work: the sermons of MS. Longleat 4’, <title>Medium Aevum</title> 53 (1984), pp. 220–38 at p. 237 n. 50.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Hudson, A., ‘Lollardy: the English heresy?’, <title>Lollards and their books</title> (London: Hambledon Press, 1985), pp. 141–63 at p. 141 n. 3.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Spencer, H. L., <title>English preaching in the late Middle Ages</title> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1993), pp. 277, 373 nn. 64, 66, 406 n. 141, 451 n. 88, 468 nn. 97–8, 473 n. 30, 495 n. 41.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Scott, K. L. (gen. ed.), <title>An index of images in English manuscripts from the time of Chaucer to Henry VIII, c.1380–c.1509: the Bodleian Library, Oxford</title>, 3 vols (Turnhout: Harvey Miller Publishers, 2000–02), vol. 2, p. 60 no. 567.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Blumreich, K. M. (ed.), <title>The Middle English <q>Mirror</q>: an edition based on Bodleian Library, MS. Holkham misc. 40</title> (Arizona: Centre for Medieval and Renaissance Studies, 2002).</bibl>
                        <bibl>Duncan, T. G. and Connolly, M. (eds), <title>The Middle English <q>Mirror</q>: sermons from Advent to Sexagesima</title> (Heidelberg: Universitätsverlag Winter, 2003).</bibl>
                        <bibl>Hanna, R., ‘English biblical texts before Lollardy and their fate’, in Somerset, F. and Havens, J. C. (eds), <title>Lollards and their influence in late medieval England</title> (Woodbridge: Boydell, 2003), pp. 141–53.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Hanna, R., <title>London literature, 1300–1380</title> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2005), pp. 16, 28, 41 n. 21, 217 n. 44 and <foreign rend="italic">passim</foreign>, 219 n. 54, 306–7.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Dove, M., <title>The first English Bible: the text and context of the Wycliffite versions</title> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2007), p. 300.</bibl>
                        <bibl>O’Mara, V. and Paul, S. (eds), <title>A repertorium of Middle English prose sermons</title> (Turnhout: Brepols, 2007), pp. 2047–165.</bibl>
                     </listBibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2023-03-24">Add Solopova description.</change>
         <change when="2017-07-01">First online publication.</change>
         <change when="2017-05-25"><persName>James Cummings</persName> Up-converted the markup using <ref target="https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl">https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl</ref></change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>