<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="manuscript_8921">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>MS. Selden Supra 51</title>
            <title type="collection">MSS. Selden Supra</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Description</resp>
               <persName>Elizabeth Solopova</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Revision</resp>
               <persName>Andrew Dunning</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </publisher>
            <idno type="msID">MS_Selden_Supra_51</idno>
            <idno type="collection">Selden_supra</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="MS_Selden_Supra_51" xml:lang="en">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <region type="county">Oxfordshire</region>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <institution>University of Oxford</institution>
                  <repository>Bodleian Library</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">MS. Selden Supra 51</idno>
                  <idno type="ieArk">ark:29072/x0zg64tk013k</idno><idno type="crArk">ark:29072/x0bk128b45bb</idno><altIdentifier type="internal">
                     <idno type="SCN">3439</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents>
                  <textLang mainLang="enm" otherLangs="la">Middle English with Latin</textLang>
                  <msItem>
                     <note>Fols. 1–3 are parchment flyleaves; fol. 3r–v is ruled for two columns (see Provenance).</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="1">
                     <locus from="4r" to="12v">(fols. 4r–12v)</locus>
                     <note>[item 1 occupies quire I]</note>
                     <title type="desc"><foreign rend="italic">Capitula</foreign>-list of New Testament</title>
                     <note>Chapter numbers in red in the margins, sections for each chapter start with blue or red initials. Usual order of the Later Version of the Wycliffite Bible, but Philemon is omitted. The table is the same as in MS. e Mus. 110 (Forshall, J. and Madden, F. (eds), <title>The Holy Bible … in the earliest English versions made from the Latin Vulgate by John Wycliffe and his followers</title>, 4 vols (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1850), vol. 1, p. xlvii). Fol. 13r is ruled for the calendar-lectionary, but blank.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="2">
                     <locus from="13v" to="25r">(fols. 13v–25r)</locus>
                     <note>[items 2–3 occupy quires II–III]</note>
                     <title key="work_10703" type="desc">Sarum calendar-lectionary in English</title>
                     <note>Written in black and red, laid out one month per two-page opening, approximately one-third full. Identical to the calendar of MS. Selden Supra 49, apart from the presence of Vincent of Saragossa (22 January) and some vigils absent in MS. Selden Supra 49. Included Botulph (17 June); does not include David, Chad or other saints promulgated after 1415 under Archbishop Chichele (Pfaff, R. W., <title>The liturgy in medieval England: a history</title> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2009), pp. 438–41). At the bottom of the second page for February are the dominical letters followed by <q>þus lettris failen in leep ȝeris</q>; at the bottom of the page for April is a note on determining the date of Easter in English, incomplete, possibly cropped off. Easter is called <q>Aȝenrising of oure lord</q> in both Selden Supra 49 and 51. The feast of Thomas Becket, his translation and titles ‘pope’ are erased. Entries for readings consist of a reference to a book and chapter of the Bible, an indexing letter in red, the opening words of a reading, <q>ende</q> in red, the closing words of a reading and double strokes in red. Entries for Old Testament readings are also accompanied by letters and numbers in the margins in red, used to identify readings in the Old Testament lectionary (see below and MS. Ashmole 1517).</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="3">
                     <locus from="25v" to="32v">(fols. 25v–32v)</locus>
                     <title type="desc">Table of lections</title>
                     <rubric>Here bigynneþ a reule þat telliþ in whiche chapitris of þe bible a man may fynde þe lessouns pistlis and gospels þat red in holy chirche at masse þoruȝ al þe ȝeer after þe vss of salisbiry markid wiþ lettris bi þe ordre as þei stonden in þe abc bigynnynge at þe firste sonday in aduent</rubric>
                     <note>Includes the temporal and commemorations only. The entries consist of a liturgical occasion in red, abbreviated reference to a book and chapter of the Bible, an indexing letter in red, the opening words of a reading, <q>ende</q> in red, the closing words of a reading and double strokes in red. Entries for Old Testament readings are also accompanied by letters and numbers in the margins in red, used to identify the readings in the Old Testament lectionary. Commemorations are in the following order: Our Lady, cross, Trinity, Holy Ghost, angels, <foreign rend="italic">salus populi</foreign>, brothers and sisters, peace, clear weather, rain, in time of battles, <q>a man for hym silf</q>, pestilence of beasts, pilgrims, weddings, sinners, sick and dead. Running titles with names of liturgical seasons.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="4">
                     <locus from="33r" to="283r">(fols. 33r–283r)</locus>
                     <note>[item 4 occupies quires IV–XXXIV and fol. 283]</note>
                     <title key="work_13437" type="desc">New Testament in the Later Version of the Wycliffite Bible</title>
                     <note>With usual prologues, usual rubrics in red or underlined in red, and chapter numbers in red as words or Roman numerals. Blue paraphs at the start of sections within the text. Running titles in red on both rectos and versos consisting of abbreviated titles of books and chapter numbers. Indexing letters set between double bounding lines in the margins entered at the start of lections rather than consistently; double strokes at the ends of lections. Corrections in the original or contemporary hands, occasionally text crossed out in red. Added material within the text is underlined in red; a few glosses in the margins (particularly on fols. 237r–240v).</note>
                     <note>The Apocalypse ends half-way through the first column on fol. 283r and fol. 283v is blank.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="5">
                     <locus from="284r" to="326v">(fols. 284r–326v)</locus>
                     <note>[item 5 occupies quires XXXV–XL]</note>
                     <title type="desc">Old Testament lectionary of Type II</title>
                     <note>The readings are preceded by rubrics in red, introductory statements (e.g., <q>The lord god of oostis seiþ þes þingis</q>, fol. 284v) underlined in red, and letters and numbers that identify each reading. The letters subdivide the lectionary into five parts, A–E, and in addition each reading is given a number, e.g., a1, a2, a3, etc. The same letters and numbers are used as part of references to Old Testament readings in the calendar-lectionary and the table of lections (a similar system is used to identify readings in the Old Testament lectionary in MS. Ashmole 1517). Added material within the text is occasionally underlined in red. Includes the readings for the temporal, commemorations, the proper and common. The common ends imperfectly because of the loss of leaves, but the final reading is completed in the lower margin of fol. 326v in a different contemporary hand.</note>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="perg">
                        <support>parchment</support>
                        <extent><measure type="leaf" quantity="325">325</measure> leaves, <foreign rend="italic">c.</foreign><dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                              <height>146</height>
                              <width>208</width>
                           </dimensions></extent>
                        <foliation>modern in pencil: 1–127 + 129–326</foliation>
                        <collation><locus from="1" to="2">(fols. 1–2)</locus> parchment flyleaves | <locus from="3" to="12">(fols. 3–12)</locus> I (10) | <locus from="13" to="20">(fols. 13–20)</locus> II (8) | <locus from="21" to="32">(fols. 21–32)</locus> III (12) | <locus from="33" to="272">(fols. 33–272)</locus> IV–XXXIII (8) | <locus from="273" to="282">(fols. 273–282)</locus> XXXIV (10) | <locus from="283" to="283">(fol. 283)</locus> singleton | <locus from="284" to="315">(fols. 284–315)</locus> XXXV–XXXVIII (8) | <locus from="316" to="325">(fols. 316–325)</locus> XXXIX (10) | <locus from="326" to="326">(fol. 326)</locus> XL (first leaf of a quire (?), followed by four stubs). <signatures>Quire signatures partially survive; a new series starts on fol. 284 at the beginning of Old Testament lectionary.</signatures>
                           <secFol><q>tewisday mt xxi</q> (table of lections, fol. 10r); <q>marie þe modir</q> (gospel, fol. 17r)</secFol>
                        </collation>
                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout columns="2" writtenLines="33 34">ruled for two columns with single vertical and triple horizontal bounding lines extending the full height and width of page; a second set of double bounding lines in the upper, lower and outer margins, used as the ruling for running titles and indexing letters; 33–4 lines per page; prickings survive; written space: <foreign rend="italic">c.</foreign><dimensions type="ruled" unit="mm">
                              <height>90</height>
                              <width>135</width>
                           </dimensions></layout>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc>
                     <handNote script="textualisNorthern">informal textura, black and brown ink; the work of several scribes</handNote>
                  </handDesc>
                  <decoDesc>
                     <decoNote type="decInit">4- to 8-line gold initials on blue and pink background at the beginnings of New Testament books and the Old Testament lectionary; the initial at the beginning of Matthew is decorated with sprays of leaves and gold disks.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="flourInit">4-line penwork initials at the beginnings of 2 John–Jude.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="flourInit">3-line gold initial on blue and pink background at the beginning of the prologue to Matthew; 3-line blue initials with red penwork at the beginnings of other prologues.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="flourInit">3- to 4-line blue initials with red penwork at the beginnings of chapters and readings in the Old Testament lectionary.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="rubrication">Rubrics in red; blue paraphs.</decoNote>
                  </decoDesc>
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <binding contemporary="true">
                        <p>Contemporary English binding; worn plain red leather over wood boards. Five raised bands on spine. Holes left by the fittings of two clasps on the upper cover and by two pins on the lower cover, all now lost. Paper label on spine with handwritten ‘3439’.</p>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origPlace>
                        <country key="place_7002445">England</country>
                     </origPlace>
                     <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="1415" notBefore="1400">15th century, first quarter, before 1415 (?)</origDate>
                     <p>The calendar is similar to MS. Selden Supra 49.</p>
                     <p>Dialect survey: <list>
                           <item>any(10), ech(10), fyr(3)/fijr(7), gouun(9)/ȝouen(1), lijf(6)/lyf(3)/lif(1), lijk(10), myche(10), siȝ(7) (sg.), sien(1)/syen(1)/saien(2)/siȝen(1) (pl.), silf(10), sich(2)/ siche(7), þouȝ(7), þoruȝ(9)/þorou(1)</item>
                           <item>-iþ(7)/-eþ(3) (pres.ind.3sg.), -en(10) (pres.ind.pl.), -inge(9)/-ynge(1) (pres. part.), sche(10) (3sg.fem.pronoun, nom.), þei(10) (3pl.pronoun, nom.), hem(10) (3pl.pronoun, oblique), her(10) (3pl.pronoun, possessive)</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                  </origin>
                  <provenance><q>super honorem deo pathr noster quy us…</q>
                     <locus from="2r" to="2r">(fol. 2r)</locus>; <q>John</q>
                     <locus>(fols. 2r, 3r)</locus>, <q>Ihus</q> in a square frame <locus from="128v" to="128v">(fol. 128v)</locus>; <q><persName role="fmo">Thomas Lucas</persName></q>
                     <locus from="195v" to="195v">(fol. 195v)</locus>; <q>Thomas</q>, <q><persName role="fmo">John Robynes</persName> boke as longe as he lewe ande after hym gorge ys</q>
                     <locus from="218r" to="218r">(fol. 218r)</locus>, in several hands, all 16th century.</provenance>
                  <provenance>The feasts of <persName key="person_100187947">Thomas Becket</persName> and titles ‘pope’ are erased in the calendar-lectionary, presumably at Reformation.</provenance>
                  <provenance notAfter="1654"><persName key="person_51728429" role="fmo">John Selden</persName>, 1584–1654.</provenance>
                  <acquisition>Bodleian Library. Earlier shelfmark: ‘15’, fol. 1r.</acquisition>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>Elizabeth Solopova, <title><ref target="https://jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1gn6cmr">Manuscripts of the Wycliffite Bible in the Bodleian and Oxford College Libraries</ref></title>, Exeter Medieval Texts and Studies (Liverpool: Liverpool University Press, 2016), no. 46. Previously described: <listBibl>
                              <bibl facs="aap0655.gif" type="SC">Summary Catalogue, Vol. 2 Part 1, p. 634</bibl>
                           </listBibl>
                        </source>
                     </recordHist>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl type="WRAPPER">
                     <listBibl type="PRINT">
                        <bibl>Forshall, J. and Madden, F. (eds), <title>The Holy Bible … in the earliest English versions made from the Latin Vulgate by John Wycliffe and his followers</title>, 4 vols (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1850), vol. 1, p. xlviii.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Madan, F. and Craster, H. H. E., <title>Summary catalogue of western manuscripts in the Bodleian Library at Oxford</title>, vol. 2, part I <title>(collections received before 1660 and miscellaneous MSS acquired during the first half of the 17th century), nos. 1–3490</title> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1922), no. 3437.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Hudson, A., ‘Lollard book production’, in Griffiths, J. and Pearsall, D. A. (eds), <title>Book production and publishing in Britain 1375–1475</title> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1989), pp. 125–42, p. 140.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Scott, K. L. (gen. ed.), <title>An index of images in English manuscripts from the time of Chaucer to Henry VIII, c.1380–c.1509: the Bodleian Library, Oxford</title>, 3 vols (Turnhout: Harvey Miller Publishers, 2000–02), vol. 3, p. 76, no. 1015.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Dove, M., <title>The first English Bible: the text and context of the Wycliffite versions</title> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2007), pp. 59 n. 116, 301.</bibl>
                     </listBibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2023-03-24">Add Solopova description.</change>
         <change when="2022-04-04">Add binding information from Summary Catalogue.</change>
         <change when="2019-10-31" xml:id="MMM">
            <persName>Toby Burrows/Mapping Manuscript Migrations</persName>Provenance and acquisition information added using <ref target="https://github.com/mapping-manuscript-migrations/oxford-tei-updates/blob/master/update_oxford_prov.rb">https://github.com/mapping-manuscript-migrations/oxford-tei-updates/blob/master/update_oxford_prov.rb</ref> in collaboration with the <ref target="http://mappingmanuscriptmigrations.org/">Mapping Manuscript Migrations</ref> project.</change>
         <change when="2017-07-01">First online publication.</change>
         <change when="2017-05-25">
            <persName>James Cummings</persName> Up-converted the markup using <ref target="https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl">https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl</ref>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>