<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="manuscript_8919">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>MS. Selden Supra 49</title>
            <title type="collection">MSS. Selden Supra</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Description</resp>
               <persName>Elizabeth Solopova</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Revision</resp>
               <persName>Andrew Dunning</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </publisher>
            <idno type="msID">MS_Selden_Supra_49</idno>
            <idno type="collection">Selden_supra</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="MS_Selden_Supra_49" xml:lang="en">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <region type="county">Oxfordshire</region>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <institution>University of Oxford</institution>
                  <repository>Bodleian Library</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">MS. Selden Supra 49</idno>
                  <idno type="ieArk">ark:29072/x0pg15bd52zq</idno>
                  <idno type="crArk">ark:29072/x0bc386j78qd</idno>
                  <altIdentifier type="internal">
                     <idno type="SCN">3437</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents>
                  <textLang mainLang="enm" otherLangs="la">Middle English with Latin</textLang>
                  <msItem>
                     <note>Fol. i is ruled for two columns, but originally blank (see Provenance).</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="1">
                     <locus from="2r" to="7v">(fols. 2r–7v)</locus>
                     <note>[item 1 occupies quire I]</note>
                     <title key="work_10703" type="desc">Sarum calendar</title>
                     <note>Laid out one month per page, written in black and red, in English, not graded, approximately one-third full, nearly identical to the calendar of MS. Selden Supra 51. Included Botulph (17 June); does not include David, Chad or other saints whose feasts were promulgated after 1415 under Archbishop Chichele (Pfaff, R. W., <title>The liturgy in medieval England: a history</title> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2009), pp. 438–41). At the bottom of the page for February is a list of dominical letters, followed by <q>þus lettris fallen in þe lepe ȝeeris</q>; at the bottom of the page for April is a note in English on determining the date of Easter. Easter is called <q>Aȝenrisyng of oure lord</q> in both Selden Supra 49 and 51. The feast and octave of Thomas Becket, most titles ‘pope’ and ‘abbot’ are erased.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem>
                     <note>Fol. 8r–v is ruled for the table of lections, but blank.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="2">
                     <locus from="9r" to="15r">(fols. 9r–15r)</locus>
                     <note>[item 2 occupies quire II]</note>
                     <title type="desc">Table of lections of Type I</title>
                     <rubric>Here bigynneþ a rule þat telliþ in whiche chapiters of þe foure euangelistis ȝe may fynde þe gospels þat ben rad in þe chirche aftir þe vse of salisbirie markid wiþ lettris of þe abc ffirst ben sett sonedaies &amp; ferials togidere and after þe sanctorum comyn &amp; propre togidere of al þe ȝeer ffirst is writun a clause of þe bigynnynge þerof &amp; a clause of þe ending þerof also</rubric>
                     <note>Includes the temporal, followed by commemorations and the sanctoral, all containing readings from gospels only. Includes all feasts characteristic of the Later Version of the Wycliffite Bible, apart from Giles (1 September) (Forshall, J. and Madden, F. (eds), <title>The Holy Bible … in the earliest English versions made from the Latin Vulgate by John Wycliffe and his followers</title>, 4 vols (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1850), vol. 4, pp. 683, 690–6). The entries consist of a liturgical occasion in red, abbreviated reference to a book and chapter of the Bible, an indexing letter in black, the opening words of a reading, <q>ende</q> in red, the closing words of a reading and double strokes in red. Larger initials or blue paraphs at Conception of Our Lady, Candlemas, Matthew, Annunciation, Mark, Nativity of John the Baptist, Peter and Paul, Mary Magdalene, Lammas, Lawrence, Assumption, Nativity of Our Lady, Holy Rood, Luke and All Saints. Commemorations are in the following order: Our Lady, Trinity, Holy Ghost, cross, angels, brothers and sisters, <foreign rend="italic">salus populi</foreign>, peace, clear weather, rain, in time of battles, <q>a man for him silf</q>, pestilence of beasts, pilgrims, weddings, sinners, sick and dead. At the end <q>Thus eendiþ þis kalender of þe foure gospelers</q>. Fol. 15v is blank, apart from an early modern ownership inscription (see Provenance).</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="3">
                     <locus from="16r" to="149r">(fols. 16r–149r)</locus>
                     <note>[item 3 occupies quires III–XIX]</note>
                     <title key="work_12092" type="desc">Four gospels in the Later Version of the Wycliffite Bible</title>
                     <note>With usual prologues, usual rubrics and chapter numbers in red as words or Roman numerals. Blue paraphs at the start of sections within the text. Running titles in red on both rectos and versos, consisting of the titles of gospels only, preceded by blue paraphs. Indexing letters in the margins entered at the start of lections, rather than consistently; double strokes at the ends of lections. Many corrections in the original or contemporary hands; cross-references to biblical books occasionally in the margins. Many medieval <q>nota</q> in the margins throughout.</note>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="perg">
                        <support>parchment</support>
                        <extent><measure type="leaf" quantity="150">150</measure> leaves, <foreign rend="italic">c.</foreign><dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                              <height>101</height>
                              <width>145</width>
                           </dimensions></extent>
                        <foliation>modern in pencil: 1–150</foliation>
                        <collation><locus from="1" to="1">(fol. 1)</locus> parchment flyleaf | <locus from="2" to="7">(fols. 2–7)</locus> I (6) | <locus from="8" to="150">(fols. 8–150)</locus> II–XIX (8). <catchwords>Catchwords survive;</catchwords>
                           <signatures>some quire signatures survive, particularly at the beginning where they run consecutively starting with ‘a’.</signatures>
                           <secFol><q>tewisday mt xxi</q> (table of lections, fol. 10r); <q>marie þe modir</q> (gospel, fol. 17r)</secFol>
                        </collation>
                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout columns="2" writtenLines="31">ruled for two columns with single vertical and double horizontal bounding lines extending the full height and width of page; 31 lines per page; written space: <foreign rend="italic">c.</foreign><dimensions type="ruled" unit="mm">
                              <height>71</height>
                              <width>105</width>
                           </dimensions></layout>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc>
                     <handNote script="textualisNorthern">textura, black ink; the work of at least two scribes: (1) fols. 16r–31v; (2) fols. 32r–149r; the second scribe may have been also responsible for the calendar and the table of lections</handNote>
                  </handDesc>
                  <decoDesc>
                     <decoNote type="decInit">5- to 6-line initials on gold background, and 3-sided borders made of gold, blue and pink bars, decorated with foliage.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="flourInit">2-line blue initials with red penwork at the beginnings of prologues and chapters.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="rubrication">Rubrics in red; blue paraphs.</decoNote>
                  </decoDesc>
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <binding notAfter="1600" notBefore="1500">
                        <p>English, 16th century, brown leather over pasteboard. Rectangular figure at the centre of both covers, made of blind floral and geometric decoration, framed with blind fillet lines. Inside the rectangular figure is a rosette surmounted by a crown and stamped initials ‘T S’ (Thomas Stanley, see Provenance). Four raised bands on spine. Fragment of a paper label at the top of spine. Fragments of two ties, now lost. ‘49’ written in ink on the edge of textblock.</p>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origPlace>
                        <country key="place_7002445">England</country>
                     </origPlace>
                     <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="1415" notBefore="1400">15th century, first quarter, before 1415 (?)</origDate>
                     <p>The calendar is similar to MS. Selden Supra 51.</p>
                     <p>Dialect survey: <list>
                           <item>ony(10), ech(4)/eche(6), fier(10), gouun(9)/ȝouen(1), lijf(3)/lyf(7), lijk(3)/ lyk(7), myche(10), saiȝ(1)/siȝ(4)/sai(1)/saw(1) (sg.), saien(2)/sawen(4) (pl.), silf(10), sich(2)/siche(7), þouȝ(8), þourȝ(1)/þoru(9)</item>
                           <item>-iþ(7)/-eþ(3) (pres.ind.3sg.), -en(10) (pres.ind.pl.), -inge(4)/-ynge(5)/-yng(1) (pres.part.), sche(10) (3sg.fem.pronoun, nom.), þei(10) (3pl.pronoun, nom.), hem(10) (3pl.pronoun, oblique), her(10) (3pl.pronoun, possessive)</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                  </origin>
                  <provenance><q>Codex <persName role="fmo" key="person_3913">thome stanley de Grays Inne</persName></q>, 16th century <locus>(fol. 1v; see also fols. 2r, 15v, 16r, 74r, 149r)</locus>.</provenance>
                  <provenance>A fragment of an account of <q>Holborne Empcions</q>, i.e., purchases in <placeName key="place_1004682">Holborn</placeName> (?) (Madan, F. and Craster, H. H. E., <title>Summary catalogue of western manuscripts in the Bodleian Library at Oxford</title>, vol. 2, part I <title>(collections received before 1660 and miscellaneous MSS acquired during the first half of the 17th century), nos. 1–3490</title> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1922), no. 3437), for <q>Die Sab’[…]</q>, used as a pastedown for the binding. Contains various food items.</provenance>
                  <provenance>Feasts of <persName key="person_100187947">Thomas Becket</persName> and most titles ‘pope’ and ‘abbot’ are erased, presumably at Reformation.</provenance>
                  <provenance notAfter="1654"><persName key="person_51728429" role="fmo">John Selden</persName>, 1584–1654.</provenance>
                  <acquisition>Bodleian Library. Earlier shelfmarks: ‘19’, ‘A 9’ <locus from="1r" to="1r">(fol. 1r)</locus>.</acquisition>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>Elizabeth Solopova, <title>
                              <ref target="https://jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1gn6cmr">Manuscripts of the Wycliffite Bible in the Bodleian and Oxford College Libraries</ref>
                           </title>, Exeter Medieval Texts and Studies (Liverpool: Liverpool University Press, 2016), no. 45. Previously described: <listBibl>
                              <bibl facs="aap0655.gif" type="SC">Summary Catalogue, Vol. 2 Part 1, p. 634</bibl>
                           </listBibl>
                        </source>
                     </recordHist>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl type="WRAPPER">
                     <listBibl type="PRINT">
                        <bibl>Forshall, J. and Madden, F. (eds), <title>The Holy Bible … in the earliest English versions made from the Latin Vulgate by John Wycliffe and his followers</title>, 4 vols (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1850), vol. 1, p. xlviii.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Madan, F. and Craster, H. H. E., <title>Summary catalogue of western manuscripts in the Bodleian Library at Oxford</title>, vol. 2, part I <title>(collections received before 1660 and miscellaneous MSS acquired during the first half of the 17th century), nos. 1–3490</title> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1922), no. 3437.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Hudson, A., ‘Lollard book production’, in Griffiths, J. and Pearsall, D. A. (eds), <title>Book production and publishing in Britain 1375–1475</title> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1989), pp. 125–42, p. 140.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Scott, K. L. (gen. ed.), <title>An index of images in English manuscripts from the time of Chaucer to Henry VIII, c.1380–c.1509: the Bodleian Library, Oxford</title>, 3 vols (Turnhout: Harvey Miller Publishers, 2000–02), vol. 3, p. 76, no. 1014.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Dove, M., <title>The first English Bible: the text and context of the Wycliffite versions</title> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2007), pp. 59 n. 116, 301.</bibl>
                     </listBibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2023-03-24">Add Solopova description.</change>
         <change when="2022-04-04">Add binding information from Summary Catalogue.</change>
         <change when="2019-10-31" xml:id="MMM">
            <persName>Toby Burrows/Mapping Manuscript Migrations</persName>Provenance and acquisition information added using <ref target="https://github.com/mapping-manuscript-migrations/oxford-tei-updates/blob/master/update_oxford_prov.rb">https://github.com/mapping-manuscript-migrations/oxford-tei-updates/blob/master/update_oxford_prov.rb</ref> in collaboration with the <ref target="http://mappingmanuscriptmigrations.org/">Mapping Manuscript Migrations</ref> project.</change>
         <change when="2017-07-01">First online publication.</change>
         <change when="2017-05-25">
            <persName>James Cummings</persName> Up-converted the markup using <ref target="https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl">https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl</ref>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
