<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="manuscript_6440">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>MS. Lat. liturg. a. 2</title>
            <title type="collection">MSS. Lat. liturg. (Latin liturgical)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp when="2013">Cataloguer</resp>
               <persName>Elizabeth Solopova</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp when="2024">Encoding</resp>
               <persName>Matthew Holford</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </publisher>
            <idno type="msID">MS_Lat_liturg_a_2</idno>
            <idno type="collection">Lat liturg</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="MS_Lat_liturg_a_2" xml:lang="en">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <region type="county">Oxfordshire</region>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <institution>University of Oxford</institution>
                  <repository>Bodleian Library</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">MS. Lat. liturg. a. 2</idno>
                  <idno type="ieArk">ark:29072/x0fb494814j4</idno>
                  <idno type="crArk">ark:29072/x0pg15bd75zc</idno>
                  <altIdentifier type="internal">
                     <idno type="SCN">30554</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
               <head>Ferial Choir Psalter with Antiphons, Dominican Use (companion volume to MS.
                  Lat. liturg. a. 3); Italy, Brescia or Padua (?), 15th century, third
                  quarter</head>
               <msContents>
                  <msItem class="#liturgica #biblia" n="1" xml:id="MS_Lat_liturg_a_2-item1">
                     <title key="work_14098" type="desc">Ferial Choir Psalter with Antiphons,
                        Dominican Use</title>
                     <note>Companion volume to MS. Lat. liturg. a. 3.</note>
                     <note>[item 1 occupies quire I] </note>
                     <msItem n="1">
                        <note> (fols. ii verso–3v) Probably original parchment fly-leaves, filled
                           with liturgical texts, some with music (square notation on staves of four
                           red lines), in several different hands, added soon after the manuscript
                           was made. The texts include psalm 5 (Uerba mea auribus percipe ...’)
                           (fols. 1v–2v), hymn Hec dies quam fecit dominus ... (Chevalier, no. 7585)
                           with music (fol. 3r), invitatoria with rubrics (fol. 3v), possibly the
                           earliest addition. 17th-century corrections in the margins. Fol. i is a
                           blank paper fly-leaf; fol. ii recto is blank. </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <note>[item 2 occupies quires II–XIV]</note>
                     <msItem n="2">
                        <locus>(fols. 4r–119v)</locus>
                        <note> Psalms in the order Sunday Matins, Sunday Lauds, Little Hours,
                           Vespers on Sunday and during the week, and Compline in secular use, laid
                           out with each verse starting on a new line, some with titles ‘psalmus’ or
                           ‘psalmus dauid’, without numbers. Punctuated throughout with punctus
                           flexus used to mark minor pauses, colon used to mark metrum, and punctus
                           used to mark the ends of verses. The verses with punctus flexus are
                           identified with a special sign in the margins, sometimes decorated with
                           penwork human profiles (cf. MS. Lat. liturg. a. 3). The psalms are
                           accompanied by antiphons, versicles and invitatoria with rubrics and
                           music (square notation on staves of four red lines). Subdivisions within
                           psalms are not indicated, apart from psalm 118, subdivided into eleven
                           16-verse units. The text contains corrections in contemporary and later
                           hands. Psalm 109 (Vespers) starts on a new quire. The scribe ran out of
                           space on the preceding quire and completed the sequence for None, which
                           comes immediately before Vespers, on an added bifolium. Most of the
                           second leaf (fol. 75) of the bifolium was originally left blank, but in
                           the 16th century the verso was filled with Regina celi (see below).
                           Psalms, canticles and creeds are in the following order: <list>
                              <head>Sunday Matins (fol. 4v)</head>
                              <item> 1, 2 (imperfect), 3 (imperfect), 6–20; Psalms 2: 8–3: 8 are
                                 missing because of the loss of a leaf after fol. 5</item>
                           </list><list>
                              <head> Sunday Lauds (fol. 37r)</head>
                              <item> 92, 99, 62, 66</item>
                              <item> Benedicite omnia opera (fol. 39v)</item>
                              <item> 148–150</item>
                              <item> Benedictus dominus deus (fol. 44r)</item>
                           </list><list>
                              <head> Prime (fol. 45v)</head>
                              <item> 21 (imperfect), 23 (imperfect), 24–25, 53, 117, 118: 1, 118:
                                 17</item>
                              <item>Psalms 21: 27–32 and 23: 1–8 are missing because of the loss of
                                 a bifolium after fol. 47. Presumably the missing leaves also
                                 contained Psalm 22 as part of the sequence for Sunday Prime</item>
                              <item> Athanasian Creed (Quicumque uult ... ) (fol. 57v)</item>
                           </list><list>
                              <head> Terce (fol. 61r)</head>
                              <item> 118: 33, 118: 49, 118: 65</item>
                           </list><list>
                              <head> Sext (fol. 66v)</head>
                              <item> 118: 81, 118: 97, 118: 113</item>
                           </list><list>
                              <head> None (fol. 71r)</head>
                              <item> 118: 129, 118: 145, 118: 161</item>
                              <item> Regina celi with music added in a 16th-century Italian hand on
                                 fol. 75v, originally left blank</item>
                           </list><list>
                              <head> Sunday Vespers (fol. 76r)</head>
                              <item> 109–113</item>
                           </list><list>
                              <head> Monday Vespers (fol. 82v)</head>
                              <item> 114–116, 119–120</item>
                           </list><list>
                              <head> Tuesday Vespers (fol. 86v)</head>
                              <item> 121–125</item>
                           </list><list>
                              <head> Wednesday Vespers (fol. 90v)</head>
                              <item> 126–130</item>
                           </list><list>
                              <head> Thursday Vespers (fol. 95r)</head>
                              <item> 131–132, 134–136</item>
                           </list><list>
                              <head> Friday Vespers (fol. 102r)</head>
                              <item> 137–141</item>
                           </list><list>
                              <head> Saturday Vespers (fol. 109r)</head>
                              <item> 143–147</item>
                              <item> Magnificat (fol. 115v)</item>
                           </list><list>
                              <head> Compline (fol. 116v)</head>
                              <item> 4, 30, 90, 133</item>
                           </list> Psalms at the beginning of sections for different Canonical Hours
                           start with historiated initials (see ‘Decoration’). Psalm 109 starts with
                           a larger historiated initial and a historiated border. Some liturgical
                           divisions are marked with parchment bookmarks. MS. Lat. liturg. a 2 is a
                           companion volume to MS. Lat. liturg. a 3, which contains the rest of the
                           ferial psalter. </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <note>[item 3 occupies quire XV] </note>
                     <msItem n="3">
                        <locus>(fols. 120r–121r)</locus>
                        <note> 17th-century additions on paper, comprising versicles, responses and
                           invitatoria with rubrics and music (square notation on staves of four red
                           lines). Fol. 121v is ruled for music but otherwise blank. [item 4 is on
                           an added paper leaf] </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="4">
                        <locus>(fol. 122r–v)</locus>
                        <note> Parchment fly-leaf with a paper leaf pasted to the recto. The paper
                           leaf contains ‘Hec dies quam fecit dominus ...’ with music, added in a
                           17th-century hand. Fol. 122v is blank; fol. 123 is a paper fly-leaf,
                           blank apart from modern notes. </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <p><secFol> diem tentationis <locus>(invitatoria, fol. 1r)</locus></secFol></p>
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="perg">
                        <support> Parchment; paper fly-leaves. Many leaves are mutilated (usually
                           the margins are cut off, without the loss of text) and repaired with
                           pieces of paper or parchment, presumably when the manuscript was rebound
                           in the 17th century. The strips of parchment are also used to strengthen
                           quires. Many pieces of parchment have text (not always clearly visible)
                           and come from medieval Italian manuscripts, including the following:
                           (fol. 52) fragment of a 14th-century Italian manuscript with text on both
                           sides; on the verso is <persName role="aut" key="person_78769600"
                              >Cicero</persName>, <title key="work_1251">Tusculan
                              Disputations</title>, Book III, around sections XXIX–XXX (73–74) (cf.
                           MS. Lat. liturg. a. 3); (fols. 62v, 76v, 80r, 83r–v) offsets from a
                           15th-century document in an Italian cursive script which was pasted with
                           text downwards and is now gone apart from small fragments; (fols. 76r and
                           85r) 15th-century fragment in Latin; (fols. 117r, 118r) 13th-century
                           fragment in Latin, in a small Gothic book hand.</support>
                        <extent> 122 leaves <dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                              <height quantity="535">c. 535</height>
                              <width>385</width>
                           </dimensions><note>Leaves were trimmed in rebinding, occasionally causing
                              the loss of decoration; 17th-century folio numbers were also
                              occasionally lost.</note>
                        </extent>
                        <foliation> 17th-century foliation in ink, some trimmed off; modern
                           foliation on flyleaves, and modern restorations and corrections to the
                           17th-century foliation in pencil, ink and purple crayon; i–ii + 1–6/7 +
                           8–48/50 + 51–123.</foliation>
                        <collation> (fols. i–ii) fol. i is a paper fly-leaf, conjoint with the upper
                           pastedown (?); a modern paper bifolium (smaller size, unnumbered) is
                           pasted to fol. i recto; fol. ii is a parchment leaf with a laid paper
                           leaf pasted to its recto | (fols. 1–3) I (4−1 (?)) missing 1 (?) | (fols.
                           4–13) II (10−1) missing 3 | (fols. 14–43) III–V (10) | (fols. 44–53) VI
                           (10−2) missing 5 and 6 | (fols. 54–73) VII–VIII (10) | (fols. 74–75) IX
                           (2) | (fols. 76–115) X–XIII (10) | (fols. 116–119) XIV (4) | (fols.
                           120–121) XV (2) added paper leaves | (fols. 122–123) fol. 122 is a
                           parchment fly-leaf with a paper leaf pasted to its recto; fol. 123 is a
                           paper fly-leaf, conjoint with the upper pastedown (?). Fols. 6, 48 and 49
                           were lost after the manuscript was foliated in ink in the 17th century,
                           as indicated by irregularities in foliation. Catchwords
                           survive</collation>




                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout rulingMedium="ink" columns="1" writtenLines="17">Ruled in ink with
                           single vertical bounding lines extending the full height of page; 17
                           lines per page; written below the top line; written space: <dimensions
                              type="written" unit="mm">
                              <height quantity="380">c. 380</height>
                              <width>245</width>
                           </dimensions></layout>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc>
                     <handNote script="textualisSouthern" execution="formata">Large formal Gothic
                        book hand; black ink (often flaking); antiphons, versicles, invitatoria,
                        etc. without music and some rubrics are in a smaller script.</handNote>
                  </handDesc>
                  <musicNotation>
                     <p>Square notation on staves of four red lines.</p>
                  </musicNotation>
                  <decoDesc>
                     <!-- <summary>Attributed to the  (<ref
                           target="https://catalog.hathitrust.org/Record/000468709">Pächt and
                           Alexander</ref> ii. 682, pl. LXV):</summary>
                     <decoNote type="border">Fine historiated and other borders.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="histInit">Fine historiated initials. </decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="decInit">Fine other initials. </decoNote>-->


                     <summary>The illumination is by an artist known as the <persName
                           key="person_26856190" role="art">Maestro del Messale Barbo</persName>
                        (Bollati, 2004), named after Padua, Biblioteca del Seminario MS. 355, missal
                        with the arms of Barbo. This artist’s work is found in other Bodleian
                        manuscripts produced in Brescia or Padua in the third quarter of the 15th
                        century, including MS. Canon. Liturg. 328, MS. Douce 272, MS. Canon. Misc.
                        382 and MS. Lat. liturg. a. 3.</summary>
                     <decoNote type="histInit">Historiated initials on gold background, decorated
                        with foliage, flowers and scrolls, and borders, some historiated, most
                        formed by sprays of foliage, flowers and gold discs, at liturgical
                        divisions. <list>
                           <item>fol. 4v, Psalm 1 (initial B(eatus)), 12-line initial with King David,
                              kneeling in prayer, his psaltery lying on a rock beside him, looking
                              up at half-figure of God, holding an orb and blessing; landscape with
                              a town in the background.</item>
                           <item>(full border) Coiled tendrils, flowers, fruit and foliage on gold
                              and white background, Annunciation in the upper margin with a kneeling
                              angel (upper left corner), white dove and the Virgin Mary (upper right
                              corner); bishop (St Ubaldus (?), bishop of Gubbio, Umbria) holding
                              crosier and blessing, surrounded by six kneeling Dominicans in the
                              lower margin; St Catherine of Alexandria with a crown and wheel (lower
                              left corner) and another female saint, crowned with a wreath by an
                              angel (lower right corner); winged putto in the left margin.</item>
                           <item>fol. 37r, Psalm 92 (initial D(ominus)), 4-line initial with King
                              David, kneeling in prayer, looking up at rays of light; landscape in
                              the background.</item>
                           <item> fol. 45v, Psalm 21 (initial D(eus)), 4-line initial with a bearded
                              saint in a Dominican habit, seated, holding an open book; landscape in
                              the background.</item>
                           <item>fol. 61r, Psalm 118: 33 (initial L(egem)), 5-line initial with King
                              David, kneeling in prayer, looking up at rays of light, his crown next
                              to him on the ground; landscape in the background.</item>
                           <item>fol. 66v, Psalm 118: 81 (initial D(efecit)), 5-line initial with King
                              David, kneeling in prayer, looking up at rays of light; landscape in
                              the background.</item>
                           <item>fol. 71r, Psalm 118: 129 (initial M(irabilia)), 5-line initial with a
                              seated bishop-saint (St Ubaldus (?)), in prayer, with crosier and an
                              open book; landscape in the background.</item>
                           <item>fol. 76r, Psalm 109 (initial D(ixit)), 6-line initial with the
                              Trinity: God-the-Father with a triangular nimbus, seated, holding an
                              orb and blessing; Christ seated, pointing to a wound in his side;
                              white dove hovering above; landscape in the background.</item>
                           <item>(border, left margin) Sprays of foliage, flowers and gold discs
                              extending into margins (mutilated). Two panels, one with half-figure
                              of a praying king, another with half-figure of a praying
                              prophet.</item>
                           <item>fol. 82v, Psalm 114 (initial D(ilexi)), 4-line initial with St
                              Ubaldus, seated, nimbed, holding crosier and blessing; lettering ‘S
                              VBALDUS’ above the shoulders of the figure; landscape in the
                              background.</item>
                           <item>fol. 86v, Psalm 121 (initial L(etatus)), 4-line initial with St
                              Jerome in penance before crucifix, beating his chest with a stone;
                              landscape in the background.</item>
                           <item>fol. 90v, Psalm 126 (initial N(isi)), 5-line initial with St Dominic
                              (?), kneeling in prayer, looking up at rays of light; landscape in the
                              background.</item>
                           <item>fol. 95r, Psalm 131 (initial M(emento)), 6-line initial with a
                              kneeling nimbed prophet looking up at rays of light, holding a blank
                              scroll and raising a finger in a gesture of teaching; landscape in the
                              background.</item>
                           <item>fol. 102r, Psalm 137 (initial C(onfitebor)), 5-line initial with St
                              Dominic (?), kneeling in prayer; landscape in the background.</item>
                           <item>fol. 109r, Psalm 143 (initial B(enedictus)), 5-line initial with a
                              standing bearded saint, holding a scroll with lettering ‘CREDO IN
                              DEO’; landscape in the background.</item>
                           <item>fol. 116v, Psalm 4 (initial C(um)), 3-line initial on gold background
                              decorated with a flower and foliage.</item>
                        </list></decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="border">Borders: see above.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="decInit">2- to 3-line pink, green and blue initials on gold
                        background, decorated with foliage, flowers, scrolls, arabesque and
                        geometric designs at the beginnings of psalms; similar initials with yellow
                        instead of gold background at the beginnings of antiphons, versicles,
                        invitatoria, etc.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="flourInit">The opening words of texts starting with illuminated
                        initials are written in capitals in black ink, decorated with penwork
                        designs, including human heads and profiles.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="flourInit">1-line alternating red and blue initials with
                        contrasting purple or red penwork at the beginnings of verses and
                        periods.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="rubrication">Rubrics in red ink.</decoNote>

                  </decoDesc>
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <binding notAfter="1900" notBefore="1800">
                        <p> Brown leather over pasteboard, 19th century (perhaps made for the
                           Bodleian). Borders on both covers made of crossing single and triple
                           blind fillet lines. Originally there were five false raised bands on
                           spine, framed by triple blind fillet lines, but three are now missing.
                           Gilt lettering on spine ‘PSALTERUM’ and ‘MS’. Paper pastedowns and
                           fly-leaves, no watermarks. Floral blind roll decorations on turn-ins and
                           edges of covers. Fols. ii and 122 (parchment with paper pasted to the
                           side facing the cover) were the pastedowns of an earlier 17th-century
                           binding. They show considerable worm damage and traces left by seven
                           broad sewing support slips. Similar to MS. Lat. liturg. a. 3 and MS. Lat.
                           liturg. b. 1. </p>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="1475" notBefore="1450">15th century,
                        third quarter</origDate>
                     <origPlace cert="low">
                        <country key="place_1000080">Italian</country>, <settlement
                           key="place_7005764">Brescia</settlement> or <settlement
                           key="place_7003085">Padua</settlement>
                        (?)<!--ORIGINAL: Italian, Brescia or Padua (?)--></origPlace>
                  </origin>
                  <provenance>Made in Brescia or Padua (?) for a Dominican house, perhaps in Gubbio,
                     Umbria (historiated initial with St Ubaldus, fol. 82v; miniature, fol. 4v) (cf.
                     MS. Lat. liturg. a. 3). Historiated border with St Catherine. Decorated by an
                     artist whose work is found in manuscripts from Brescia, Padua and elsewhere,
                     dating from the third quarter of the 15th century. </provenance>
                  <provenance>The manuscript was foliated, rebound, repaired with strips of
                     parchment and paper, and supplemented with additions on paper, while still in
                     use in the 17th century. Bookmarks may have been added at the same time. </provenance>
                  <acquisition when="1885">'Found at the end of MSS. Liturg. in 1885' (Summary
                     catalogue, vol. 5). </acquisition>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source> Elizabeth Solopova, <title>Latin
                              Liturgical Psalters in the Bodleian Library: A Select
                              Catalogue</title> (Oxford, 2013), pp. 566–72. Previously described in
                           the Summary Catalogue. <listBibl>
                              <bibl facs="aam0871.gif" type="SC">Summary Catalogue, vol. 5, p.
                                 834</bibl>
                           </listBibl>
                        </source>
                     </recordHist>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl type="WRAPPER">
                     <listBibl type="PRINT">
                        <bibl>Frere, no. 153.</bibl>
                        <bibl>van Dijk (1958), fols. 130–1.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Pächt and Alexander (1966–73), vol. 2, no. 682, pl. LXV.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Canova, G. M., ‘Il recupero di un complesso librario dimenticato: i
                           corali quattrocenteschi di S. Giorgio Maggiore a Venezia’, <title>Arte
                              Veneta</title> 27 (1973), pp. 38–64, at p. 50 and fig. 60 (fol.
                           4v).</bibl>
                        <bibl>——, ‘I manoscritti liturgici miniati del Quattrocento nella Biblioteca
                           Antoniana’, <title>Il Santo</title>, s. II, 14 (1974), pp. 5–61, at p. 58
                           n. 23 and pl. 18 (fol. 4v).</bibl>
                        <bibl>Bollati (2004), p. 622.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Baroffio, G., ‘Liturgia e musica nella tradizione domenicana’ in C.
                           Parmeggiani, <title>Canto e colore: i corali di San Domenico di Perugia
                              nella Biblioteca comunale Augusta, XIII–XIV sec., 11 marzo–17 aprile
                              2006, Perugia, Sala Lippi, Unicredit banca, Corso Vannucci, 39</title>
                           [exhibition catalogue] (Perugia: Volumnia, 2006), pp. 33–68, at p.
                           62.</bibl>
                     </listBibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2024-08">Convert full description from Solopova catalogue.</change>
         <change when="2017-07-01">First online publication.</change>
         <change when="2017-05-25">
            <persName>James Cummings</persName> Up-converted the markup using <ref
               target="https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl"
               >https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl</ref>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
