<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="manuscript_10266">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Merton College MS. 168</title>
            <title type="collection">Merton College MSS.</title>
            <respStmt xml:id="RM">
               <resp when="2009">Cataloguer</resp>
               <persName>R. M. Thomson</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="TA">
               <resp when="2019">Encoding</resp>
               <persName>Tuija Ainonen</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition/>
            <funder>Conversion of the printed catalogue to TEI funded by the Warden and Fellows of <orgName>Merton College <graphic url="https://www.merton.ox.ac.uk/sites/default/files/inline-images/logo.png"/></orgName>.</funder>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </publisher>
            <idno type="msID">Merton_College_MS_168</idno>
            <idno type="collection">Merton_College</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="Merton_College_MS_168" xml:lang="en">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <repository>Merton College</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">Merton College MS. 168</idno>
                  <idno type="ieArk">ark:29072/e6h415p846gc</idno><idno type="crArk">ark:29072/e6h128nc635h</idno><altIdentifier type="former">
                     <idno>M. 2. 1</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
               <head>NICHOLAS GORRAN ON PSALMS; S. XIV in. </head>
               <msContents>
                  <textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>
                  <msItem n="1">
                     <locus from="1" to="306v">(fols. 1–306v)</locus>
                     <author key="person_101584149">NICHOLAS GORRAN OP</author>
                     <title key="work_3293">Commentary on the Psalter</title>
                     <incipit><quote>Laudacionem Domini loquetur os meum ...;</quote> Loquens sapiens de Spiritu Sancto inspirante</incipit>
                     <incipit><quote>Beatus uir</quote> ...; s. glossa prohemiale totalis liber iste psalmorum in tres partes diuiditur ... </incipit>
                     <explicit>nec dormire poterat nec lassari, ad quam patriam nos perducat ille qui ... .</explicit>
                     <finalRubric>Expliciunt postille fratris Nicholai de Gorham super psalterium, quibus quiscumque usus fuerit, roget pro anima domini Hugonis de Notingham per quem quo ad omnia exhibite sunt expense. Et eciam pro anima fratris Willelmi de eadem per cuius tediosam sollicitudinem quia dum actu Oxonie regens erat taliter erant scripte.</finalRubric>
                     <note>Pr. Frankfurt 1617; Stegmüller, <title>Bibl.</title> 5750. </note>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <p>
                     <secFol>-lo caret</secFol>
                  </p>
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="perg">
                        <support>Parchment</support>
                        <extent>307 leaves <dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                              <height>380</height>
                              <width>270</width>
                           </dimensions>
                           <dimensions type="written" unit="mm">
                              <height>275</height>
                              <width>170</width>
                           </dimensions>
                        </extent>
                        <collation>1–3<hi rend="superscript">12</hi>, 4<hi rend="superscript">16</hi>(+ a slip after 16), 5–15<hi rend="superscript">12</hi>, 16<hi rend="superscript">6</hi>, 17–22<hi rend="superscript">12</hi>, 23<hi rend="superscript">8</hi>, 24–6<hi rend="superscript">12</hi>; framed catchwords, quire-signatures of the usual late medieval form, coloured leaf-numbers. </collation>
                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout columns="2" writtenLines="59">Ruled with pencil in 2 cols of 59 lines. The Psalter text occurs in blocks of 2–3 lines, written in larger script on every second line, and as underlined lemmata in the gloss. Running heads between ruled lines.</layout>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc>
                     <handNote>Written throughout in the expert gothic rotunda bookhand of <persName key="person_39768873" role="scr">William of Nottingham</persName><!-- (<hi rend="italic">Pl. 58</hi>)-->. Marginal annotation in neat anglicana, s. xiv in., probably also William’s, quotes e.g. <persName key="person_16017787">Innocent III</persName>, <title key="work_2191">De Miseria Conditionis Humanae</title>, <persName key="person_32799411">Andrew of St Victor</persName>.</handNote>
                  </handDesc>
                  <decoDesc>
                     <decoNote>Large and handsome red and blue flourished initials with partial borders to prol., Pss. 1, 51, 52, 68, 97, 101, 110; blue initials flourished in red; small red initials, red or blue paraphs; running heads in both colours. At the ends of some quires are notes in red, blue or pencil of the number and cost of the coloured initials.</decoNote>
                  </decoDesc>
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <binding calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="1500" notBefore="1300">
                        <p>Medieval: tawed skin, repaired, over flush wooden boards, the rear one thicker and with a wide bevel; sewn on seven bands, slightly raised on the spine; plain head- and tail-bands, sewn through the cover skin. The front board had straps at head and tail, covered by the skin. Two broad straps of tanned leather from recesses at the foredge to catches in the rear board, now gone. The mark of a brass chain-staple near the head of the foredge of the front board. Near the foot of the rear pastedown are two contiguous sets of marks from the large chain-staple<!-- (<hi rend="italic">Pl. 39c</hi>)-->. One set, with associated rust, does not pierce the board. The other set, which does, has associated verdigris. Clearly the rear board and skin cover are later than the front board. Either this or MS 167 was rebound in 1436–7<!--: Appendix B, no. 95-->.</p>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="1325" notBefore="1300">S. XIV in.</origDate>
                     <origPlace><country key="place_7002445">England</country>, <settlement key="place_7011931">Oxford</settlement></origPlace>
                  </origin>
                  <provenance cert="medium" notAfter="1314">Written by <persName key="person_39768873" role="scr">William of Nottingham</persName> OFM (d. 1336; <title>BRUO</title> 1377–8), presumably for his Order, while he was lector at Oxford 1312–14, at the expense of Sir <persName key="person_4081">Hugh of Nottingham</persName>, clerk in the royal exchequer: B. Smalley, ‘Which William of Nottingham?’, in her <title>Studies in Medieval Thought and Learning</title> (London, 1981), pp. 248–87, esp. 252–3. </provenance>
                  <provenance when="1374">Given to the College by <persName key="person_96298161" role="fmo dnr">William Reed</persName> in 1374: UO49. 91. The second of a set of ten volumes, of which eight survive: the others are MSS 166, 169–72. For William Reed, see MS 8. </provenance>
                  <provenance>On the front pastedown: ‘In hoc uolumine continentur postille super Psalterium per fratrem Nicholaum de Gorham’; ‘Liber M. Willelmi Reed episcopi Cicestrensis quem emit a uenerabili patre domino <persName key="person_2996" role="fmo">Thoma Tryllek</persName> episcopo Roffensi Orate igitur pro utroque. Postilla Nicholai Gorham super psalterium’; ‘Liber domus scolarium de Merton’ in Oxon’ in communi libraria eiusdem et ad usum communem sociorum ibidem studencium cathenandus. Ex dono uenerabilis patris domini Willelmi tertii episcopi Cicestr’. Oretis igitur pro eodem et benefactoribus eiusdem ac fidelium animabus a purgatorio liberandis’; ‘Orare eciam dignemini pro <persName key="person_4066">Waltero Roberti</persName> scriba et notarius uenerabilis patris predicti qui suprascripti tituli et titulos aliorum 99. librorum per dictum patrem eidem domui datorum ad emendacionem librarie eiusdem inscripsit et circa eosdem libros et alios quamplures per diuersa collegia uniuersitatis Oxon’ per ipsum uenerabilem patrem distributos diligenter insudauit’; ‘Gorranus super Psalterium’ and ‘O. 6. 8. Art:’, s. xvii, the second canc. and replaced by ‘M. 2. 1 (CLXVIII)’ in red; the College bookplate. ‘8’ is inked on the foredge.</provenance>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>
                           <bibl>R. M. Thomson, <title>A descriptive catalogue of the medieval manuscripts of Merton College, Oxford</title> (Cambridge: D. S. Brewer), 2009.</bibl>
                        </source>
                     </recordHist>
                     <availability>
                        <p>For enquiries relating to this manuscript please contact <ref target="https://www.merton.ox.ac.uk/library-and-archives/contact">Merton College Library</ref>.</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl type="PRINT">
                     <bibl>Coxe, p. 67; Powicke, no. 551.</bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2019-07-02">First online publication</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>