<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="manuscript_10169">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Merton College MS. 71</title>
            <title type="collection">Merton College MSS.</title>
            <respStmt xml:id="RM">
               <resp when="2009">Cataloguer</resp>
               <persName>R. M. Thomson</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="MLH">
               <resp when="2018">Markup and encoding</resp>
               <persName>Matthew Holford</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition/>
            <funder>Conversion of the printed catalogue to TEI funded by the Warden and Fellows of <orgName>Merton College <graphic url="https://www.merton.ox.ac.uk/sites/default/files/inline-images/logo.png"/></orgName>.</funder>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </publisher>
            <idno type="msID">Merton_College_MS_71</idno>
            <idno type="collection">Merton_College</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="Merton_College_MS_71" xml:lang="en">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <repository>Merton College</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">Merton College MS. 71</idno>
                  <idno type="ieArk">ark:29072/e61g05fb49qp</idno><idno type="crArk">ark:29072/e61c18df66dt</idno><altIdentifier type="former">
                     <idno>K. 2. 6</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
               <head>THOMAS BRADWARDINE; 1369 </head>
               <msContents>
                  <summary>MS 71 is an important copy of the major work of Thomas Bradwardine, one of the most eminent of the so-called 'Merton school' of scientists, archbishop of Canterbury in 1349. It was copied professionally in 1369 for Fellow Simon Lambourne, who gave it to the College. Before and after the main text he transcribed, in his own hand, two otherwise unknown letters from Bradwardine to the Fellows relating to the composition of the work.</summary>
                  <textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>
                  <msItem>
                     <note> fol. i blank.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem>
                     <locus from="1" to="266v">(fols. 1–266v)</locus>
                     <author key="person_76375851">Thomas Bradwardine</author>
                     <title key="work_4788">De Causa Dei contra Pelagianos</title>
                     <rubric>De causa Dei contra Pellagium et de uirtute causarum Thome de Bredewardyna cancellarii Londonie</rubric>
                     <incipit>Magnorum et multorum peticionibus atque repeticionibus cumulatis incessanter</incipit>
                     <note>(<foreign rend="italic"><foreign rend="italic">capitula</foreign></foreign> fols. 2–4v)</note>
                     <incipit>In primis firmissime supponatur quod Deus est summe perfectus et bonus in totum</incipit>
                     <explicit><note>(q. 53; f. 265v)</note> ad scientiam ueritatis et in ipsa indeclinabiter confirmetur</explicit>
                     <note><note>(<hi rend="italic">In another hand</hi>)</note> Isti 36 articuli subscripti secundum doctorem istum in tantum sunt falsi et erronei; quod ipsos magno desiderio affectabat ab ecclesia condempnari ac eorum ut premittitur opposita confirmari...</note>
                     <finalRubric>Explicit istud opus de causa Dei contra Pelagium et de uirtute causarum uirtute Dei cause causarum perscriptum London’ anno milesimo trecentesimo quadragesimo quarto Domini Ihesu Christi</finalRubric>
                     <note>pr. H. Savile (London, 1618) / repr. Frankfurt, 1976; Stegmüller, <title>Sent</title>. 896–8; Sharpe, <title>Handlist</title>, p. 643.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem>
                     <note>On the originally blank col. b of fol. 4v, in the anglicana hand of <persName key="person_3144" role="scr">Simon Lambourne</persName>, is a letter from Bradwardine (headed ‘T. de B.’) to the warden and fellows of Merton: ‘Dilectis fratribus et amicis custodi ac scolaribus aule de Mertone in Oxonia Spiritus Sancti graciam septiformem. Aliquociens accidisse comperi ut in rerum difficilium tractacione ...’, notifying them of his new book. pr. Savile, pp. cxvii-xviii. The same hand copies another in the blank space left on col. b of fol. 266v: ‘Dilectis fratribus et amicis custodi et sociis aule de Mertone in Oxonia Thomas de B. salutem et gratiam in omnibus feliciter prosperandi. Peticioni uestre mox obtemperare uolui ...’, to accompany a copy of his work which he is sending them. pr. Savile, p. 876. Each of the three books begins a new quire; hence fols. 137v-8v are blank (text begun on fol. 138 was scraped off), and so are fols. 200–2v.</note>
                     <note> fol. 267v is blank.</note>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <p>
                     <secFol><locus>(capitula)</locus> in ipsa namque</secFol>
                     <secFol><locus from="5" to="5">(fol. 5)</locus> quapropter</secFol>
                  </p>
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="perg">
                        <support>Parchment</support>
                        <extent>268 leaves (<seg type="leaf"><measure type="laterEndleaf" quantity="1">i</measure> + <measure type="leaf" quantity="267">267</measure></seg>) <dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                              <height>380</height>
                              <width>260</width>
                           </dimensions>
                           <dimensions type="written" unit="mm">
                              <height>300</height>
                              <width>220</width>
                           </dimensions>
                        </extent>
                        <collation>a singleton, 1<hi rend="superscript">4</hi>, 2–12<hi rend="superscript">12</hi>, a bifolium, 13–16<hi rend="superscript">12</hi>, 17<hi rend="superscript">10</hi>, 18<hi rend="superscript">6</hi>, 19–21<hi rend="superscript">12</hi>, 22<hi rend="superscript">6</hi>, 23<hi rend="superscript">12</hi>, 24<hi rend="superscript">10</hi>, a singleton; <catchwords>framed catchwords</catchwords>; <signatures>pencilled quire-signatures of the usual late medieval form</signatures>. </collation>
                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout columns="2" writtenLines="60">Ruled with crayon in 2 cols of <hi rend="italic">c.</hi> 60 lines. </layout>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc>
                     <handNote>Written, probably by one variable hand, in a mixture of gothic rotunda bookhand and anglicana<!--(<hi rend="italic">Pl. 59</hi>)-->.</handNote>
                  </handDesc>
                  <decoDesc>
                     <decoNote>Books open with large and handsome red and blue flourished initials, with partial borders in the colours. Blue initials flourished in red; red or blue paraphs; running heads in red and blue capitals.</decoNote>
                  </decoDesc>
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <binding calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="2000" notBefore="1900">
                        <p>s. xx, <orgName key="org_125" role="bnd">Maltby</orgName>; bare oak boards, backed with vellum; resewn on five bands. On fol. 265v are marks of two clasps at the foredge and one each at head and tail, of a brass chain-staple from the foredge near the head, and of the large iron chain-staple near the foot.</p>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origDate calendar="Gregorian" cert="high" when="1369">1369 </origDate>
                     <origPlace><country key="place_7002445">England</country>, <settlement key="place_7011931">Oxford</settlement></origPlace>
                  </origin>
                  <provenance when="1369">On fol. i<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>‘Liber M. <persName key="person_3144" role="fmo dnr">Simonis Lambourn’</persName> prec’ vii marcarum. Scriptus anno Domini mccclxix.’ There is no need to suppose that Lambourne was the scribe; the book is doubtless a professional product and made at Oxford. He does, however, annotate and provide marginal <hi rend="italic">auctoritates</hi>. At the foot of fol. 266v, very faint, is ‘Liber domus scolarium de Merton’ in Oxon’ datus per Magistrum <supplied>Symonem Lambourn</supplied>’, s. xv. At the head of fol. 267, probably autograph, is ‘Liber M. Simonis Lambourn’ d<supplied>atus</supplied> aule de Merton’ ad perpetuum usum sociorum eiusdem.’ Lambourne (<title>BRUO</title> 1087) was fellow 1347–61, later canon of Southwell. He left MS 284 to John Bloxham (<title>BRUO</title> 204), and gave MS 306 to the College. On fol. i<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>is ‘Donavit Bibliothecae Mr. Simon Lambourn’ and ‘N. 6. 5. Art:’, s. xvii, the second canc. and replaced with ‘K. 2. 6 (LXXI)’, in red. Beneath is the College bookplate.</provenance>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>
                           <bibl>R. M. Thomson, <title>A descriptive catalogue of the medieval manuscripts of Merton College, Oxford</title> (Cambridge: D. S. Brewer), 2009.</bibl>
                        </source>
                     </recordHist>
                     <availability>
                        <p>For enquiries relating to this manuscript please contact <ref target="https://www.merton.ox.ac.uk/library-and-archives/contact">Merton College Library</ref>.</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl type="PRINT">
                     <bibl>Coxe, pp. 43–4; Powicke, no. 523; S. H. Thomson, <title>Latin Bookhands of the Later Middle Ages 1100–1500</title> (Cambridge, 1969), pl. 101; Watson, <title>Dated and Datable Oxford</title>, no. 838, pl. 202.</bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2018-08-01">First online publication</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>