<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="manuscript_884">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>MS. Barlow 22</title>
            <title type="collection">MSS. Barlow</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp when="2013">Cataloguer</resp>
               <persName>Elizabeth Solopova</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp when="2024">Encoding</resp>
               <persName>Matthew Holford</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </publisher>
            <idno type="msID">MS_Barlow_22</idno>
            <idno type="collection">Barlow</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="MS_Barlow_22" xml:lang="en">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <region type="county">Oxfordshire</region>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <institution>University of Oxford</institution>
                  <repository>Bodleian Library</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">MS. Barlow 22</idno>
                  <idno type="ieArk">ark:29072/x0zk51vf84p9</idno>
                  <idno type="crArk">ark:29072/x03t945r78sv</idno>
                  <altIdentifier type="internal">
                     <idno type="SCN">6461</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
               <head>Monastic Psalter; England, Fenlands, perhaps for Ramsey Abbey,
                  later adapted for Peterborough Abbey; 14th century, first half</head>
               <msContents>
                  <msItem class="#liturgica #biblia" n="1" xml:id="MS_Barlow_22-item1">
                     <title key="work_14114" type="desc">Monastic Psalter</title>
                     <msItem n="1">
                        <note> (fol. i recto–verso) See below, endleaves. </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="2">
                        <note>(fol. 1r–v) See below, endleaves.</note>
                     </msItem>
                     <note>[item 3 occupies quire I]</note>
                     <msItem n="3">
                        <locus from="2r" to="4v">(fols. 2r–4v)</locus>
                        <note> 14th-century additions, including a commemoration office with three
                           lessons of the Common of Martyrs (fol. 2r); lessons for the votive
                           offices of Sts Benedict (fol. 2v), Peter (fol. 3v) and the Virgin Mary
                           (fol. 4r) with three lessons for each office and a prayer to the Virgin
                           Mary, ‘O regina mundi stella celi tronus dei ianua paradisi . . .’ (fol.
                           4v). Followed by stubs from an excised quire, with traces of decoration.
                        </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <note> [item 4 occupies quire II]</note>
                     <msItem n="4">
                        <locus from="5r" to="10v">(fols. 5r–10v)</locus>
                        <note> Calendar of Ramsey Abbey, adapted for Peterborough Abbey, laid out
                           one month per page, written in brown, red and blue, approximately
                           two-thirds full, graded to 12 lessons, ‘in cappis’ and ‘in albis’.
                           Includes Wulstan, bishop of Worcester (19 January), Oswald of Worcester
                           (29 February), Cuthbert (20 March), Guthlac (11 April), Alfheah (19
                           April), Ivo (‘Inventio sancti yuonis’, 24 April), Dunstan (19 May),
                           Athelthryth (23 June), Neot (31 July), Oswald (5 August) with added
                           octave, Edmund (20 November), and the feast (21 March), translation (11
                           July) with octave and ‘Tumulatio’ of Benedict (4 December), all in blue
                           or red. Added feasts, with initials either plain or not filled in,
                           include the translation of Kyneburga, Kyneswida and Tibba (6 March),
                           Athelwold (1 August) and his translation (10 September), Florentinus (27
                           September), ‘(D)edicatio ecclesie burgi’ (28 September) with octave, the
                           feast of relics (21 October), Hugh, bishop of Lincoln (16 November) and
                           his translation (6 October), all in red; Paul the Hermit (10 January),
                           Babylas (25 January), Werburgh (3 February), Cedd (2 March), Athanasius
                           (2 May), Aidan (31 August), the translation of Cuthbert (4 September),
                           Wilfrid (12 October), Mellonis (22 October) and Hilda (17 November) in
                           brown. Added obits of the abbots of Peterborough, most (up to Geoffrey of
                           Crowland, d. 1321) in the same hand, and several others, starting with
                           Henry of Morcot (d. 1353), in other hands. Verses on the ‘Egyptian’ days,
                           corresponding to Hennig’s (1955) type III and notes on the number of days
                           and nights in a month at the top of each page; notes on the number of
                           hours in day and night at the bottom of each page. The feasts of Thomas
                           Becket and titles ‘pape’ are erased. </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <note> [item 5 occupies quire III]</note>
                     <msItem n="5">
                        <locus from="11r" to="14v">(fols. 11r–14v)</locus>
                        <note> Miniatures on fols. 12v–14v (see ‘Decoration’); fols. 11r–12r are
                           ruled as if for miniatures but blank, except for a leadpoint note
                           ‘Suscipe dign[eris hos psalmos ... (?)]’, fol. 11r (see Bennett, 1982).
                        </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <note> [item 6 occupies quires IV–XXIII]</note>
                     <msItem n="6">
                        <locus from="15r" to="166r">(fols. 15r–166r)</locus>
                        <note> Psalms 1–150, in the biblical order, laid out with each verse
                           starting on a new line, without titles, with numbers added in the margins
                           in medieval Arabic numerals (now mostly cropped off and/or erased) and in
                           a post-medieval hand over or near erasures. Punctuated throughout with
                           punctus used to mark the ends of verses, punctus elevatus used to mark
                           metrum, and punctus or punctus elevatus used to mark minor pauses. There
                           are textual divisions at psalms 26, 38, 51, 52, 68, 80, 97, 101 and 109.
                           Psalm 109 starts in a new quire. Subdivisions within psalms are marked
                           with 2-line initials at 9: 20 (fol. 21r), 17: 26 (fol. 28v), 36: 27 (fol.
                           61r), 138: 11 (Et dixi ...) (fol. 157a), 143: 9 (fol. 160v), 144: 10
                           (fol. 162r); ‘diuisio’ is added in the margin at 68: 17, (fol. 83r), 77:
                           36 (fol. 94v), 104: 23 (fol. 122v), 105: 32 (fol. 125r) and 106: 25 (fol.
                           128r). Psalm 118 is subdivided into twenty-two 8-verse units. Fols.
                           166v–167r are blank; fol. 167v is ruled but blank. </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <note>[items 7–8 occupy quires XXIV–XXV]</note>
                     <msItem n="7">
                        <locus from="168r" to="177v">(fols. 168r–177v)</locus>
                        <note> Weekly canticles, without titles: <list>
                              <item> (1) Confitebor tibi domine (Isaiah 12);</item>
                              <item> (2) Ego dixi (Isaiah 38: 10–21);</item>
                              <item> (3) Exultauit cor meum (1 Samuel 2: 1–11);</item>
                              <item> (4) Cantemus domino (Exodus 15: 1–20);</item>
                              <item> (5) Domine audiui (Habakkuk 3);</item>
                              <item> (6) Audite celi (Deuteronomy 32: 1–44).</item>
                           </list>
                        </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="8">
                        <locus from="177v" to="184r">(fols. 177v–184r)</locus>
                        <note> Daily canticles, prayers and creeds, without titles: <list>
                              <item> (1) Benedicite omnia opera (fol. 177v);</item>
                              <item> (2) Benedictus dominus deus (fol. 178v);</item>
                              <item> (3) Te deum laudamus (fol. 179v);</item>
                              <item> (4) Magnificat (fol. 180v);</item>
                              <item> (5) Nunc dimittis (fol. 181r);</item>
                              <item> (6) Athanasian Creed (Quicumque uult ...) (fol. 181v), the last
                                 4½ lines on fol. 184r in a hand responsible for Peterborough
                                 additions.</item>
                           </list>
                        </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <note> [items 9–12, additions made at Peterborough Abbey, occupy quires
                        XXVI–XXVIII]</note>
                     <msItem n="9">
                        <locus from="184r" to="189r">(fols. 184r–189r)</locus>
                        <note> Peterborough litany, including Peter (doubled, first) among the
                           apostles; Oswald (doubled, second), Florentinus, Alban, Edmund and
                           Alfheah among the martyrs; Æduuold (Athelwold (?)) (double invocation
                           added), Benedict (doubled), Cuthbert, Guthlac, Wilfrid, Swithin, Dunstan,
                           Aidan, Botulph, Wulstan, Hugh and Edmund among the confessors; and
                           Kyneburga, Kyneswida and Tibba (near the top of the list), Athelthryth
                           and Werburgh among the virgins. Thomas Becket erased. Followed by
                           collects (fols. 187v–189r): <list>
                              <item> (1) Deus cui proprium est misereri semper et parcere suscipe
                                 ...</item>
                              <item> (2) Omnipotens sempiterne deus qui facis mirabilia magna solus
                                 ...</item>
                              <item> (3) Pretende domine famulis et famulabus tuis dexteram celestis
                                 auxilii ut de toto corde ...</item>
                              <item> (4) Ure igni sancti spiritus renes nostros ...</item>
                              <item> (5) Actiones nostras quesumus domine et aspirando preueni
                                 ...</item>
                              <item> (6) Adesto domine supplicationibus nostris et uiam famulorum
                                 tuorum in salutis tue ...</item>
                              <item> (7) A domo tua quesumus domine spirituales nequicie repellantur
                                 et aeriarum discedat malignitas tempestatum ...</item>
                              <item> (8) Deus a quo sancta desideria recta consilia et iusta sunt
                                 ...</item>
                              <item> (9) Ecclesie tue quesumus domine preces placatus admitte ut
                                 destructis ...</item>
                              <item> (10) Animabus quesumus domine famulorum famularumque tuarum
                                 misericordiam concede perpetuam</item>
                              <item> (11) Deus qui es sanctorum tuorum splendor mirabilis atque
                                 lapsorum subleuator ...</item>
                           </list>
                        </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="10">
                        <locus from="189r" to="196r">(fols. 189r–196r)</locus>
                        <note> An office with a rubric ‘Commendacio anime exeuntis de corpore ...’,
                           including suffrages for apostles Peter (not doubled), Paul, Andrew, John
                           and James; martyrs Stephen, Clement, Oswald (doubled), Lawrence and
                           Vincent; confessors Silvester, Martin, Nicholas, Dunstan, Athelwold and
                           Benedict (doubled); virgins Mary Magdalene, Felicitas, Perpetua,
                           Scholastica and Kyneburga, Kyneswida and Tibba. </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="11">
                        <locus from="196r" to="203r">(fols. 196r–203r)</locus>
                        <note> Office of the Dead, use of Peterborough (Tolhurst, 1941–42). </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem n="12">
                        <note> (fol. 203v) Added prayers, 15th century. </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <p><secFol> Regem regum <locus>(commemoration office, fol. 2r)</locus></secFol></p>
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="perg">
                        <support>parchment</support>
                        
                        <extent> <measure type="leaf" quantity="204">204</measure> leaves <dimensions unit="mm" type="leaf">
                           <height quantity="266">c. 266</height><width>174</width> </dimensions><note>(leaves trimmed in rebinding)</note></extent>


                        <foliation> modern, in pencil and ink; i + 1–203.</foliation>
                        <collation> (fols. i–1) single leaves, fol. i is a lifted pastedown | (fols.
                           2–4) I (4−1) missing 1; 8-leaf quire cut out after fol. 4 | (fols. 5–10)
                           II (8−2 (?)) missing 1 and 2 | (fols. 11–14) III (4) | (fols. 15–46)
                           IV–VII (8) | (fols. 47–56) VIII (10) | (fols. 57–128) IX–XVII (8) |
                           (fols. 129–131) XVIII (4−1) missing 4 | (fols. 132–161) XIX–XXII (8) |
                           (fols. 162–167) XXIII (6) | (fols. 168–199) XXIV–XXVII (8) | (fols.
                           200–203 and pastedown) XXVIII (6−1) 5th leaf cancelled, 6th leaf is a
                           pastedown. <catchwords>Catchwords</catchwords> and <signatures type="leaf">leaf signatures</signatures> survive, change in leaf
                           signatures after fol. 184.</collation>
                       
                       
                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout writtenLines="19" columns="1">Ruled in plummet and subsequently in pink ink with single
                           horizontal and vertical bounding lines extending the full height and
                           width of the page, and further bounding lines in the margins; 19 lines
                           per page; written below the top line; written space: <dimensions type="written" unit="mm">
                              <height quantity="170">c. 170</height>
                              <width>110</width>
                           </dimensions></layout>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc>
                     <handNote script="textualisNorthern" execution="formata">At least two main scribes (the second takes over at fol.
                        184r), large formal Gothic book hands, brown ink.</handNote>
                  </handDesc>
                  <decoDesc>
                     <summary>The decoration is related to a group of Fenland East Anglian psalters
                        (Sandler, 1974, 1986); illumination in the section added at Peterborough is
                        by a different artist.</summary>
                     <decoNote type="monogram"> Gold KL monograms on blue and pink background in the
                        calendar.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="miniature">Prefatory miniatures (fols. 12v–14v), illustrating
                        the life of Christ (the choice of subjects is identical to that in the
                        Ramsey Psalter (New York, Pierpont Morgan Library MS. M. 302)), set four to
                        a page, in rectangular frames, on alternating gold, blue, pink and red
                        backgrounds with geometric designs: Annunciation (angel holding a scroll),
                        Nativity, Adoration of the Magi, Presentation in the Temple, Christ among
                        the Doctors (Christ as a beardless young man preaching to a group of five
                        men, one seated on a chair and holding a book, and two children), Betrayal,
                        Flagellation, Christ carrying the Cross, Crucifixion (with Stephaton and
                        Longinus pointing to his eye whilst spearing Christ’s side), Descent from
                        the Cross (with the Virgin Mary, St John and Joseph of Arimathea),
                        Entombment, Resurrection, Noli me tangere, Incredulity of St Thomas,
                        Ascension, Pentecost, Coronation of the Virgin (larger panel, occupying the
                        upper half of the page), Dormition of the Virgin (the Virgin lying on a bed,
                        Christ standing beside, holding her soul), Assumption (two angels holding
                        mandorla, containing a small figure of a young woman with hands joined in
                        prayer; empty bed and apostles below).</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="histInit">Historiated initials (10 lines high at psalm 1, 7
                        lines high at psalm 109, 4 to 6 lines high at other psalms) on gold
                        backgrounds and borders, made of blue, pink and gold bars, decorated with
                        foliage, human heads and grotesques at liturgical divisions. <list>
                           <item>fol. 15r Psalm 1 (initial B(eatus)) Jesse Tree (sleeping Jesse with
                              a tree growing out of his chest, with figures and scenes among its
                              branches, including the Virgin and Child, the Throne of Grace,
                              prophets with scrolls and kings playing musical instruments).</item>
                           <item>(full border) Panels with portrait heads, and French and English
                              royal arms.</item>
                           <item>fol. 37v Psalm 26 (initial D(ominus)) King David kneeling before an
                              altar, pointing to his eyes; nimbed dove in clouds above.</item>
                           <item>fol. 53r Psalm 38 (initial D(ixi)) King David kneeling before an
                              altar, holding a book, hand raised; half-figure of God above,
                              blessing, holding a book.</item>
                           <item>fol. 67r Psalm 51 (initial Q(uid)) Suicide of Saul; half-naked Fool
                              (?) with a bladder on a stick in the border below.</item>
                           <item>fol. 68r Psalm 52 (initial D(ixit)) King David, seated, holding a
                              sceptre, speaking to the Fool, wrapped in a cloak, holding a bladder
                              on a stick, pointing above.</item>
                           <item>fol. 82r Psalm 68 (initial S(aluum)) Jonah in waters, in the mouth
                              of a whale, praying to Christ in clouds above.</item>
                           <item>fol. 99r Psalm 80 (initial E(xultate)) King David, seated, playing
                              three bells with hammers; standing musician holding an organ.</item>
                           <item>(border, left and lower margin) Grotesque playing a drum and a
                              pipe.</item>
                           <item>fol. 114v Psalm 97 (initial C(antate)) Three tonsured clerics
                              singing from a book open on a lectern.</item>
                           <item>(border, left and lower margin) Hybrid playing vielle.</item>
                           <item>fol. 132r Psalm 109 (initial D(ixit)) Trinity: two seated figures,
                              holding books, God blessing, Christ as a youth with a raised hand;
                              head of a white dove in clouds above.</item>
                        </list></decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="border">Borders: see above.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="decInit">3-line pink and blue initials, infilled with portrait
                        heads on tooled gold backgrounds at the beginnings of psalm 101 (fol. 116v)
                        and weekly canticles (fol. 168r); 3-line foliate/ inhabited initials at
                        psalm 119 (fol. 146v) and the Office of the Dead (fol. 196r).</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="decInit">2-line pink and blue initials on tooled gold
                        backgrounds, and borders made of pink, blue and gold bars, decorated with
                        foliage, animal and human heads, and grotesques, at the beginnings of
                        psalms, canticles, litany, prayers and sections of the Office of the Dead.
                        Many initials infilled with portrait heads of men and women.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="flourInit">1-line alternating blue initials with red penwork
                        and gold initials with blue penwork at the beginnings of verses and periods;
                        penwork often extends into the upper and lower margins.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="lineFill">Pink, blue and gold line-endings with geometric
                        designs and ornament in white.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="rubrication"> rubrics in red ink; blue paragraph
                        marks</decoNote>
                  </decoDesc>
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <binding notAfter="1500" notBefore="1400">
                        <p> English medieval binding: faded, originally red 15th-century (?), skin
                           chemise over white (?) skin over 14th-century (?) bevelled oak boards.
                           Two nail-holes in the inner face of the back board are traces of two
                           clasps of the former binding; traces of a later single clasp attaching
                           from the middle of the front board to the middle of the back board. Sewn
                           on six tawed straps, pegged into horizontal channels in the inner faces
                           of the boards. ‘22’ painted white on spine. Bodleian paper label on spine
                           ‘Arch. F. || d. 5’. Upper pastedown, currently detached, is fol. i;
                           parchment lower pastedown. Painted edges of the textblock, including
                           fleurs-de-lis and leopards (cf. Beatus-initial). </p>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="1341" notBefore="1321">c.
                        1321–41</origDate>
                     <origPlace>
                        <country key="place_7002445">English</country>, <region>Fenlands</region>,
                           <orgName key="org_121821230">Ramsey Abbey</orgName> (?), later adapted
                        for <orgName key="org_139684558">Peterborough Abbey</orgName>
                        <!--ORIGINAL: English, Peterborough-->
                     </origPlace>
                  </origin>
                  <provenance>Made for the <orgName role="fmo" key="org_121821230">Abbey of St Mary and St Benedict, Ramsey</orgName>, at an unknown
                     centre, probably in the East Anglian Fenlands ‘workshop’ that produced
                     illuminated manuscripts for Crowland, Ramsey and Peterborough. The original
                     calendar was of Ramsey and the picture-cycle is nearly identical to that in the
                     Ramsey Psalter; the original litany was apparently not of Peterborough and
                     therefore had to be replaced (see Sandler, 1974, pp. 121–2; Bennett, 1982). </provenance>
                  <provenance>Adapted for use at the <orgName key="org_139684558" role="fmo">Abbey of St Peter, Peterborough</orgName> (perhaps for
                     Rouceby, see below) with a large number of additions and erasures in the
                     calendar and the addition of litany and other texts. </provenance>
                  <provenance>Belonged to <persName role="fmo" key="person_3939">Brother Walter de Rouceby</persName>, whose obit is in the calendar,
                     dated 4 May 1341 (fol. 7r): ‘Psalterium fratris Walteri de Rouceby cuius anime
                     misereatur deus. Amen. Item psalterium beate uirginis cum letan’ (fol. 2r). </provenance>
                  <provenance>15th-century inscriptions on lower pastedown. </provenance>
                  <provenance>Thomas Becket erased in the calendar and litany, and titles ‘pape’
                     erased in the calendar, presumably at the Reformation. </provenance>
                  <provenance><persName role="fmo" key="person_3938">John Harborne</persName>, 20 December 1604 (lower pastedown). </provenance>
                  <provenance><persName role="fmo" key="person_465">Thomas Barlow (1608/9–1691)</persName>, see ODNB, 1661: ‘Lib: Tho: Barlow è Coll:
                     Reg: Oxon. Anno. M.DC.LXI.’ and a note about the obit of Walter de Rouceby (?)
                     (fol. 2r). </provenance>
                  <acquisition when="1691">Bodleian Library: bequeathed by Barlow. Earlier shelfmarks: ‘(19)’
                     (fols. 1r, 1v) with ‘NE’ added before the former (see Summary catalogue, vol.
                     1, p. xii), ‘MS Linc. 22’ (fol. 1r) and the location ‘Arch F. d. 15’ (upper
                     cover). </acquisition>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>Elizabeth Solopova, <title>Latin
                              Liturgical Psalters in the Bodleian Library: A Select
                              Catalogue</title> (Oxford, 2013), pp. 174–82. Previously described in
                           the Summary Catalogue. <listBibl>
                              <bibl facs="aaq0415.gif" type="SC">Summary Catalogue, Vol. 2 Part 2,
                                 p. 1056</bibl>
                           </listBibl>
                        </source>
                     </recordHist>
                     <availability status="restricted">
                        <p>To ensure its preservation, access to this item is restricted, and
                           readers are asked to work from reproductions and published descriptions
                           as far as possible. If you wish to apply to see the original, please
                           click the request button above. When your request is received, you will
                           be asked to contact the relevant curator outlining the subject of your
                           research, the importance of this item to that research, and the resources
                           you have already consulted.</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <surrogates>
                     <bibl subtype="partial" type="digital-facsimile">
                        <ref target="https://digital.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/objects/9c615e5c-4f2a-4666-b153-4205bc0318d0/">
                           <title>Digital Bodleian</title>
                        </ref>
                        <note>(25 images from 35mm slides)</note>
                     </bibl>
                  <bibl type="microfilm">Microfilm available in the open shelf collections in the Weston Library (R. Films 101)</bibl></surrogates>
                  <listBibl type="WRAPPER">
                     <listBibl type="INTERNET">
                        <head>Online resources:</head>
                        <bibl>
                           <ref target="https://www.diamm.ac.uk/sources/490/">
                              <title>DIAMM: Digital Image Archive of Medieval Music</title>
                           </ref>
                        </bibl>
                        <bibl>
                           <ref target="http://mlgb3.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/mlgb/book/184">
                              <title>MLGB3: Medieval Libraries of Great Britain</title>
                           </ref>
                        </bibl>
                     </listBibl>
                     <listBibl type="PRINT">
                        <head>Printed descriptions:</head>
                        <bibl>S. J. P. van Dijk, <title>Latin Liturgical Manuscripts in the Bodleian
                              Library, Oxford, vol. 2: Office Books</title> (typescript, 1957),
                              <citedRange unit="page" from="18" to="18">p. 18</citedRange>
                        </bibl>
                        <bibl>S. J. P. van Dijk, <title>Latin Liturgical Manuscripts in the Bodleian
                              Library, Oxford, vol. 6: Fragments - Office Books, Rituals,
                              Directories</title> (typescript, 1957), <citedRange unit="page" from="246" to="246">p. 246</citedRange>
                        </bibl>
                     </listBibl>
                     <listBibl>
                        <head>Selected bibliography to 2007:</head>
                        <bibl>Cockerell, S. C., <title>The Gorleston Psalter</title> (London, 1907),
                           pp. 2 and n. 3, 17 n. 1, 19 n. 1.</bibl>
                        <bibl>James, M. R., <title>A Peterborough psalter and bestiary of the
                              fourteenth century</title> (Oxford: Roxburghe Club, 1921), p.
                           35.</bibl>
                        <bibl>——, <title>Lists of manuscripts formerly in Peterborough Abbey library</title>,
                           Supplement to the Bibliographical Society’s Transactions 5 (Oxford: OUP,
                           1926), p. 15.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Millar, E. G., <title>English illuminated manuscripts from the XIVth
                              to the XVth centuries</title> (Paris; Brussels: G.</bibl>
                        <bibl>van Oest, 1928), pp. 10 and pls. 22, 23.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Harrison, F., <title>Treasures of illumination: English manuscripts of
                              the fourteenth century (c. 1250–1400)</title> (London: The Studio; New
                           York: The Studio Publications, 1937), p. 14, pl. 17.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Summary catalogue, vol. 2, part 2, no. 6461.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Tolhurst, J. B. L. (ed.), <title>The monastic breviary of Hyde Abbey,
                           Winchester: mss. Rawlinson liturg. e. 1*, and Gough liturg. 8, in the
                           Bodleian Library, Oxford</title>, vol. 6, Henry Bradshaw Society 80 (London:
                           Harrison and Sons, 1941–42), p. 240.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Hughes, A., <title>Medieval polyphony in the Bodleian Library</title>
                           (Oxford: Bodleian Library, 1951), p. 8.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Rouse, E. C., ‘Wall paintings in the church of St Pega,
                              Peakirk, Northamptonshire’, <title>Archaeological Journal 60</title> (1954),
                           pp. 135–49, at p. 149 and pls. XXXIVb, XXXVI.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Harrison, F. L., <title>Music in medieval Britain</title> (London:
                           Routledge &amp; Kegan Paul, 1958), p. 153.</bibl>
                        <bibl>van Dijk (1958), fols. 18–18b.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Apfel, E., <title>Studien zur Satztechnik der mittelalterlichen
                              englischen Musik</title>, 2 vols. (Heidelberg: C. Winter, 1959), vol.
                           1, p. 62.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Sanders, E. H., ‘Cantilena and discant in 14th-century English
                              polyphony’, first published in 1965, reprinted in his collected
                              articles, <title>French and English polyphony of the 13th and 14th centuries:
                              style and notation</title> (Aldershot: Variorum, 1998), Article II, p.
                           36.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Reaney, G. (ed.), <title>Manuscripts of polyphonic music c. 1320–1400</title>
                           (Munich: G. Henle Verlag, 1966), pp. 247–8 and passim.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Sandler, L. F., ‘A follower of Jean Pucelle in England’, <title>Art
                              Bulletin 52</title> (1970), pp. 363–72, at p.</bibl>
                        <bibl>367.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Ragusa, I., ‘An illustrated psalter from Lyre Abbey’, <title>Speculum
                              46</title> (1971), pp. 267–81, at p.</bibl>
                        <bibl>280.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Pächt and Alexander (1966–73), vol. 3, no. 572, pl. LVII.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Sandler (1974), pp. 56, 121–2, 150–1, figs. 116–30, 134–5, and
                           passim.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Sandler, L. F., ‘An early fourteenth-century English psalter in
                              the Escorial’, JWCI XLII (1979), pp. 65–80, at p. 76.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Yapp, W. B., ‘The birds of English medieval manuscripts’,
                              <title>Journal of Medieval History 5</title> (1979), pp. 315–48, at p.
                           336.</bibl>
                        <bibl> Harrison, F. Ll., <title>Music in medieval Britain</title>, 4th edn.
                           (Buren, Netherlands: F. Knuf, 1980), p. 153.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Verdier, P., <title>Le couronnement de la Vierge: les origines et les
                              premiers développements d’un thème iconographique</title> (Montréal:
                           Institut d’études médiévales; Paris: Vrin, 1980), pp. 109, 148.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Marks, R. and Morgan, N., <title>The golden age of English manuscript
                              painting, 1200–1500</title> (London: Chatto &amp; Windus, 1981), p.
                           18.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Bennett, A., review of Sandler, A Peterborough Psalter, <title>Art
                              Bulletin 64</title> (1982), pp. 502–8.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Sandler, L. F., <title>The psalter of Robert de Lisle in the British
                              Library</title> (London: H. Miller; New York: OUP, 1983), p. 42 n.
                           22.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Michael, M. A.,‘A manuscript wedding gift from Philippa of
                              Hainault to Edward III’,  <title>Burlington Magazine</title> 77 (1985), pp.
                           582–601, at p. 586 and n. 19.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Park, D., ‘Cistercian wall painting and panel painting’ in C.
                              Norton and D. Park (eds.), <title>Cistercian art and architecture in the
                              British Isles</title> (Cambridge: CUP, 1986), pp. 181–210, at p. 202
                           n. 148.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Sandler (1986), vol. 1, pp. 27, 29; vol. 2, no. 91, pp. 19, 32, 87,
                           89, 101, 102, 103, 105, 106, 121, 238, 242, 243.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Alexander and Binski (1987), nos. 205, 360.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Norton, C., Park, D. and Binski, P., <title>Dominican painting in East
                              Anglia: the Thornham Parva retable and the Musée de Cluny
                              frontal</title> (Woodbridge: Boydell, 1987), pp. 71–2.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Michael, M. A., ‘Oxford, Cambridge and London: towards a theory
                              for “grouping” Gothic manuscripts’, <title>Burlington Magazine 130</title>
                           (1988), pp. 107–15, at p. 115.</bibl>
                        <bibl>——, ‘Destruction, reconstruction and invention: the Hungerford Hours
                           and English manuscript illumination of the early fourteenth century’,
                           <title>English manuscript studies</title> 1100–1700 2 (1990), pp. 33–108, at pp. 65, 66,
                           75, 77, 85.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Mezger, W., <title>Narrenidee und Fastnachtsbrauch: Studien zum
                              Fortleben des Mittelalters in der europäischen Festkultur</title>, Konstanzer
                              Bibliothek 15 (Constance: Universitätsverlag Konstanz, 1991),
                           p. 239 Abb. 127.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Johnson, I., ‘Language and literary expression’ in C.
                              Given-Wilson (ed.), <title>An illustrated history of late medieval
                              England</title> (Manchester and New York: Manchester University Press,
                           1996), pp. 127–51, at p. 148 plate (fol. 13).</bibl>
                        <bibl>Stones, A., ‘The stylistic context of the Roman de Fauvel, with
                              a note on Fauvain’ in M. Bent and A. Wathey (eds.), <title>Fauvel studies:
                              allegory, chronicle, music, and image in Paris, Bibliothèque nationale
                              de France, MS français 146</title> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1998),
                           pp. 529–67, at p. 561.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Dennison, L., ‘Monastic or secular? The artist of the Ramsey
                              Psalter, now at Holkham Hall, Norfolk’ in T. Benjamin (ed.),
                              <title>Monasteries and society in medieval Britain: proceedings of the 1994
                              Harlaxton Symposium</title> (Stamford: Paul Watkins, 1999), pp.
                           223–61, at p. 244 nn. 77, 82; p. 245 nn. 83, 86.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Sandler (1999), p. 51 n. 100, p. 55 n. 115, p. 70 nn. 186, 190, p. 81
                           n. 252, p. 133 n. 452, p. 138, ill. 52 (fol. 13).</bibl>
                        <bibl>Smith, K. A., ‘The Neville of Hornby Hours and the design of
                              literate devotion’, <title>Art Bulletin 81</title> (1999), pp. 72–92, pl.
                           24.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Friis-Jensen, K. and Willoughby, J. M. W. (eds.), <title>Peterborough Abbey</title>,
                           Corpus of British Medieval Library Catalogues 8 (London: British Library
                           in association with the British Academy, 2001), BP10.13, BP21.85a,
                           BP21.288a.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Joslin, M. C. and Joslin Watson, C. C., <title>The Egerton
                              Genesis</title> (London: British Library; Toronto: University of
                           Toronto Press, 2001), p. 79.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Smith, K. A., <title>Art, identity and devotion in fourteenth-century
                              England: three women and their books of hours</title> (London: British
                           Library and University of Toronto Press, 2003), p. 291 n. 58.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Ayers, T., <title>The medieval stained glass of Wells
                              Cathedral</title> (Oxford: Published for the British Academy by OUP,
                           2004), pp. 162, 233 and fig. II.46, 308–9.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Büttner, F. O., ‘Der illuminierte Psalter im Westen’ in
                              Büttner (2004), pp. 1–106, at pp. 33 n. 176, 71 n. 37.</bibl>
                        <bibl> Golden, J. K., ‘The iconography of authority in the depiction
                              of seated, cross-legged figures’ in C. Hourihane (ed.), <title>Between the
                              picture and the word: manuscript studies from the Index of Christian
                              Art</title> (Princeton, NJ: Penn State Press, 2005), pp. 81–99, at p.
                           85.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Webber, T., ‘The Bible and its study from the cloisters to the
                           university’ in P. Binski and S. Panayotova (eds.), <title>The Cambridge illuminations: ten centuries of book
                           production in the medieval west</title> (London: H. Miller, 2005), pp. 75–117
                           (nos. 19–42), cited at no. 41.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Brown (2006), pp. 24, 30.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Brown, M. P., <title>The Holkham Bible picture book: a
                              facsimile</title> (London: British Library, 2007), p. 16.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Randall, L. M. C., ‘Sense and sensibilities in an early
                              fourteenth-century psalter from East Anglia’ in K. A. Smith and C. H.
                              Krinsky, <title>Tributes to Lucy Freeman Sandler: studies in manuscript
                              illumination</title> (London: H. Miller, 2007), pp. 219–33, at p. 227
                           n. 50.</bibl>
                     </listBibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
               <msPart xml:id="MS_Barlow_22-folirv">
                  <msIdentifier>
                     <altIdentifier type="partial">
                        <idno type="part">MS. Barlow 22, endleaf, fol. i (lifted pastedown)</idno>
                     </altIdentifier>
                  </msIdentifier>
                  <msContents>
                     <textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>
                     <msItem><note> Responds with music in three parts.</note></msItem>


                  </msContents>
                  <physDesc>
                     <objectDesc form="codex">
                        <supportDesc material="perg">
                           <support>parchment</support>
                        </supportDesc>
                     </objectDesc>
                     <musicNotation>
                        <p>Ars Nova type notation (see Hughes, 1951; Harrison, 1958, p. 153;
                           Apfel, 1959, vol. I, p. 62; Reaney, 1966; The Digital Image Archive of
                           Medieval Music).</p>
                     </musicNotation>
                  </physDesc>
                  <history>
                     <origin>
                        <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notBefore="1300" notAfter="1400">14th century</origDate>
                     </origin>
                  </history>
               </msPart>
               <msPart xml:id="MS_Barlow_22-fol1rv">
                  <msIdentifier>
                     <altIdentifier type="partial">
                        <idno type="part">MS. Barlow 22, endleaf, fol. 1</idno>
                     </altIdentifier>
                  </msIdentifier>
                  <msContents>
                     <textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>
                     <msItem> 
                        <locus from="1r" to="1v">(fol. 1r–v)</locus> <title type="desc" key="work_10641">Leaf from a choir breviary</title> </msItem>
                  </msContents>
                  <physDesc>
                     <objectDesc form="codex">
                        <supportDesc material="perg">
                           <support>parchment</support>
                           <extent>One leaf</extent>
                        </supportDesc>
                     </objectDesc>
                  </physDesc>
                  <history>
                     <origin>
                        <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notAfter="1300" notBefore="1200">13th century</origDate>
                     </origin>
                  </history>
               </msPart>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2024-02">Revised to incorporate full description from Solopova.</change>
         <change when="2022-04-04">Add binding information from Summary Catalogue.</change>
         <change when="2021-12-14">Add provenance information from MLGB3.</change>
         <change when="2019-10-31" xml:id="MMM">
            <persName>Toby Burrows/Mapping Manuscript Migrations</persName>Provenance and
            acquisition information added using <ref target="https://github.com/mapping-manuscript-migrations/oxford-tei-updates/blob/master/update_oxford_prov.rb">https://github.com/mapping-manuscript-migrations/oxford-tei-updates/blob/master/update_oxford_prov.rb</ref>
            in collaboration with the <ref target="http://mappingmanuscriptmigrations.org/">Mapping
               Manuscript Migrations</ref> project.</change>
         <change when="2017-07-01">First online publication.</change>
         <change when="2017-05-25">
            <persName>James Cummings</persName> Up-converted the markup using <ref target="https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl">https://github.com/jamescummings/Bodleian-msDesc-ODD/blob/master/convertTolkien2Bodley.xsl</ref>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>